<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 22:16:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Fritz Kreisler &#8211; Liebesleid</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-fritz-kreisler-liebesleid/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 22:10:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 4: Orchestrating Wind Instruments]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=483</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The title, Love’s Sorrow, perfectly encapsulates its bittersweet character. There’s some sorrow running through the piece, yet it never feels tragic. Instead, it has a gentle, almost playful sadness, as if reminiscing on love that...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The title, <em>Love’s Sorrow</em>, perfectly encapsulates its bittersweet character. There’s some sorrow running through the piece, yet it never feels tragic. Instead, it has a gentle, almost playful sadness, as if reminiscing on love that was once joyful but is now just a memory.</p>



<p>What stood out to me most was how expressive the violin line is. Kreisler’s writing makes full use of the instrument’s singing quality. The use of rubato is essential here, giving the piece a natural, speech-like fluidity. I particularly enjoyed the way the melody lingers on certain notes before moving forward, as if the violin itself is hesitating between sorrow and sweet recollection.</p>



<p>The accompaniment plays a crucial role in shaping the mood. The piano doesn’t just provide harmonic support, as it adds rhythmic movement and a subtle dance-like quality, almost like a slow waltz. This contrast between the flowing violin line and the steady, lilting accompaniment adds to the charm of the piece, making it feel intimate and conversational.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Gustav Holst &#8211; The Planets &#8211; IV. Jupiter</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-gustav-holst-the-planets-iv-jupiter/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 22:37:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 4: Orchestrating Wind Instruments]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=479</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to this piece was an interesting experience for me. I was amazed by how much ground the piece covers in just around seven minutes. It feels far longer than its actual duration. What stood...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to this piece was an interesting experience for me. I was amazed by how much ground the piece covers in just around seven minutes. It feels far longer than its actual duration. What stood out most was how cinematic it felt. I couldn’t help but associate the music with various film genres: moments of intense drama, romantic scenes, and even Western. This made me reflect on how music is so deeply connected with culture and personal memory. I found it fascinating that while I instinctively connected <em>Jupiter</em> to film scores, Holst composed it long before film music as we know it even existed. It made me wonder how much our listening experiences are shaped by what we’ve already heard, and how Holst’s music may have influenced the soundtracks that followed.</p>



<p>One of my favorite moments in the piece is when the beautiful D section emerges in the middle of all the energetic, almost chaotic sounds that come before it. The way the strings and horns gently introduce this melody feels like a breath of fresh air, and I loved how it gradually expanded to include the entire orchestra. This build-up was incredibly moving for me.</p>



<p>As I listened, I also noticed how well Holst balances contrasting moods and textures. The rhythmic drive and dynamic changes kept me on my toes, while the lyrical moments gave me time to reflect and immerse myself in the music’s beauty. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Antonín Dvořák &#8211; &#8220;Song to the Moon&#8221; from Rusalka</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-antonin-dvorak-song-to-the-moon-from-rusalka/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 21:51:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 4: Orchestrating Wind Instruments]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=481</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The piece is filled with an aching sense of longing, and from the very first notes, I felt completely drawn into its dreamlike atmosphere, pushed by the harp. It felt much like moonlight shimmering on...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The piece is filled with an aching sense of longing, and from the very first notes, I felt completely drawn into its dreamlike atmosphere, pushed by the harp. It felt much like moonlight shimmering on water.</p>



<p>One thing that struck me was how the orchestration enhances the voice without overpowering it. The strings provide a delicate, flowing foundation, while the woodwinds play an especially expressive role. At times, they blend with the vocal line, doubling or supporting the melody to create a sense of warmth and intimacy. At other moments, they respond to the voice in a call-and-answer, almost as if the night itself is echoing Rusalka’s plea. This dialogue between the voice and the orchestra gives the aria a deeply organic feel, as if it’s breathing and evolving naturally.</p>



<p>I also loved how Dvořák used dynamics and phrasing to shape the emotional contour of the piece. The melody starts softly, almost hesitantly, then gradually grows, reaching soaring heights before retreating again into a hushed, intimate ending. The harp adds a subtle shimmer throughout, reinforcing the celestial, dreamlike quality of the music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
