<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Coursework &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 22:12:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Research point: links between Wagner and Nazism</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-links-between-wagner-and-nazism/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 22:12:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1846</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Wagner&#8217;s dramatic and emotionally charged music has long had a powerful influence not just on music lovers, but&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Wagner&#8217;s dramatic and emotionally charged music has long had a powerful influence not just on music lovers, but also on political movements seeking a sense of mythic destiny. This mystical attraction of music was and still is used by political propaganda and proved fatally potent when adopted by Hitler and the Nazis. But does Wagner&#8217;s music itself contain some intrinsic quality that made it the perfect vehicle for Nazism?</p>



<p>There is no doubt that Wagner had an anti-Semitic view of the world. In his notorious 1850 essay &#8220;On Judaism in Music,&#8221; Wagner expressed extremely offensive racist views towards Jewish people that were later exploited by the Nazis. He stereotyped Jews and said they could not truly make great art. Though a distortion, Hitler and other Nazis admired Wagner and saw him as an inspiration for their antisemitism.</p>



<p>I believe that there are aspects of Wagner&#8217;s works that undoubtedly appealed to the Nazi psyche. The huge mythical operas about heroes and gods match the Nazis&#8217; huge self-glorification. The medieval German settings and Norse mythology in works like The Ring suit the Nazi love of old Germanic purity.</p>



<p>The raw emotion in Wagner&#8217;s scores, for example, the extreme excitement when the music climaxes, is like the fevered Nazi rallies choreographed by Hitler and Goebbels. The gut power of songs like The Ride of the Valkyries taps into wild passions that override morality – just what the Nazis did so well.</p>



<p>Yet we must be aware of overstating this case. While Wagner&#8217;s operas worked well for the Nazis, the music itself isn&#8217;t Fascist. I couldn&#8217;t find information showing that there is anything intrinsically Fascist about the music itself. The emotional range of Wagner&#8217;s scores captures the full spectrum of human experience—from the uplifting to the disturbing. As with all art, his works are open to multiple interpretations.</p>



<p>I firmly believe that art and the artist should be separated and appreciated independently. Wagner&#8217;s music is no exception. We can still find value in his compositions while acknowledging the problematic aspects of the composer as an individual. We can reclaim his works for more positive purposes – his music leading us to contemplate humanity&#8217;s deeper bonds rather than divisions.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1705529244453 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Walsh, M. (1992) <em>The case of Wagner &#8212; again</em>. https://content.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,974661-1,00.html.</p>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (2024) <em>Richard Wagner | Biography, Music, Compositions, Operas, &amp; Facts</em>. https://www.britannica.com/biography/Richard-Wagner-German-composer/Wagners-anti-Semitism.</p>



<p>Burton-Hill, C. (2022) &#8216;Is Wagner’s Nazi stigma fair?,&#8217; <em>BBC Culture</em>, 24 February. https://www.bbc.com/culture/article/20130509-is-wagners-nazi-stigma-fair.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Go to a concert</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-go-to-a-concert/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 21:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1841</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A few days ago, I attended the Mozart Requiem concert performed by the Orquestra Filarmónica Portuguesa at the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>A few days ago, I attended the Mozart Requiem concert performed by the Orquestra Filarmónica Portuguesa at the Aula Magna in Lisbon. The concert was conducted by the conductor Osvaldo Ferreira and featured a choir and four soloists: Marco Alves dos Santos, tenor, Carolina Figueiredo, mezzo-soprano, Raquel Alão, soprano and Miguel Maduro-Dias, bass.</p>



<p>The performance of Mozart&#8217;s Requiem by the Orquestra Filarmónica Portuguesa was a sublime and moving experience. The full orchestra, choir, and four solo vocalists brought Mozart&#8217;s immortal composition to life in a profound way.</p>



<p>The instruments used included the typical setup found in a classical orchestra &#8211; strings, woodwinds, brass and timpani. The strings provided the lush foundation, while the winds and brass added color and accent. The timpani gave dramatic punctuation while the four vocal soloists gave the Requiem an operatic quality during their featured parts.</p>



<p>While the Requiem is a familiar and often performed piece, hearing it live gave it an emotional immediacy and power beyond any recording. The soaring crescendos and hushed moments of silence resonated deeply. No media reproduction can truly capture the experience of hearing these sublime sounds &#8220;in the flesh.&#8221;</p>



<p>The program notes provided useful background and context about the piece and its history that enhanced my enjoyment and understanding. Learning about the mysterious circumstances of the Requiem&#8217;s composition and its intersection of the earthly and divine added deeper meaning.</p>



<p>Overall, this was a profoundly enjoyable and moving concert that will stay with me for a long time. I had never heard Mozart’s Requiem live before, and I was surprised by the difference it makes. I felt that the music had more life, more intensity, more depth. I could perceive the details, the nuances, the emotions of the musicians and the singers. I also felt more involved, more connected, more participant of the work. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Transcribing for the piano</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-transcribing-for-the-piano/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 22:31:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1838</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I listened to Glenn Gould&#8217;s 1968 recording. The most evident difference between Beethoven&#8217;s original and Liszt&#8217;s transcription is&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I listened to Glenn Gould&#8217;s 1968 recording.</p>



<p>The most evident difference between Beethoven&#8217;s original and Liszt&#8217;s transcription is the instrumentation. Beethoven&#8217;s composition, created for a full orchestra, provides a vast palette of colours, timbres, and effects, allowing the music to be expressed with expansive variety.</p>



<p>In contrast, Liszt&#8217;s transcription scored solely for piano, introduces intrinsic physical constraints evident in the performance: The range and depth of sounds are not as broad as those produced by an orchestra; a piano&#8217;s sustained notes fall short when compared to those of wind or string instruments; and while dynamic contrasts can be substantial, they typically do not reach the extremes possible within an orchestra, even though the version I listened to did had significant dynamic variation.</p>



<p>However, there is a distinctive positive aspect to Liszt&#8217;s arrangement: intimacy. A single instrument, managed by one performer, transforms a grand, collective work into a more personal and individual experience. The piano takes the spotlight and, particularly during the Romantic era, places the pianist at the forefront. A single instrument offers performers greater liberty and room for expression; they can shape the tempo, articulation, and pedalling, ultimately making the performance a personal statement of the player&#8217;s own style.</p>



<p>I believe that Liszt’s piano version captures a lot of the spirit of the symphony, following the same structure and themes as Beethoven’s original. Liszt also tries to evoke the same feelings and moods, like tension, drama, contrast, and resolution. It’s not just a copy, but a new interpretation that honours Beethoven’s talent.</p>



<p>Regarding my preference, I found merit in listening to both versions, as they provide distinct interpretations of the same composition. However, if I had to pick one, I&#8217;d go with Beethoven’s original symphony. I feel it embodies the music&#8217;s essence more authentically and powerfully. I also appreciate Beethoven&#8217;s skill in balancing and contrasting various sections, themes, and instruments, as well as the way he develops and resolves musical ideas.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Expressing national identity</title>
		<link>./../../../../../expressing-national-identity/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 21:58:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1835</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to Albéniz&#8217;s &#8220;Suite Española No. 1&#8221;, I was immediately drawn to the piece &#8220;Asturias (Leyenda)&#8221; for its&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to Albéniz&#8217;s &#8220;Suite Española No. 1&#8221;, I was immediately drawn to the piece &#8220;Asturias (Leyenda)&#8221; for its familiar Spanish elements. As a Portuguese listener, I found parallels to music from my own country.</p>



<p>The piano mimics a Spanish guitar, reflecting the central role of the guitar in Spanish musical culture. Repeated rhythmic strumming patterns capture the spirit of Spanish folk music traditions.</p>



<p>An insistent flamenco rhythm drives the piece forward, evoking the heel-taps of dancers. The struck chords suggest the clapping hands often accompanying flamenco.</p>



<p>The melody itself encapsulates Spanish folk idioms with its modal tonality and distinctive phrasing. This is the very essence of Iberian traditional music.</p>



<p>In naming the piece after the Asturias region, Albéniz implies a musical portrait, conjuring a sense of Spanish regional identity and local color. The title prepares the listener to be transported to the province through sound.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Programme music</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-programme-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2023 21:55:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1821</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hector Berlioz&#8217;s Symphonie Fantastique, composed in 1830, perfectly reflects the obsessive mind of its composer, Berstein said in&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hector Berlioz&#8217;s Symphonie Fantastique, composed in 1830, perfectly reflects the obsessive mind of its composer, Berstein said in its Young People&#8217;s Concerts. But when I first listened to the symphony, I hadn&#8217;t watched Berstein&#8217;s video, so I expected something more contained and safe like other works from that period. But I soon realized why it&#8217;s called &#8220;Fantastique.&#8221; For me, the word &#8220;fantastique&#8221; evokes not grandness but a sense of surreal fantasy. In my interpretation, the symphony, rather than presenting a linear narrative, unfolds as flashes of disconnected dreams, each reflecting the protagonist&#8217;s shifting emotions and his fixation on an unattainable woman.</p>



<p>The first dream depicts meeting his beloved; the second involves a failed attempt to reach her at a ball; the third transports him to a tranquil rural setting, offering a brief respite from the turmoil; the fourth descends from a dream into a nightmarish execution; the final movement plunges him into a fantastical afterlife world. My feeling at the end is that maybe the woman of his dreams was only a woman in his dreams. </p>



<p>The reason I previously stated that I felt Fantastique was related to fantasy,  was due to the surreal and psychedelic nature of the music, which portrays the lovesick hallucinations and nightmares of the protagonist. Musically, Berlioz employed unexpected dynamic changes and unsettling orchestration, such as the use of real thunder in the storm scenes, taking a step further from Beethoven’s approach. He also innovatively used the main theme. This idée fixe is not merely a static melody; it undergoes a captivating transformation throughout the symphony, mirroring the protagonist’s evolving emotions and the unfolding narrative. As the symphony progresses, the idée fixe becomes increasingly distorted and anguished, reflecting the depths of the protagonist’s obsession and despair.</p>



<p>The first appearance of the idée fixe seems different from when a main theme is typically introduced, for example, in Beethoven&#8217;s Symphony No. 6. First, it doesn&#8217;t appear until around 5 minutes into the first movement, after an extended setup section &#8211; almost like an introduction leading us into the dream. When the idée fixe finally enters, it is in the form of a long, unaccompanied melody in the woodwinds, with bursts of energetic strings punctuating it. This unique presentation reminded me a bit of the surprising and unsettling rhythms in Stravinsky&#8217;s Rite of Spring. That unexpected rhythm must have been a shocking revelation for early 20th-century listeners.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="596" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-1024x596.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1823" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-1024x596.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-300x175.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-768x447.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-1536x893.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-2048x1191.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-640x372.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-960x558.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03.png 2816w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Although as I said before, the Idée fixe is transformed through the movements, its use in the fourth movement is extremely symbolic in its subtlety and, I must say, humour. This movement engages in the musical depiction of a march to execution. After the pastoral setting of the previous movement, the music abruptly shifts to the protagonist&#8217;s march to the scaffold, accompanied by a marching band. I was surprised because I expected a solemn setting, but instead it sounds almost celebratory, like a fanfare. The booming percussion and horns set a marching rhythm while the strangely cheerful melodies in the woodwinds and strings portray the crowd jeering the prisoner to his death. Just before the fatal blow, the idée fixe appears one last time on the clarinet, only to be suddenly, brutally cut off, symbolizing the severing of the head. The vivid musical imagery transported me right to the exact scene Berlioz intended to depict, which I found brilliant.</p>



<p>In the fourth movement, there are two main themes—a descending theme and a march theme—as well as a countermelody for the first theme. These all contribute to the overall feeling of the movement. The descending theme introduces a sense of despair, while the march theme brings the strangely cheerful contrast I mentioned earlier. One interesting thing is how the descending theme contrasts with the Idée Fixe melody—the Idée Fixe has a hopeful, ascending trajectory, whereas the descending theme embarks on a continuous, hopeless downward journey.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="242" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-1024x242.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1829" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-1024x242.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-300x71.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-768x182.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-1536x363.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-2048x485.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-640x151.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-960x227.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1.png 2172w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">First appearance of the Idée Fixe</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="259" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-1024x259.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1830" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-1024x259.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-300x76.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-768x194.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-1536x389.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-2048x519.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-640x162.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-960x243.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1.png 2172w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Movement 4 main theme</figcaption></figure>



<p>In the end, I must say that I adored this symphony. I feel that Berlioz brings a dramatic and theatrical sensibility to the symphonic writing, vividly portraying the emotional world of his desperate protagonist. So while fantastique may not be about grandness in the heroic sense, it represents a daring new musical language filled with psychedelic fantasy.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1702245310254 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Trine (2022) <em>Leonard Bernstein &#8211; Young People’s Concerts: Berlioz takes a trip</em>. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zl9S5D3BLMA.</p>



<p><em>Berlioz’s Symphonie fantastique: Keeping Score | PBS</em> (no date). https://www.pbs.org/keepingscore/berlioz-symphonie-fantastique.html.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Classical and Romantic</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-classical-and-romantic/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 21:36:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1815</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Beethoven&#8217;s first piano sonata (No. 1 in F minor, Op 2) displays the hallmarks of the Classical style.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Beethoven&#8217;s first piano sonata (No. 1 in F minor, Op 2) displays the hallmarks of the Classical style. It contains a straightforward sonata form structure, opening with a lively first movement dotted with playful melodies. The middle movements provide contrast &#8211; a peaceful Adagio followed by a brisk dance-like section similar to a minuet. The finale introduces a vigorous theme. Throughout the piece, Beethoven focuses on balanced phrases and graceful melodies, supported by conventional harmony and rhythms &#8211; all trademarks of the Classical period.</p>



<p>In contrast, his final piano sonata (No. 32 in C minor, Op 111) exhibits innovations that push toward Romanticism. While still structured into movements, the form is more ecstatic, especially in the mystical opening movement. In this sonata, I hear many more chromatic harmonies and elastic rhythms and feel there&#8217;s an emotional range from brooding melancholy to joyful jubilation. The enriched harmonic palette and depth of expression represent the early Romantic style. </p>



<p>My research, in general, supports my feelings.</p>



<p>In the Opus 2 sonatas of his early period, Beethoven hews more closely to the balanced elegance of Mozart and Haydn. But flashes of his revolutionary voice emerge even then in the intense, turbulent passages. It contains a straightforward sonata form structure, opening with a lively first Molto Allegro movement characterized by accelerating small phrases leading to mini-climaxes, followed by pauses for theatrical effect. The middle Adagio movement offers the only overtly &#8216;pretty&#8217; music in the whole sonata &#8211; simple, serene melodies decorated with lavish ornamentation. The Allegretto finale features a slightly anxious minute tune pieced together from repeated fragments, counteracted by a smoother, more elegant major-mode Trio section.</p>



<p>The Op. 111 is regarded as one of Beethoven&#8217;s best piano compositions. It is a departure from previous sonatas, having only two movements, which led his publisher to question if it wasn&#8217;t a mistake. The sonata is described as powerful, passionate and inventive. For example, Beethoven transforms a simple and singable theme into five variations, ending in a serene and transcendent mood. Yet the animated fugue demonstrates Beethoven&#8217;s contrapuntal mastery cultivated in the Classical tradition. This piano sonata encapsulates Beethoven&#8217;s musical evolution from formal lucidity toward mystical, subjective soundscapes, prefiguring Romantic ideals.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1701123445593 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Tayama, M. (2022) <em>Beethoven Piano sonata in F minor (Op. 2 No. 1)</em>. https://practisingthepiano.com/beethoven-piano-sonata-no-1-in-f-minor/.</p>



<p>G. Gíslason, D. (2022) <em>Sonata No. 1 in F minor&nbsp; Op. 2 No. 1 Archives &#8211; Vancouver Recital Society</em>. https://vanrecital.com/tag/sonata-no-1-in-f-minor-op-2-no-1/.</p>



<p>Pizarro, A. (no date) <em>BBC &#8211; Radio 3 &#8211; Beethoven Piano Sonata No. 1 in F minor, Op. 2 No. 1</em>. https://www.bbc.co.uk/radio3/classical/pizarro/sonata1.shtml.</p>



<p>Kramer, L. (1993b) <em>Music as Cultural Practice, 1800-1900</em>. Univ of California Press.</p>



<p>Vrs (2019) <em>Sonata in C minor Op. 111 Archives &#8211; Vancouver Recital Society</em>. https://vanrecital.com/tag/sonata-in-c-minor-op-111/.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point: Bass Clarinet</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-bass-clarinet/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 21:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1779</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The bass clarinet is a woodwind instrument with a deep, rich tone, it provides a foundation for the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The bass clarinet is a woodwind instrument with a deep, rich tone, it provides a foundation for the woodwind section and entire ensemble. Though the bass clarinet has a relatively short history compared to other orchestral instruments, it has evolved into an expressive voice capable of solo works as well as supporting roles.</p>



<p>The earliest predecessor of the bass clarinet was the basset horn, developed in the 1770s. This instrument paved the way for lower-pitched clarinets. The first true bass clarinets emerged in the late 18th century. Heinrich Grenser is credited with creating one of the earliest examples in 1793. However, it was the pioneering instrument maker Adolphe Sax who developed the first fully satisfactory bass clarinet in 1838. Sax gave the instrument a wider bore and re-designed the key work to improve intonation across all registers. His innovations established the bass clarinet design that is still used today.</p>



<p>While the bass clarinet was slow to be accepted into orchestras at first, composers soon began to appreciate its unique timbre. Meyerbeer featured the instrument prominently in his 1836 opera Les Huguenots, one of the earliest uses of the bass clarinet in the orchestra. By the late 19th century, the bass clarinet had become a permanent member of the orchestra&#8217;s woodwind section. Its mellow, velvety tone contrasted with the more piercing oboe and soprano clarinet timbres.</p>



<p>In the orchestra, the bass clarinet typically provides harmonic support in the tenor and bass range. It handles the lower woodwind parts while the bassoon takes higher tenor lines. The bass clarinet has a remarkable three-octave range, overlapping the bassoon at the bottom end and the soprano clarinet at the top. This allows composers flexibility in orchestration. The instrument&#8217;s dark, brooding resonance lends itself well to dramatic effects.</p>



<p>Many composers took advantage of the bass clarinet&#8217;s solo potential as well. In Mahler&#8217;s Symphony No. 6, the bass clarinet introduces a moving theme in the first movement. Tchaikovsky exploits the instrument&#8217;s deep sound in The&nbsp;Nutcracker&#8217;s Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy. Stravinsky showcases the agility of the bass clarinet at the beginning of The Rite Of Spring.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1699394026604 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><em>The Origins of the Clarinet：The birth of the clarinet&nbsp; &#8211; Musical Instrument Guide &#8211; Yamaha Corporation</em> (no date). https://www.yamaha.com/en/musical_instrument_guide/clarinet/structure/.</p>



<p><em>Bass clarinet | VSL &#8211; Academy</em> (no date). https://www.vsl.info/en/academy/woodwinds/bass-clarinet.</p>



<p>Tan, C. (2019) <em>Our top 5 moments from the bass clarinet, underdog of the orchestra &#8211; Classical KUSC</em>. https://www.kusc.org/culture/staff-blog/top-5-bass-clarinet-underdog-of-the-orchestra/.</p>



<p>Wikipedia contributors (2023a) <em>Bass clarinet</em>. https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bass_clarinet.</p>



<p><em>Clarinetist Allan Rosenfeld’s Top 10 Orchestral Bass Clarinet Solos | Charlotte Symphony Orchestra</em> (2021). https://www.charlottesymphony.org/blog/clarinetist-allan-rosenfeld-top-10-orchestral-bass-clarinet-solos/.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p>William Schuman&#8217;s Symphony No. 3 (Part II, Toccata)Bass clarinet showcases virtuosic technique.</p>



<p>Gershwin&#8217;s Concerto in F (Second movement)Clarinet section soli with bass clarinet filling out bass line.</p>



<p>Shostakovich&#8217;s Symphony No. 8 (Fifth movement)Boisterous display of the bass clarinet&#8217;s low register mischief.</p>



<p>Wagner&#8217;s Tristan und Isolde (Act II, scene 3)Emphasizes the lyrical capabilities of the bass clarinet.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point: The Piccolo</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-the-piccolo/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 21:49:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1781</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The history of the piccolo is closely tied to that of the flute. The first transverse flute was&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The history of the piccolo is closely tied to that of the flute. The first transverse flute was developed in the Middle Ages as an adaptation of the recorder. As military bands adopted the flute, a smaller version was created to make the flute parts more prominent. This petite flute was initially keyed like a recorder with six finger holes and was used to play melodies an octave above the flute.</p>



<p>In the early 18th century, the first piccolos appeared in orchestral scores, including works by Jean-Philippe Rameau. However, it was initially referred to by names like &#8220;flautino&#8221; or &#8220;petite flute&#8221; rather than piccolo. The instrument continued to develop alongside the flute, especially after Theobald Böehm invented the modern flute fingering system in 1832. Böehm&#8217;s revolutionary key mechanism was soon adapted for the piccolo as well.</p>



<p>One of the earliest major works to feature the piccolo was Handel&#8217;s opera Rinaldo in 1711. Composers began to utilize its unique shrill timbre to provide colour and brilliance. For example, Beethoven used the piccolo in his 6th Symphony to imitate the sound of whistling birds. Its high register allows it to be heard over the entire orchestra, making it an excellent accent instrument.</p>



<p>Today, the piccolo is a standard member of the orchestra and band. Its most common variant is pitched an octave above the concert flute, although piccolos pitched a major third above the flute are also used. Its highest notes can reach up to C7, above the treble clef staff.</p>



<p>The piccolo&#8217;s bright sound serves to bring out melodic lines and add sparkle to orchestral textures. As one of the highest instruments in the orchestra, the piccolo&#8217;s clear notes cut through dense arrangements. Composers often utilize the piccolo to introduce themes or complement the woodwinds. </p>



<p>While associated with the flute section, the piccolo player may switch between the regular flute and piccolo multiple times in a single piece. Due to its penetrating timbre, the piccolo is used with good judgment to avoid overpowering the ensemble. However, short piccolo solos and highlights prevent listener fatigue.</p>



<p>Piccolo parts require advanced techniques to handle the altissimo register and quick figurations composers write. Rapid passages showcase the piccolo&#8217;s agile nature. Trills, runs, and arpeggios demand precise finger dexterity. The small size necessitates strict embouchure control. Intonation can also prove tricky with so few open finger holes to adjust the pitch.</p>



<p>While the piccolo often plays an accompaniment role, there are also many famous solos and melodies written for it. For example, the piccolo solo in the first movement of Shostakovich&#8217;s 6th Symphony. The soloist plays with delicate restraint, creating a thoughtful and powerful moment. Other works that highlight the piccolo include Tchaikovsky&#8217;s The Nutcracker, which features the piccolo along with the flute flute engaging in a lively duet, in the Chinese Dance. and John Philip Sousa&#8217;s &#8220;The Stars and Stripes Forever,&#8221; which features a famous piccolo countermelody above the marching band.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1699566934359 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Oxford University Press (2017) <em>A tiny instrument with a tremendous history: the piccolo</em>. https://blog.oup.com/2015/07/small-instrument-large-history-piccolo/.</p>



<p><em>Eight times the piccolo was secretly the most badass member of the orchestra</em> (no date). https://www.classicfm.com/discover-music/latest/best-piccolo-orchestra/.</p>



<p><em>Piccolo | VSL &#8211; Academy</em> (no date). https://www.vsl.info/en/academy/woodwinds/piccolo.</p>



<p>Perkins, C. (2021) &#8216;What’s the difference between a flute and a piccolo?,&#8217; <em>Yamaha Music</em>, 27 August. https://hub.yamaha.com/winds/wood/whats-the-difference-between-a-flute-and-a-piccolo/.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
