<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 23:10:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Chopin &#8211; Nocturne Eb major Op. 9 no. 2 </title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-chopin-nocturne-eb-major-op-9-no-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 22:39:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1873</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As one of Chopin&#8217;s most famous piano works, I&#8217;ve heard this lovely Nocturne many times before but listened&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As one of Chopin&#8217;s most famous piano works, I&#8217;ve heard this lovely Nocturne many times before but listened to it closely again recently. True to the nocturne style, it&#8217;s a short, simple piece with a straightforward structure centred on a lovely, almost naive melody that is instantly accessible and deeply romantic. The focus is absolutely on the long-lined vocal quality of the melody rather than complex harmonies, which remain mostly diatonic throughout. </p>



<p>While there&#8217;s not much harmonic tension, the interest comes from Chopin&#8217;s ornamentation that showcases the piano&#8217;s ability to quickly change notes, including trills, turns, and appoggiaturas. Despite its simplicity, or perhaps because of it, this nocturne is profoundly emotional to me. The famous melody is so classically romantic and intimate, that it&#8217;s no wonder it has moved listeners for almost 200 years.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Chopin &#8211; Prelude No 4 in E minor, Op 28</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-chopin-prelude-no-4-in-e-minor-op-28/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 23:07:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1876</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is probably my favourite Chopin piece and one of my all-time favourite piano works. The sheer amount&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is probably my favourite Chopin piece and one of my all-time favourite piano works. The sheer amount of emotion Chopin packs into this short and simple prelude never ceases to amaze me. It feels heavy, deep, and lamenting &#8211; almost like a funeral march. The constant, heartbeat-like rhythm creates a dark and brooding atmosphere, especially when combined with the descending harmonic progression that forms the backdrop of the piece.</p>



<p>There is barely any melody to speak of, just a simple descending scale figure that is repeated and varied. Yet despite its simplicity, the melody is incredibly lyrical and sings with a beautiful, melancholic tone. In this relatively basic musical texture, Chopin captures something raw and overwhelmingly human.</p>



<p>The ending is my favourite part &#8211; the way Chopin delays the final cadence builds the tension to almost unbearable levels before resolving. That tragic, delayed resolution encapsulates the mournful and evocative nature of this stunning prelude.</p>



<p><a href="https://girlinbluemusic.com/the-power-of-chopins-prelude-in-e-minor-op-28-no-4/#:~:text=The%20piece%20is%20one%20page,so%20effective%20from%20this%20texture." target="_blank"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Brahms &#8211; Piano Concerto No. 2 in B-flat major Op. 83</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-brahms-piano-concerto-no-2-in-b-flat-major-op-83/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 22:09:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1879</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I listened to Yuja Wang&#8217;s performance of this concerto, I was drawn into a musical conversation. The&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When I listened to Yuja Wang&#8217;s performance of this concerto, I was drawn into a musical conversation. The piano starts quietly, making small talk with the orchestra. But soon it shows a bold personality, interrupting the orchestra strongly.</p>



<p>There&#8217;s something remarkably compelling when the piano interrupts the orchestra. It&#8217;s like the small piano is shouting against the group. These interruptions give the concerto a sense of struggle and triumph that adds to the piece&#8217;s drama.</p>



<p>Sometimes it sounds like the piano and orchestra are having a dynamic conversation, taking turns. Other times they angrily argue, competing for attention. This conversation keeps changing from calm to passionate. The piano brings thoughtful melody and skill, balancing the orchestra&#8217;s powerful sections.</p>



<p>In the second movement, the dramatic piano storms against the mellow orchestra. The orchestra sometimes responds mildly, creating a vivid contrast that heightens the overall excitement of the movement.</p>



<p>The gentle third movement has a flowing lyricism, with the cello spinning a beautiful song. This movement is rich and sumptuous. It&#8217;s a peaceful contrast from all the arguments before.</p>



<p>But it is the final movement that leaves an indelible mark. Here, the piano shifts from gracious to loud and forceful. The piano showcases its full range of expression. This movement captures the whole spirit of the concerto &#8211; starting peacefully and ending spectacularly.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Schumann &#8211; Carnaval, op. 9</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-schumann-carnaval-op-9/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 22:06:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1868</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to Schumann&#8217;s Carnaval, took me into a grand masquerade, where masked partygoers come together to celebrate the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to Schumann&#8217;s Carnaval, took me into a grand masquerade, where masked partygoers come together to celebrate the festivities of Carnival. Even Chopin appeared at this fictitious party. This piano suite, composed between 1834 and 1835, consists of 21 short movements, each representing a character or caricature from the carnival scene.</p>



<p>Schumann turned this piece into a storytelling breathing life into the characters. Pierrot, the sad clown, dances poignantly, while Harlequin, the mischievous trickster, bounds with infectious energy.</p>



<p>At times, the technical challenges posed by Carnaval seemed daunting, even overwhelming. Yet as I studied the piece more deeply, I developed a greater understanding of Schumann&#8217;s composition. Learning about his mental health struggles and how they may have shaped this music gave me new insight. I realized that the complex and shifting emotions woven throughout Carnaval serve to enhance its overall poignant effect. Every musical detail—each note, chord, melodic twist and turn—contributes to this emotional impact.</p>



<p>It is not the kind of work that I would love to listen to repeatedly. Still, I get the sense that it is a work that is important to establish the piano as an extremely expressive instrument and will continue to captivate listeners.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Marta Pereira da Costa &#8211; Tiny Desk Concert</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-marta-pereira-da-costa-tiny-desk-concert/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 22:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1812</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I happened to catch this concert and decided to listen since it featured a Portuguese artist playing the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I happened to catch this concert and decided to listen since it featured a Portuguese artist playing the Portuguese guitar, something you don&#8217;t often see on international channels.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Marta Pereira da Costa: Tiny Desk Concert" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wzlZ68ts-IU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I hadn&#8217;t heard of Marta Pereira da Costa before, although I knew her name. She&#8217;s the world&#8217;s first and only professional female Portuguese guitar player in Fado music.</p>



<p>Right away the sound reminded me of Carlos Paredes, a legendary Portuguese guitarist, but with a fresher vibe, mainly from the percussion. Traditionally the Portuguese guitar is accompanied by two guitars, but here it&#8217;s one guitar plus percussion, bringing a modern twist which I enjoy.</p>



<p>I&#8217;m biased since I love the Portuguese guitar, but Marta&#8217;s playing conveys so much expression and goes beyond mellow tunes. Even faster, danceable songs have a singing, soaring quality from her guitar.</p>



<p>Another thing I enjoyed was how Marta lets the other instruments shine, especially in the last song. The interplay of bass and treble, each with its moment, creates a really beautiful, rich sound.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@nprmusic"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Antonio Vivaldi &#8211; Piccolo Concerto in C Major, RV 443</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-antonio-vivaldi-piccolo-concerto-in-c-major-rv-443/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 21:01:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1808</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Antonio Vivaldi wrote three concertos for a small, high-pitched instrument called the &#8220;flautino&#8221;. The exact instrument Vivaldi intended&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Antonio Vivaldi wrote three concertos for a small, high-pitched instrument called the &#8220;flautino&#8221;. The exact instrument Vivaldi intended is unknown, but scholars believe it was either the sopranino recorder or the flageolet. In the 18th century, the transverse flute replaced both the recorder and flageolet and a new edition of Vivaldi&#8217;s concerto was published for the piccolo, a member of the flute family. This is the version that is typically performed today and it was the one I listened to.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="A. Vivaldi - Piccolo Concerto in C major (RV443)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FBNq-F80uFc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>As soon as the orchestra begins the opening Allegro molto, the piccolo enters with a joyful, singing melody in the upper octave that immediately grabs my attention. The piccolo part requires technical agility as it features fast runs and trills, but the melodies flow so naturally that the difficulty is masked and it looks easy.</p>



<p>The calm and emotional middle Largo movement offers a lovely change from the faster outer movements. The piccolo carries a gorgeous, flowing melody above soft strings, reminiscent of a soulful operatic aria. It&#8217;s my favourite part—a moment where the piccolo&#8217;s expressiveness truly shines.</p>



<p>The concluding Allegro brings back the cheerful mood, with the piccolo presenting new melodic material over the orchestra&#8217;s constant, pulsing motion. The themes are fragmented with trills, creating a perpetually moving, spinning sensation. The cadenza features more rapid runs that showcase the soloist&#8217;s skill.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Tchaikovsky &#8211; The Nutcracker&#8217;s Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-tchaikovsky-the-nutcrackers-dance-of-the-sugar-plum-fairy/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 21:46:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1804</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Of course, I already knew the melody of the Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy, since it is&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Of course, I already knew the melody of the Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy, since it is one of the most used melodies in Christmas ads. But at this time I listened to it closely. In the beginning, I was immediately struck by the beauty of the music. The melody is light and airy and has a childish magical quality that transports you to another world. The use of the celesta gives the music a unique, ethereal and enchanting sound.</p>



<p>The presence of the bass clarinet is brief but it is truly remarkable. It brings a new tone and colour that adds depth to the beginning of the piece. The choice of the bass clarinet seems to bring a warm, mellow and rounded sound in contrast to the brighter, crystalline tones of the celesta. This elevates the overall feeling of the fantastical and mysterious setting.</p>



<p>Overall, it evokes a profound sense of innocent joy and wonder for me. The music exudes a youthful spirit of fantasy and imagination. It&#8217;s a timeless piece that brings out the inner child in me. Every listen renews feelings of wide-eyed enchantment and marvel.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to John Coltrane &#8211; Naima</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-john-coltrane-naima/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2023 21:01:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1776</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[John Coltrane&#8217;s composition &#8220;Naima&#8221; is a lush, emotional ballad that showcases his virtuosic command of the tenor saxophone.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>John Coltrane&#8217;s composition &#8220;Naima&#8221; is a lush, emotional ballad that showcases his virtuosic command of the tenor saxophone. The song is a tribute to Coltrane’s wife, Juanita Naima Grubbs, and is one beautiful ballads. The saxophone is the centerpiece of the song, accompained by the piano, the bass and the drums.</p>



<p>As soon as the saxophone enters, I am enveloped in the bittersweet melancholy of the piece. The tone is robust yet smooth, almost vocal-like in the way he caresses each note with vibratos and slight inflections that hint at a longing.</p>



<p>The flexibility and range of the saxophone allows Coltrane to truly sing through his instrument, conveying a depth of feeling that spans smooth joy to deep sorrow. I find his playing meditative and prayerful.</p>



<p>One of the things that makes Coltrane’s saxophone so expressive is his use of dynamics. He’s able to play softly and delicately one moment and then switch to a more forceful and aggressive style the next.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Samuel Barber &#8211; Adagio For Strings</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-samuel-barber-adagio-for-strings/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 20:46:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1771</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last night I had the pleasure of attending a live performance of Mozart&#8217;s Requiem. When the conductor stepped&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Last night I had the pleasure of attending a live performance of Mozart&#8217;s Requiem. When the conductor stepped up, he surprised us all by announcing they would open with Samuel Barber&#8217;s Adagio for Strings before moving into the Requiem. Though I knew the piece from movies and commercials, I had never truly listened closely before. I found it profoundly moving.</p>



<p>The opening immediately establishes a heavy, mournful mood brimming with emotional weight. It&#8217;s easy to understand why this piece is often played at funerals, including Einstein&#8217;s.</p>



<p>The main theme is deceptively simple &#8211; just three notes ascending. Yet the aching slowness, the dragging tempo, creates the sense of struggling to lift upwards only to fall back down. I loved how the stately, elongated melody passes from the violins to the violas and finally, the cellos, maintaining its emotional power throughout.</p>



<p>To me, it sounded extremely beautiful, but the melody alone doesn&#8217;t convey the full emotional impact. That comes from the harmony of the other strings, which inspire the melody with all its feelings. The rich harmonies and colours of the string orchestra add emotive depth. </p>



<p>This piece perfectly captures the universality of grief, transcending time and place. Though it was composed in 1936, it speaks profoundly to the shared human experience across cultures and generations. Little did Barber know what the world was about to witness and how this song would be embraced as an expression of mourning, remembrance, and hope.</p>



<p>In the end, it proved the perfect prelude to Mozart&#8217;s Requiem. Well-chosen, maestro.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
