<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>From Present to Past &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 22:22:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Assignment 1 &#8211; Reflective account</title>
		<link>./../../../1624-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 21:54:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1624</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This course unit was quite challenging, especially since I decided to take on a full-time job alongside my&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This course unit was quite challenging, especially since I decided to take on a full-time job alongside my studies. Balancing a full-time job, being a parent, and studying part-time has been quite demanding. As a result, my reflection centres around my perception that I wasn&#8217;t able to go as deeply into the subjects as I would have liked.</p>



<p>I found the first two projects to be incredibly valuable. They kickstarted my reflection on various aspects of music, such as its nature, what constitutes good music, and the differences between popular and classical music. This led me to question many of my preconceived notions.</p>



<p>One thing that pleasantly surprised me in this unit was the diverse range of music I was exposed to. From movie soundtracks to Indian music and contemporary styles I hadn&#8217;t encountered before, it expanded my musical horizons. Since my musical background was one of my main challenges, this exposure was truly beneficial. In hindsight, I think it would have been great to take this course as my first.</p>



<p>But, looking back, I wish I had spent more time on each subject. For example, I had a strong affinity for holy minimalist composers, and I would have loved to explore them further. On the other hand, microtonality and spectralism were not as enjoyable for me. I believe that with more time and study, I might have come to understand and appreciate what these composers are trying to convey.</p>



<p>The projects that focused on the Batman soundtrack and researching Magnus Lindberg were the ones I dedicated the most time to. Perhaps that&#8217;s why I found them particularly rewarding. Both projects allowed me to exercise a skill I had developed in the Stylistic Techniques course: writing about music. In both cases, I aimed to bring my own perspective to the table, going beyond regurgitating information readily available online. I hope I succeeded in conveying my own viewpoint while grounding it in factual information.</p>



<p>When I consider the overall content of the unit, I realize that some projects, such as those on orchestral instruments and music notation, had already been covered in other courses. If this had been my first course, those projects would have been perfect. However, since I had already delved into those topics before, I chose to skip them and dedicate more time to other projects.</p>



<p>Ultimately, I see progression in my studies, particularly in the broadening of my &#8220;musical baggage&#8221;. As for my writing skills, I have discovered that I find reflective texts much easier to write than &#8220;listening&#8221; ones. The most important lesson I have learned thus far is the need to improve my listening skills. I want to write about my experiences with music in a way that is clear, accurate, and captures everything that makes the music special to me.</p>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to contemporary music styles</title>
		<link>./../../../listening-to-contemporary-music-styles/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 21:06:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1618</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Religious composers (holy minimalism) John Tavener &#8211; The LambI liked this song. I didn&#8217;t know John Tavener until&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 id="religious-composers-holy-minimalism" class="wp-block-heading">Religious composers (holy minimalism)</h3>



<p><strong>John Tavener &#8211; The Lamb<br></strong>I liked this song. I didn&#8217;t know John Tavener until today, and I was very impressed by this choral piece. It was peaceful, calm, and it seemed to be written to enjoy the echo of a church. This means that I didn&#8217;t feel sudden changes in the voices. Instead, they seemed to float on their own and slowly fade out.</p>



<p><strong>Arvo Pärt &#8211; Spiegel im Spiegel<br></strong>Another piece that I enjoyed, and I didn&#8217;t know the composer. The piano is very simple, but I think its purpose is to allow the violin to express long sustained notes. I can imagine this being played at a church, and the sound echoing through the walls. I have the desire to understand how deeply rooted this song is in Estonian traditional music.</p>



<p><strong>Henryk Górecki &#8211; Symphony No 3<br></strong>The music seems very peaceful but mournful at the same time, especially in the middle of the first movement when the soprano starts singing. I liked that the first half of the first movement seems like it is building up for a big explosion, but it never arrives. Overall, I think this symphony could be a soundtrack for a movie or documentary. I believe Zimmer thought so too.</p>



<h3 id="minimalism" class="wp-block-heading">Minimalism</h3>



<p><strong>Steve Reich &#8211; Music for 18 Musicians<br></strong>I find this type of music harder to enjoy. The simple sound and repetitive nature with subtle changes are not my preference. I understand the exploration of sounds, similar to Ravel&#8217;s Bolero, and can appreciate it to some extent. However, the length of the repetition is too much for me. Listening to it as a whole might induce a trance-like feeling and it made me wonder if this kind of music could also be used for religious purposes.</p>



<p><strong>Terry Riley &#8211; In C<br></strong>I tried to listen attentively to the entire piece, but once again, aside from the interesting exercise, I don&#8217;t find this art form truly enjoyable. What stood out to me was how the introduction of new sounds and instruments took the music on different paths. This was more noticeable when I skipped ahead a few minutes from time to time. I understand that the composer probably didn&#8217;t intend his music to be listened to this way, but for me, it provided a more interesting experience.</p>



<p><strong>Philip Glass &#8211; Glassworks<br></strong>I found this album much easier to appreciate than the previous two. Although there is still repetition, there is a sense of progression. It feels like the music is going somewhere. Some moments reminded me of Radiohead, which added another layer of interest. Another notable aspect of Glass&#8217;s music is the varied tempo compared to the previous pieces, creating interesting contrasts between songs.</p>



<h3 id="new-complexity" class="wp-block-heading">New complexity</h3>



<p><strong>Brian Ferneyhough &#8211; Exordium<br></strong>It&#8217;s difficult for me to write about this piece. I felt uncomfortable at times and wasn&#8217;t sure if I liked it or not. It seemed highly complex and lacked direction after my initial hearing. It felt more like an exploration of sounds rather than a cohesive composition. While I acknowledge that there is certainly thought behind this piece, I couldn&#8217;t fully grasp it.</p>



<h3 id="choral-music-tonality" class="wp-block-heading">Choral music/tonality</h3>



<p><strong>John Rutter &#8211; Requiem<br></strong>All of Rutter&#8217;s Requiem felt accessible to me. Even though I wasn&#8217;t familiar with the artist, there was a sense of déjà vu while listening to the pieces. It reminded me of Górecki, and I could imagine it as a movie soundtrack. The harmonies are simple, and the instrumentation is understated. However, this simplicity doesn&#8217;t diminish the emotional impact. For example, Agnus Dei felt mysterious and sombre to me.</p>



<p><strong>Eric Whitacre &#8211; Cloudburst<br></strong>The introduction was surprising and bewildering, with the gradual rise of all the sounds. I couldn&#8217;t determine if it was purely vocal or if other instruments were involved. I enjoyed how the voices floated at times, each having its own line, but I was even more captivated when they harmonized and created a powerful sonority.</p>



<h3 id="microtonality-and-spectralism" class="wp-block-heading">Microtonality and spectralism</h3>



<p><strong>Tristan Murail &#8211; Allegories<br></strong>I have limited knowledge of microtonality and spectralism, so this is a new experience for me. This particular piece left me uncertain about my feelings by the end. I attempted to identify recurring elements, but I struggled to do so. Instead, I found myself focusing on the electronic sounds and trying to differentiate them from the acoustic sounds. It was challenging for me to discern between the two. I couldn&#8217;t help but wonder if this blurring of sounds was intentional on the part of the composer.</p>



<p><strong>Gérard Grisey – Les Espaces Acoustiques<br></strong>The overall pace of the music is slow, but it has a captivating effect. The first piece starts with a beautiful melody played by the viola which I really enjoyed. It had a certain pattern that kept coming back, and I couldn&#8217;t help but focus on it. As the piece progressed, more instruments joined in, which I found less interesting than the solo instrument.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise &#8211; Exploring genres</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-exploring-genres/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 21:25:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1559</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Classical Music I haven&#8217;t been into classical music before. As a child, I didn&#8217;t have many chances to&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 id="classical-music" class="wp-block-heading">Classical Music</h3>



<p>I haven&#8217;t been into classical music before. As a child, I didn&#8217;t have many chances to experience it, and as I got older, I leaned towards other genres. But since I started this course, my understanding and, consequently, my love for classical music have grown.</p>



<h3 id="contemporary-music" class="wp-block-heading">Contemporary Music</h3>



<p>I&#8217;m not very familiar with this genre, especially contemporary classical music. Nowadays, I don&#8217;t pay as much attention to it as I do to more traditional classical music.</p>



<h3 id="country-music" class="wp-block-heading">Country Music</h3>



<p>As someone who didn&#8217;t grow up in North America, country music did not made part of my listening environment as a child. I&#8217;ve come across some interesting songs, but I haven&#8217;t paid much attention to it. Lately, I&#8217;ve been enjoying the music of Johnny Cash and Dolly Parton.</p>



<h3 id="dance-music" class="wp-block-heading">Dance Music</h3>



<p>I was exposed to this genre a lot while growing up, whether through my brother or from going to nightclubs. However, it never really captured my interest. For me, the intensive repetition of music, with endless loops, bores me. Nevertheless, I do enjoy listening to Prodigy and Fatboy Slim.</p>



<h3 id="early-music" class="wp-block-heading">Early Music</h3>



<p>I have to admit, I didn&#8217;t listen to this genre very often. My main exposure to it was during my studies, when I explored it for academic reasons.</p>



<h3 id="folk-music" class="wp-block-heading">Folk Music</h3>



<p>I enjoy listening to Portuguese Folk Music, but besides my own country&#8217;s folk heritage, I don&#8217;t know much about folk music from around the world. The folk music I am familiar with is mainly from classical compositions that incorporated elements of folk music.</p>



<h3 id="jazz-music" class="wp-block-heading">Jazz Music</h3>



<p>Jazz took some time to grow on me. Initially, I didn&#8217;t have much of an affinity for it. However, as I delved deeper into learning about instruments and music theory, my appreciation for jazz started to blossom. Nowadays, it&#8217;s one of the genres I listen to the most. Stan Getz and Billie Holiday played a significant role in cultivating my love for jazz.</p>



<h3 id="musical-theatre-music" class="wp-block-heading">Musical Theatre Music</h3>



<p>As a child, I didn&#8217;t understand why characters in musical movies suddenly burst into song during conversations. This made me dislike the genre as a whole, including Disney movies. Over time, I&#8217;ve come to appreciate the music itself, but I still don&#8217;t enjoy the theatrical and cinematic elements that accompany it.</p>



<h3 id="opera-music" class="wp-block-heading">Opera Music</h3>



<p>Opera music, like musical theater, presents a similar challenge due to its complexity and occasional intricate ornamentation.</p>



<h3 id="pop-music" class="wp-block-heading">Pop Music</h3>



<p>What&#8217;s not to like in Pop Music? It&#8217;s catchy, easy to listen to, and often uplifting. I like pop music in general, especially when it offers something unique. Current pop artists I admire are Dua Lipa, Lizzo and Mark Ronson.</p>



<h3 id="rnb-music" class="wp-block-heading">R’n’B Music</h3>



<p>I was more exposed to R&#8217;n&#8217;B in the 2000&#8217;s when artists like Alicia Keys and Beyoncé exploded. However, my recent interest has shifted towards 70s music, which features incredible R&#8217;n&#8217;B artists like Marvin Gaye and Stevie Wonder.</p>



<h3 id="rap-music" class="wp-block-heading">Rap Music</h3>



<p>Rap music is a genre that I either really love or strongly dislike. I&#8217;ve listened to a lot of rap music, particularly in the 2000s, which helped me develop an appreciation for artists like Eminem and Outkast. Recently, I&#8217;ve been enjoying De La Soul and The Roots after discovering J Dilla&#8217;s songs.</p>



<h3 id="reggae-music" class="wp-block-heading">Reggae Music</h3>



<p>Honestly, I don&#8217;t know much about Reggae beyond Bob Marley. It&#8217;s mostly unfamiliar territory to me.</p>



<h3 id="rock-music" class="wp-block-heading">Rock Music</h3>



<p>In general, my listening attention is divided between Rock and Funk, so it&#8217;s a genre I appreciate a lot. I love the combination of bass, guitar, and drums. It&#8217;s amazing how these instruments can create such great music. I also find it fascinating how Rock has evolved over the years.</p>



<h3 id="soul-music" class="wp-block-heading">Soul Music</h3>



<p>As I&#8217;m getting older, I&#8217;ve been enjoying Soul music more and more. I&#8217;m particularly drawn to Soul songs that feature a strong bass line and keyboard melodies. They grab my attention right away.</p>



<p></p>



<h1 id="exploring-new-music" class="wp-block-heading">Exploring new music</h1>



<h3 id="reggae" class="wp-block-heading">Reggae</h3>



<p><strong>Ini Kamoze &#8211; World A Music</strong></p>



<p>I like how the beats syncopate on the 2nd and 4th. The sound that catches my attention the most is the reverb—it&#8217;s a bit excessive, but it adds that characteristic Reggae touch. The bassline is wonderfully uncomplicated, yet it perfectly complements the overall mood of the song. The vocals have such a relaxed vibe, which again aligns beautifully with the song and the genre. Overall, I really enjoyed it, although I must admit that the repetitive nature can get a bit monotonous after a while.</p>



<p><strong>Freak Out &#8211; Jackie Mittoo</strong></p>



<p>I enjoyed listening to this song. Even though it maintains the characteristic repetitiveness of Reggae, I find that being an instrumental piece adds a refreshing touch. What&#8217;s more, it strikes a perfect balance with the reverb—it&#8217;s not overpowering, and I genuinely appreciate that.</p>



<p></p>



<h3 id="opera" class="wp-block-heading">Opera</h3>



<p><strong>Mark-Anthony Turnage – Lament for a Hanging Man</strong></p>



<p>This wasn&#8217;t the kind of opera I was expecting to listen to. Most of the operas I&#8217;ve listened to were composed before the 19th century. But this one, released in 1995, has a more modern vibe. The instruments used in the orchestra are diverse, including saxophones, bass clarinets, and percussion. This creates different sounds and rhythms that sometimes feel energetic and unpredictable, while other times they are more controlled and melodic. Overall, I liked it more than I was expecting. Especially the jazzy parts.</p>



<h3 id="indian" class="wp-block-heading">Indian</h3>



<p><strong>Ravi Shankar – Song From The Hills</strong></p>



<p>Besides the main differences of not having a common Western harmonic development, the difference I found insteresting in this music is the instrumentation. For example, in this piece, they use instruments like the tabla, which is a type of drum that creates rhythmic beats. It adds a lively and energetic feel to the music. There is also a shaking instrument that produces a shaking sound that adds some texture to the overall sound. Personally, I enjoyed listening to this piece and its unique style. However, since it doesn&#8217;t relate directly to my own culture, I couldn&#8217;t connect with it on a deep level. Even though this style of music may not be familiar to us, it can still be enjoyable to listen to and appreciate.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point &#8211; Contemporary music</title>
		<link>./../../../research-point-contemporary-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 22:03:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1571</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Before we dive into the topic, I want to share a quick observation. When I first encountered the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Before we dive into the topic, I want to share a quick observation. When I first encountered the term &#8220;contemporary music,&#8221; my immediate thought was about classical contemporary music. However, I questioned myself and wondered why that was the case. What exactly is contemporary music? So, I researched, and the most satisfactory answer for me came from the Berkeley website, which defines contemporary music as an approach rather than a specific genre. It involves creating and performing rhythmically, harmonically, and texturally current music while incorporating diverse influences and cross-pollination of genres (Mirisola, 2019). </p>



<p>Living in Lisbon, a big city, offers many opportunities to enjoy live music by composers who are currently active. The Portuguese music scene is lively right now, with new composers emerging regularly, while still honoring established ones. What&#8217;s interesting is that Portugal, especially Lisbon, is a melting pot of cultures, and this diversity is reflected in the contemporary music scene. It&#8217;s amazing to witness the fusion of hip-hop and classical music, Cape Verdean melodies blending with fado, and even the recent combination of Flamenco and pop music. The physical spaces complement this musical movement, showing the interconnectedness of it all. There are more dedicated venues for contemporary music, both large ones like Centro Cultural de Belém and Gulbenkian, and smaller spaces throughout the city, even the streets themselves become stages for different composers.</p>



<p>Contemporary music analysis can be quite a challenge. We&#8217;ve seen throughout history that time plays a crucial role in determining its true worth. It needs the space to grow and evolve before we can make a fair judgment. That&#8217;s when we can truly grasp what will stand the test of time and hold cultural significance in the future. I understand that contemporary music serves as a mirror of our times, capturing the spirit and emotions of the present era. It thrives on pushing boundaries and challenging conventional norms, constantly evolving to reflect the changing world around us. But at times it may be challenging to fully grasp the intricacies of contemporary music. Whenever I come across contemporary music that doesn&#8217;t conform to the usual standards, my initial reaction tends to be one of hesitation. I find myself wondering if it&#8217;s using certain sounds and techniques just for the sake of it, without a clear purpose. But I make an effort to listen and try to understand its value. Let me share an example: when I first listened to Magnus Lindberg&#8217;s Kraft, I wasn&#8217;t immediately drawn in. It sounded like random noise, I have to admit. However, as I delved deeper into researching the composer, I realized the importance of considering it within the broader musical landscape. But that&#8217;s the analytical side of appreciating music. On an emotional level, I often find that the more unconventional the music, the less it captures my interest.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1688594181439 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Mirisola, J. (2019) <em>What Is Contemporary Music?</em> Available at: https://www.berklee.edu/news/berklee-now/what-contemporary-music (Accessed: July 5, 2023).</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise &#8211; Exploring contemporary classical composition</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-exploring-contemporary-classical-composition/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 21:59:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1605</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Magnus Lindberg, born in 1958 in Helsinki, burst onto the global contemporary music scene in the early 80s,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Magnus Lindberg, born in 1958 in Helsinki, burst onto the global contemporary music scene in the early 80s, seamlessly blending different styles, from total serialism to rock.</p>



<p>Finland nurtured his composition career. He joined Sibelius Academy at 15, studying under Paavo Heininen, who fueled his interest in European trends. In 1977, he co-founded Korvat auki with Kaija Saariaho and Esa-Pekka Salonen. In 1980, he founded Toimii Ensemble a creative laboratory that became the birthplace of his innovative compositional experiments.</p>



<p>Mellor (2016) highlights the fascinating evolution of Lindberg&#8217;s compositional style. Over about two decades, he transitioned from an impassioned modernist to a &#8220;mellow composer&#8221; who crafts exquisite orchestral pieces with hints of Romanticism.</p>



<p>After his studies, he travelled to Paris and Berlin, where he discovered punk rock and specifically the German metal band Einstürzende Neubauten. This exposure changed his musical style, turning him into an &#8220;angry modernist,&#8221; (Mellor, 2016) as reflected in his most ambitious composition, Kraft (1985), written for orchestra, electronics, and junkyard percussion. When I heard it, I understood why it is considered such a powerful piece. It radiates tremendous strength, astonishing the listener with its bold changes in dynamics. It brought to mind Stravinsky&#8217;s Rite of Spring, but went even further in terms of instrumentation and a feeling of aggression. While I didn&#8217;t find it as captivating as Rite of Spring overall, there were elements, particularly at the start of each section, that I enjoyed.</p>



<p>In 1994, he composed Aura, a symphony in four movements for a large orchestra. As I listened to each part, I noticed something unexpected—it seemed closer to Rite of Spring rather than moving further away. Interestingly, I even recognized a hint of the famous Rite of Spring rhythm around the ninth minute of the first movement in the recording by the Finnish Radio Symphony Orchestra. On the whole, there is a sense of clarity, balance, and harmony that sharply contrasts with Kraft. If I had to guess how Lindberg&#8217;s sound would evolve ten years after Kraft, I would have imagined a greater emphasis on electronic elements rather than acoustic ones. This pleasant surprise increased my admiration for Aura.</p>



<p>In 2002, he created the Clarinet Concerto, which garnered positive reviews from the critics I read. Surprisingly, it is his most popular piece on Spotify. And I can see why. Compared to the previous two compositions, this piece felt more approachable, melodious, and well-structured. The instrumentation has a more traditional quality. It felt like a refined version of Aura. According to Clemments (2005), this single-movement work is sprinkled with allusions to other composers. Although I may not possess the musical knowledge to identify them, I was delighted to recognize the reference to Gershwin&#8217;s Rhapsody in Blue. Actually, that was my favourite part of this piece.</p>



<p>Overall, I was delighted to meet Magnus Lindberg. One thing that stood out in the compositions I listened to was his ability to combine tension/release. His music slowly builds up suspense, and then it bursts forth with pure joy. But what matters to me is how this demonstrates that artists can evolve and freely change their sound without being tied to a specific style. It reminded me of an interview with Rosalía where she says that she couldn&#8217;t do two similar albums because she desires to showcase her diverse emotions across different moments in time. It&#8217;s truly a testament to artistic evolution.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1688248461088 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Clements, A. (2005) “Lindberg: Clarinet Concerto; Gran Duo; Chorale, Kriikku/Finnish Radio SO/ Oramo,” <em>The Guardian</em>, 9 September. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/2005/sep/09/classicalmusicandopera.shopping3 (Accessed: July 1, 2023).</p>



<p>Howell, T. (2014) “Magnus Lindberg: Narratives of Time and Space,” <em>Contemporary Music Review</em> [Preprint]. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1080/07494467.2014.977025.</p>



<p>Mellor, A, (2016). &#8220;Magnus Lindberg: the influential Finnish composer&#8217;s creative output continues to resist easy categorization.&#8221; <em>Gramophone</em>, vol. 93, no. 1131, pp. 72+. <em>Gale General OneFile</em>, link.gale.com/apps/doc/A444655727/ITOF?u=ucca&amp;sid=bookmark-ITOF&amp;xid=0b404893. (Accessed: July 1, 2023).</p>



<p>Richey, J. (1999). &#8220;Review of&nbsp;<em>Compositeurs d’aujourd’hui: Magnus Lindberg</em>, by M. Lindberg&#8221; <em>Computer Music Journal</em>, vol. 23, no. 3, pp. 111–12. <em>JSTOR</em>, http://www.jstor.org/stable/3681247 (Accessed: July 1, 2023).</p>



<p>Tom Service (2013) “A guide to Magnus Lindberg’s music,” <em>The Guardian</em>, 16 April. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/musicblog/2013/apr/16/contemporary-music-guide-magnus-lindberg (Accessed: July 1, 2023).</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Tchaikovsky &#8211; The Seasons</title>
		<link>./../../../listening-to-tchaikovsky-the-seasons/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 21:24:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1461</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tchaikovsky&#8217;s Seasons is probably the less known &#8220;seasons&#8221; of major composers. My opinion is that, because they were&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Tchaikovsky&#8217;s Seasons is probably the less known &#8220;seasons&#8221; of major composers. My opinion is that, because they were composed for a bigger audience, including amateurs, they lack the virtuosity and complexity that pianists prefer in order to showcase their skills.</p>



<p>The collection was composed between November 1875 and May 1876 and commissioned by Nikolay Matveyevich Bernard, the publisher of Le Nouvelliste, a monthly music magazine in St. Petersburg. The intention of the publisher was to release one piece per month, but Tchaikovsky wrote the majority of the pieces between April and May 1876.</p>



<p>In opposition to Vivaldi&#8217;s &#8220;The Four Seasons&#8221;, Tchaikovsky&#8217;s seasons are composed of 12 pieces, each one dedicated to each month of the year, showcasing a glimpse of something characteristic of the month, for example, Carnival (February), The Harvest (August) or Christmas (December).</p>



<p>I would not say that this romantic work is programmatic, but one cannot definitely distance himself from the theme of each piece and hear it as absolute music.</p>



<p>My thoughts after listening to each piece:</p>



<ul>
<li>January: Warm, cosy, and familiar, Evokes a feeling of being at home with the cold outside, warmed by a fireplace and surrounded by loved ones.</li>



<li>February: Playful, cheery, festive. Just like Carnival should be.</li>



<li>March: Melancholic and distant, evoking a sense of reflection for the cold month of March.</li>



<li>April: Charming and optimistic. The end of winter means the start of spring.</li>



<li>May: Serene and tranquil, but warm just like the nights of May.</li>



<li>June: There&#8217;s a certain melancholy in this piece that I find beautiful. It looks like a very romantic piece.</li>



<li>July: The summer spirit is present with a catchy and cheerful tone.</li>



<li>August: The initial and final sections of this piece weren&#8217;t to my liking. It feels chaotic and excessively flourishing for my taste.</li>



<li>September: Majestic and spirited. It resembles a fanfare that complements the eerie ambience of this time of year.</li>



<li>October: Among the pieces in this set, this one evokes a particularly somber mood, but is my favourite. Winter is coming.</li>



<li>November: Somehow, the beggining, reminds me of impressionist pieces. It showcases familiar tunes and notable variations.</li>



<li>December: A refined and courteous waltz-like composition, that brings a warm and festive sensation.</li>
</ul>



<p>Ultimately, I think Tchaikovsky successfully captured the essence of each month, while also preserving a sense of coherence throughout the entire composition. It was a fantastic initial listening, and I eagerly anticipate revisiting it in the future.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Listening to music in film</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-listening-to-music-in-film/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 22:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1593</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Dark Knight, the second film of the Dark Knight Trilogy, is one of my favourite movies. The&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Dark Knight, the second film of the Dark Knight Trilogy, is one of my favourite movies. The reason I love it is that it portrays both the hero and villain as flawed, human characters with blurred lines between good and bad. However, I had never watched it with a focus on the music until now.</p>



<p>Composed by Hans Zimmer and James Newton Howard, the music beautifully captures the duality of the characters. Acoustic instruments (mostly orchestral instruments) dominate when Bruce Wayne appears, while electronic instruments (ranging from electric guitars to synthesizers and audio effects) take over when Batman is present. This stark contrast creates a tranquil atmosphere for Bruce and intense action sequences for Batman.</p>



<p>Intense scenes often feature string ostinati or percussive 16th-note rhythms. Ostinati create sonic continuity when using shorter note values and busy rhythms, they enhance forward momentum and drive.</p>



<p>Despite the complex character development, the main characters&#8217; motifs are remarkably simple. Batman&#8217;s motif consists of two notes (D-F), and the Joker&#8217;s motif is a single note (D). These motifs are strategically used throughout the film to highlight each character&#8217;s presence and convey their essence.</p>



<p>Batman&#8217;s motif, often played by brass with digital effects, brings brightness and hope. It signifies his moments of triumph, like emerging unscathed from the Batmobile crash. On the other hand, the Joker&#8217;s motif, a single note played by a processed cello and razorblade-driven electric guitar, creates a nervy, unsettling feeling akin to an ever-present mosquito. Sometimes the note ascends aimlessly over the D drone, capturing Joker&#8217;s anarchist mindset.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="194" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-23-at-20.57.49-1024x194.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1596" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-23-at-20.57.49-1024x194.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-23-at-20.57.49-300x57.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-23-at-20.57.49-768x146.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-23-at-20.57.49-640x121.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-23-at-20.57.49-960x182.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-23-at-20.57.49.png 1298w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The film&#8217;s core message is that Batman and the Joker are not as different as they seem. Analyzing these motifs made me realize that musically they are related as well.  Both motifs start with the same note, D, but Batman&#8217;s controlled ascent to F contrasts with the Joker&#8217;s anarchic, uncontrollable rise.</p>



<p>This exercise was enjoyable, and it sparked my interest in analyzing how Batman and his villains have been musically portrayed over time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point &#8211; world music style</title>
		<link>./../../../research-point-world-music-style/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 21:28:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1561</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Japanese traditional music, also called hōgaku, is generally defined as all Japanese musical forms from the 10th century,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Japanese traditional music, also called <em>hōgaku</em>, is generally defined as all Japanese musical forms from the 10th century, until the introduction of Western music. But the consensus is that the term <em>hōgaku</em> refers to traditional Japanese music made during or after Japan’s Edo Period (17th to mid-19th centuries) (Sonosky, 2013).</p>



<p>During my research, I found an article by Britten Dean (1985) that discusses Japanese traditional music. According to Dean, unfamiliar Western listeners often perceive it as monotonous, aimless, and shrill. The author attributes this perception to five main differences compared to Western music: monophony, scales, noise, singing, and subtlety. While a detailed explanation can be found in the article, a brief overview is enough to grasp the essential elements of this style.</p>



<p>Traditional Japanese instrumental music features unique instruments such as koto, shamisen (strings meant to be plucked), shakuhachi, fue, shinobue (types of flute), and percussion instruments like shimedaiko, okawa, and kotsuzumi.</p>



<p>Dean mentions that Japanese traditional music follows a long tradition of having a single melody without supporting chords. This can make the music seem thin and lack the progressive harmony that Western listeners expect. It may give the impression of simplicity, but an example provided by the author illustrates the complexity of a single melody. At times, the voice and accompaniment play the same melody but are intentionally desynchronized by a half-beat.</p>



<p>According to Dean, Japanese traditional music primarily relies on the pentatonic scale. This scale is evident in instruments like the five-hole shakuhachi and the tuning of the koto strings. Variations of the pentatonic scale (perhaps the equivalent of Western music modes) often result in a wider interval between the last note of the scale and the tonic, exceeding a whole step. Consequently, the prominence of the leading note is not as anticipated, giving the music a sense of lacking progression and purpose.</p>



<p>Dean also explores the idea of noise, highlighting its contrasting use in Japanese traditional music compared to Western music. While noise is typically avoided in Western music, it serves as an artistic expression in Japanese traditional music. For instance, when the shamisen&#8217;s string is struck by the plectrum, a subtle clicking sound is produced. Contemporary composers even push the boundaries by incorporating intentional beating and pounding of instruments to create a diverse range of sounds. Although these sounds may appear dissonant, they harmoniously blend with the music and are aesthetically pleasing.</p>



<p>Japanese traditional music is also known for its prominent vocal element, as the majority of compositions are sung. Unlike in Western music, Japanese singers do not focus on projecting their voices because there are fewer accompanying instruments. Furthermore, a convention dictates that singers should refrain from showing their teeth. As a result, Japanese singing is characterized by a gentle delivery and a narrower range of vocal dynamics compared to Western music.</p>



<p>Finally, subtlety is a prominent aspect of Japanese traditional music. In the past, hōgaku was intended for intimate settings with small audiences in compact spaces. As a result, the contrast in volume is minimized, and the extremes of the dynamic range are consciously avoided. This creates a sense of consistent and stable music, where the surprises lie within the subtle details.</p>



<p>In the end, I came to understand that while these features strongly contrast with Western music, there is one aspect that stands out as even more remarkable and contrasting. Traditional Japanese music has remained nearly unchanged for nine centuries, while Western music has undergone constant evolution. This leads me to believe it is a music deeply rooted in tradition, embracing gradual enhancements, and upholding a profound reverence for past composers.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="&quot;Onoe no Matsu&quot;  「尾上の松」:Tokumaru Jumei" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nwCuI3Xn7_E?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Having familiarized myself with the notable aspects of hōgaku, I am now able to appreciate them through actual listening, as demonstrated in the aforementioned example. Sankyoku, a musical form involving a koto player who also sings, accompanied by a samisen and a shakuhachi, allows me to perceive the delicacy, ethereal quality, seemingly spontaneous nature, and monophonic texture. Moreover, I find it intriguing to observe the lack of synchronization between the vocals and instruments, a detail that had previously eluded my attention.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Soloists Of The Ensemble Nipponia ‎– Japan (Traditional Vocal &amp; Instrumental Music) [Full Album]" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4emogJU_pdA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>After exploring additional compositions, I discovered that hōgaku possesses a wonderful sense of serenity, seriousness, and contemplation while maintaining a delicate balance and lightness.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1687381530744 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Sosnoski, D. (2013) <em>Introduction to Japanese Culture</em>. Tuttle Publishing.</p>



<ol></ol>



<p>Dean, B. (1985) “That `Howling’ Music. Japanese Hogaku in Contrast to Western Art Music,” <em>Monumenta Nipponica</em>, 40(2), p. 147. Available at: https://doi.org/10.2307/2384717.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise &#8211; The qualities of pop music</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-the-qualities-of-pop-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2023 15:22:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1550</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is no music that can be classified as inherently good or bad. In my perspective, art defies&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>There is no music that can be classified as inherently good or bad. In my perspective, art defies the notion of being labelled as incorrect. Poems, dances, sculptures—they can&#8217;t be deemed as wrong. The same applies to music; there is no right or wrong. Its value lies in the connection it forges with the listener. Interestingly, this notion was shared with me by a 19-year-old person I had a conversation. When I inquired about their perception of good and bad pop music, they responded by saying that good music must have a captivating rhythm and powerful meaning to themselves.</p>



<p>Considering this, it is really hard for me to tell what makes pop music good or bad. However, it is easier for me to distinguish between pop music I feel is relevant to me and the ones that don&#8217;t.</p>



<p>A truly good or relevant pop song must possess a blend of remarkable melodies, seamless harmonic progressions, grab the listeners&#8217; attention in the first seconds, and incorporate repetition. Above all, it should offer a touch of innovation, presenting a fresh perspective to the realm of music, thereby paving the way for future compositions.</p>



<p>My favourite example of pop music is Queen&#8217;s Bohemian Rhapsody. Despite being classified as Rock Music, it is also recognized as Progressive Pop due to its incorporation of various features from the Progressive Rock genre, including dramatic contrasts and frequent tempo shifts. Astonishingly, they managed to merge the three distinct sections of the song seamlessly, resulting in a cohesive piece with catchy melodies, captivating instrumentals, and powerful lyrics. For that reason, it is regarded as one of the most important songs of all time. Each time I listen to it, I am amazed by how effortlessly they transition between sections while still maintaining their distinctiveness. Furthermore, it has another remarkable feature for a pop song: it clocks in at nearly 6 minutes, yet it never feels lengthy.</p>



<p>Another example of excellent pop music, though in a contrasting genre, is Los Del Rio&#8217;s Macarena, specifically the Bayside Boys remix. This song epitomizes pop music at its finest. It dominated the charts in 1996 and even secured the No. 7 spot on Billboard&#8217;s All-Time Top 100 in 2012. With its catchy melody, simple two-chord harmony, and a blend of clave rhythm and techno beats, this song is undeniably pop. The Spanish-English lyrics are lively and empowering to women, contributing to the girl power movement alongside the Spice Girls. Furthermore, it had a lasting impact on Latin music for years to come. While it may not align with my taste nor be a song I would listen to repeatedly, I acknowledge that it possesses all the qualities of exceptional pop music.</p>



<p>A more recent example of great pop music is SZA&#8217;s Kill Bill, released in 2022. This song was an immediate success, spending 19 weeks in the top three of Billboard&#8217;s Hot 100. Its most remarkable aspect is the contrast of a truly beautiful melody with dark lyrics. This contrast is enhanced by an exquisite introduction, a captivating boom-bap rhythm, and simple harmonies. The song, superficially, sounds like a simple pop song but going into the complex composition, we find that it deviates from the typical structure and incorporates intentionally off-key instruments. It is this innovative compositional work that attracts me to the song, and it will likely serve as a trendsetter for similar music in the future.</p>



<p>Conversely, bad or irrelevant pop music is predictable, recycling previous musical forms, and attempting to ride the success trends of its time. In other words, it becomes excessively formulaic.</p>



<p>A recent example of a poor pop song is Meghan Trainor&#8217;s Mother. Following the success of her earlier hit, All About That Bass, which showcased innovative lyrics and messaging, Trainor attempted to replicate that triumph by creating a song that adheres almost identically to the formula of her previous success. It features the same rhythm, and excessively polished sound, and utilizes a familiar melody to increase its appeal. As a result, it comes across as mechanically produced, lacking the artist&#8217;s artistic vision, ultimately rendering it disposable.</p>



<p>Another instance is Rebecca Black&#8217;s Friday. Although it achieved tremendous popularity, it is widely regarded as one of the worst-recorded songs. The lyrics are superficial, the vocals are heavily processed with autotune, and the instrumentation feels synthetic. It is a song that becomes predictable from the very beginning and, in my opinion, it remains relevant today, but solely for its negative quality.</p>



<p>In conclusion, I believe that there are no inherently good or bad songs. However, certain characteristics differentiate the significance and relevance of music throughout the history of pop music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Erik Satie &#8211; Gymnopédie No.1</title>
		<link>./../../../listening-to-erik-satie-gymnopedie-no-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 13:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1544</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Composed in 1888, Gymnopédie No. 1 is one of three piano pieces. The term &#8220;gymnopédie&#8221; refers to a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Composed in 1888, Gymnopédie No. 1 is one of three piano pieces. The term &#8220;gymnopédie&#8221; refers to a dance performed by young men in ancient Greece, characterized by their nudity. Satie&#8217;s music beautifully captures a sense of ethereal beauty and melancholic nostalgia.</p>



<p>As I learned in my previous studies, Satie influenced Debussy in rejecting the conventions and rules of the era. Gymnopédie No. 1 holds great historical significance as it marked a departure from the prevailing Romantic style of that time.</p>



<p>The composition revolves around a single musical idea, depicted in the image below. To me, it resembles a steady heartbeat that pervades the entire piece, setting its rhythm and atmosphere. Throughout the composition, I anticipated an eruption or a contrasting texture, like in Debussy&#8217;s Clair de Lune, but it never arrived. Even the melody lacks such contrast, with the only variety stemming from the harmony.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="285" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-1024x285.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1545" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-1024x285.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-300x83.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-768x213.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-640x178.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-960x267.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00.png 1346w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Interestingly, upon initial listening, the melody seems simplistic and somewhat predictable, while the harmonies are surprisingly unexpected. Although I couldn&#8217;t find a tonal centre, the music appears to shift between D Major and G Major, introducing delightful contrasts, such as the A minor.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-1024x565.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1547" width="512" height="283" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-1024x565.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-300x166.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-768x424.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-640x353.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-960x530.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42.png 1228w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /></figure>



<p>After several listens, I find the music to be ethereal, creating a contemplative and soothing experience. The choice of the piano as the instrument contributes to this sensation, as it conveys tranquillity more effectively than an orchestra, such as Debussy&#8217;s orchestration. The absence of a narrative or progression in the music makes me wonder whether Satie paved the way for ambient music.<br></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point – Pop music and Classical music</title>
		<link>./../../../research-point-pop-music-and-classical-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 12:02:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1537</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Defining pop music proves to be a more challenging task compared to defining classical music. The scope of&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Defining pop music proves to be a more challenging task compared to defining classical music. The scope of classical music encompasses a wide range of definitions. For instance, Oxford Dictionaries defines classical music as &#8220;music written in a Western musical tradition, usually using an established form (for example a symphony).&#8221; Personally, I perceive classical music in a broader sense, encompassing compositions performed by traditional acoustic instruments without a vocal melody. On the contrary, pop music transcends the confines of a singular genre. Pop music, at its core, is music that is appreciated by a mass audience. When looking at the Music Genres Wikipedia entry, we discover that popular music encompasses numerous genres, with pop music serving as a sub-genre with dozens of genres in itself. As a result, the genres that constitute pop music have undergone continuous evolution since the mid-1950s. For instance, during the 1950s, rock &#8216;n&#8217; roll dominated the pop music scene, while in the early 1990s, Latin music took centre stage, and in the late 2000s, dance music emerged as a prominent force.</p>



<p>The main clash in the definition of pop and classical music is highlighted in the Oxford Dictionary of Music. According to the dictionary, &#8220;since the late 1950s (&#8230;) pop has had the special meaning of non-classical mus[ic]&#8221; (Kennedy, 1994:686). This definition raises intriguing questions. Does it imply that there are only two distinct genres of music? Does it suggest that classical music can never attain the status of popular music?</p>



<p>Among the various articles I read on this topic, the one written by James O. Young, titled &#8220;How Classical Music is Better than Popular Music&#8221; (2016)  struck a chord with me. Although I must admit that I do not agree with the title, I agree with the article&#8217;s main argument. Young states that, in general, classical music is more expressive than pop music because it possesses more expressive resources. Classical compositions often boast a broader range of harmonic resources, including complex chord progressions, intricate counterpoint, and rich orchestration, thereby increasing their potential for &#8220;psychological insight and profundity&#8221; (Young, 2016).</p>



<p>For me, Young&#8217;s perspective can be summarized as variety.  Classical compositions tend to have fewer repetitions and more unexpected progressions compared to popular music. Given that the latter is tailored to a wide audience, it&#8217;s unsurprising that they have more repetitions and basic harmonic structures to make it easier to listen, memorize and enjoy. That makes me wonder if this is why modulation is becoming rarer in popular music.</p>



<p>Given this, it&#8217;s not surprising that classical music is frequently seen as superior to popular music. Usually, people tend to think that complex works are better than simpler ones, but this is a subjective belief that might not be entirely accurate. Creating something simple that resonates with a wide audience is a difficult task, and creating complexity just for the sake of it might not turn it into an interesting work.</p>



<p>When it comes to art, I tend to appreciate simpler works. I truly believe that simple art is not an easy art. When faced with Rococo architecture and Bauhaus buildings, my preference leans towards the latter. The same with painting, poetry and music. I find it truly captivating when an artist can express their perspectives and emotions through the simplicity of their art, thereby engaging a wider audience that may otherwise be pushed away from complexity.</p>



<p>In summary, I don&#8217;t believe that the question of good and bad music applies to a discussion about what differentiates popular music and classical music. These are two music genres, each encompassing multiple subgenres, with unique characteristics, strengths, and weaknesses. Classical music is expected to exhibit greater expressiveness, diversity, and intellectual depth. Popular music is expected to have the ability to appeal to a large audience and to be more accessible to composers. Given the choice, I would opt for pop music due to its democratic nature, benefiting both composers and listeners.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1686657558924 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Kennedy, M. (1994) <em>The Oxford Dictionary of Music</em>. Oxford University Press.</p>



<p>Wikipedia contributors (2023c) “List of music genres and styles,” <em>Wikipedia</em> [Preprint]. Available at: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_music_genres_and_styles.</p>



<p>Young, J.B. (2016) “How Classical Music is Better than Popular Music,” <em>Philosophy</em>, 91(4), pp. 523–540. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1017/s0031819116000334.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise: How would you define music?</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-how-would-you-define-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 21:19:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1533</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Trying to define music is a rabbit hole that many musicologists, ethnomusicologists, philosophers, musicians, music students, and others&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Trying to define music is a rabbit hole that many musicologists, ethnomusicologists, philosophers, musicians, music students, and others alike, have fallen. Researching through Google and the UCA Library has confirmed this observation. The nature of music is inherently subjective, and it is as hard as attempting to define any other form of art.</p>



<p>Nonetheless, it is a great exercise to do, especially when starting this unit.</p>



<p>To kick off this exercise, I went into the world of other people&#8217;s music definitions. I hopped from dictionary entries to books, interviews, essays, and opinion articles. Among the definitions I found, some were analytical and detached, such as the Concise Oxford Dictionary&#8217;s description as &#8220;the art of combining vocal or instrumental sounds (or both) to produce beauty of form, harmony, and expression of emotion.&#8221; Other definitions had a philosophical tone, such as Beethoven&#8217;s perspective that &#8220;Music is a higher revelation than all wisdom and philosophy.&#8221; I also encountered spiritual viewpoints, like Charlie Parker&#8217;s belief that &#8220;Music is your own experience, your own thoughts, your wisdom.&#8221; I even came across thought-provoking definitions, such as Frank Zappa&#8217;s assertion that &#8220;Anything can be music.&#8221;</p>



<p>This helped form my own opinion about how I would define music. </p>



<p>Music can be characterized by elements that are relatively easier to define, such as rhythm, melody, and harmony. These components are concrete, measurable, and easy to categorize. And we can indeed say that if these elements are present, it can be identified as music. However, deep down, I intuitively know that music is much more than the sum of those elements. Music transcends the boundaries of its components. So, what is music?</p>



<p>In order to exist, music must have three participants: the composer, the performer, and the listener. They can be the same the person. Think of someone improvising in a piano. But the composer and the performer don&#8217;t need to be human. Think of a bird singing. However, the listener in this triad has to be human. A bird cannot say that it is listening to music. Only an human listener has the rational capability to identify the emotional impact of those sounds composed and performed by someone or something. Therefore, I believe that the definition of music has much more to do with the listener than the sound.</p>



<p>In order for music to exist, it requires three essential participants: the composer, the performer, and the listener. Interestingly, these roles can sometimes be fulfilled by the same person. Think of a pianist improvising alone in a room. However, it&#8217;s important to note that the composer and performer don&#8217;t need to be exclusively human. Take the example of a bird joyfully singing its song. Yet, when it comes to the listener in this trio, it must be a human being. A bird cannot claim to be truly listening to music, as it lacks the rational capacity to understand the emotional impact behind the composition and performance. Only a human listener has the rational ability to identify and appreciate the emotional effect that those sounds, can have. Thus, I maintain that the definition of music is largely shaped by the listener rather than just by the sounds.</p>



<p>Of course, it is fair to say that this definition could be challenged, considering that people who are deaf cannot physically hear music. However, they possess the remarkable ability to perceive and discern the presence of music through alternative means, such as vibrations. That is precisely why I intentionally used the term &#8220;listen&#8221; instead of &#8220;hear.&#8221; A deaf person can listen music by other meanings other than using their ears. </p>



<p>If I were to draft an analytical and impartial definition of music, it would state that music is a compilation of sounds crafted by a composer and executed by a performer, which holds emotional significance for a human listener.</p>



<p>However, personally, I find myself drawn to a definition that carries a touch more spirit. Ultimately, I gravitate towards the perspective offered by Frank Zappa. I would say that music is anything that the listener decides it is music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
