<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignment &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 10:08:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.5</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Project 1: Tutorial</title>
		<link>./../../../../../project-1-tutorial/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 16:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=151</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reflection Ending this Project 1, I find myself in a unique position. With a background in journalism, many of the research skills covered in this Project were familiar to me. However, this does not mean...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Reflection</h2>



<p>Ending this Project 1, I find myself in a unique position. With a background in journalism, many of the research skills covered in this Project were familiar to me. However, this does not mean revisiting these isn&#8217;t worth refreshing my mind. Journalism has sparked my insterest inthe importance of careful research, but I find that academic writing demands even more rigour in ensuring the information&#8217;s credibility.</p>



<p>I must confess that sometimes I rely on easily accessible sources like Wikipedia for research. Additionally, I tend to seek out information that supports my existing arguments, neglecting to consider contraditory sources. These habits can lead to incomplete or biased research. In my previous level, I have learned to use academic databases more effectively and to cross-reference information from multiple sources to ensure its accuracy.</p>



<p>As a creative writer by profession, I&#8217;m used to taking certain liberties with facts for narrative effect. However, this served as a reminder that there is a clear difference between creative and academic use of sources. It&#8217;s important to always ground my academic work in verifiable facts and reputable sources.</p>



<p>Perhaps the most significant takeaway from this project is the renewed commitment to analytical thinking and factual precision in my academic writing. As it happened in my first level, I sometimes find myself going into a more prosaic style, using evocative language that may not always be academically appropriate. This project has reinforced the reminder to keep a clear distinction between my creative and academic writing. In creative writing, embellishing details can turn my writing more interesting, but in academic writing, these practices can undermine the credibility of my work. In the future, I aim to use straightforward language, avoid unnecessary flourishes, and ensure that every argument is backed by solid evidence.</p>



<p>This project has also inspired me to look into the topic of &#8216;fake news&#8217; in various fields more deeply. Understanding how misinformation spreads and affects public perception is something I find extremely interesting, not just in music history but in all areas of study. For instance, examining case studies of misinformation in different fields can provide valuable insights into how false or poor information is constructed and disseminated. This knowledge can help me critically evaluate sources and improve my research practices.</p>



<p>As I proceed with my chosen pathways, I will carry this refreshed commitment to academic writing. I look forward to applying these skills to my studies, confident that the balance between my creative background and this academic approach will make my learning experience better and contribute to more interesting academic work. This balance allows me to bring a unique perspective to my academic writing, combining the creativity of storytelling with the rigour of academic research.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Statement of Intent</h2>



<p>As I continue my music degree, I have decided to pursue the Composition and Orchestration pathways. This choice aligns with my long-term career goals and personal interests, as well as my professional background and future aspirations.</p>



<p>For over 15 years, I have worked in the advertising industry as a copywriter. During this time, I developed a deep appreciation for the music of the ads we created. The use of music to create an atmosphere and convey emotions always fascinated me. This passion led me to pursue a music degree, with the aim of sustaining my creative process and acquiring the technical skills necessary to compose music professionally.</p>



<p>My recent career shift to the learning and development industry was intentional. I have always been drawn to education and the idea of nurturing the next generation. This move reflects my long-term goal of teaching music, in addition to composing. </p>



<p>The Composition pathway is my primary focus because it directly aligns with my career aspirations. I believe that composing music for ads, films, and video games requires a solid foundation in music theory, creativity, and technical skills. Through this pathway, I aim to develop a deep understanding of music theory. This will enable me to create compositions that are not only original but also harmonically and melodically rich. Learning different compositional techniques and styles, will allow me to expand my creative toolkit.</p>



<p>The Orchestration pathway complements the Composition pathway by providing me with the skills to arrange music for different ensembles and instruments. Learning how to effectively write for different instruments will allow me to create more dynamic and interesting compositions. Orchestration also adds depth and complexity to music. I hope to gain the understanding to be able to add rich textures and layers to my compositions.</p>



<p>Ultimately, my goal is to become a well-rounded composer and arranger, capable of creating music for various media formats. In the distant future, I also aspire to teach music, sharing my knowledge and passion with aspiring musicians.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
