<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Part 2 Romanticism &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 15:45:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Research Point 2.2 – Wagner’s Ring Cycle</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-2-2-wagners-ring-cycle/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 15:41:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=991</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Wagner took around 26 years to complete the Ring Cycle, which consists of four German-language epic music dramas&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Wagner took around 26 years to complete the Ring Cycle, which consists of four German-language epic music dramas lasting about 16 hours. Although the briefing asked for a 500-word essay, I found it challenging to condense such a monumental cycle to that length. The result was a longer text. I watched Opera North&#8217;s performance of The Ring Cycle.</p>



<p>“The Nibelungen Myth as Sketch for a Drama” was Wagner’s first prose sketch in 1848, which sparked his interest in the project. When Wagner began writing the poem (the libretto) for Siegfried’s Death (which became Götterdämmerung), he noticed that the heroic Siegfried had to be described in much more detail and clarity. By working backwards, he crafted Siegfried’s heroic youth story. Siegfried’s parentage and the family history of the Wälsungs are told in Die Walküre. Additionally, Wagner wanted to show how Alberich (the Nibelung dwarf) forged the ring of power from the Rhinegold. The story had been written from end to beginning, and now the music would be composed from beginning to end. In November 1874, the final score for The Ring was completed (Hoover, n.d.).</p>



<p>In Wagner’s vision, this cycle would be set at a festival and performed over three days and one evening. Historically, Wagner had been fascinated by Greek tragedy for some time, and the concept of this opera was a logical fit with those ideals (Hoover, n.d.).</p>



<p>Wagner considered this to be not just a musical composition, but an experience. He introduced the term ‘gesamtkunstwerk’, which means “total work of art”, in two essays in 1849: Art and Revolution and The Artwork of the Future. His goal was to reunite the most common forms of art – music, drama, poetry, and staging (Krause, 2020).</p>



<p>During the development of this opera, he developed much larger orchestras, invented new instruments (the Wagner Tuba was created by him), and took the staging to an entirely unprecedented level. In all likelihood, he was the one who pushed for the lights to be turned down and the drama played in the dark to ensure a better viewing experience (Huizenga &amp; Daugert, 2008). His obsessive specifications led him to build a radically redesigned theatre in Bayreuth, Germany. In doing so, he forever changed the landscape of musical theatre.</p>



<p>In terms of music, this cycle is notable for its use of leitmotifs (over sixty in total). While leitmotifs existed before Wagner, he used them creatively, altering keys, upside down, mixing them together, and more (Midgette, 2021). His music became a narrator and participant in the action, instead of just acting as an accompanist.</p>



<p>This led to the idea of a talking orchestra (Midgette, 2021). It was Wagner’s desire for the orchestra to function like the chorus of a Greek tragedy, predicting, showing, and commenting on what happens. This required sixty-four stringed instruments, four times as many wind instruments, and more prominence for the brass section than was common at the time.</p>



<p>All this grandiosity led to an enormous challenge for the singers. In addition to the length of the opera, the greatest challenge for the singers was to make themselves heard over such a powerful orchestra. The technical difficulty of singing these operas has given rise to the term Wagnerian voice: a voice that is substantial, dense in tone, extremely powerful, and ideally evenly balanced throughout.</p>



<p>Personally, I was most impressed by the amount of work Wagner put into The Ring Cycle. The more research I do, the more I realize how innovative and impactful his work was for our music. By using the orchestra as a storyteller, the music feels a lot like a soundtrack for a movie, very similar to what contemporary composers compose for movies today. It is clear now why composers like Korngold cite Wagner as an inspiration (Ross, 2020).</p>



<p>The development of the characters was another thing I liked. There is no clear line between good and evil. All characters have strengths and flaws, akin to Game Of Thrones and less to Lord Of The Rings. This makes them more human (even Gods) and complex, and the music reflects this.</p>



<p>On the negative side, I felt overwhelmed. Too much is happening all the time, with too many leitmotifs, plots, and themes. It’s true that the leitmotifs appear again and again during the operas, but there isn’t much sense of repetition that makes the ears rest from the continuous novelty. There is almost an impression that Wagner wanted to show all of his virtuosity in one work and to develop his ideas as much as possible. However, it’s always a good idea to remember that less is more.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1667572981065 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><em>Watch online: The ring cycle</em> (no date) <em>Opera North</em>. Available at: https://www.operanorth.co.uk/the-ring-cycle/ (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Hoover, K. (no date) <em>The miracle of Richard Wagner&#8217;s ring</em>, <em>Triangle Wagner Society</em>. Available at: https://trianglewagnersociety.com/resources/the-miracle-of-richard-wagners-ring (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p><em>The beginner&#8217;s guide to wagner: Discover opera: Eno</em> (no date) <em>English National Opera</em>. Available at: https://www.eno.org/discover-opera/operas/the-beginners-guide-to-wagner/ (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Krause, P. (2020) <em>The drama of Love in Richard Wagner&#8217;s &#8220;Ring of the nibelungen&#8221; ~ the imaginative conservative</em>, <em>The Imaginative Conservative</em>. Available at: https://theimaginativeconservative.org/2020/01/drama-love-richard-wagner-ring-of-the-nibelungen-paul-krause.html (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Huizenga, T. and Daugert, K. (2008) <em>The self-help guide to Wagner</em>, <em>NPR</em>. NPR. Available at: https://www.npr.org/2008/05/29/90286740/the-self-help-guide-to-wagner (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Midgette, A. (2021) <em>A conductor&#8217;s view of the &#8220;Ring.&#8221;</em>, <em>The Washington Post</em>. WP Company. Available at: https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/style/wp/2016/05/19/a-conductors-view-of-the-ring/ (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Ross, A. (2020) <em>The force is still strong with John Williams</em>, <em>The New Yorker</em>. Available at: https://www.newyorker.com/culture/persons-of-interest/the-force-is-still-strong-with-john-williams (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to The Pharcyde &#8211; Runnin</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-the-pharcyde-runnin/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 13:28:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=984</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the last few weeks, I&#8217;ve been reading the book Dilla Time, about the life of James DeWitt&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the last few weeks, I&#8217;ve been reading the book Dilla Time, about the life of James DeWitt Yancey, better known as J Dilla and Jay Dee. He was an American record producer, drummer, rapper, songwriter, and rapper. It is Dilla&#8217;s &#8220;drunk&#8221;, and &#8220;laid back&#8221; time-feel that makes his work unique and difficult to interpret, define, or translate. His production style has inspired some of the world&#8217;s most renowned pop, hip-hop, and jazz musicians &#8212; achieved, in part, because he didn&#8217;t quantize his music (Fitzpatrick, 2011).</p>



<p>While I don&#8217;t listen to a lot of hip-hop, I was intrigued by his stories and how he blew everyone away with his eccentric rhythms, so I decided to check out some of the music he produced or composed (Stadnicki, 2017). My favourite was Running by The Pharcyde, released in 1995.</p>



<p>It begins with a simple maracas sample from James Moody, followed by acoustic guitar from Luiz Bonfá. As I listen to these samples, I realize that the tempo is not always right. I start to understand why people talk about J Dilla when the drums start playing. It seems like the kick drum is rushing (perhaps running?) while the snare is dragging after the hi-hats. This results in strangely relaxed music, with an endless forward motion.</p>



<p>These kinds of not quantized drum sounds are somehow normal nowadays and explored by a lot of musicians, but I can imagine how refreshing it was to listen to such a relaxed and “humanized” beat after listening to so much on-tempo electronic music from the late ’80s and early ’90s.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1667471184588 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Fitzpatrick, R. (2011) <em>J Dilla: The mozart of hip-hop</em>, <em>The Guardian</em>. Guardian News and Media. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/2011/jan/27/j-dilla-suite-ma-dukes (Accessed: November 3, 2022).</p>



<p>Stadnicki, D.A. (2017) “Play like jay: Pedagogies of drum kit performance after J Dilla,” <em>Journal of Popular Music Education</em>, 1(3), pp. 253–280. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1386/jpme.1.3.253_1.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 2.1: Hector Berlioz &#8211; Harold en Italie</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-2-1-hector-berlioz-harold-en-italie/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 10:51:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=972</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Symphonie Fantastique, one of Hector Berlioz&#8217;s most well-known compositions, was composed in 1830. After winning the Prix de&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1666180011170 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1666180011196" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="click-here-to-see-the-briefing" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">Click here to see the briefing</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<p>Write around 400 words on your impression of the score and music. Among other things consider:</p>



<ol><li>To what extent do you find the composition depicts its programme?</li><li>What do you find extraordinary?</li><li>What catches your eye or your ear?</li><li>How is the solo viola used?</li></ol>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1666180011198" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
			</div>
</div>

</div>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Hector Berlioz- Harold en Italie [With score]" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SGkzjX6A1-s?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Symphonie Fantastique, one of Hector Berlioz&#8217;s most well-known compositions, was composed in 1830. After winning the Prix de Rome, the composer spent fifteen months in Italy between 1831 and 1832, and this experience is especially evident in Harold in Italy. Berlioz preferred the Abruzzi mountains over the academy&#8217;s environment, concerts, and operas in Rome (Bynog et al., 2021).</p>



<p>After Paganini’s commission of Harold in Italy, Berlioz finished it in 1834, not only recalling his experience in Italy as an inspiration for the programmatic structure of this symphony but also drawing inspiration from Lord Byron’s popular poem Childe Harold’s Pilgrimage. This resulted in Berlioz utilizing descriptive titles for each movement and the corresponding programmatic nature of the music since he was aiming for writing “a musical impression of the archetypal romantic hero” (Clements, 2001):</p>



<ul><li>Harold in the mountains</li><li>Procession of the Pilgrims Singing Their Evening Prayer</li><li>Serenade</li><li>The Orgy of the Brigands</li></ul>



<p>Unifying all these movements is the solo instrument: the viola. In his plan, Berlioz envisaged “a series of orchestral scenes in which the viola would be involved […] like an actual person, retaining the same character throughout”. That character would be “a melancholy dreamer in the&nbsp;style of Byron’s Childe Harold” (Deller, 2019).</p>



<p>The most interesting thing is that, facing a plan like this, a composer would be compelled to write strong, loud and bold viola lines in every movement, making the instrument and the player shine. But Berlioz took another approach. In order to create a character like Harold, he made the viola gentle, shy, and quiet. It is the orchestra that can sometimes be loud, rough, and strong.</p>



<p>I was struck by the instruction to play the viola as softly as possible &#8211; barely audible. This paradoxically draws more attention to the instrument. A very quiet performance requires an effort on the part of the audience to be able to hear it. The viola player, however, needs to be highly skilled, since it is more difficult to play loudly than softly. For the sound intensity to be maintained along the bow&#8217;s full length, the performer&#8217;s stance must be firmly grounded with solid shoulders and right arm stability (Bathurst, 2016).</p>



<p>This piece was written in the aftermath of the French Revolution and the Napoleonic devastation and trauma, when society was deciding whether to be ruled by a charismatic leader of a totalitarian or by a humane, humble and compassionate leader (Bathurst, 2016). As a humanitarian (Klein, 1969), I believe Berlioz used the viola as a symbol of the latter, being subtle and quiet and allowing the orchestra to shine when necessary, rather than being the solo instrument that always takes center stage. Paganini might not have realized this when he read the score, but after hearing it and watching the viola&#8217;s role, he understood.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Beethoven dead there was no one but Berlioz who could bring him back to life; and I who have experienced your divine compositions worthy of a genius such as yours, believe it is my duty to beg you to be willing to accept as a sign of my homage 20,000 francs.</p><cite>Letter from Paganini to Berlioz</cite></blockquote>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1666623938633 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Bynog, D.M. (2021) “3: Hector Berlioz: Harold in Italy, op. 16,” in Notes for violists: A guide to the repertoire. New York, NY: Oxford University Press.</p>



<p>Clements, A. (2001) <em>Belioz: Harold in Italy</em>, <em>The Guardian</em>. Guardian News and Media. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2001/nov/16/shopping.artsfeatures4 (Accessed: October 24, 2022).</p>



<p>Deller, T. (2019) <em>A musical outcast? Harold en italie as metaphor for the viola itself</em>, <em>The Strad</em>. Available at: https://www.thestrad.com/debate/a-musical-outcast-harold-en-italie-as-metaphor-for-the-viola-itself/9006.article (Accessed: October 24, 2022).</p>



<p>Bathurst, R. (2016) <em>Berlioz&#8217;s Harold in Italy: Leading softly</em>, <em>Elgar Online: The online content platform for Edward Elgar Publishing</em>. Edward Elgar Publishing Ltd. Available at: https://www.elgaronline.com/view/journals/lath/4-1/lath.2016.01.02.xml (Accessed: October 24, 2022).</p>



<p>Klein, J. W. (1969) <em>Berlioz’s Personality. Music &amp; Letters, vol. 50, no. 1, 1969, pp. 15–24</em>, <em>JSTOR</em>. Available at: http://www.jstor.org/stable/732896 (Accessed: October 24, 2022).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Jörg Widmann &#8211;  Viola Concerto</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-jorg-widmann-viola-concerto/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 22:45:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=974</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It was while researching Berlioz&#8217;s Harold in Italy that I came across an article by French violist Antoine&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It was while researching Berlioz&#8217;s Harold in Italy that I came across an article by French violist Antoine Tamestit. This article stated, in 2015, when he played Harold with John Eliot for the first time, he told German composer Jörg Widmann how delighted he was with the piece. Therefore, Widmann composed a viola concerto filled with narration, journeys and interactions with multiple orchestral instruments.</p>



<p>Based on this description, I decided to watch Tamestit&#8217;s performance with the Frankfurt Radio Symphony conducted by Andrés Orozco-Estrada.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Widmann: Viola Concerto ∙ hr-Sinfonieorchester ∙ Antoine Tamestit ∙ Andrés Orozco-Estrada" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_5WraTt_l_U?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>My overall reaction was one of awe and I still don&#8217;t know if I liked it or not. However, I believe that was the purpose of this concerto. In one interview, Tamestit explains that this piece is intended to disorient the listener (Todes, 2021). While I sometimes understood what the composer was saying, other times I felt disoriented and I wondered if it wasn&#8217;t just too much theatrical for show&#8217;s sake.</p>



<p>In the same interview, Tamestit talks about how the instrumentation is unusual. This concerto, for instance, requires the soloist to scream throughout and requires the pianist to hold a whiskey glass.</p>



<p>I wasn&#8217;t expecting such a theatrical performance with such an emphasis on the viola soloist. But as an homage or follow-up to Berlioz&#8217;s symphony, Widmann seemed to want to keep the viola at the center of this performance.</p>



<p>The viola is the focus of this piece, for me. As it takes the listener through the viola&#8217;s different sounds, blending and clashing with other instruments, and finding its place within the orchestra.</p>



<p>Berlioz&#8217;s symphony and this concerto have many connections, but for me, the biggest one is the instrument&#8217;s representation. In Harold in Italy, the viola embodied Harold, here the instrument symbolized itself. As I realized, Widmann attempted to meta-characterize the viola. And that was a brilliant idea.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1666218709706 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Todes, A. (2021) <em>&#8216;it is in my blood&#8217;: Antoine Tamestit on Jörg Widmann&#8217;s Viola Concerto</em>, <em>London Symphony Orchestra</em>. Available at: https://lso.co.uk/whats-on/alwaysplaying/read/1473-it-is-in-my-blood-antoine-tamestit-on-jorg-widmann-s-viola-concerto.html (Accessed: October 19, 2022).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 2.0</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-2-0/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 15:21:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=966</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[During this exercise, I struggled a lot, so I did some more research about transposing. I found this&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>During this exercise, I struggled a lot, so I did some more research about transposing. I found this video by Mattia Chiappa explaining transposing with the guitar (an instrument I am more familiar with) and explaining the difference between the two steps: writing and reading. As a result, I understand better the process of transposing and was able to do the exercise more efficiently.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Transposing instruments made easy" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/I2WzVRj9k1A?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Horns, Don Juan, bb.1-5, sounding pitch:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="263" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-1024x263.png" alt="" class="wp-image-968" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-1024x263.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-300x77.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-768x197.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-1536x394.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-2048x525.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-640x164.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-960x246.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns.png 2075w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Clarinets, Don Juan, bb.1-5, sounding pitch:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="132" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-1024x132.png" alt="" class="wp-image-969" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-1024x132.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-300x39.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-768x99.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-1536x198.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-2048x264.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-640x83.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-960x124.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets.png 2171w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 2.0: The orchestral score￼</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-2-0-the-orchestral-score%ef%bf%bc/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 15:29:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=961</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My go-to book behind bars was helpful in researching the instrument order on an orchestral score. I discovered&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>My go-to book behind bars was helpful in researching the instrument order on an orchestral score.</p>



<p>I discovered that orchestral and large ensemble scores group instrumental sections in the following order: woodwinds, brass, percussion, keyboards, and strings.</p>



<p>Additionally, no matter how few staves are present within a score, instrumental staves remain in the same position.</p>



<p>Each instrument should be listed in the following order:</p>



<p>Piccolo</p>



<p>Flute</p>



<p>Oboe</p>



<p>Cor Anglais</p>



<p>Clarinet</p>



<p>Bass Clarinet</p>



<p>Saxophones</p>



<p>Bassoon</p>



<p>Contrabassoon</p>



<p>Horns</p>



<p>Trumpets</p>



<p>Trombones</p>



<p>Tuba</p>



<p>Timpani</p>



<p>Percussion</p>



<p>Harp and plucked stringed instruments</p>



<p>Keyboard instruments</p>



<p>Soloists or Choir</p>



<p>Violin I</p>



<p>Violin II</p>



<p>Viola</p>



<p>Cello</p>



<p>Contrabass</p>



<p></p>



<p>In terms of translating instruments, these are the most common languages:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>English</strong></td><td><strong>Italian</strong></td><td><strong>German</strong></td><td><strong>French</strong></td></tr><tr><td>Piccolo</td><td>Flauto piccolo or Ottavino</td><td>Kleine Flote</td><td>Petite Flute</td></tr><tr><td>Flute</td><td>Flauto</td><td>Flote or Grosse Flote</td><td>Flute or Grande Flute</td></tr><tr><td>Oboe</td><td>Oboe</td><td>Hoboe</td><td>Hautbois</td></tr><tr><td>English Horn</td><td>Corno Inglese</td><td>Englischhorn</td><td>Cor Anglais</td></tr><tr><td>Clarinet</td><td>Clarinetto</td><td>Klarinette</td><td>Clarinette</td></tr><tr><td>Bass Clarinet</td><td>Clarinetto basso</td><td>Bassklarinette</td><td>Clarinette basse</td></tr><tr><td>Bassoon</td><td>Fagotto</td><td>Fagott</td><td>Basson</td></tr><tr><td>Contrabassoon</td><td>Contrafagotto</td><td>Kontrafagott</td><td>Contrebasson</td></tr><tr><td>Horn or French Horn</td><td>Corno</td><td>Horn/Horner</td><td>Cor</td></tr><tr><td>Trumpet</td><td>Tromba</td><td>Trompete</td><td>Trompette</td></tr><tr><td>Trombone</td><td>Trombone</td><td>Posaune</td><td>Trombone</td></tr><tr><td>Tuba</td><td>Tuba</td><td>Tuba</td><td>Tuba</td></tr><tr><td>Kettle drums</td><td>Timpani</td><td>Pauken</td><td>Timbales</td></tr><tr><td>Triangle</td><td>Triangolo</td><td>Triangel</td><td>Triangle</td></tr><tr><td>Cymbals</td><td>Piatti/Cinelli</td><td>Becken</td><td>Cymbales</td></tr><tr><td>Glockenspiel</td><td>Campanelli</td><td>Glockenspiel</td><td>Jeu de timbres or Carillon</td></tr><tr><td>Harp</td><td>Arpa</td><td>Harfe</td><td>Harpe</td></tr><tr><td>Violin</td><td>Violino</td><td>Violine</td><td>Violon</td></tr><tr><td>Viola</td><td>Viola</td><td>Bratsche</td><td>Alto</td></tr><tr><td>Cello</td><td>Violoncello</td><td>Violoncello</td><td>Violoncelle</td></tr><tr><td>Contrabass</td><td>Contrabasso or Basso</td><td>Kontrabass</td><td>Contrebasse</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
