<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignments &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2021 13:29:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reflection on Assignment 1</title>
		<link>./../../../../../reflection-on-assignment-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 07:41:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=206</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Prior to this, I had never written music in notation, had no experience with Sibelius, and my only&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="i-started-this-course-two-months-ago-and-already-feel-like-ive-come-a-long-way" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628924741753 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-2 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>I started this course two months ago and already feel like I&#8217;ve come a long way.</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Prior to this, I had never written music in notation, had no experience with Sibelius, and my only understanding of percussion instruments was limited to those found in a rock drum kit.</p>



<p>During these two months, I read various books and watched videos to better grasp how to notate music, how to listen to music, and how different instruments sound. Among my sources are:</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Black, D. and Gerou, T., 2005.&nbsp;<em>Essential Dictionary of Orchestration</em>. 3rd ed. Los Angeles, CA: Alfred Music.</li><li>Solomon, S., 2002.&nbsp;<em>How to write for percussion</em>. 1st ed. New York: SZSolomon.</li><li>Blatter, A. and Blatter, A., 1997.&nbsp;<em>Instrumentation and orchestration</em>. New York: Schirmer Books.</li><li>Adler, S., 2002. The study of orchestration. 3rd ed. New York: W.W. Norton.</li><li>Holland, J., 2005.&nbsp;<em>Practical percussion</em>. Lanham, Md.: Scarecrow Press.</li><li>Byrne, D., 2013.&nbsp;<em>How music works</em>. McSweeney’s, San Francisco.</li><li>Youtube.com. n.d.&nbsp;<em>Vic Firth Company</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/c/VicFirthCompany&gt;.</li><li>Youtube.com. n.d.&nbsp;<em>Black Swamp Percussion</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/c/BlackSwampPercussion&gt;.</li></ul>



<h2 id="about-assignment-1" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628923998205 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>About Assignment 1</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Following the finishing of the composition, I&#8217;m quite satisfied with the outcome, despite the fact that it took me longer than I anticipated. But I have to admit that making a plan ahead of time helped me stay focused and save time. This is an important lesson to remember for future projects.</p>



<p>As with all challenges, there were some parts that were easier than others.</p>



<p>Because of my professional background, I found the narrative section to be the most straightforward to write, therefore it was the first thing I did. Another thing that came naturally to me was writing themes depending on the story I wanted to tell.</p>



<p>Working with unpitched instruments was the most difficult part for me, and I often felt like I needed a pitched instrument to make a melody. Along the way, I discovered that employing various sounding percussion instruments might help in the creation of a melody. That&#8217;s what I sought to achieve with my composition.</p>



<p>Another challenge I faced was figuring out how to use the rests. Mostly, because most percussion instruments have such a short decay that the note&#8217;s duration is irrelevant and should be stated in an easy-to-read notation (Blatter and Blatter, 1997). I tried to make it simple for the players to read the rests by using the strong beat.</p>



<p>Overall, my ability to construct a 2-minute composition exceeded my expectations. The use of the variable meter has especially&nbsp;impressed me. I found it really beneficial in transmitting the devils&#8217; sense of disorder, and I ended up using it a lot more than I expected. On the other side, I believe I could do a better job of not using too many notes, or complicating things too much.</p>



<p>The key takeaway from this composition is that creating music in notation allows me to think more slowly about each section of the song and to delve deeper into each particular instrument.</p>



<p>As I previously stated, this was my first time using just percussion and non-pitched instruments, and my aim is that it will provide me with the foundations to write with a variety of instruments, specially tuned ones.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628923848042 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Blatter, A. and Blatter, A., 1997.&nbsp;<em>Instrumentation and orchestration</em>. New York: Schirmer Books, p.194.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 1</title>
		<link>./../../../../../assignment-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 07:40:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=194</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The first assignment&#8217;s brief is really exciting: to complete an unfinished ballet score called Wild Dance, of which&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="assignment-1-a-composition-for-a-group-of-untuned-percussion" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628920059263 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-2 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Assignment 1: A composition for a group of untuned percussion</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The first assignment&#8217;s brief is really exciting: to complete an unfinished ballet score called Wild Dance, of which only the first 14 bars have been completed and the sole indication is: Curtain rises &#8211; enter a group of demons. The goal is to create a complete composition with unpitched percussion that lasts between 2 and 3 minutes.</p>



<p>I looked deeper into the composition and made a few tweaks to the concept after<a href="/project-4-about-structure/" data-type="URL" data-id="/project-4-about-structure/" target="_blank"> the plan I developed in Project 4</a>. The most notable difference is in the narrative, which has an impact on the structure.</p>



<p>You can find the score <a href="https://bit.ly/pedroassignment1" data-type="URL" data-id="https://bit.ly/pedroassignment1" target="_blank">here</a> and listen to it below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Assignment-1-Wild-dance-Kontakt.mp3"></audio></figure>



<h2 id="theme-story" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628867810567 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Theme /Story</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Do you know how you feel when you&#8217;re about to do something that makes you uncomfortable? Maybe the first time you kissed a person you loved? Or when you&#8217;re taking an exam that you haven&#8217;t prepared for? Or every time you perform in front of a large crowd?</p>



<p>A lot of things happen in your head: adrenaline rushes, you feel dizzy, and your mind is filled with conflicting thoughts. &#8220;I can&#8217;t do it,&#8221; &#8220;What if everything goes wrong?&#8221; &#8220;I&#8217;m not prepared,&#8221; &#8220;I think I can do it!&#8221; and &#8220;I&#8217;ll do it!&#8221;<br>Inside your head, it&#8217;s like a war between demons and angels.</p>



<p>This is the subject of this piece. Sometimes the angels prevail, and other times your anxieties triumph. Demons win in this one.</p>



<h2 id="structure" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628867818771 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Structure</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>I constructed a structure for the piece using the &#8220;Wild Dance&#8221; as a starting point, with the form: A B C B&#8217; A&#8217;.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-regular cnvs-block-core-table-1628498574118"><table><thead><tr><th>Theme</th><th>Section</th><th>Duration / Tempo</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>A &#8211; A horde of demons appear on stage, dancing around the angels and provoking them. The angels are standing calmly nearby.</td><td>Introduction</td><td>~30 seconds at 153 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>B &#8211; The demons strike strongly and rhythmically, but with hesitation, insecurity, and anxiety. They get tired in the end.</td><td>Principal</td><td>~40 seconds at 153 bpm</td></tr><tr><td>C &#8211; The angels continue to live in peace. They are serene, self-assured, and wise. They don&#8217;t desire war, so they demonstrate this by dancing slowly and peacefully.</td><td>Subsidiary</td><td>~40 seconds at 85 bpm</td></tr><tr><td>B&#8217; &#8211; The demons retaliate, but they are stronger and more aggressive. They used the angels&#8217; passiveness to gain strength.</td><td>Reprise</td><td>~20 seconds at 153 bpm</td></tr><tr><td>A&#8217; &#8211; The demons win. Now it&#8217;s their time to make their happy dance, similar to the one in the beginning, but slower and more confident.</td><td>Closing</td><td>~20 seconds at 120 bpm</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 id="composition" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628867829203 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Composition</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><strong>Part A</strong> Bars 1 &#8211; 30</p>



<p>This section serves as an introduction, introducing the demons. I decided to keep the provided piece and extend it until the 30th Bar. The provided score begins with a motif that I utilized to introduce the demons. I used the same instruments as the demons: cymbals, tambourine, snare, and bass drum.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39.png" alt="" class="wp-image-188" width="234" height="291" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39.png 500w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39-241x300.png 241w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39-300x373.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 234px) 100vw, 234px" /></figure>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Bars 15-16 are the repetition of bars 3-4.</li><li>Bars 17-18 the tambourine is silenced for the first bar, and the 7/8 time signature is introduced to offer some variety to the dance.</li><li><meta charset="utf-8">Bars 19-20 are the repetition of bars 3-4.</li><li>Bar 21 the tambourine comes to a halt to give the rhythm a break.</li><li><meta charset="utf-8">Bars 22-23 are the repetition of bars 3-4.</li><li>Bars 24-26 the tambourine increases the strokes towards the end of the first part.</li><li>Bars 27-30 the bass drum and snare drum mimic each other until the end. </li></ul>



<p><strong>´</strong></p>



<p><strong>Part B </strong>Bars 31 &#8211; 77</p>



<p>Here we have the attack of the demons. Although the tempo is the same, the intensity is bigger with the snare having more prominence than in the introduction, giving the feeling of a faster section. I kept the variable meter from the introduction, as it passes the sense of nervousness. </p>



<p>I thought of an attack motif as an inversion of the time signature of the introduction, 3/8 &#8211; 5/8 instead of 5/8 &#8211; 3/8, to give some familiarity while maintaining the 3 2 3. This motif ends with a small pause since I want to give the listener the feeling of hesitation. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43.png" alt="" class="wp-image-197" width="244" height="302" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43.png 684w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43-242x300.png 242w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43-300x372.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43-640x793.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 244px) 100vw, 244px" /></figure>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled has-regular-font-size"><li>Bar 31 the Part B starts with a wink to Part A, with the crescendo working as the launch of the attack. I repeat it several times to work as the launch of each attack. </li><li>Bars 32-41 the snare establishes the motif. </li><li>Bars 42-46 are the repetition of bars 31-35 with some modifications.</li><li>Bars 47-57 the tambourine substitutes the snare and derives from the motif.</li><li>Bars 58-67 the motif continues and the cymbal strikes more often, reaching the climax.</li><li>Bars 68-71 the first part of the motif is repeated to reach the climax and end the Part B</li><li>Bars 72-77 the ritardando is used to transmit the demons&#8217; tiredness and build a bridge to Part C, with the Tam-Tam and Bass Drum (Bar 76) ending it.</li></ul>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Part C</strong> Bars 78 &#8211; 98</p>



<p>Part C is devoted to the angels. This section contrasts with the previous ones by being slower and with fewer instrument strikes. I want the listener to breathe from the previous strikes and to prepare for the following ones. For the angels&#8217; instruments, I picked Finger Cymbals &#8211; Cabasa &#8211; Bongos &#8211; Bass Drum. The motif came after I watched the tremolo Finger Cymbal technique in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dt6nyCLf45s" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dt6nyCLf45s" target="_blank">this Zildjian video</a>. I liked how spacial it sounded. Then I thought that the cabasa would be a good fit for the Finger Cymbals, so I researched some playing techniques and ended up finding <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UAwVq2VbBbc" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UAwVq2VbBbc" target="_blank">this video</a> showing the player hitting the cabasa and shaking it, which sounded perfect for me. The Bass drum provides the base rhythm and the Bongos provide the dance rhythm.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10.png" alt="" class="wp-image-199" width="253" height="298" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10.png 740w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10-254x300.png 254w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10-300x354.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10-640x756.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px" /></figure>



<p>The time signature is always 5/8 &#8211; 5/8 &#8211; 6/8 to keep it simple and predictable.</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Bars 78-80 establishes the motif, ending in a kind of delay sound for the cabasa.</li><li>Bars 81-94 are the repetition of the motif but with the bongos providing the danceable rhythm.</li><li>Bars 95-98 the repetition and the acceleration of the snare brings us a new attack, to the B&#8217; part.</li></ul>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Part B&#8217;</strong> Bars 99 &#8211; 120</p>



<p>This reprise is a shortened version of Part B, where the motif is repeated at first, but then the tambourine joins the snare in a new pattern to gain force in this last attack. In the end, they defeat the angels.</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Bars 99-103 are the repetition of the 32-35 bars.</li><li>Bars 104-116 we can hear the last attack, the tambourine joins the snare and the cymbal joins the bass drum. All instruments grow in presence.</li><li>Bars 117-120 are a passage to the closing. The claves enter to make a celebratory dance, very childish and naive, but very simple. Only later I noticed it sounds like the intro of Rage Against The Machine&#8217;s Killing In The Name.</li></ul>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Part C&#8217;</strong> Bars 121 &#8211; 136</p>



<p>The dance ends as it started, but is slower. Since the demons won, they don&#8217;t need to make all the rush they did at the beginning, but can make a slow and confident victory dance. Ending with the same motif from the beginning makes a full circle, meaning that like the demons in your head, they always come and go, and this is not an isolated battle.</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Bars 121-128 are the repetition of bars 3-10, with the little addition of bass drum to add more base sound, because of the slower tempo.</li><li>Bars 129-130 the repetition continues but with the increase of the cymbal and snare.</li><li>Bars 131-136 the cymbal has a little motif of 5 consecutive strokes with all the other instruments increasing in strokes until the end.</li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Assignment-1-Wild-dance-Kontakt.mp3" length="3224994" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
