<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 20:46:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>CMP Assignment 2: Piano Composition &#8211; Reflection</title>
		<link>./../cmp-assignment-2-piano-composition-reflection/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 20:46:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=209</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For this assignment, I composed a piano piece titled &#8220;Putting Bernardo to Sleep,&#8221; inspired by a short theme I played while putting my son to sleep. The goal was to create a soothing and simple...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For this assignment, I composed a piano piece titled &#8220;Putting Bernardo to Sleep,&#8221; inspired by a short theme I played while putting my son to sleep. The goal was to create a soothing and simple lullaby, with a soft and gentle melody.</p>



<p>The composition begins with a thin, but as the piece progresses, I experimented with thicker textures to add variety and depth. I also played with the range of the piano, starting with closely spaced notes and gradually expanding into the upper register. This choice was intentional, aiming to maintain a light and innocent feel, which I associate with the sound of higher pitches.</p>



<p>I incorporated octaves to enrich the sound and give the piece a fuller presence without overwhelming the intended softness. In the fourth section, I felt a modulation was needed to keep it interesting. To achieve this, I decided to descend chromatically by fifths.</p>



<p>While I am satisfied with the gentle, calming atmosphere the piece evokes, I can&#8217;t help but feel that it turned out somewhat predictable and similar to a simple pop piano music. While there&#8217;s nothing inherently wrong with this style, I had hoped to achieve a deeper, more classical sound. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Bach &#8211; Harpsichord concerto in F minor BWV 1056</title>
		<link>./../listening-to-bach-harpsichord-concerto-in-f-minor-bwv-1056/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 20:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=205</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What stood out most to me was the dynamic relationship between the harpsichord and the string orchestra. The way Bach manipulates this relationship throughout the piece creates a constantly evolving sound that kept me interested...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>What stood out most to me was the dynamic relationship between the harpsichord and the string orchestra. The way Bach manipulates this relationship throughout the piece creates a constantly evolving sound that kept me interested from beginning to end. I found myself particularly drawn to the moments of contrast: when the strings would suddenly align rhythmically with the harpsichord, or when they would stop completely, leaving the harpsichord in the spotlight, or even when the strings played sustained notes.</p>



<p>The emotional range of the piece was also captivating. While I felt there was a dramatic tone in the work, I appreciated the moments of lightness. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Beethoven &#8211; String quartet Op 18 No 1 in F major: Allegro con brio</title>
		<link>./../listening-to-beethoven-string-quartet-op-18-no-1-in-f-major-allegro-con-brio/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 20:29:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=202</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Allegro con brio stood out for its energy and dynamism. Throughout the quartet, Beethoven uses and reuses the musical material, creating a sense of cohesion and development across the movement. One of the most...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Allegro con brio stood out for its energy and dynamism. Throughout the quartet, Beethoven uses and reuses the musical material, creating a sense of cohesion and development across the movement.</p>



<p>One of the most interesting aspects of the piece was how he playful manipulates the listener&#8217;s expectations. The moments where the music seemed to approach a conclusion, only to continue in unexpected ways, kept me engaged and often surprised throughout the performance.</p>



<p>What I found most fascinating was Beethoven&#8217;s approach to thematic development. His ability to create a sense of familiarity by reusing and transforming musical material throughout the piece. This reminded me of how in modern music, the chorus often brings back familiar themes that feel comforting and satisfying. Beethoven seemed to anticipate this idea, exploring how good it feels to hear something recognisable.</p>



<p>The varied use of texture and dynamics also stood out to me. At times, the texture was very thin, with just the high notes of a solo violin, creating a delicate, almost fragile sound. Other times, the texture became rich and full as all four instruments played together, producing a powerful and dense sound. The dynamics were constantly shifting, adding to the drama and excitement of the piece.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Eugene Bozza &#8211; Ballade for Trombone and Piano</title>
		<link>./../listening-to-eugene-bozza-ballade-for-trombone-and-piano/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 21:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=200</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to this piece, composed in 1944, was a pleasant surprise that showcased the expressive capabilities of the trombone and the potential for an interesting musical dialogue between both instruments. The way the two instruments...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to this piece, composed in 1944, was a pleasant surprise that showcased the expressive capabilities of the trombone and the potential for an interesting musical dialogue between both instruments.</p>



<p>The way the two instruments conversed musically, changing character together, created a sense of unity and purpose in the performance. This interplay added depth to the piece and kept me interested throughout the 8 minutes.</p>



<p>The diversity of styles employed by Bozza was what felt most interesting to me. The progression from a ballad through impressionistic and jazzy sections to a humorous conclusion showcased not only Bozza&#8217;s intention but also the trombone&#8217;s versatility. This stylistic journey made the piece feel like a mini-tour of 20th-century musical idioms.</p>



<p>While the strong presence of the trombone added to the piece&#8217;s dynamic nature, I did find that it occasionally dominated the piano. This dominance sometimes made it challenging to fully appreciate the piano&#8217;s contribution to the musical dialogue. However, this could be an intentional choice by Bozza to highlight the trombone&#8217;s capabilities.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Toshiko Akiyoshi &#8211; The Village</title>
		<link>./../listening-to-toshiko-akiyoshi-the-village/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 21:22:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=198</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I first listened to &#8220;The Village&#8221;, I was immediately surprised and captivated. From what I read about Akiyoshi before listening to this piece, I had expected a classic big-band jazz piece. But what I...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@icedrum1"></a>When I first listened to &#8220;The Village&#8221;, I was immediately surprised and captivated. From what I read about Akiyoshi before listening to this piece, I had expected a classic big-band jazz piece. But what I found was a fusion of big band jazz with Afro-Cuban and African influences.</p>



<p>Right from the beginning, the piece caught my attention with a rhythm that more closely resembled Afro-Cuban patterns than traditional jazz. This rhythmic foundation, established by the congas and supported by a repetitive bass piano pattern, created an exotic and somewhat hypnotic mood that I found very appealing.</p>



<p>Throughout the piece, I noticed how different instruments were given opportunities to shine. The congas, in particular, played a prominent role in shaping the piece&#8217;s unique character. I found the interplay between the traditional big band instruments and the Afro-Cuban percussion created a fascinating texture that kept me engaged throughout the extended duration of the piece.</p>



<p>I must admit that my background in jazz is limited, so I may have missed some nuances. However, I was able to identify some classic big band elements, such as the strident sound of the horns and the energetic rhythms that reminded me of what I know about 1920s jazz. Interestingly, despite knowing that Akiyoshi is Japanese, I couldn&#8217;t detect any obvious Japanese influences in the piece. </p>



<p>While I found the middle section, featuring more traditional big band elements, less interesting than the opening, it still offered exciting moments, particularly in the trombone features. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 4: Comparing Dynamics</title>
		<link>./../exercise-4-comparing-dynamics/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 21:26:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=196</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In Mozart’s Piano Sonata No. 10 in C Major K330, dynamics are used in a straightforward way typical of the Classical period. Although is a manuscript, I can find some basic dynamic markings such as...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In Mozart’s Piano Sonata No. 10 in C Major K330, dynamics are used in a straightforward way typical of the Classical period. Although is a manuscript, I can find some basic dynamic markings such as (p), (f), (sfz) and crescendo.</p>



<p>In contrast, Lili Boulanger’s piece was composed in 1911, and has a more detailed and specific approach to dynamics. Beyond the dynamic markings, that sometimes are different for each hand, the piece has hairpin dynamics. Additionally, sudden changes in dynamics, such as subito, are frequently used. </p>



<p>The key difference here may come from the composers&#8217; differing approaches to their art and their relationship with performers. Mozart was likely composing with the expectation that performers would showcase their skills through interpretation and ornamentation. The sparse dynamic markings suggest a space for the performers&#8217; abilities to make appropriate choices based on established performance practices of the time.</p>



<p>Boulanger, on the other hand, was at the end of the romantic era, where we saw a shift towards the composer asserting more of their own personality through the music. It was increasingly expected to see more of the composer&#8217;s intent explicitly notated in the score. This change reflects a growing emphasis on the composer&#8217;s unique voice and vision, with the expectation that performers would follow the written instructions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 3 Melodic Doubling</title>
		<link>./../exercise-3-melodic-doubling/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 20:29:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=190</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The main difference I noticed is that the octave-doubled version of the melody maintains the original harmonic purity while expanding its vertical range. This seems to create a fuller, more expansive sound without changing the...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-gallery has-nested-images columns-1 is-cropped wp-block-gallery-1 is-layout-flex wp-block-gallery-is-layout-flex">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="2222" height="1915" data-id="192" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling.png" alt="" class="wp-image-192" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling.png 2222w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-300x259.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-1024x883.png 1024w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-768x662.png 768w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-1536x1324.png 1536w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-2048x1765.png 2048w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-700x603.png 700w" sizes="(max-width: 2222px) 100vw, 2222px" /></figure>
</figure>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="892" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-2-1-1024x892.png" alt="" class="wp-image-193" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-2-1-1024x892.png 1024w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-2-1-300x261.png 300w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-2-1-768x669.png 768w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-2-1-1536x1338.png 1536w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-2-1-2048x1784.png 2048w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Composition-Excercise-3-Melodic-Doubling-2-1-700x610.png 700w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p>The main difference I noticed is that the octave-doubled version of the melody maintains the original harmonic purity while expanding its vertical range. This seems to create a fuller, more expansive sound without changing the piece&#8217;s character. </p>



<p>In contrast, the fifth-doubled version introduces new harmonic colours, resulting in a richer, more complex texture that significantly changes the melody&#8217;s emotional impact. </p>



<p>This experiment was helpful for me to understand how octave doubling can be a technique that enhances a melody&#8217;s presence without altering its identity, whereas the fifths doubling can transform the melodic character.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 2: Colouring Two Pitches</title>
		<link>./../exercise-2-colouring-two-pitches/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 21:15:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=179</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This exercise was challenging due to the limitation of using only two pitches. To maintain interest, I focused on the following aspects: Rhythm: Varied rhythmic patterns and syncopation were crucial in creating momentum and interest....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="764" height="1024" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0001-1-764x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-184" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0001-1-764x1024.png 764w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0001-1-224x300.png 224w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0001-1-768x1030.png 768w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0001-1-1146x1536.png 1146w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0001-1-1528x2048.png 1528w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0001-1-700x938.png 700w" sizes="(max-width: 764px) 100vw, 764px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="716" height="1024" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0002-1-716x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-185" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0002-1-716x1024.png 716w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0002-1-210x300.png 210w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0002-1-768x1099.png 768w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0002-1-1073x1536.png 1073w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0002-1-1431x2048.png 1431w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0002-1-700x1002.png 700w" sizes="(max-width: 716px) 100vw, 716px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="716" height="1024" src="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0003-1-716x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-186" srcset="./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0003-1-716x1024.png 716w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0003-1-210x300.png 210w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0003-1-768x1099.png 768w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0003-1-1074x1536.png 1074w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0003-1-1432x2048.png 1432w, ./../wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Exercise-2-Colouring-Two-Pitches_0003-1-700x1001.png 700w" sizes="(max-width: 716px) 100vw, 716px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p>This exercise was challenging due to the limitation of using only two pitches. To maintain interest, I focused on the following aspects:</p>



<p><strong>Rhythm</strong>: Varied rhythmic patterns and syncopation were crucial in creating momentum and interest.</p>



<p><strong>Texture</strong>: The piece evolves from a sparse texture to a dense one, creating a sense of journey.</p>



<p><strong>Timbre</strong>: The violoncello offers a warm foundation, while the marimba provides woody, percussive patterns. The flute contributes bright, agile movements in the upper register, contrasting with the glockenspiel&#8217;s sparkling, bell-like punctuations. The trombone adds a brassy tones.</p>



<p><strong>Dynamics</strong>: The dynamic changes add expressivity.</p>



<p>This exercise reinforced the importance of elements beyond pitch in composition. It also highlighted how limitations can push my creativity, forcing me to explore other musical tools beyond pitches. In this case, the challenge of maintaining listener interest with just two pitches led to a greater focus on the rhymitcally interplay between instruments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 1: Listening to Timbre and Texture</title>
		<link>./../exercise-1-listening-to-timbre-and-texture/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 21:29:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=177</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Mozart’s “Eine kleine Nachtmusik, I. Allegro”</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Texture</strong>: Primarily homophonic with occasional polyphonic sections.</li>



<li><strong>Timbre</strong>: Bright and lively, with sharp, clear violins and warmer, resonant cellos and violas.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>



<p></p>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Bobby McFerrin’s “Don’t Worry, Be Happy”</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Texture</strong>: Mostly homophonic with a clear melody over a repetitive harmonic background.</li>



<li><strong>Timbre</strong>: Light and personal, with a deep bass background from Bobby&#8217;s voice and a bright, relaxed whistle.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>



<p></p>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>John Williams’ “Somewhere in My Memory” from Home Alone</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Texture</strong>: Clearly homophonic, with a constant melodic line moving from strings to horns to a choir.</li>



<li><strong>Timbre</strong>: Warm and nostalgic, with a bright and soft initial flute, Christmas chimes, dreamy harp, intimate violins and horns, and a bright child choir.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Florence Beatrice Price &#8211; Dances in the Canebrakes</title>
		<link>./../listening-to-florence-beatrice-price-dances-in-the-canebrakes/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 21:07:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=207</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As someone unfamiliar with Price&#8217;s work, I was immediately struck by the piece&#8217;s vibrant energy and its exciting rhythms in the piano. The ragtime influences in the first movement, &#8220;Nimble Feet,&#8221; were immediately apparent and...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As someone unfamiliar with Price&#8217;s work, I was immediately struck by the piece&#8217;s vibrant energy and its exciting rhythms in the piano.</p>



<p>The ragtime influences in the first movement, &#8220;Nimble Feet,&#8221; were immediately apparent and enjoyable, evoking the spirit of Scott Joplin&#8217;s compositions. However, it was the second movement, &#8220;Tropical Noon,&#8221; that really captured my attention. The slower tempo and the incorporation of tango rhythms created a more introspective mood that I found particularly engaging.</p>



<p>From a learning perspective, I found &#8220;Dances in the Canebrakes&#8221; to be extremely relevant to my current studies. The use of octaves in the melody brought a playful and contrasting tone. Similarly, the light texture at the beginning of the &#8220;Silk Hat&#8221; section was a great constrast with the other movements.</p>



<p>This listening experience has sparked my curiosity to explore more works by African American composers. Learning that Price was the first African American woman to have her music performed by a major symphony orchestra lended a greater significance to this piece. In particular, this experience led me to discover Fred Onovwerosuoke and his &#8220;Studies in African Rhythm,&#8221; which I plan to listen to closely in the future.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
