<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 13:15:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Exercise 4: Your Own Frame of Reference</title>
		<link>./../exercise-4-your-own-frame-of-reference/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 13:11:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Critical Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=540</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Born in 1984, I didn’t grow up surrounded by musicians. No one in my family played an instrument or talked much about music. But the radio was always on, especially during car rides, meals, and...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Born in 1984, I didn’t grow up surrounded by musicians. No one in my family played an instrument or talked much about music. But the radio was always on, especially during car rides, meals, and everyday routines. At first, I found this constant background music annoying. Over time, though, it exposed me to a wide mix of genres and gave me a broader musical vocabulary than most of my friends. That early exposure helped me develop a flexible ear and a love for musical contrast, both of which are key parts of my compositions now.</p>



<p>In college, things changed. I became more curious and started to explore music on my own. I developed a strong taste for grunge and rock, especially bands like the Red Hot Chili Peppers and Pearl Jam. This period was key in shaping how I connected emotionally with music. Over time, my taste has expanded. These days, I find myself drawn more to the classics, like The Beatles, David Bowie, and Pink Floyd. Their songwriting, textures, and innovation continue to inspire my creative choices.</p>



<p>I also joined a band as a bassist in college, even though I had never played the instrument before. I later picked up the trombone and began songwriting, all without much formal theory. Today, I mostly play piano, and this self-directed path has helped me form a personal, expressive voice that values both curiosity and individuality.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reading Task 2: Autobiography and Biography Part 1</title>
		<link>./../reading-task-2-autobiography-and-biography-part-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 12:56:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Critical Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=536</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Note on sections on Autobiography and Biography: My ideas of how biographies can enhance my understanding of musical works:]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Note on sections on Autobiography and Biography:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>The biography of composers and musicians has been an important part of musicology since its beginning. </li>



<li>Musical biography is a type of literary genre that puts in order facts about the composer&#8217;s life and the context of their life in relation to other people and specific places. </li>



<li>Many biographies include information beyond the composer&#8217;s life and expand into the assumed connections between the composer&#8217;s life and their work. </li>



<li>Through this method, the biography provides a context through which the work can be understood and interpreted. </li>
</ul>



<p><br>My ideas of how biographies can enhance my understanding of musical works:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Providing context</strong>: Situating the work within the composer&#8217;s life experiences, relationships, and the social and cultural environment in which they lived and worked.</li>



<li><strong>Highlighting influences</strong>: Revealing individuals, events, or earlier music that may have shaped the composer&#8217;s creative process and the characteristics of their works.</li>



<li><strong>Aiding interpretation</strong>: Offering insights into the potential meanings and expressive intentions behind the music by connecting it to the composer&#8217;s life and personal circumstances.</li>



<li>Considering subjectivity: Exploring the composer&#8217;s sense of self and how their personal experiences, including aspects like sexuality, may be reflected in their music.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 3: Making an Argument</title>
		<link>./../exercise-3-making-an-argumentsss/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 21:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Critical Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=530</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Popularity doesn&#8217;t always mean a piece of music is good or important. Just because a song is well-known or gets played a lot doesn&#8217;t mean it has more value than music that isn&#8217;t as popular....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Popularity doesn&#8217;t always mean a piece of music is good or important. Just because a song is well-known or gets played a lot doesn&#8217;t mean it has more value than music that isn&#8217;t as popular. It&#8217;s important to separate how many people like something from how meaningful or creative it is.</p>



<p>One reason popular music spreads so easily is because of a psychological idea called the mere-exposure effect, discovered by psychologist Robert Zajonc. He found that people tend to like things more the more they are exposed to them. At first, we might not like or understand something new. But if we keep hearing it, we start to enjoy it just because it feels familiar (Zajonc, 1968). Music companies use this idea by playing songs on the radio and in ads over and over again. This doesn’t mean the music is better, it&#8217;s just that the audience gotten used to it.</p>



<p>This shows how personal music taste is. Someone who enjoys experimental jazz might not enjoy a pop hit, while someone else might feel the opposite. Neither person is wrong. Our tastes depend on our experiences, personalities, and what we’re used to. Saying that popular music is automatically “better” ignores how different people experience music.</p>



<p>History also shows us that many great musical works weren’t popular when they first came out. Albums that later became very important often didn’t sell well at first. Some artists care more about expressing themselves than making money, and their work often inspires future musicians, even if it never reaches the top of the charts. This proves that popularity isn’t the same as creativity or long-term impact.</p>



<p>Still, many people believe that if music is popular, it must be good. This belief is misleading. Just because something sells well doesn’t mean it has more artistic value. Popular artists often have access to expensive studios and teams of professionals, which makes their music sound polished. But that doesn’t mean they’re more talented. Independent musicians who don’t have those resources can still make powerful, original music. Quality doesn’t always come from money or fame.</p>



<p>Saying that “only popular music is good” ignores what art is really about. It turns music into a product, instead of an experience. It tells us to trust advertising and charts instead of our taste. True musical value goes beyond sales and streaming numbers. When we only focus on what’s popular, we miss out on the rich variety of music that exists. Good music is hard to define, but one thing is clear: good music speaks to us, challenges us, and stays with us, even if it isn’t on the charts.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Resources</h2>



<p>Zajonc, R.B. (1968) ‘Attitudinal effects of mere exposure.’, <em>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</em>, 9(2, Pt.2), pp. 1–27. doi:10.1037/h0025848.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 2: Exploring Subjectivity</title>
		<link>./../exercise-2-exploring-subjectivity/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 21:50:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Critical Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=527</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Challenges in Proving the Statement: Process of Gathering Evidence Suitable Evidence Supporting the Statement However, even with this evidence, the statement remains unprovable as absolute fact because &#8220;greatest&#8221; lacks objective measurement. A more academically sound...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Challenges in Proving the Statement:</h3>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Inherent Subjectivity</strong>: &#8220;Greatest&#8221; is a subjective term that varies based on personal taste, cultural background, and musical education.</li>



<li><strong>Lack of Defined Criteria</strong>: The statement doesn&#8217;t specify what makes a composer &#8220;great&#8221;. Is it innovation, technical skill, emotional impact, historical influence, popularity, or commercial success?</li>



<li><strong>Cross-Cultural Limitations</strong>: The claim implicitly centers Western classical music tradition while ignoring accomplished composers from other musical traditions worldwide.</li>



<li><strong>Competing Evidence</strong>: Many accomplished composers (Bach, Mozart, Debussy, Stravinsky, etc.) could be considered &#8220;greatest&#8221; using different criteria.</li>
</ol>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Process of Gathering Evidence</h3>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Define Criteria for &#8220;Greatness&#8221;:</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Establish clear parameters for evaluating a composer.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Review Historical and Musical Contributions:</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Examine Beethoven&#8217;s compositions for their technical complexity and emotional impact.</li>



<li>Investigate his role in transitioning from Classical to Romantic music.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Analyse Scholarly Opinions:</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Gather perspectives from musicologists and historians who have studied Beethoven’s work extensively.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Consider Audience Reception:</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Look at how Beethoven’s music has been received historically and in modern times.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Suitable Evidence Supporting the Statement</h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Technical Innovation:</strong>&nbsp;Beethoven expanded the symphonic form (e.g., Symphony No. 9 introduced choral elements).</li>



<li><strong>Emotional Depth:</strong>&nbsp;Works like the &#8220;Moonlight Sonata&#8221; and &#8220;Eroica Symphony&#8221; demonstrate profound expressiveness.</li>



<li><strong>Historical Influence:</strong>&nbsp;Beethoven bridged the Classical and Romantic eras, influencing countless composers.</li>



<li><strong>Popularity:</strong>&nbsp;His music remains widely performed and celebrated globally.</li>



<li><strong>Endurance:</strong>&nbsp;Many of his works are considered timeless masterpieces.</li>
</ul>



<p>However, even with this evidence, the statement remains unprovable as absolute fact because &#8220;greatest&#8221; lacks objective measurement. A more academically sound approach would be to reframe the statement as: &#8220;Beethoven made significant contributions to Western classical music through his innovative compositional techniques and profound emotional expression, influencing generations of composers who followed.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 1: When is a Desk not a Desk?</title>
		<link>./../exercise-1-when-is-a-desk-not-a-desk/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 21:43:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Critical Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=525</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In considering when a desk is not a desk, I can identify several circumstances where the function changes the classification:]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In considering when a desk is not a desk, I can identify several circumstances where the function changes the classification:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>When used for dining, it becomes a dining table</li>



<li>When stood upon to reach something high, it functions as a platform</li>



<li>When sat upon, it serves as a bench or seat</li>



<li>When used primarily for storage with nothing on the surface, it might be considered a storage unit</li>



<li>When flipped on its side and used as a barricade</li>



<li>When used as a surface for art projects or crafts, it becomes a workbench</li>



<li>When used for changing a baby&#8217;s diaper, it becomes a changing table</li>



<li>When used for a game of table tennis (with a net), it becomes a ping-pong table</li>
</ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Task 1: Rhetoric</title>
		<link>./../research-task-1-rhetoric/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 21:40:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Critical Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=521</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Rhetoric, the ancient art of persuasive discourse using figures of speech and compositional techniques, found a powerful application in Baroque music. During this period (approximately 1600-1750), the connection between rhetoric and music was particularly strong....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Rhetoric, the ancient art of persuasive discourse using figures of speech and compositional techniques, found a powerful application in Baroque music. During this period (approximately 1600-1750), the connection between rhetoric and music was particularly strong. Composers deliberately applied rhetorical principles to move the emotions (affections) of listeners and create persuasive musical arguments (Beard &amp; Gloag, 2016).</p>



<p>The structure of classical rhetoric—inventio (finding arguments), dispositio (ordering), elocutio (style), memoria, and pronuntiatio (delivery)—provided a template for musical composition. The rhetorical aims of movere (to move), delectare (to delight), and docere (to instruct) became central to Baroque musical aesthetics.</p>



<p>Influenced by René Descartes&#8217; <em>Les Passions de l&#8217;âme</em>, Baroque composers sought to evoke specific emotional states through music (Buelow, 1973). Each piece typically aimed to express a unified emotional character, using musical techniques to arouse particular responses in the audience, similar to how orators used speech to evoke emotions.</p>



<p>The most direct application of rhetoric to music came through musical figures. Within the German <em>musica poetica</em> tradition, theorists like Joachim Burmeister and Christoph Bernhard developed musical equivalents to rhetorical figures of speech. These figures served to ornament musical language and provide dramatic emphasis to text, creating a vocabulary for musical expression (<em>The Cambridge History of Western Music theory</em> 2002).</p>



<p>Rhetorical concepts shaped the structural organization of Baroque compositions. Johann Mattheson advocated for musical works to follow a structure mirroring classical oration: exordium (introduction), medium (development), and finis (conclusion). This approach allowed composers to create coherent musical arguments that followed logical patterns similar to well-constructed speeches.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Resources</h2>



<p>Wilson, B., Buelow, G.J. and Hoyt, P.A. (2001) <em>Rhetoric and music</em>, <em>Groove Music Online</em>. Available at: https://www-oxfordmusiconline-com.libezproxy.open.ac.uk/grovemusic/display/10.1093/gmo/9781561592630.001.0001/omo-9781561592630-e-0000043166#omo-9781561592630-e-0000043166 (Accessed: 01 April 2025).<br></p>



<p>Buelow, G.J. (1973) ‘Music, rhetoric, and the concept of the affections: A selective bibliography’, <em>Notes</em>, 30(2), p. 250. doi:10.2307/895972.s<br></p>



<p>Beard, D. and Gloag, K. (2016) in <em>Musicology: The key concepts</em>. New York, NY: Routledge, pp. 76–77.</p>



<p>McCreless, P. (2002) ‘Music and rhetoric’, in T. Christensen (ed.) <em>The Cambridge History of Western Music Theory</em>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press (The Cambridge History of Music), pp. 845–879.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ORC Assignment 5: Arranging for Nonet</title>
		<link>./../495-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 21:57:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Developing Orchestration Skills]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=495</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Orchestration Structure for Bruyères Section Measures Instrumentation &#38; Texture Details/Character A Section (Calme) mm. 1–12 Clarinet (melody), string accompaniment woodwind interplay – The clarinet introduces the main theme, supported by a warm string texture. Codetta...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Orchestration Structure for <em>Bruyères</em></strong></h3>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><thead><tr><th><strong>Section</strong></th><th><strong>Measures</strong></th><th><strong>Instrumentation &amp; Texture</strong></th><th><strong>Details/Character</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>A Section (Calme)</strong></td><td>mm. 1–12</td><td><strong>Clarinet (melody), string accompaniment  woodwind interplay</strong></td><td>– The clarinet introduces the main theme, supported by a warm string texture.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Codetta</strong></td><td>mm. 13–18</td><td><strong>Pentatonic flourishes in winds, light strings</strong></td><td>– Flute, oboe and clarinet highlight pentatonic fragments.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>B Section (Doux et léger, Increased Energy)</strong></td><td>mm. 19–22</td><td><strong>Flute (melody), tremolo strings, no bass</strong></td><td>– A fragile, floating passage.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>B Section (Un peu animé, Joyeux Theme)</strong></td><td>mm. 23–28</td><td><strong>Flute and first violin (melody), fuller wind harmonization</strong></td><td>– The joyful B-flat major theme emerges.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Interruption &amp; Harmonic Shift</strong></td><td>mm. 29–32</td><td><strong>Woodwinds in interplay, shifting harmonies, subtle strings</strong></td><td>– A sudden change in character.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Return of Joyeux Theme</strong></td><td>mm. 33–37</td><td><strong>Clarinet, and first violin (melody), richer orchestration</strong></td><td>– The joyful theme returns.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>A&#8217; Section</strong></td><td>mm. 38–44</td><td><strong>Winds and first violin (melody), fuller strings</strong></td><td>– A smooth transition back to A-flat major.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Coda (En retenant)</strong></td><td>mm. 45–end</td><td><strong>Flute and oboe (melody), sustained strings for warmth</strong></td><td>– A gentle conclusion with light, floating textures.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Reflective Commentary</h2>



<p>My primary objective was to preserve the light, flowing nature of the piece while showcasing the unique timbral qualities of each instrument.</p>



<p>In the opening section (bars 1–13), I assigned the clarinet the lead melody, introducing the theme with warmth and fluidity. However, rather than maintaining a single lead voice, I opted to distribute the melodic material among the other winds, allowing for a gentle interplay that mirrors Debussy’s coloristic approach. The first violin serves as an accompanying voice, grounding the harmony while maintaining a sense of lightness.</p>



<p>Bars 14–18 introduce a delicate woodwind exchange, making the texture more transparent. I chose this approach to prevent the orchestration from becoming too dense, maintaining the prelude’s airy quality. The section from bars 19–22 is particularly fragile, with tremolo strings and soft flute lines contributing to an ethereal soundscape. Here, I stripped away the bass voices to enhance the sense of weightlessness, emphasizing Debussy’s harmonic ambiguity.</p>



<p>At bar 23, the violin takes over the melody, accompanied by the flute, to introduce a brighter, more lyrical quality. This decision was made to highlight the shift in character while maintaining a delicate balance between strings and winds. The sudden contrast in bar 29 sees the woodwinds take control again, engaging in a dynamic interplay.</p>



<p>Returning to the earlier theme in bar 33, I combined the clarinet and violin to create a rich, expressive timbre. This section builds toward the final passage, where flute, oboe, and violin enhance the drama before the coda’s serene resolution. To conclude, I used flute and oboe in the final bars to impart a sense of weightlessness and tranquility.</p>



<p>The greatest challenge was balancing the independence of each instrument while ensuring cohesion. I did not make any dramatic changes to the piece’s harmony and melody but rather chose to play with timbres. By distributing the melodic and harmonic roles, I aimed to maintain the impressionistic essence of <em>Bruyères</em>, capturing its fluidity while exploring the distinct colors of the nonet.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Robert Schumann &#8211; Intermezzo from Faschingsschwank aus Wien, Op. 26</title>
		<link>./../listening-to-robert-schumann-intermezzo-from-faschingsschwank-aus-wien-op-26/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 22:26:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Developing Orchestration Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=519</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The contrast between the flowing accompaniment and the slower, expressive melody creates a sense of emotional push and pull, as if the music is caught between longing and unrest. There is something almost poetic about...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The contrast between the flowing accompaniment and the slower, expressive melody creates a sense of emotional push and pull, as if the music is caught between longing and unrest. There is something almost poetic about the way the melody unfolds, and I am particularly drawn to how Schumann maintains a sense of melancholy even in moments of intensity.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to João Gilberto &#8211; Estate</title>
		<link>./../listening-to-joao-gilberto-estate/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 22:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Developing Orchestration Skills]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=517</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[At first, I wasn’t sure what language João Gilberto was singing in. His Brazilian accent makes the Italian lyrics sound unique. Once I realized it was Italian, it made perfect sense. The piece feels like...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>At first, I wasn’t sure what language João Gilberto was singing in. His Brazilian accent makes the Italian lyrics sound unique. Once I realized it was Italian, it made perfect sense. The piece feels like a fusion of Ennio Morricone’s cinematic style and the relaxed sophistication of bossa nova. I love how the orchestral elements create a dreamy atmosphere, while the guitar keeps it grounded in a more intimate style. </p>



<p>The piece begins with an orchestral introduction, featuring what sounds like a saxophone and flute, supported by rich, flowing strings. This creates a smooth, cinematic atmosphere. When the acoustic guitar enters, it immediately adds the tone, bringing the familiar syncopated rhythm and warm chord voicings of bossa nova. The contrast between the orchestral backdrop and the guitar makes the texture feel both sophisticated and intimate.</p>



<p>The timbre is warm and smooth, with the strings providing a velvety foundation while the saxophone and flute add a light, airy touch. The acoustic guitar’s soft, rhythmic strumming brings a sense of familiarity and warmth, grounding the piece in the bossa nova tradition. João Gilberto’s voice, with its signature breathy quality adding to the song’s nostalgic and reflective mood.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 2: Bartók Orchestration</title>
		<link>./../exercise-2-bartok-orchestration/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 22:25:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Developing Orchestration Skills]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../index.html?p=492</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The original composition has a lively dialogue between the left and right hands, using a rising and falling three-note motif. This interplay led me to a distribution among the woodwind instruments to capture the piece&#8217;s...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The original composition has a lively dialogue between the left and right hands, using a rising and falling three-note motif. This interplay led me to a distribution among the woodwind instruments to capture the piece&#8217;s playful character.</p>



<p><strong>Instrumentas:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>In bars 1-7, the piano&#8217;s left and right hands engage in a conversation based on a three-note motif. To emulate this interplay, I assigned the left-hand part to the oboe and the right-hand part to the clarinet, with the bassoon and horn punctuating.</li>



<li>Beginning at bar 9, the right hand explores higher pitches with repeated F6 notes followed by a new melody. Introducing the flute at this part captured the airy quality of this passage.</li>



<li>In bars 26-27, where the dialogue shifts to the bass clef, I employed the clarinet with the horn and bassoon to maintain the depth of the lower register.</li>



<li>Sustained notes and countermelodies in the lower register, often moving in parallel, are recurring elements. Assigning these parts to the horn and bassoon provided a warm harmonic foundation that contrasted with the brighter tones of the oboe, clarinet, and flute.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
