<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 20:05:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Wendy Carlos &#8211; March from A Clockwork Orange</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-wendy-carlos-march-from-a-clockwork-orange/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 23:26:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=2002</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By my tutor&#8217;s suggestion, I heard the work Wendy Carlos did with the Clockwork Orange soundtrack and was&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>By my tutor&#8217;s suggestion, I heard the work Wendy Carlos did with the Clockwork Orange soundtrack and was amazed by the mixture of classical and electronic music, especially with Beethoven&#8217;s 9th symphony.</p>



<p>From my research, Carlos was one of the pioneers of synthesizers, working with Robert Moog to develop the famous Moog synthesizer. She launched the hugely controversial Switched-on Bach album with music by Bach performed on a Moog synthesizer. Later, she continued combining synthesized and classical music, and she combined Beethoven&#8217;s 9th Symphony with a new hardware that converted the human voice into electronic signals and would later be famously known as a vocoder.</p>



<p>This is the work that ended up in Clockwork Orange&#8217;s soundtrack and has an important role in it. Beethoven&#8217;s music works as a leitmotif for the main character, Alex, and violence. In the beginning, the music is acoustic, but after Alex&#8217;s shock therapy, the music is synthesized. The effect on the listener is quite radical and direct. What was once familiar, rooted in the past, and established, turns into a weird, futuristic, and almost childish sound. The vocoder works perfectly into making the famous choir turn into robots, which can be seen as a direct relation to what happens on screen: the deviant character is forced into normalcy.</p>



<p>Musically speaking, I really enjoyed listening to it. The sound sounds fresh even though it was composed in 1972, but that&#8217;s no surprise because synthesizers and vocoders are more and more common in contemporary music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Muse -Exogenesis: Symphony</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-muse-exogenesis-symphony/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 22:01:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1996</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I heard this piece when trying to find pieces for the assignment. Although I would love to explore&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I heard this piece when trying to find pieces for the assignment. Although I would love to explore it in a deeper level, I didn&#8217;t find it fit the assignment context. Nevertheless, I listened to it several times, and found that it&#8217;s filled with romantic composers influences.</p>



<p>Muse, and especially its main composer, Matt Bellamy, are a contemporary rock band that is self-admittedly influenced by classical music. One can find direct usage of music from previous eras such as Palestrina&#8217;s Sanctus and Benedictus rearrangement in the music Drones; Saint-Saëns&#8217;s Mon cœur s&#8217;ouvre à ta voix in I Belong to You; and Tchaikovsky&#8217;s &#8216;Piano Concerto No.1: Allegro Non Troppo E Molto Maestoso in Hoodoo. But there are far more examples of direct influence such as Bach&#8217;s toccatas in Plug In Baby, The Handler and In Your World;</p>



<p>Exogenesis: Symphony is divided into three movements entitled &#8220;Overture&#8221;, &#8220;Cross-Pollination&#8221; and &#8220;Redemption, and has a programmatic story of humanity coming to an end and everyone pinning their hopes on a group of astronauts who go out to explore space and spread humanity to another planet. Matt Bellamy, the composer, said that this composition was &#8220;influenced by Rachmaninov, Strauss, Chopin and Pink Floyd.&#8221;</p>



<p>Right from the beginning of the piece, I can find similarities with Wagner&#8217;s The Rhinegold prelude. The floating arpeggios building up on top of a drone bass, creating a long and slow build up and setting the mood, made it look like at least the composer used the same style as Wagner&#8217;s. This establishes the beginning of the programme of humanity coming to an end.</p>



<p>When Bellamy&#8217;s voice enters, it is with a long falsetto that is not common in rock music. The several repeated questions that the lyrics present, go very well with the repetition of the arpeggios.</p>



<p>The second movement starts with only a piano playing a chromatic introduction that resembles Chopin&#8217;s Etude n°10 opus 25. The next part resembles Liszt&#8217;s Transcendental Etude No.5, Feux Follets. But another quick change in mood brings an accompaniment that sounds again like Chopin, in this case, his Nocturne op.9 n°2 in E flat Major.</p>



<p>The beginning of the third movement has a straightforward feeling of Beethoven&#8217;s Piano Sonata No. 14, mostly because of its triplets arpeggios, but for me it brought to mind the melody of Liszt&#8217;s Liebestraum No. 3 in the insisting high note.</p>



<p>Overall, I really liked this song, although it&#8217;s not my favourite from Muse, I like how they were able to mix classical influences in a somehow Rock Opera while at the same time sounding like Muse.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Arturo Márquez &#8211; Danzón No. 2</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-arturo-marquez-danzon-no-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 22:57:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1999</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I recently came across this piece on social media and quickly remembered of having heard it before in&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I recently came across this piece on social media and quickly remembered of having heard it before in the TV show Mozart In The Jungle. However, I hadn&#8217;t given it much attention until now. I&#8217;ve just listened to the performance of the Orquesta Sinfónica Simón Bolívar conducted by Gustavo Dudamel.</p>



<p>This is the type of music I am naturaly drawn to. Great melodies combined with a dancing Latin rhythm is something that I find fits beautifully with an orchestral setting.</p>



<p>Here I found the instrumentation to be interesting, not only for the inclusion of non-traditional Western instruments like the Claves and the Guiro, but also the use of the violas as guitars with their strings being plucked.</p>



<p>The opening minutes of the piece have a medley-like quality, with various rhythms and tonal colors unfolding. From the smooth melodic start on the winds, passing to the strings and then a build-up of the piano before the full orchestra blows in a surge of powerful brass and percussion, instantly recognisable as a quintessential Latin sound.</p>



<p>This change in mood is perhaps what I liked more about this piece. The melodies are beautiful and soft, but when the rhythmic part enters in action, the whole piece gains an energy that is danceable and contagious.</p>



<p>Overall, I thoroughly enjoyed this piece, and since I&#8217;m not yet familiar with the work of Arturo Márquez, I&#8217;m eager to explore more of his compositions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
