<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 23:10:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reflection</title>
		<link>./../../../../reflection-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 09:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1860</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Studying Part Three was a real mix of feelings for me. I love the Romantic era in music&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Studying Part Three was a real mix of feelings for me. </p>



<p>I love the Romantic era in music – it’s my favourite. Especially because I like seeing how history has shaped today&#8217;s music and this era was particularly impactful in today&#8217;s music. During the Romantic era, people started to see musicians as heroes which is reflected in today&#8217;s famous artists. Music and songs became a way for them to share deep feelings. I also enjoyed learning about how music started to reach more people, making it easier for regular folks to enjoy and play. It was a time for the democratisation of music. </p>



<p>The exploration of Romantic-era music ignited this fascination with the concept of musical evolution. How composers drew inspiration from their predecessors, adapted styles to suit their creative vision, and eventually paved the way for new musical forms was truly inspiring.</p>



<p>But, even though I liked studying this period in music, I also missed doing the compositional part of my course: writing and making music is what excites me. That hands-on part is something I look forward to and wish I had more of now.</p>



<p>Similar to my experience with the previous parts of my learning, I encountered challenges in managing my time effectively. However, the support and guidance from my tutor played a great role in keeping me motivated and determined to make progress, no matter how slow it may have seemed. I&#8217;ve come to realize that the journey of learning is not always about speed, but about the steady and dedicated progress one makes, regardless of the pace.</p>



<p>One part I feel good about is my assignment on how pianos changed in the Romantic era. I spent a lot of time researching and it paid off. I wrote a well-structured text that shows how the piano became key to all kinds of music.</p>



<p>Despite the challenges, I felt a sense of accomplishment as I progressed through Part Three. The time and effort invested were worth it, as I had gained a deeper understanding of the Nineteenth century&#8217;s music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 3</title>
		<link>./../../../../assignment-3-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 08:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1853</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lately, I’ve been interested in the piano as a player and listener. Therefore, I decided to research its&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Lately, I’ve been interested in the piano as a player and listener. Therefore, I decided to research its development during the Romantic era. A new emphasis on powerful emotion, individualism and expressiveness in the arts characterised this period. As opposed to the reason and order valued during the Enlightenment, Romantic artists sought to explore the full range of human emotion and experience. Music was profoundly impacted by this philosophical shift, with composers experimenting with passionate, dramatic works to evoke strong sentiments from audiences. The piano emerged during this period as a revolutionary instrument that epitomised the Romantic spirit.</p>



<p>Gill Green&#8217;s &#8220;History of Piano Tuning&#8221; (2020) discusses the nineteenth-century upheaval and innovation in the piano industry, highlighting the rapid advancements during that time. The main innovation was the ability of this instrument to vary tone and volume based on touch, unlike the fixed volume of the harpsichord. Implementing metal and heavier wooden frames allowed for increased string tension and enhanced the piano&#8217;s capacity for thunderous fortissimo and delicate pianissimo voicings. The new double escapement action enabled rapid repeated notes through its responsive key return and hammer resetting mechanisms. Also, the expanded keyboard range of over seven octaves permitted a wider spectrum of tonal colour.</p>



<p>Ultimately, the new piano&#8217;s capabilities made the Romantic era paying audiences, especially the middle class, captivated by its ability to channel profound personal expression. This demand fuelled the prominence of new miniature genres and forms such as short piano compositions which perfectly showcased the piano&#8217;s expressive versatility.</p>



<p>Conversely, composers started exploiting the piano&#8217;s rich harmonies, creating melodies and dynamic gradations to conjure passion, conflict, intimacy and all shades of Romantic experience.</p>



<p>For example, Chopin&#8217;s nocturnes, such as his famous Nocturne Op. 9 No.2, spotlight the instrument&#8217;s singing lyricism and range of colouristic voicings to evoke moods from brooding melancholy to gentle bliss. Also, his études and preludes for solo piano, the Prelude Op. 28, no. 4 in E minor and no. 20 in C minor being two great examples for me, capturing shifting qualities of emotion through intense passages and lyrical melodies.  Chopin brought the bel canto to the piano, redefining its expressive capabilities and influencing generations of pianists and composers to come. </p>



<p>The piano&#8217;s expanding expressive powers also began to influence the sound and direction of Romantic orchestral music. No longer confined to a supporting continuo role, the piano emerged as a prominent solo voice within the rich orchestral texture, providing a contrasting intimate quality. Composers increasingly incorporated the piano as a soloist in concertos and symphonic works, juxtaposing its unique timbre and dynamic fluctuations against the grand orchestral forces.</p>



<p>For example, Brahms’ Second Piano Concerto integrates the solo piano part as an equal partner in dialogue with the orchestra, accompanying or contrasting with its passages. The most beautiful parts are when the piano adds a dimension of lyrical sensitivity and virtuosity to balance the orchestra&#8217;s imposing, expansive passages. Similarly, Tchaikovsky’s First Piano Concerto exploits the piano&#8217;s capacity for thunderous bravura and whisper-soft poeticism, especially in the third movement. It transitions from soft, to playful, to a raging force, enlivening the dramatic trajectory of the piece.</p>



<p>The piano&#8217;s small size and versatility had a significant impact backstage and may have contributed to the development of large-scale works such as ballet. According to Parakilas (1999), the rehearsal of operas, ballets, oratorios, orchestral works, and masses, was greatly influenced by the piano, as one instrument could stand in for an entire orchestra during rehearsals. This allowed singers, dancers, and solo performers to practice more affordably and efficiently.</p>



<p>The piano provided an ideal creative canvas for Romantic composers to explore new musical forms that departed from Classical norms. Short and personal forms emerged during the Romantic era as vehicles for piano solo composition such as rhapsody, nocturne, and song cycle. They all showcased the composer as well as the pianist’s virtuosity. Audiences were drawn to the drama and excitement of watching pianists conquer seemingly impossible passages and spark deep emotions through their playing. The spectacle of the virtuoso at the keyboard cultivated a “cult of genius” surrounding renowned pianist-composers. Their impassioned expressions of Romanticism struck a chord with middle-class audiences, who saw these artists as visionaries unveiling profound truths through music.</p>



<p>Liszt in particular cultivated an ultra-Romantic ideal of meritocracy, encapsulated in his quote “My talent ennobles me,” as noted by Greenberg (2013) in his analysis of Romantic era composers. Liszt became a hugely famous star, admired by audiences for his virtuosic piano skills. The poet Heinrich Heine coined the term &#8220;Lisztomania&#8221; to describe the frenzy surrounding Liszt&#8217;s celebrity and performances, which were known for dazzling technical displays. His prowess at the piano made him an iconic embodiment of the Romantic ethos of the artist-hero. His Piano Sonata in B Minor showcases how he could compose extremely technically demanding passages, pushing the boundaries of what was considered possible on the piano.</p>



<p>In addition to Liszt&#8217;s virtuosity, Clara Schumann, one of the female pianists to enjoy acclaim during this male-dominated era, set new standards for performance by playing recitals and concertos from memory, being a skilled improviser who brought creativity to her performances, and promoting contemporary composers like her husband Robert Schumann and Johannes Brahms.</p>



<p>Character pieces for piano also flourished during the Romantic period. These brief works captured a single mood, place, person or situation through music. Titles like Chopin’s “Raindrop” Prelude, Mendelssohn’s “Song Without Words” and Schumann’s “Scenes from Childhood” gave clues to the miniatures’ poetic aims. This genre allowed experimentation with new harmonies, textures and forms within a condensed timeframe ranging from just one to ten minutes in length typically.</p>



<p>The condensed scope, alongside the small size of the piano and the development of publishing, made character pieces quite accessible to amateur pianists. These short piano works proliferated in musical salons and amateur recitals alongside the more ambitious sonatas and concertos aimed at virtuoso performers. Even complex programmatic cycles like Schumann’s Carnaval incorporated character pieces as movements. The character piece&#8217;s brevity and focus suited the more casual playing of non-professionals in home settings. With the rise of sheet music distribution, amateurs could readily acquire these bite-sized impressionistic works to perform for their own enjoyment or for small gatherings of friends and family.</p>



<p>This also led to the development of art songs, with composers sometimes organising songs with similar themes into collections called song cycles. Schubert notably created song cycles like “The Fair Maid of the Mill” and “Winter Journey,” based on the poems of German poet Muller, both evoking feelings of sadness.</p>



<p>As the piano became more accessible, art songs became a popular genre for home music-making, providing women in the 19th century a unique opportunity. This led to an increase in compositions by women composers, unprecedented in previous centuries, resulting in their rise to fame. Fanny Mendelssohn Hensel, for example, composed about 500 musical pieces, including approximately 120 for piano and many art songs (Lieder), such as the elegant piece “Warum sind den die Rosen so blass.”</p>



<p>By cultivating these innovative genres for solo piano, Romantic composers ensured the instrument remained at the heart of mainstream middle-class musical culture. Whether expressed through compact character sketches or sprawling sonata structures, the piano gave Romantic composers their ideal canvas to paint bold new musical narratives filled with drama, poetry and intimacy previously unexplored in past eras. </p>



<p>The instrument shaped both listening habits and amateur music-making for generations to come. Its influence has been so profound that it is now the only instrument that features across all popular Western musical genres, including jazz, hip-hop, EDM, and rock.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1706305140689 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Green, G. (2020) <em>The history of piano tuning</em>. In: PTA News 04/2020 p.10.</p>



<p>Parakilas, J. (1999) <em>Piano roles: Three Hundred Years of Life with the Piano</em>. Yale University Press.</p>



<p>Greenberg, R. and Courses, T.G. (2013) <em>How to Listen to and Understand Great Music, 3rd Edition</em>. The Great Courses.</p>



<p>Hall, D. (2022) <em>Chapter 15: Music of the Romantic Era</em>. https://louis.pressbooks.pub/exploringarts/chapter/575/.</p>



<p>White, W.B. (2022) <em>Theory and practice of piano construction: With a Detailed, Practical Method for Tuning</em>.</p>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (2023a)  <em>Romanticism | Definition, characteristics, artists, history, art, poetry, literature, &amp; music</em>. https://www.britannica.com/art/Romanticism/Music.</p>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (2023a) <em>Fanny Mendelssohn | Romantic era, female composer, piano works</em>. https://www.britannica.com/biography/Fanny-Mendelssohn.</p>



<p><em>Get to know: Clara Schumann | LA Phil</em> (no date). https://www.laphil.com/about/watch-and-listen/get-to-know-clara-schumann.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Chopin &#8211; Nocturne Eb major Op. 9 no. 2 </title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-chopin-nocturne-eb-major-op-9-no-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 22:39:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1873</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As one of Chopin&#8217;s most famous piano works, I&#8217;ve heard this lovely Nocturne many times before but listened&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As one of Chopin&#8217;s most famous piano works, I&#8217;ve heard this lovely Nocturne many times before but listened to it closely again recently. True to the nocturne style, it&#8217;s a short, simple piece with a straightforward structure centred on a lovely, almost naive melody that is instantly accessible and deeply romantic. The focus is absolutely on the long-lined vocal quality of the melody rather than complex harmonies, which remain mostly diatonic throughout. </p>



<p>While there&#8217;s not much harmonic tension, the interest comes from Chopin&#8217;s ornamentation that showcases the piano&#8217;s ability to quickly change notes, including trills, turns, and appoggiaturas. Despite its simplicity, or perhaps because of it, this nocturne is profoundly emotional to me. The famous melody is so classically romantic and intimate, that it&#8217;s no wonder it has moved listeners for almost 200 years.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Chopin &#8211; Prelude No 4 in E minor, Op 28</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-chopin-prelude-no-4-in-e-minor-op-28/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 23:07:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1876</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is probably my favourite Chopin piece and one of my all-time favourite piano works. The sheer amount&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is probably my favourite Chopin piece and one of my all-time favourite piano works. The sheer amount of emotion Chopin packs into this short and simple prelude never ceases to amaze me. It feels heavy, deep, and lamenting &#8211; almost like a funeral march. The constant, heartbeat-like rhythm creates a dark and brooding atmosphere, especially when combined with the descending harmonic progression that forms the backdrop of the piece.</p>



<p>There is barely any melody to speak of, just a simple descending scale figure that is repeated and varied. Yet despite its simplicity, the melody is incredibly lyrical and sings with a beautiful, melancholic tone. In this relatively basic musical texture, Chopin captures something raw and overwhelmingly human.</p>



<p>The ending is my favourite part &#8211; the way Chopin delays the final cadence builds the tension to almost unbearable levels before resolving. That tragic, delayed resolution encapsulates the mournful and evocative nature of this stunning prelude.</p>



<p><a href="https://girlinbluemusic.com/the-power-of-chopins-prelude-in-e-minor-op-28-no-4/#:~:text=The%20piece%20is%20one%20page,so%20effective%20from%20this%20texture." target="_blank"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Brahms &#8211; Piano Concerto No. 2 in B-flat major Op. 83</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-brahms-piano-concerto-no-2-in-b-flat-major-op-83/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 22:09:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1879</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I listened to Yuja Wang&#8217;s performance of this concerto, I was drawn into a musical conversation. The&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When I listened to Yuja Wang&#8217;s performance of this concerto, I was drawn into a musical conversation. The piano starts quietly, making small talk with the orchestra. But soon it shows a bold personality, interrupting the orchestra strongly.</p>



<p>There&#8217;s something remarkably compelling when the piano interrupts the orchestra. It&#8217;s like the small piano is shouting against the group. These interruptions give the concerto a sense of struggle and triumph that adds to the piece&#8217;s drama.</p>



<p>Sometimes it sounds like the piano and orchestra are having a dynamic conversation, taking turns. Other times they angrily argue, competing for attention. This conversation keeps changing from calm to passionate. The piano brings thoughtful melody and skill, balancing the orchestra&#8217;s powerful sections.</p>



<p>In the second movement, the dramatic piano storms against the mellow orchestra. The orchestra sometimes responds mildly, creating a vivid contrast that heightens the overall excitement of the movement.</p>



<p>The gentle third movement has a flowing lyricism, with the cello spinning a beautiful song. This movement is rich and sumptuous. It&#8217;s a peaceful contrast from all the arguments before.</p>



<p>But it is the final movement that leaves an indelible mark. Here, the piano shifts from gracious to loud and forceful. The piano showcases its full range of expression. This movement captures the whole spirit of the concerto &#8211; starting peacefully and ending spectacularly.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Schumann &#8211; Carnaval, op. 9</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-schumann-carnaval-op-9/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 22:06:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1868</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to Schumann&#8217;s Carnaval, took me into a grand masquerade, where masked partygoers come together to celebrate the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to Schumann&#8217;s Carnaval, took me into a grand masquerade, where masked partygoers come together to celebrate the festivities of Carnival. Even Chopin appeared at this fictitious party. This piano suite, composed between 1834 and 1835, consists of 21 short movements, each representing a character or caricature from the carnival scene.</p>



<p>Schumann turned this piece into a storytelling breathing life into the characters. Pierrot, the sad clown, dances poignantly, while Harlequin, the mischievous trickster, bounds with infectious energy.</p>



<p>At times, the technical challenges posed by Carnaval seemed daunting, even overwhelming. Yet as I studied the piece more deeply, I developed a greater understanding of Schumann&#8217;s composition. Learning about his mental health struggles and how they may have shaped this music gave me new insight. I realized that the complex and shifting emotions woven throughout Carnaval serve to enhance its overall poignant effect. Every musical detail—each note, chord, melodic twist and turn—contributes to this emotional impact.</p>



<p>It is not the kind of work that I would love to listen to repeatedly. Still, I get the sense that it is a work that is important to establish the piano as an extremely expressive instrument and will continue to captivate listeners.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point: links between Wagner and Nazism</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-links-between-wagner-and-nazism/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 22:12:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1846</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Wagner&#8217;s dramatic and emotionally charged music has long had a powerful influence not just on music lovers, but&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Wagner&#8217;s dramatic and emotionally charged music has long had a powerful influence not just on music lovers, but also on political movements seeking a sense of mythic destiny. This mystical attraction of music was and still is used by political propaganda and proved fatally potent when adopted by Hitler and the Nazis. But does Wagner&#8217;s music itself contain some intrinsic quality that made it the perfect vehicle for Nazism?</p>



<p>There is no doubt that Wagner had an anti-Semitic view of the world. In his notorious 1850 essay &#8220;On Judaism in Music,&#8221; Wagner expressed extremely offensive racist views towards Jewish people that were later exploited by the Nazis. He stereotyped Jews and said they could not truly make great art. Though a distortion, Hitler and other Nazis admired Wagner and saw him as an inspiration for their antisemitism.</p>



<p>I believe that there are aspects of Wagner&#8217;s works that undoubtedly appealed to the Nazi psyche. The huge mythical operas about heroes and gods match the Nazis&#8217; huge self-glorification. The medieval German settings and Norse mythology in works like The Ring suit the Nazi love of old Germanic purity.</p>



<p>The raw emotion in Wagner&#8217;s scores, for example, the extreme excitement when the music climaxes, is like the fevered Nazi rallies choreographed by Hitler and Goebbels. The gut power of songs like The Ride of the Valkyries taps into wild passions that override morality – just what the Nazis did so well.</p>



<p>Yet we must be aware of overstating this case. While Wagner&#8217;s operas worked well for the Nazis, the music itself isn&#8217;t Fascist. I couldn&#8217;t find information showing that there is anything intrinsically Fascist about the music itself. The emotional range of Wagner&#8217;s scores captures the full spectrum of human experience—from the uplifting to the disturbing. As with all art, his works are open to multiple interpretations.</p>



<p>I firmly believe that art and the artist should be separated and appreciated independently. Wagner&#8217;s music is no exception. We can still find value in his compositions while acknowledging the problematic aspects of the composer as an individual. We can reclaim his works for more positive purposes – his music leading us to contemplate humanity&#8217;s deeper bonds rather than divisions.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1705529244453 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Walsh, M. (1992) <em>The case of Wagner &#8212; again</em>. https://content.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,974661-1,00.html.</p>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (2024) <em>Richard Wagner | Biography, Music, Compositions, Operas, &amp; Facts</em>. https://www.britannica.com/biography/Richard-Wagner-German-composer/Wagners-anti-Semitism.</p>



<p>Burton-Hill, C. (2022) &#8216;Is Wagner’s Nazi stigma fair?,&#8217; <em>BBC Culture</em>, 24 February. https://www.bbc.com/culture/article/20130509-is-wagners-nazi-stigma-fair.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Go to a concert</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-go-to-a-concert/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 21:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1841</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A few days ago, I attended the Mozart Requiem concert performed by the Orquestra Filarmónica Portuguesa at the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>A few days ago, I attended the Mozart Requiem concert performed by the Orquestra Filarmónica Portuguesa at the Aula Magna in Lisbon. The concert was conducted by the conductor Osvaldo Ferreira and featured a choir and four soloists: Marco Alves dos Santos, tenor, Carolina Figueiredo, mezzo-soprano, Raquel Alão, soprano and Miguel Maduro-Dias, bass.</p>



<p>The performance of Mozart&#8217;s Requiem by the Orquestra Filarmónica Portuguesa was a sublime and moving experience. The full orchestra, choir, and four solo vocalists brought Mozart&#8217;s immortal composition to life in a profound way.</p>



<p>The instruments used included the typical setup found in a classical orchestra &#8211; strings, woodwinds, brass and timpani. The strings provided the lush foundation, while the winds and brass added color and accent. The timpani gave dramatic punctuation while the four vocal soloists gave the Requiem an operatic quality during their featured parts.</p>



<p>While the Requiem is a familiar and often performed piece, hearing it live gave it an emotional immediacy and power beyond any recording. The soaring crescendos and hushed moments of silence resonated deeply. No media reproduction can truly capture the experience of hearing these sublime sounds &#8220;in the flesh.&#8221;</p>



<p>The program notes provided useful background and context about the piece and its history that enhanced my enjoyment and understanding. Learning about the mysterious circumstances of the Requiem&#8217;s composition and its intersection of the earthly and divine added deeper meaning.</p>



<p>Overall, this was a profoundly enjoyable and moving concert that will stay with me for a long time. I had never heard Mozart’s Requiem live before, and I was surprised by the difference it makes. I felt that the music had more life, more intensity, more depth. I could perceive the details, the nuances, the emotions of the musicians and the singers. I also felt more involved, more connected, more participant of the work. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Transcribing for the piano</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-transcribing-for-the-piano/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 22:31:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1838</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I listened to Glenn Gould&#8217;s 1968 recording. The most evident difference between Beethoven&#8217;s original and Liszt&#8217;s transcription is&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I listened to Glenn Gould&#8217;s 1968 recording.</p>



<p>The most evident difference between Beethoven&#8217;s original and Liszt&#8217;s transcription is the instrumentation. Beethoven&#8217;s composition, created for a full orchestra, provides a vast palette of colours, timbres, and effects, allowing the music to be expressed with expansive variety.</p>



<p>In contrast, Liszt&#8217;s transcription scored solely for piano, introduces intrinsic physical constraints evident in the performance: The range and depth of sounds are not as broad as those produced by an orchestra; a piano&#8217;s sustained notes fall short when compared to those of wind or string instruments; and while dynamic contrasts can be substantial, they typically do not reach the extremes possible within an orchestra, even though the version I listened to did had significant dynamic variation.</p>



<p>However, there is a distinctive positive aspect to Liszt&#8217;s arrangement: intimacy. A single instrument, managed by one performer, transforms a grand, collective work into a more personal and individual experience. The piano takes the spotlight and, particularly during the Romantic era, places the pianist at the forefront. A single instrument offers performers greater liberty and room for expression; they can shape the tempo, articulation, and pedalling, ultimately making the performance a personal statement of the player&#8217;s own style.</p>



<p>I believe that Liszt’s piano version captures a lot of the spirit of the symphony, following the same structure and themes as Beethoven’s original. Liszt also tries to evoke the same feelings and moods, like tension, drama, contrast, and resolution. It’s not just a copy, but a new interpretation that honours Beethoven’s talent.</p>



<p>Regarding my preference, I found merit in listening to both versions, as they provide distinct interpretations of the same composition. However, if I had to pick one, I&#8217;d go with Beethoven’s original symphony. I feel it embodies the music&#8217;s essence more authentically and powerfully. I also appreciate Beethoven&#8217;s skill in balancing and contrasting various sections, themes, and instruments, as well as the way he develops and resolves musical ideas.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Expressing national identity</title>
		<link>./../../../../expressing-national-identity/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 21:58:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1835</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to Albéniz&#8217;s &#8220;Suite Española No. 1&#8221;, I was immediately drawn to the piece &#8220;Asturias (Leyenda)&#8221; for its&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to Albéniz&#8217;s &#8220;Suite Española No. 1&#8221;, I was immediately drawn to the piece &#8220;Asturias (Leyenda)&#8221; for its familiar Spanish elements. As a Portuguese listener, I found parallels to music from my own country.</p>



<p>The piano mimics a Spanish guitar, reflecting the central role of the guitar in Spanish musical culture. Repeated rhythmic strumming patterns capture the spirit of Spanish folk music traditions.</p>



<p>An insistent flamenco rhythm drives the piece forward, evoking the heel-taps of dancers. The struck chords suggest the clapping hands often accompanying flamenco.</p>



<p>The melody itself encapsulates Spanish folk idioms with its modal tonality and distinctive phrasing. This is the very essence of Iberian traditional music.</p>



<p>In naming the piece after the Asturias region, Albéniz implies a musical portrait, conjuring a sense of Spanish regional identity and local color. The title prepares the listener to be transported to the province through sound.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Marta Pereira da Costa &#8211; Tiny Desk Concert</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-marta-pereira-da-costa-tiny-desk-concert/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 22:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1812</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I happened to catch this concert and decided to listen since it featured a Portuguese artist playing the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I happened to catch this concert and decided to listen since it featured a Portuguese artist playing the Portuguese guitar, something you don&#8217;t often see on international channels.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Marta Pereira da Costa: Tiny Desk Concert" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wzlZ68ts-IU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I hadn&#8217;t heard of Marta Pereira da Costa before, although I knew her name. She&#8217;s the world&#8217;s first and only professional female Portuguese guitar player in Fado music.</p>



<p>Right away the sound reminded me of Carlos Paredes, a legendary Portuguese guitarist, but with a fresher vibe, mainly from the percussion. Traditionally the Portuguese guitar is accompanied by two guitars, but here it&#8217;s one guitar plus percussion, bringing a modern twist which I enjoy.</p>



<p>I&#8217;m biased since I love the Portuguese guitar, but Marta&#8217;s playing conveys so much expression and goes beyond mellow tunes. Even faster, danceable songs have a singing, soaring quality from her guitar.</p>



<p>Another thing I enjoyed was how Marta lets the other instruments shine, especially in the last song. The interplay of bass and treble, each with its moment, creates a really beautiful, rich sound.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@nprmusic"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Programme music</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-programme-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2023 21:55:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1821</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hector Berlioz&#8217;s Symphonie Fantastique, composed in 1830, perfectly reflects the obsessive mind of its composer, Berstein said in&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Hector Berlioz&#8217;s Symphonie Fantastique, composed in 1830, perfectly reflects the obsessive mind of its composer, Berstein said in its Young People&#8217;s Concerts. But when I first listened to the symphony, I hadn&#8217;t watched Berstein&#8217;s video, so I expected something more contained and safe like other works from that period. But I soon realized why it&#8217;s called &#8220;Fantastique.&#8221; For me, the word &#8220;fantastique&#8221; evokes not grandness but a sense of surreal fantasy. In my interpretation, the symphony, rather than presenting a linear narrative, unfolds as flashes of disconnected dreams, each reflecting the protagonist&#8217;s shifting emotions and his fixation on an unattainable woman.</p>



<p>The first dream depicts meeting his beloved; the second involves a failed attempt to reach her at a ball; the third transports him to a tranquil rural setting, offering a brief respite from the turmoil; the fourth descends from a dream into a nightmarish execution; the final movement plunges him into a fantastical afterlife world. My feeling at the end is that maybe the woman of his dreams was only a woman in his dreams. </p>



<p>The reason I previously stated that I felt Fantastique was related to fantasy,  was due to the surreal and psychedelic nature of the music, which portrays the lovesick hallucinations and nightmares of the protagonist. Musically, Berlioz employed unexpected dynamic changes and unsettling orchestration, such as the use of real thunder in the storm scenes, taking a step further from Beethoven’s approach. He also innovatively used the main theme. This idée fixe is not merely a static melody; it undergoes a captivating transformation throughout the symphony, mirroring the protagonist’s evolving emotions and the unfolding narrative. As the symphony progresses, the idée fixe becomes increasingly distorted and anguished, reflecting the depths of the protagonist’s obsession and despair.</p>



<p>The first appearance of the idée fixe seems different from when a main theme is typically introduced, for example, in Beethoven&#8217;s Symphony No. 6. First, it doesn&#8217;t appear until around 5 minutes into the first movement, after an extended setup section &#8211; almost like an introduction leading us into the dream. When the idée fixe finally enters, it is in the form of a long, unaccompanied melody in the woodwinds, with bursts of energetic strings punctuating it. This unique presentation reminded me a bit of the surprising and unsettling rhythms in Stravinsky&#8217;s Rite of Spring. That unexpected rhythm must have been a shocking revelation for early 20th-century listeners.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="596" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-1024x596.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1823" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-1024x596.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-300x175.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-768x447.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-1536x893.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-2048x1191.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-640x372.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03-960x558.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/Screenshot-2023-12-05-at-22.07.03.png 2816w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Although as I said before, the Idée fixe is transformed through the movements, its use in the fourth movement is extremely symbolic in its subtlety and, I must say, humour. This movement engages in the musical depiction of a march to execution. After the pastoral setting of the previous movement, the music abruptly shifts to the protagonist&#8217;s march to the scaffold, accompanied by a marching band. I was surprised because I expected a solemn setting, but instead it sounds almost celebratory, like a fanfare. The booming percussion and horns set a marching rhythm while the strangely cheerful melodies in the woodwinds and strings portray the crowd jeering the prisoner to his death. Just before the fatal blow, the idée fixe appears one last time on the clarinet, only to be suddenly, brutally cut off, symbolizing the severing of the head. The vivid musical imagery transported me right to the exact scene Berlioz intended to depict, which I found brilliant.</p>



<p>In the fourth movement, there are two main themes—a descending theme and a march theme—as well as a countermelody for the first theme. These all contribute to the overall feeling of the movement. The descending theme introduces a sense of despair, while the march theme brings the strangely cheerful contrast I mentioned earlier. One interesting thing is how the descending theme contrasts with the Idée Fixe melody—the Idée Fixe has a hopeful, ascending trajectory, whereas the descending theme embarks on a continuous, hopeless downward journey.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="242" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-1024x242.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1829" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-1024x242.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-300x71.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-768x182.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-1536x363.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-2048x485.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-640x151.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1-960x227.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-5-1.png 2172w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">First appearance of the Idée Fixe</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="259" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-1024x259.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1830" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-1024x259.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-300x76.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-768x194.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-1536x389.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-2048x519.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-640x162.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1-960x243.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/12/untitled-3-1.png 2172w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Movement 4 main theme</figcaption></figure>



<p>In the end, I must say that I adored this symphony. I feel that Berlioz brings a dramatic and theatrical sensibility to the symphonic writing, vividly portraying the emotional world of his desperate protagonist. So while fantastique may not be about grandness in the heroic sense, it represents a daring new musical language filled with psychedelic fantasy.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1702245310254 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Trine (2022) <em>Leonard Bernstein &#8211; Young People’s Concerts: Berlioz takes a trip</em>. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zl9S5D3BLMA.</p>



<p><em>Berlioz’s Symphonie fantastique: Keeping Score | PBS</em> (no date). https://www.pbs.org/keepingscore/berlioz-symphonie-fantastique.html.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Classical and Romantic</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-classical-and-romantic/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 21:36:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1815</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Beethoven&#8217;s first piano sonata (No. 1 in F minor, Op 2) displays the hallmarks of the Classical style.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Beethoven&#8217;s first piano sonata (No. 1 in F minor, Op 2) displays the hallmarks of the Classical style. It contains a straightforward sonata form structure, opening with a lively first movement dotted with playful melodies. The middle movements provide contrast &#8211; a peaceful Adagio followed by a brisk dance-like section similar to a minuet. The finale introduces a vigorous theme. Throughout the piece, Beethoven focuses on balanced phrases and graceful melodies, supported by conventional harmony and rhythms &#8211; all trademarks of the Classical period.</p>



<p>In contrast, his final piano sonata (No. 32 in C minor, Op 111) exhibits innovations that push toward Romanticism. While still structured into movements, the form is more ecstatic, especially in the mystical opening movement. In this sonata, I hear many more chromatic harmonies and elastic rhythms and feel there&#8217;s an emotional range from brooding melancholy to joyful jubilation. The enriched harmonic palette and depth of expression represent the early Romantic style. </p>



<p>My research, in general, supports my feelings.</p>



<p>In the Opus 2 sonatas of his early period, Beethoven hews more closely to the balanced elegance of Mozart and Haydn. But flashes of his revolutionary voice emerge even then in the intense, turbulent passages. It contains a straightforward sonata form structure, opening with a lively first Molto Allegro movement characterized by accelerating small phrases leading to mini-climaxes, followed by pauses for theatrical effect. The middle Adagio movement offers the only overtly &#8216;pretty&#8217; music in the whole sonata &#8211; simple, serene melodies decorated with lavish ornamentation. The Allegretto finale features a slightly anxious minute tune pieced together from repeated fragments, counteracted by a smoother, more elegant major-mode Trio section.</p>



<p>The Op. 111 is regarded as one of Beethoven&#8217;s best piano compositions. It is a departure from previous sonatas, having only two movements, which led his publisher to question if it wasn&#8217;t a mistake. The sonata is described as powerful, passionate and inventive. For example, Beethoven transforms a simple and singable theme into five variations, ending in a serene and transcendent mood. Yet the animated fugue demonstrates Beethoven&#8217;s contrapuntal mastery cultivated in the Classical tradition. This piano sonata encapsulates Beethoven&#8217;s musical evolution from formal lucidity toward mystical, subjective soundscapes, prefiguring Romantic ideals.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1701123445593 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Tayama, M. (2022) <em>Beethoven Piano sonata in F minor (Op. 2 No. 1)</em>. https://practisingthepiano.com/beethoven-piano-sonata-no-1-in-f-minor/.</p>



<p>G. Gíslason, D. (2022) <em>Sonata No. 1 in F minor&nbsp; Op. 2 No. 1 Archives &#8211; Vancouver Recital Society</em>. https://vanrecital.com/tag/sonata-no-1-in-f-minor-op-2-no-1/.</p>



<p>Pizarro, A. (no date) <em>BBC &#8211; Radio 3 &#8211; Beethoven Piano Sonata No. 1 in F minor, Op. 2 No. 1</em>. https://www.bbc.co.uk/radio3/classical/pizarro/sonata1.shtml.</p>



<p>Kramer, L. (1993b) <em>Music as Cultural Practice, 1800-1900</em>. Univ of California Press.</p>



<p>Vrs (2019) <em>Sonata in C minor Op. 111 Archives &#8211; Vancouver Recital Society</em>. https://vanrecital.com/tag/sonata-in-c-minor-op-111/.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Antonio Vivaldi &#8211; Piccolo Concerto in C Major, RV 443</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-antonio-vivaldi-piccolo-concerto-in-c-major-rv-443/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 21:01:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1808</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Antonio Vivaldi wrote three concertos for a small, high-pitched instrument called the &#8220;flautino&#8221;. The exact instrument Vivaldi intended&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Antonio Vivaldi wrote three concertos for a small, high-pitched instrument called the &#8220;flautino&#8221;. The exact instrument Vivaldi intended is unknown, but scholars believe it was either the sopranino recorder or the flageolet. In the 18th century, the transverse flute replaced both the recorder and flageolet and a new edition of Vivaldi&#8217;s concerto was published for the piccolo, a member of the flute family. This is the version that is typically performed today and it was the one I listened to.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="A. Vivaldi - Piccolo Concerto in C major (RV443)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FBNq-F80uFc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>As soon as the orchestra begins the opening Allegro molto, the piccolo enters with a joyful, singing melody in the upper octave that immediately grabs my attention. The piccolo part requires technical agility as it features fast runs and trills, but the melodies flow so naturally that the difficulty is masked and it looks easy.</p>



<p>The calm and emotional middle Largo movement offers a lovely change from the faster outer movements. The piccolo carries a gorgeous, flowing melody above soft strings, reminiscent of a soulful operatic aria. It&#8217;s my favourite part—a moment where the piccolo&#8217;s expressiveness truly shines.</p>



<p>The concluding Allegro brings back the cheerful mood, with the piccolo presenting new melodic material over the orchestra&#8217;s constant, pulsing motion. The themes are fragmented with trills, creating a perpetually moving, spinning sensation. The cadenza features more rapid runs that showcase the soloist&#8217;s skill.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Tchaikovsky &#8211; The Nutcracker&#8217;s Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-tchaikovsky-the-nutcrackers-dance-of-the-sugar-plum-fairy/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 21:46:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1804</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Of course, I already knew the melody of the Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy, since it is&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Of course, I already knew the melody of the Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy, since it is one of the most used melodies in Christmas ads. But at this time I listened to it closely. In the beginning, I was immediately struck by the beauty of the music. The melody is light and airy and has a childish magical quality that transports you to another world. The use of the celesta gives the music a unique, ethereal and enchanting sound.</p>



<p>The presence of the bass clarinet is brief but it is truly remarkable. It brings a new tone and colour that adds depth to the beginning of the piece. The choice of the bass clarinet seems to bring a warm, mellow and rounded sound in contrast to the brighter, crystalline tones of the celesta. This elevates the overall feeling of the fantastical and mysterious setting.</p>



<p>Overall, it evokes a profound sense of innocent joy and wonder for me. The music exudes a youthful spirit of fantasy and imagination. It&#8217;s a timeless piece that brings out the inner child in me. Every listen renews feelings of wide-eyed enchantment and marvel.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point: Bass Clarinet</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-bass-clarinet/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 21:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1779</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The bass clarinet is a woodwind instrument with a deep, rich tone, it provides a foundation for the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The bass clarinet is a woodwind instrument with a deep, rich tone, it provides a foundation for the woodwind section and entire ensemble. Though the bass clarinet has a relatively short history compared to other orchestral instruments, it has evolved into an expressive voice capable of solo works as well as supporting roles.</p>



<p>The earliest predecessor of the bass clarinet was the basset horn, developed in the 1770s. This instrument paved the way for lower-pitched clarinets. The first true bass clarinets emerged in the late 18th century. Heinrich Grenser is credited with creating one of the earliest examples in 1793. However, it was the pioneering instrument maker Adolphe Sax who developed the first fully satisfactory bass clarinet in 1838. Sax gave the instrument a wider bore and re-designed the key work to improve intonation across all registers. His innovations established the bass clarinet design that is still used today.</p>



<p>While the bass clarinet was slow to be accepted into orchestras at first, composers soon began to appreciate its unique timbre. Meyerbeer featured the instrument prominently in his 1836 opera Les Huguenots, one of the earliest uses of the bass clarinet in the orchestra. By the late 19th century, the bass clarinet had become a permanent member of the orchestra&#8217;s woodwind section. Its mellow, velvety tone contrasted with the more piercing oboe and soprano clarinet timbres.</p>



<p>In the orchestra, the bass clarinet typically provides harmonic support in the tenor and bass range. It handles the lower woodwind parts while the bassoon takes higher tenor lines. The bass clarinet has a remarkable three-octave range, overlapping the bassoon at the bottom end and the soprano clarinet at the top. This allows composers flexibility in orchestration. The instrument&#8217;s dark, brooding resonance lends itself well to dramatic effects.</p>



<p>Many composers took advantage of the bass clarinet&#8217;s solo potential as well. In Mahler&#8217;s Symphony No. 6, the bass clarinet introduces a moving theme in the first movement. Tchaikovsky exploits the instrument&#8217;s deep sound in The&nbsp;Nutcracker&#8217;s Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy. Stravinsky showcases the agility of the bass clarinet at the beginning of The Rite Of Spring.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1699394026604 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><em>The Origins of the Clarinet：The birth of the clarinet&nbsp; &#8211; Musical Instrument Guide &#8211; Yamaha Corporation</em> (no date). https://www.yamaha.com/en/musical_instrument_guide/clarinet/structure/.</p>



<p><em>Bass clarinet | VSL &#8211; Academy</em> (no date). https://www.vsl.info/en/academy/woodwinds/bass-clarinet.</p>



<p>Tan, C. (2019) <em>Our top 5 moments from the bass clarinet, underdog of the orchestra &#8211; Classical KUSC</em>. https://www.kusc.org/culture/staff-blog/top-5-bass-clarinet-underdog-of-the-orchestra/.</p>



<p>Wikipedia contributors (2023a) <em>Bass clarinet</em>. https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bass_clarinet.</p>



<p><em>Clarinetist Allan Rosenfeld’s Top 10 Orchestral Bass Clarinet Solos | Charlotte Symphony Orchestra</em> (2021). https://www.charlottesymphony.org/blog/clarinetist-allan-rosenfeld-top-10-orchestral-bass-clarinet-solos/.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p>William Schuman&#8217;s Symphony No. 3 (Part II, Toccata)Bass clarinet showcases virtuosic technique.</p>



<p>Gershwin&#8217;s Concerto in F (Second movement)Clarinet section soli with bass clarinet filling out bass line.</p>



<p>Shostakovich&#8217;s Symphony No. 8 (Fifth movement)Boisterous display of the bass clarinet&#8217;s low register mischief.</p>



<p>Wagner&#8217;s Tristan und Isolde (Act II, scene 3)Emphasizes the lyrical capabilities of the bass clarinet.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point: The Piccolo</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-the-piccolo/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 21:49:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1781</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The history of the piccolo is closely tied to that of the flute. The first transverse flute was&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The history of the piccolo is closely tied to that of the flute. The first transverse flute was developed in the Middle Ages as an adaptation of the recorder. As military bands adopted the flute, a smaller version was created to make the flute parts more prominent. This petite flute was initially keyed like a recorder with six finger holes and was used to play melodies an octave above the flute.</p>



<p>In the early 18th century, the first piccolos appeared in orchestral scores, including works by Jean-Philippe Rameau. However, it was initially referred to by names like &#8220;flautino&#8221; or &#8220;petite flute&#8221; rather than piccolo. The instrument continued to develop alongside the flute, especially after Theobald Böehm invented the modern flute fingering system in 1832. Böehm&#8217;s revolutionary key mechanism was soon adapted for the piccolo as well.</p>



<p>One of the earliest major works to feature the piccolo was Handel&#8217;s opera Rinaldo in 1711. Composers began to utilize its unique shrill timbre to provide colour and brilliance. For example, Beethoven used the piccolo in his 6th Symphony to imitate the sound of whistling birds. Its high register allows it to be heard over the entire orchestra, making it an excellent accent instrument.</p>



<p>Today, the piccolo is a standard member of the orchestra and band. Its most common variant is pitched an octave above the concert flute, although piccolos pitched a major third above the flute are also used. Its highest notes can reach up to C7, above the treble clef staff.</p>



<p>The piccolo&#8217;s bright sound serves to bring out melodic lines and add sparkle to orchestral textures. As one of the highest instruments in the orchestra, the piccolo&#8217;s clear notes cut through dense arrangements. Composers often utilize the piccolo to introduce themes or complement the woodwinds. </p>



<p>While associated with the flute section, the piccolo player may switch between the regular flute and piccolo multiple times in a single piece. Due to its penetrating timbre, the piccolo is used with good judgment to avoid overpowering the ensemble. However, short piccolo solos and highlights prevent listener fatigue.</p>



<p>Piccolo parts require advanced techniques to handle the altissimo register and quick figurations composers write. Rapid passages showcase the piccolo&#8217;s agile nature. Trills, runs, and arpeggios demand precise finger dexterity. The small size necessitates strict embouchure control. Intonation can also prove tricky with so few open finger holes to adjust the pitch.</p>



<p>While the piccolo often plays an accompaniment role, there are also many famous solos and melodies written for it. For example, the piccolo solo in the first movement of Shostakovich&#8217;s 6th Symphony. The soloist plays with delicate restraint, creating a thoughtful and powerful moment. Other works that highlight the piccolo include Tchaikovsky&#8217;s The Nutcracker, which features the piccolo along with the flute flute engaging in a lively duet, in the Chinese Dance. and John Philip Sousa&#8217;s &#8220;The Stars and Stripes Forever,&#8221; which features a famous piccolo countermelody above the marching band.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1699566934359 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Oxford University Press (2017) <em>A tiny instrument with a tremendous history: the piccolo</em>. https://blog.oup.com/2015/07/small-instrument-large-history-piccolo/.</p>



<p><em>Eight times the piccolo was secretly the most badass member of the orchestra</em> (no date). https://www.classicfm.com/discover-music/latest/best-piccolo-orchestra/.</p>



<p><em>Piccolo | VSL &#8211; Academy</em> (no date). https://www.vsl.info/en/academy/woodwinds/piccolo.</p>



<p>Perkins, C. (2021) &#8216;What’s the difference between a flute and a piccolo?,&#8217; <em>Yamaha Music</em>, 27 August. https://hub.yamaha.com/winds/wood/whats-the-difference-between-a-flute-and-a-piccolo/.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to John Coltrane &#8211; Naima</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-john-coltrane-naima/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2023 21:01:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1776</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[John Coltrane&#8217;s composition &#8220;Naima&#8221; is a lush, emotional ballad that showcases his virtuosic command of the tenor saxophone.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>John Coltrane&#8217;s composition &#8220;Naima&#8221; is a lush, emotional ballad that showcases his virtuosic command of the tenor saxophone. The song is a tribute to Coltrane’s wife, Juanita Naima Grubbs, and is one beautiful ballads. The saxophone is the centerpiece of the song, accompained by the piano, the bass and the drums.</p>



<p>As soon as the saxophone enters, I am enveloped in the bittersweet melancholy of the piece. The tone is robust yet smooth, almost vocal-like in the way he caresses each note with vibratos and slight inflections that hint at a longing.</p>



<p>The flexibility and range of the saxophone allows Coltrane to truly sing through his instrument, conveying a depth of feeling that spans smooth joy to deep sorrow. I find his playing meditative and prayerful.</p>



<p>One of the things that makes Coltrane’s saxophone so expressive is his use of dynamics. He’s able to play softly and delicately one moment and then switch to a more forceful and aggressive style the next.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Samuel Barber &#8211; Adagio For Strings</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-samuel-barber-adagio-for-strings/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 20:46:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1771</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last night I had the pleasure of attending a live performance of Mozart&#8217;s Requiem. When the conductor stepped&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Last night I had the pleasure of attending a live performance of Mozart&#8217;s Requiem. When the conductor stepped up, he surprised us all by announcing they would open with Samuel Barber&#8217;s Adagio for Strings before moving into the Requiem. Though I knew the piece from movies and commercials, I had never truly listened closely before. I found it profoundly moving.</p>



<p>The opening immediately establishes a heavy, mournful mood brimming with emotional weight. It&#8217;s easy to understand why this piece is often played at funerals, including Einstein&#8217;s.</p>



<p>The main theme is deceptively simple &#8211; just three notes ascending. Yet the aching slowness, the dragging tempo, creates the sense of struggling to lift upwards only to fall back down. I loved how the stately, elongated melody passes from the violins to the violas and finally, the cellos, maintaining its emotional power throughout.</p>



<p>To me, it sounded extremely beautiful, but the melody alone doesn&#8217;t convey the full emotional impact. That comes from the harmony of the other strings, which inspire the melody with all its feelings. The rich harmonies and colours of the string orchestra add emotive depth. </p>



<p>This piece perfectly captures the universality of grief, transcending time and place. Though it was composed in 1936, it speaks profoundly to the shared human experience across cultures and generations. Little did Barber know what the world was about to witness and how this song would be embraced as an expression of mourning, remembrance, and hope.</p>



<p>In the end, it proved the perfect prelude to Mozart&#8217;s Requiem. Well-chosen, maestro.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
