<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 22:46:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Harry Partch &#8211; Sonata Dementia</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-harry-partch-sonata-dementia/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 20:01:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1728</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I must admit, prior to this, I was unfamiliar with Partch so this is my initial experience listening&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ul></ul>



<p>I must admit, prior to this, I was unfamiliar with Partch so this is my initial experience listening to any of his compositions. Partch was indeed a uniquely creative artist, as he was known for not only inventing his own musical instruments but also scoring his compositions for a 43-tone scale unique to these instruments.</p>



<p>Despite being created over 70 years ago (1950), this piece remains surprisingly fresh and innovative. The composition is marked by its distinct sound, thanks to the use of Partch&#8217;s own instruments like the Bass Marimba and the Hypobass.</p>



<p>Although the microtonal melodies and harmonies of the piece often sounded to me as dissonant and jarring, it&#8217;s the unsettling sound contrasted with the comical visual of the instruments that makes it so unique. The sonata is a satirical work going into themes of madness, delusion, and paranoia.</p>



<p>This composition thoroughly blends humour and lightness with hints of darker territories. The lyrics of the piece might seem nonsensical on the surface, but they carry potential interpretations concerning the human condition.</p>



<p>Listening to &#8216;Sonata Dementia&#8217; is a challenging experience. The microtonality might initially seem daunting, but it may not be as intricate as expected. The initial dissonance from the 43-tone scale, which might seem hard to accept at first, gradually becomes more harmonic and natural as the pieces develop.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Harry Partch: SONATA DEMENTIA (1950)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qZybJAEPu18?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Harry Partch &#8211; King Oedipus</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-harry-partch-king-oedipus/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 21:36:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1731</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I recently listened to some parts of King Oedipus, an opera composed by Harry Partch. I was drawn&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I recently listened to some parts of King Oedipus, an opera composed by Harry Partch. I was drawn to listen to it because of the information about how Partch started to dive into microtonality, as it more closely resembles the natural human voice. This actually makes total sense for opera. People don&#8217;t speak in 12 semitones, but actually in hundreds of microtones and opera relies heavily on the expression of the voice. As I listened to King Oedipus, I noticed how the voices sounded more like speech than singing.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Partch&#8217;s music for King Oedipus is a unique blend of microtonality, percussion, and spoken word. The voices sound more natural, not sung, but spoken. The instruments follow the vocals and strangely don&#8217;t sound as strange as they do in other microtonal pieces by Partch. The microtonality allows the voices to more closely match natural speech patterns, rather than conforming to the 12 notes of standard Western music. I enjoyed listening to King Oedipus, even though I did not hear the whole opera. It was a refreshing and stimulating experience that opened my ears to new possibilities of musical expression.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="HARRY PARTCH - King Oedipus 1952 (Audio)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/V2jHtfk2ljM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Julian Carrillo &#8211; Seis casi-sonatas en cuartos de tono para violoncello solo</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-julian-carrillo-seis-casi-sonatas-en-cuartos-de-tono-para-violoncello-solo/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 21:13:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1754</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Julian Carrillo&#8217;s Seis casi-sonatas en cuartos de tono para violoncello solo, performed by Gerardo Gimenez Cacho, offers a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Julian Carrillo&#8217;s Seis casi-sonatas en cuartos de tono para violoncello solo, performed by Gerardo Gimenez Cacho, offers a fascinating glimpse into the expressive potential of microtonal music. As someone accustomed to the familiar 12-tone equal temperament of Western classical music, I found these quarter-tone sonatas surprisingly easy to listen to and appreciate. The solo cello format helps make the microtones feel intimate rather than jarring.</p>



<p>With these sonatas, I could understand how dividing the octave into smaller intervals can open up new sonic palettes and colours. Microtonality provides the performer access to the &#8220;cracks between the keys&#8221; &#8211; those poignant notes that float between our conventional Western pitches. The cello seems to emote in ways that would be impossible with merely 12 notes.</p>



<p>I cannot imagine how difficult these pieces must be to perform well, given the challenge of precisely nailing pitches outside of the equal temperament celloists spend years mastering. The skill demonstrated in this recording is hugely impressive.</p>



<p>Occasionally the quarter tones sound somewhat unsettling, but more often I found they enhanced the cello&#8217;s innate expressiveness. For example, the aching melody in the third movement of Sonata No. 4 attains an extra sadness from its microtonal sounds. The result is something simultaneously familiar and novel.</p>



<p>The quarter tones may initially sound like &#8220;out of tune&#8221; notes, but one&#8217;s ear quickly adjusts, and their emotional resonance becomes apparent. Julian Carrillo has created a compelling showcase for the cello as an instrument of uncommon subtlety. Even for listeners new to microtonality, these Casi-sonatas offer an accessible and rewarding introduction.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Jacob Collier &#8211; In The Bleak Midwinter</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-jacob-collier-in-the-bleak-midwinter/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 20:37:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1748</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to Jacob Collier&#8217;s &#8220;In The Bleak Midwinter&#8221; was an enlightening experience for me as I researched microtonality&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to Jacob Collier&#8217;s &#8220;In The Bleak Midwinter&#8221; was an enlightening experience for me as I researched microtonality in modern music. As one of the most talented young musicians today, Collier&#8217;s ingenious use of microtones immediately drew me in. The track begins deceivingly simple but slowly builds in complexity. At one point, Collier modulates to what sounds like a G#. However, with microtonal inflexions, he has actually modulated to the key of G half-sharp major &#8211; something I did not detect on the first listen! The modulation is brilliantly executed, such that the music flows seamlessly.  I had to understand how he modulated and David Bruce helped me on that.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="How to Modulate to G 1/2 Sharp (Jacob Collier-style)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xd54l8gfi7M?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>As I re-listened and focused on the microtonal shift, I better appreciated Collier&#8217;s technical mastery and innovative musicality. &#8220;In The Bleak Midwinter&#8221; proves he is not just one of the best musicians of our time, but one boldly expanding the boundaries of Western music.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="In The Bleak Midwinter - Jacob Collier" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mPZn4x3uOac?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Radiohead &#8211; How to Disappear Completely</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-radiohead-how-to-disappear-completely/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 20:17:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1745</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Radiohead is not a band that I particularly enjoy listening to, but I decided to listen to How&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Radiohead is not a band that I particularly enjoy listening to, but I decided to listen to How to Disappear Completely to hear its use of microtonality. </p>



<p>The song starts off with a simple guitar and Thom Yorke&#8217;s falsetto vocals, nothing too unusual for a Radiohead track. The lyrics are vague and ambiguous, but they convey a sense of detachment and dissociation from reality. The song gradually builds up with layers of orchestral strings, guitar effects, and electronic sounds, creating a rich and complex sonic landscape. About two-thirds of the way through, the strings come in playing microtonal intervals that clash with the conventional instrumentation. These non-standard pitches on the strings create an unsettling, tense atmosphere contrasting with the dreamy opening section. The microtonal strings sound almost like they&#8217;re playing a separate song altogether, weaving an anxious counter-melody against the main chords. </p>



<p>This incoherent effect highlights Yorke&#8217;s lyrics about feeling disconnected from reality. While Radiohead isn&#8217;t my go-to band, I found &#8220;How to Disappear Completely&#8221; an interesting song with the use of microtonality to convey emotional dissociation in music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Charles Ives &#8211;  Three Quarter Tone Pieces for Two Pianos</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-charles-ives-three-quarter-tone-pieces-for-two-pianos/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 20:56:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1740</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I enjoyed Ives&#8217; Three Quarter Tone Pieces for Two Pianos more than Hába&#8217;s quarter-tone sonata. The interplay between&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I enjoyed Ives&#8217; Three Quarter Tone Pieces for Two Pianos more than Hába&#8217;s quarter-tone sonata. The interplay between the two pianos tuned a quarter tone apart, creates an intriguing sense of conversation. One piano is tuned to standard western 12-tone equal temperament, while the other uses quarter tones. At first, they both sound out of tune, which has a quirky, childlike quality. But at moments they harmonize in an unconventional way that sounds oddly &#8220;in tune.&#8221;</p>



<p>As I kept listening, I began to familiarize myself with the microtonal language. The quarter tones initially sound discordantly unfamiliar, but gradually become interesting as my ears adapt. Although the microtonal effect hasn&#8217;t become conventionally pleasing to my ears accustomed to the 12-note scale, I can recognize the inventive nature and derive pleasure from the music on its own merits.</p>



<p>Overall, the quarter-tone pieces demonstrate that microtonality is an acquired taste that requires time to appreciate. The outcome is a captivating sound that I can find enjoyable, even though it hasn&#8217;t fully convinced me.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="IVES Three Quarter Tone Pieces for Two Pianos w/ TMC Fellows" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wwj8mTiZi8o?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Alois Hába &#8211;  Sonata for quarter-tone piano, op.62</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-alois-haba-sonata-for-quarter-tone-piano-op-62/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 20:14:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1736</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Strange is the first word that comes to my mind when listening to Hába&#8217;s Sonata for Quarter-Tone Piano,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Strange is the first word that comes to my mind when listening to Hába&#8217;s Sonata for Quarter-Tone Piano, Op. 62. After researching microtonality, I&#8217;ve come to enjoy the concept and composers&#8217; reasons for exploring it. But the truth is my ears are so accustomed to the 12-semitone scale that I initially find microtonal music weird. Recent examples in rock and jazz, like King Gizzard and Jacob Collier, are growing on me. Yet even in the slower, more lyrical second movement of Hába&#8217;s sonata, I struggle to fully appreciate the quarter tones. </p>



<p>Making an effort to keep an open mind, I can sense the pioneering spirit of discovery in Hába’s quarter-tone innovations. They impart an otherworldly, dreamlike quality as my ear gradually adjusts. But my long familiarity with 12-tone equal temperament means microtones continue to sound strange at first, even as I recognize their creative possibilities. However, after listening to it more carefully, I started to notice there&#8217;s some beauty and subtlety of the quarter tones. The sonata has a lot of variation and contrast that I can see me appreciating it the more I listen to it.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Alois Hába: Sonata for quarter tone piano, op.62 (1946/1947)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FDs7ve1uGbg?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p><a href="https://bard.google.com/" target="_blank"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Greta Van Fleet &#8211; Light My Love</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-greta-van-fleet-light-my-love/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 20:20:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1751</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As a Led Zeppelin fan, I was eager to check out the band Greta Van Fleet after a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As a Led Zeppelin fan, I was eager to check out the band Greta Van Fleet after a friend&#8217;s recommendation. While I enjoyed several of their retro-rock tracks that pay homage to Zeppelin&#8217;s classic sound, the song &#8220;Light My Love&#8221; stood out as my favourite.</p>



<p>The piano melody at the start sets up an interesting intro, but after a few bars, the song explodes into a full-on rock explosion. The lead singer, Josh Kiszka, has a voice that sounds remarkably similar to the legendary Robert Plant &#8211; soaring and crystalline one moment, then shifting into joyful wails that drive the energy ever higher.</p>



<p>Though the chorus repeats in typical pop fashion, the anthemic sound of guitars and drums keeps it from being repetitive. Kiszka unleashes some spectacular high screams that electrify the lyrics. Overall, while Greta Van Fleet wears their influences proudly, &#8220;Light My Love&#8221; shows they can also craft an exhilarating retro-rock song that stands on its own. For a Led Zeppelin fan like me, it left me eager to hear more from this talented young band.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Creating my own performance of John Cage’s 4’33”</title>
		<link>./../../../../../creating-my-own-performance-of-john-cages-433/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 21:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1675</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I decided to perform John Cage&#8217;s 4&#8217;33&#8221; alone in my living room. I set a timer to keep&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I decided to perform John Cage&#8217;s 4&#8217;33&#8221; alone in my living room. I set a timer to keep up track of the time. At first, there was complete silence as I sat motionless on a chair. After about a minute, I started to hear subtle sounds &#8211; the gentle creaking of the wooden floor, distant traffic noises outside, and the occasional sound of myself shifting in their chair. These ambient sounds almost took on a musical quality as I focused intently on listening.</p>



<p>The effect was surprisingly mesmerizing. In the absence of deliberate music, the mundane sounds, often unnoticed, took centre stage, and I immediately understood what Cage intended with this piece.</p>



<p>Around the two-minute mark, the silence was broken by my stomach rumbling loudly. I had to stifle a laugh at this unexpected bodily interjection. A few moments later, a siren wailed in the distance. The juxtaposition of these random noises with the intended silence of the piece was amusing to me.</p>



<p>When the 4 minutes and 33 seconds were up, I felt a sense of accomplishment. Although an audience may have enhanced the experience, performing 4&#8217;33&#8221; alone made me appreciate the musical potential of everyday sounds. I found beauty in the silence between the noises. This piece definitely expanded my perspective on what can be considered music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
