<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Coursework &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 15:28:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Exercise 2.1 &#8211; Chopin Ornaments</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-2-1-chopin-ornaments/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 12:53:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1026</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="969" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1-1024x969.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1028" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1-1024x969.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1-300x284.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1-768x727.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1-1536x1453.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1-2048x1937.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1-640x605.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1-960x908.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1.mp3"></audio></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="995" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2-1024x995.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1030" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2-1024x995.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2-300x291.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2-768x746.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2-1536x1492.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2-2048x1989.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2-640x622.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2-960x932.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2.mp3"></audio></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="712" height="1024" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3-712x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1032" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3-712x1024.png 712w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3-208x300.png 208w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3-768x1105.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3-1067x1536.png 1067w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3-1423x2048.png 1423w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3-300x432.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3-640x921.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3-960x1381.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 712px) 100vw, 712px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-1.mp3" length="319709" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-2.mp3" length="319292" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Exercise-2.1-3.mp3" length="319292" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 2.4: Chopin Nocturne Op.9 No.3</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-2-4-chopin-nocturne-op-9-no-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 11:48:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1022</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Maria João Pires&#8217; performance was the first I heard. The dynamic range is quite wide and there is&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Chopin: Nocturne No. 3 in B Major, Op. 9, No. 3" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0NCRKFajfFE?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Maria João Pires&#8217; performance was the first I heard. The dynamic range is quite wide and there is a lot of rubato. It seems that she plays faster prior to the louder dynamics and slower prior to the quieter markings. The performance becomes less monotonous and more interesting as a result.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Chopin Nocturne Op. 9 No. 3 in B Major (Arthur Rubinstein)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/O3Apq41rrFc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Like Maria João Pires, Rubinstein uses a lot of rubato, especially on the highest notes. In his performance, he sustains high notes subtly to create a more dramatic effect. In spite of the short dynamic range in the Agitato, the last section is intense and played with an astonishing force.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Chopin Nocturne Op.9, No.3 ♪ Hiroko Nakamura (2010) ♪" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RPgywDE8DA8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I listened to Nakamura&#8217;s live performance. During the performance there was a lot of use of rubato, moving faster and slower several times within a short period of time. The first ornaments are played very slowly, compared to other performances, and she doesn&#8217;t completely stop at the fermatas. As a whole, I feel like a lot of creative liberties were taken during the performance regarding speed.</p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Nocturnes, Op. 9: No. 3 in B Major. Allegretto" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2xjje2wowwx26ZkNNCkz6n?si=aac5feb0688242e3&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This recording by Lisiecki is the one that follows the score more closely. Particularly the stacatto at the end of the main phrase. It was the only performer I listened to who played stacatto and it opened my eyes to a new perspective. Throughout the piece there is very little rubato nor a lot of variation in dynamics, making it less dramatic than other performances.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Anna Fedorova – Nocturne in B major, Op. 9 No. 3 (first stage, 2010)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QrdK47U_VKA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Foderova&#8217;s performance is very intense. Maybe because it&#8217;s a live performance. A lot of that intensity comes from the rubato and some creative liberties she takes with the score, but mainly from her pauses. She uses dramatic pauses, especially at the end of the Agitato, which lasts for almost six seconds.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 2.4: Performance practice in practice</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-2-4-performance-practice-in-practice/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 16:19:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1016</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Every artistic form that requires performers, such as theatre, cinema, dance, or music, always raises the question: how&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Every artistic form that requires performers, such as theatre, cinema, dance, or music, always raises the question: how personal should a performance be? Should the interpretation of written art be faithful to the author&#8217;s intentions? Does it make sense to contextualize old works to the era in which they were performed? Is there a set of rules to follow? If so, does that make a performance authentic? What is authenticity?</p>



<p>There are many questions when it comes to Performance Practice. I won&#8217;t be able to answer all of them, but I&#8217;ll try to answer &#8220;What is Performance Practice?&#8221;, &#8220;What factors should a performer consider when interpreting a score?&#8221; and &#8220;What makes a good performance?&#8221;.</p>



<p>The field of Performance Practice or Historical Informed Practice studies performance (Rile, 2014), specifically how performance was practised in the past. In general, it focuses on works from the 18th century and earlier that have no contemporary recordings. In order to make an informed interpretation of a piece, a performer should take into account that music reflects the culture of the place where it was composed. In addition to its composer&#8217;s personality, it reflects the values of its society at the time the piece was composed and the instruments available.</p>



<p>A successful performance practice involves a number of factors inherent to the music, including sound, physical space, tuning and temperament, articulation, tempo, and dynamics (Duffin, 2017).</p>



<p>Sound, for instance, describes how instruments sounded at the time of composition. Many instruments have changed since then. Some don&#8217;t exist anymore, and others weren&#8217;t invented until the 18th century (such as the piano). Therefore, when choosing instruments to play, the performer must consider the sound the composer intended.</p>



<p>Dynamic and tempo are also examples. It is usually up to the interpreter to decide what those indications in the scores mean. In terms of tempo, metronomes weren&#8217;t invented until the 19th century, so pieces written before that can&#8217;t be gauged concretely. In fact, there is some debate about whether Bach&#8217;s music has been played faster or slower over time (Niles, 2018). Similarly, dynamics are ambiguous. A forte or piano can mean something different to different performers or even to different venues.</p>



<p>A historically informed performance is also influenced by factors that are extrinsic to music. This includes the social and political context, the piece&#8217;s commission, and the venue where it was to be performed. Factors such as these can help determine intrinsic musical characteristics.</p>



<p>In the end, the most influential factor is the personality of the performer, which influences the interpretation of the piece greatly. Without a performer&#8217;s interpretation, all performances of a piece would sound the same. It is my belief that most composers would not wish to remove that human trait from a performance.&nbsp;</p>



<p>All arts are human by definition. As a result, such arts will always feature interpretation, improvisation, adaptation, contextualization, ambition, and imagination. Ultimately, what makes a&nbsp;good&nbsp;performance, and specifically good performance practice, will come down to the performer&#8217;s&nbsp;good&nbsp;judgment.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1668443201822 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Rile, K. (2014) <em>Christopher Hogwood, founder of the &#8216;historically informed performance &#8230;</em>, <em>Jstor</em>. Available at: https://daily.jstor.org/christopher-hogwood-founder-of-the-historically-informed-performance-movement-dies/ (Accessed: November 14, 2022).</p>



<p>Duffin, D.R.W. (2017) <em>Performance Practice: Que me veux-tu?</em>, <em>Dr Ross W Duffin Performance Practice Que me veuxtu Comments</em>. Available at: https://casfaculty.case.edu/ross-duffin/96-2/ (Accessed: November 14, 2022).</p>



<p>Niles, L. (2018) <em>Study: Performances of classical music are getting slower! I mean quicker! wait, what?</em>, <em>Violinist.com</em>. Available at: https://www.violinist.com/blog/laurie/201810/27520/ (Accessed: November 14, 2022).</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 2.3 – Globalisation</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-2-3-globalisation/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 16:17:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1004</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Some claim that the world is gradually becoming united, that it will grow into a brotherly community as&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>Some claim that the world is gradually becoming united, that it will grow into a brotherly community as distances shrink and ideas are transmitted through the air. Alas, you must not believe that men can be united in this way.</p><cite>Fyodor Dostoevsky,&nbsp;<em>The Brothers Karamazov</em>&nbsp;(1880)</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>Globalisation is “a term that describes a new era of human communication and interconnection across cultural, national, and geographic boundaries” (Beaster-Jones, 2013). In other words, it refers to a growing relationship between culture, economy, and people, with an emphasis on the economic side. In this text, cosmopolitanism and globalisation must be distinguished. The first one is a socioeconomic force that strives to homogenize consumption. The second is a personal attitude towards embracing diversity and humanizing it (Petriglieri, 2016).</p>



<p>A modern concept of globalisation might have started with the Roman Empire, which interconnected the world (part of it, to be precise), leading to easier mobility (Bora &amp; Bonelli, 2019). Globalisation was made truly global around the 16th century when the relationship between countries such as Portugal, Spain, India and China intensified (Flynn &amp; Giraldez, 2007). As transportation became easier, safer, and faster, cultures, thoughts, and rituals clashed more frequently in various aspects of society in the 17th and 18th centuries. Culture and music were not exceptions, as music is inherently social.</p>



<p>Globalisation during the romantic period was caused by three factors. First of all, the decrease in aristocracy patronage broadened audiences and gave the artist more room for experimentation with novel sounds, techniques, and instruments. Secondly, artists became more virtuosic and self-expressive, leading to a fusion of their cultural roots with traditional and local music, creating new sounds. Bartók and Chopin, for instance, are known for incorporating folk songs from their birth countries into their music. Lastly, the mobility of artists. Artists (and audiences) have become less limited by time and space and were able to interact across many locations. Apart from the increase in world fairs and music festivals that attracted worldwide audiences, music tourism and travel allowed artists to experience new cultures and be inspired by them.</p>



<p>As a result of increased globalisation, artists experimented more and audiences were predisposed to exploring different sounds, new formats, and new instruments. This resulted in even broader experimentation during the modernist era, which influenced modern music in the 20th century. If artists and audiences weren&#8217;t inclined to merge cultures and experiment with new sounds, genres like blues, jazz, rock, K-pop and reggaeton wouldn&#8217;t exist.</p>



<p>Even though society and music have made remarkable advances, there are some concerns about globalisation. A major concern is the loss of individuality. Cultural homogenization is a risk associated with globalisation, and there is a fear that the individuality and identity of a group will be lost in an effort to incorporate other cultural settings (Back, 2012). There is also concern about undue cultural appropriation, which is a more recent concern. In the context of globalisation, cultural appropriation is unavoidable. However, a question arises as to how we can use other cultures&#8217; proprieties and what processes are legitimate so that we can increase contact between cultures (Choufan, 2021).</p>



<p>In my opinion, all advances in technology are preparing society for increased globalisation. With the advent of streaming music platforms, social networks, and cheap travel, it&#8217;s more common to see the effects of globalisation, such as multi-country genres (K-Pop) or mixed-background bands (The Foreign Exchange and Superorganism). In the future, globalisation may turn into glocalisation (Roudometof, 2016) in which instead of cultural homogenization, local cultures will adapt global phenomena into their own traditions. This can be seen today, where there is a widening diversity of consumption of Spotify and iTunes in different countries than ever before (Bello &amp; Garcia, 2021).</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1667922592850 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Beaster-Jones, J. (2013) <em>Globalization</em>, <em>Groove Music Online</em>. Available at: https://www-oxfordmusiconline-com.ucreative.idm.oclc.org/grovemusic/view/10.1093/gmo/9781561592630.001.0001/omo-9781561592630-e-1002256705 (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p>Petriglieri, G. (2016) <em>In Defense of Cosmopolitanism</em>, <em>Harvard Business Review</em>. Available at: https://hbr.org/2016/12/in-defense-of-cosmopolitanism (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p>Bora, D. and Bonelli, A. (2019) <em>THE ROMAN EMPIRE Economical Globalization</em>, <em>Research Gate</em>. Available at: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/336798821_THE_ROMAN_EMPIRE_Economical_Globalization (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p>Flynn, D.O. and Giraldez, A. (2007) <em>Born again: Globalization&#8217;s sixteenth-century origins (Asian/global versus European Dynamics)</em>, <em>eScholarship, University of California</em>. Available at: https://escholarship.org/uc/item/8zw088bj#main (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p>Schmidt-Jones, C. (no date) <em>Romantic Era Explored </em>, <em>Lumen Learning</em>. Available at: https://courses.lumenlearning.com/suny-musicapp-medieval-modern/chapter/romantic-era-explored/ (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p><em>Bartók, Béla</em> (no date) <em>UNHCR Central Europe</em>. Available at: https://www.unhcr.org/ceu/9429-bartok-bela.html (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p><em>Frédéric Chopin</em> (no date) <em>Encyclopædia Britannica</em>. Encyclopædia Britannica, inc. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/biography/Frederic-Chopin (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p>Back, L. (2012) <em>Cultural sociology an introduction</em>. Chichester, West Sussex: Wiley-Blackwell.</p>



<p>Choufan, L. (2021) <em>Op-ed: The cultural appropriation paradox</em>, <em>The Business of Fashion</em>. The Business of Fashion. Available at: https://www.businessoffashion.com/opinions/news-analysis/op-ed-the-cultural-appropriation-paradox/ (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p>Roudometof, V.N. (2016) <em>Glocalization: A critical introduction</em>, <em>researchgate</em>. Available at: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/304895197_Glocalization_A_Critical_Introduction (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p>Bello, P. and Garcia, D. (2021) <em>Cultural divergence in popular music: The increasing diversity of music consumption on Spotify across countries</em>, <em>Nature News</em>. Nature Publishing Group. Available at: https://www.nature.com/articles/s41599-021-00855-1 (Accessed: November 8, 2022).</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 2.2 – Wagner’s Ring Cycle</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-2-2-wagners-ring-cycle/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 15:41:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=991</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Wagner took around 26 years to complete the Ring Cycle, which consists of four German-language epic music dramas&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Wagner took around 26 years to complete the Ring Cycle, which consists of four German-language epic music dramas lasting about 16 hours. Although the briefing asked for a 500-word essay, I found it challenging to condense such a monumental cycle to that length. The result was a longer text. I watched Opera North&#8217;s performance of The Ring Cycle.</p>



<p>“The Nibelungen Myth as Sketch for a Drama” was Wagner’s first prose sketch in 1848, which sparked his interest in the project. When Wagner began writing the poem (the libretto) for Siegfried’s Death (which became Götterdämmerung), he noticed that the heroic Siegfried had to be described in much more detail and clarity. By working backwards, he crafted Siegfried’s heroic youth story. Siegfried’s parentage and the family history of the Wälsungs are told in Die Walküre. Additionally, Wagner wanted to show how Alberich (the Nibelung dwarf) forged the ring of power from the Rhinegold. The story had been written from end to beginning, and now the music would be composed from beginning to end. In November 1874, the final score for The Ring was completed (Hoover, n.d.).</p>



<p>In Wagner’s vision, this cycle would be set at a festival and performed over three days and one evening. Historically, Wagner had been fascinated by Greek tragedy for some time, and the concept of this opera was a logical fit with those ideals (Hoover, n.d.).</p>



<p>Wagner considered this to be not just a musical composition, but an experience. He introduced the term ‘gesamtkunstwerk’, which means “total work of art”, in two essays in 1849: Art and Revolution and The Artwork of the Future. His goal was to reunite the most common forms of art – music, drama, poetry, and staging (Krause, 2020).</p>



<p>During the development of this opera, he developed much larger orchestras, invented new instruments (the Wagner Tuba was created by him), and took the staging to an entirely unprecedented level. In all likelihood, he was the one who pushed for the lights to be turned down and the drama played in the dark to ensure a better viewing experience (Huizenga &amp; Daugert, 2008). His obsessive specifications led him to build a radically redesigned theatre in Bayreuth, Germany. In doing so, he forever changed the landscape of musical theatre.</p>



<p>In terms of music, this cycle is notable for its use of leitmotifs (over sixty in total). While leitmotifs existed before Wagner, he used them creatively, altering keys, upside down, mixing them together, and more (Midgette, 2021). His music became a narrator and participant in the action, instead of just acting as an accompanist.</p>



<p>This led to the idea of a talking orchestra (Midgette, 2021). It was Wagner’s desire for the orchestra to function like the chorus of a Greek tragedy, predicting, showing, and commenting on what happens. This required sixty-four stringed instruments, four times as many wind instruments, and more prominence for the brass section than was common at the time.</p>



<p>All this grandiosity led to an enormous challenge for the singers. In addition to the length of the opera, the greatest challenge for the singers was to make themselves heard over such a powerful orchestra. The technical difficulty of singing these operas has given rise to the term Wagnerian voice: a voice that is substantial, dense in tone, extremely powerful, and ideally evenly balanced throughout.</p>



<p>Personally, I was most impressed by the amount of work Wagner put into The Ring Cycle. The more research I do, the more I realize how innovative and impactful his work was for our music. By using the orchestra as a storyteller, the music feels a lot like a soundtrack for a movie, very similar to what contemporary composers compose for movies today. It is clear now why composers like Korngold cite Wagner as an inspiration (Ross, 2020).</p>



<p>The development of the characters was another thing I liked. There is no clear line between good and evil. All characters have strengths and flaws, akin to Game Of Thrones and less to Lord Of The Rings. This makes them more human (even Gods) and complex, and the music reflects this.</p>



<p>On the negative side, I felt overwhelmed. Too much is happening all the time, with too many leitmotifs, plots, and themes. It’s true that the leitmotifs appear again and again during the operas, but there isn’t much sense of repetition that makes the ears rest from the continuous novelty. There is almost an impression that Wagner wanted to show all of his virtuosity in one work and to develop his ideas as much as possible. However, it’s always a good idea to remember that less is more.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1667572981065 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><em>Watch online: The ring cycle</em> (no date) <em>Opera North</em>. Available at: https://www.operanorth.co.uk/the-ring-cycle/ (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Hoover, K. (no date) <em>The miracle of Richard Wagner&#8217;s ring</em>, <em>Triangle Wagner Society</em>. Available at: https://trianglewagnersociety.com/resources/the-miracle-of-richard-wagners-ring (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p><em>The beginner&#8217;s guide to wagner: Discover opera: Eno</em> (no date) <em>English National Opera</em>. Available at: https://www.eno.org/discover-opera/operas/the-beginners-guide-to-wagner/ (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Krause, P. (2020) <em>The drama of Love in Richard Wagner&#8217;s &#8220;Ring of the nibelungen&#8221; ~ the imaginative conservative</em>, <em>The Imaginative Conservative</em>. Available at: https://theimaginativeconservative.org/2020/01/drama-love-richard-wagner-ring-of-the-nibelungen-paul-krause.html (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Huizenga, T. and Daugert, K. (2008) <em>The self-help guide to Wagner</em>, <em>NPR</em>. NPR. Available at: https://www.npr.org/2008/05/29/90286740/the-self-help-guide-to-wagner (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Midgette, A. (2021) <em>A conductor&#8217;s view of the &#8220;Ring.&#8221;</em>, <em>The Washington Post</em>. WP Company. Available at: https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/style/wp/2016/05/19/a-conductors-view-of-the-ring/ (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p>Ross, A. (2020) <em>The force is still strong with John Williams</em>, <em>The New Yorker</em>. Available at: https://www.newyorker.com/culture/persons-of-interest/the-force-is-still-strong-with-john-williams (Accessed: November 4, 2022).</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 2.1: Hector Berlioz &#8211; Harold en Italie</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-2-1-hector-berlioz-harold-en-italie/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 10:51:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=972</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Symphonie Fantastique, one of Hector Berlioz&#8217;s most well-known compositions, was composed in 1830. After winning the Prix de&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1666180011170 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1666180011196" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="click-here-to-see-the-briefing" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">Click here to see the briefing</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<p>Write around 400 words on your impression of the score and music. Among other things consider:</p>



<ol><li>To what extent do you find the composition depicts its programme?</li><li>What do you find extraordinary?</li><li>What catches your eye or your ear?</li><li>How is the solo viola used?</li></ol>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1666180011198" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
			</div>
</div>

</div>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Hector Berlioz- Harold en Italie [With score]" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SGkzjX6A1-s?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Symphonie Fantastique, one of Hector Berlioz&#8217;s most well-known compositions, was composed in 1830. After winning the Prix de Rome, the composer spent fifteen months in Italy between 1831 and 1832, and this experience is especially evident in Harold in Italy. Berlioz preferred the Abruzzi mountains over the academy&#8217;s environment, concerts, and operas in Rome (Bynog et al., 2021).</p>



<p>After Paganini’s commission of Harold in Italy, Berlioz finished it in 1834, not only recalling his experience in Italy as an inspiration for the programmatic structure of this symphony but also drawing inspiration from Lord Byron’s popular poem Childe Harold’s Pilgrimage. This resulted in Berlioz utilizing descriptive titles for each movement and the corresponding programmatic nature of the music since he was aiming for writing “a musical impression of the archetypal romantic hero” (Clements, 2001):</p>



<ul><li>Harold in the mountains</li><li>Procession of the Pilgrims Singing Their Evening Prayer</li><li>Serenade</li><li>The Orgy of the Brigands</li></ul>



<p>Unifying all these movements is the solo instrument: the viola. In his plan, Berlioz envisaged “a series of orchestral scenes in which the viola would be involved […] like an actual person, retaining the same character throughout”. That character would be “a melancholy dreamer in the&nbsp;style of Byron’s Childe Harold” (Deller, 2019).</p>



<p>The most interesting thing is that, facing a plan like this, a composer would be compelled to write strong, loud and bold viola lines in every movement, making the instrument and the player shine. But Berlioz took another approach. In order to create a character like Harold, he made the viola gentle, shy, and quiet. It is the orchestra that can sometimes be loud, rough, and strong.</p>



<p>I was struck by the instruction to play the viola as softly as possible &#8211; barely audible. This paradoxically draws more attention to the instrument. A very quiet performance requires an effort on the part of the audience to be able to hear it. The viola player, however, needs to be highly skilled, since it is more difficult to play loudly than softly. For the sound intensity to be maintained along the bow&#8217;s full length, the performer&#8217;s stance must be firmly grounded with solid shoulders and right arm stability (Bathurst, 2016).</p>



<p>This piece was written in the aftermath of the French Revolution and the Napoleonic devastation and trauma, when society was deciding whether to be ruled by a charismatic leader of a totalitarian or by a humane, humble and compassionate leader (Bathurst, 2016). As a humanitarian (Klein, 1969), I believe Berlioz used the viola as a symbol of the latter, being subtle and quiet and allowing the orchestra to shine when necessary, rather than being the solo instrument that always takes center stage. Paganini might not have realized this when he read the score, but after hearing it and watching the viola&#8217;s role, he understood.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow"><p>Beethoven dead there was no one but Berlioz who could bring him back to life; and I who have experienced your divine compositions worthy of a genius such as yours, believe it is my duty to beg you to be willing to accept as a sign of my homage 20,000 francs.</p><cite>Letter from Paganini to Berlioz</cite></blockquote>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1666623938633 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Bynog, D.M. (2021) “3: Hector Berlioz: Harold in Italy, op. 16,” in Notes for violists: A guide to the repertoire. New York, NY: Oxford University Press.</p>



<p>Clements, A. (2001) <em>Belioz: Harold in Italy</em>, <em>The Guardian</em>. Guardian News and Media. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2001/nov/16/shopping.artsfeatures4 (Accessed: October 24, 2022).</p>



<p>Deller, T. (2019) <em>A musical outcast? Harold en italie as metaphor for the viola itself</em>, <em>The Strad</em>. Available at: https://www.thestrad.com/debate/a-musical-outcast-harold-en-italie-as-metaphor-for-the-viola-itself/9006.article (Accessed: October 24, 2022).</p>



<p>Bathurst, R. (2016) <em>Berlioz&#8217;s Harold in Italy: Leading softly</em>, <em>Elgar Online: The online content platform for Edward Elgar Publishing</em>. Edward Elgar Publishing Ltd. Available at: https://www.elgaronline.com/view/journals/lath/4-1/lath.2016.01.02.xml (Accessed: October 24, 2022).</p>



<p>Klein, J. W. (1969) <em>Berlioz’s Personality. Music &amp; Letters, vol. 50, no. 1, 1969, pp. 15–24</em>, <em>JSTOR</em>. Available at: http://www.jstor.org/stable/732896 (Accessed: October 24, 2022).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 2.0</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-2-0/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 15:21:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=966</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[During this exercise, I struggled a lot, so I did some more research about transposing. I found this&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>During this exercise, I struggled a lot, so I did some more research about transposing. I found this video by Mattia Chiappa explaining transposing with the guitar (an instrument I am more familiar with) and explaining the difference between the two steps: writing and reading. As a result, I understand better the process of transposing and was able to do the exercise more efficiently.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Transposing instruments made easy" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/I2WzVRj9k1A?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Horns, Don Juan, bb.1-5, sounding pitch:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="263" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-1024x263.png" alt="" class="wp-image-968" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-1024x263.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-300x77.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-768x197.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-1536x394.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-2048x525.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-640x164.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns-960x246.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Horns.png 2075w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Clarinets, Don Juan, bb.1-5, sounding pitch:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="132" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-1024x132.png" alt="" class="wp-image-969" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-1024x132.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-300x39.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-768x99.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-1536x198.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-2048x264.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-640x83.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets-960x124.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/10/Excercise-2.0-Clarinets.png 2171w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 2.0: The orchestral score￼</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-2-0-the-orchestral-score%ef%bf%bc/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 15:29:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=961</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My go-to book behind bars was helpful in researching the instrument order on an orchestral score. I discovered&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>My go-to book behind bars was helpful in researching the instrument order on an orchestral score.</p>



<p>I discovered that orchestral and large ensemble scores group instrumental sections in the following order: woodwinds, brass, percussion, keyboards, and strings.</p>



<p>Additionally, no matter how few staves are present within a score, instrumental staves remain in the same position.</p>



<p>Each instrument should be listed in the following order:</p>



<p>Piccolo</p>



<p>Flute</p>



<p>Oboe</p>



<p>Cor Anglais</p>



<p>Clarinet</p>



<p>Bass Clarinet</p>



<p>Saxophones</p>



<p>Bassoon</p>



<p>Contrabassoon</p>



<p>Horns</p>



<p>Trumpets</p>



<p>Trombones</p>



<p>Tuba</p>



<p>Timpani</p>



<p>Percussion</p>



<p>Harp and plucked stringed instruments</p>



<p>Keyboard instruments</p>



<p>Soloists or Choir</p>



<p>Violin I</p>



<p>Violin II</p>



<p>Viola</p>



<p>Cello</p>



<p>Contrabass</p>



<p></p>



<p>In terms of translating instruments, these are the most common languages:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>English</strong></td><td><strong>Italian</strong></td><td><strong>German</strong></td><td><strong>French</strong></td></tr><tr><td>Piccolo</td><td>Flauto piccolo or Ottavino</td><td>Kleine Flote</td><td>Petite Flute</td></tr><tr><td>Flute</td><td>Flauto</td><td>Flote or Grosse Flote</td><td>Flute or Grande Flute</td></tr><tr><td>Oboe</td><td>Oboe</td><td>Hoboe</td><td>Hautbois</td></tr><tr><td>English Horn</td><td>Corno Inglese</td><td>Englischhorn</td><td>Cor Anglais</td></tr><tr><td>Clarinet</td><td>Clarinetto</td><td>Klarinette</td><td>Clarinette</td></tr><tr><td>Bass Clarinet</td><td>Clarinetto basso</td><td>Bassklarinette</td><td>Clarinette basse</td></tr><tr><td>Bassoon</td><td>Fagotto</td><td>Fagott</td><td>Basson</td></tr><tr><td>Contrabassoon</td><td>Contrafagotto</td><td>Kontrafagott</td><td>Contrebasson</td></tr><tr><td>Horn or French Horn</td><td>Corno</td><td>Horn/Horner</td><td>Cor</td></tr><tr><td>Trumpet</td><td>Tromba</td><td>Trompete</td><td>Trompette</td></tr><tr><td>Trombone</td><td>Trombone</td><td>Posaune</td><td>Trombone</td></tr><tr><td>Tuba</td><td>Tuba</td><td>Tuba</td><td>Tuba</td></tr><tr><td>Kettle drums</td><td>Timpani</td><td>Pauken</td><td>Timbales</td></tr><tr><td>Triangle</td><td>Triangolo</td><td>Triangel</td><td>Triangle</td></tr><tr><td>Cymbals</td><td>Piatti/Cinelli</td><td>Becken</td><td>Cymbales</td></tr><tr><td>Glockenspiel</td><td>Campanelli</td><td>Glockenspiel</td><td>Jeu de timbres or Carillon</td></tr><tr><td>Harp</td><td>Arpa</td><td>Harfe</td><td>Harpe</td></tr><tr><td>Violin</td><td>Violino</td><td>Violine</td><td>Violon</td></tr><tr><td>Viola</td><td>Viola</td><td>Bratsche</td><td>Alto</td></tr><tr><td>Cello</td><td>Violoncello</td><td>Violoncello</td><td>Violoncelle</td></tr><tr><td>Contrabass</td><td>Contrabasso or Basso</td><td>Kontrabass</td><td>Contrebasse</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
