<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 11:08:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Devonté Hynes &#8211; The Long Ride II</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-devonte-hynes-the-long-ride-ii/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 14:39:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I decided to listen to Devonté Hynes&#8217; music after reading a review in the Guardian of his concert&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Devonté Hynes: The Long Ride II; Inheritance with Adam Tendler" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_PcxLhJrkGI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I decided to listen to Devonté Hynes&#8217; music after reading a review in the Guardian of his concert with the London Symphony Orchestra. I didn&#8217;t know his work, so it was interesting to dig a bit into his work. </p>



<p>Devonté Hynes&#8217; Long Ride II is a two-piano rendition that was written for HBO&#8217;s Series “We Are Who We Are.” Hynes is primarily known for his R&amp;B and indie music, but he has recently been exploring classical music, which I find an interesting move. </p>



<p>The Long Ride II features a repetitive arpeggio and chords in one of the pianos, while the other builds upon the background, almost as if it is improvising. It has an impressionist feeling of improvisation, and perhaps in the live version, the pianist is really improvising.</p>



<p>The piece is based on an F major chord, and there doesn&#8217;t seem to be a defined structure. Instead, there is an increase in texture that keeps growing until almost the finale where one of the pianos plays alone, which is like a return to the beginning.</p>



<p>Although Devonté Hynes&#8217; Long Ride II is an intriguing piece of music that highlights his exploration of classical music, I personally don&#8217;t find its repetitive nature appealing. However, I believe that delving deeper into the music can reveal the specific elements of change or lack thereof that either draw us in or push us away. While there are examples of repetitive music that do appeal to me (such as compositions by Steve Reich, for instance), it seems that in the case of Long Ride II, there may be either insufficient or excessive variation that prevents it from capturing my interest. Nonetheless, I still believe it was worth giving it a listen.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Gamelan</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-gamelan/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 12:57:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1256</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[After reading about Debussy&#8217;s fascination with Javanese gamelan music and its influence on his compositions, I became intrigued&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>After reading about Debussy&#8217;s fascination with Javanese gamelan music and its influence on his compositions, I became intrigued and decided to listen to it myself.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Sound Tracker - Gamelan (Indonesia)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UEWCCSuHsuQ?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Balinese Gamelan - Sekar Jupun" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0RKM2xj0qKc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Angklung Pupuan" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Dwc9voKOgyw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Gamelan music, originating from Java in Indonesia, features an ensemble of tuned metal instruments, including gongs and percussion instruments. This type of music is also found throughout Southeast Asia. The sound of gamelan music is characterized by an interplay of metallic sounds defined by one of two scales: slendro, which divides the octave into five equal intervals, and pelog, which divides it into seven.</p>



<p>Balinese music is structured like a tree, with different instruments symbolizing the trunk, branches, and flowers. The core melody, or pokok, is played by one group of instruments in one octave. Another group stresses this melody at regular intervals, while a third expands it into a full melody with a range of two to three octaves. A fourth group doubles and paraphrases it an octave higher, while a fifth group plays an ornamental figuration. Gongs punctuate and structure the music, while the drums provide rhythmic support.</p>



<p>Upon listening to gamelan music, one is struck by the clear and metallic sounds, which evoke the stirring of a thousand bells. The interplay of the sounds is delicate and complex and possesses a sensuous charm. The overall effect is one of mystery, which can be quite overpowering.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1679316807717 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Channing, A. (2020) <em>Balinese gamelan: a complete guide to a unique world of sound</em>. Available at: https://www.songlines.co.uk/features/balinese-gamelan-a-complete-guide-to-a-unique-world-of-sound (Accessed: February 28, 2023).</p>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Haydn &#8211; String Quartet in E-flat, Op. 33, No. 2</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-haydn-string-quartet-in-e-flat-op-33-no-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 12:10:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1300</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In 1781, Franz Joseph Haydn composed his Op. 33 String Quartets, which he dedicated to the Grand Duke&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In 1781, Franz Joseph Haydn composed his Op. 33 String Quartets, which he dedicated to the Grand Duke Paul of Russia. Consequently, these quartets are frequently referred to as the &#8220;Russian&#8221; quartets. The second quartet in E-flat, commonly known as the &#8220;Joke&#8221; quartet, is the most celebrated of the set. The nickname &#8220;Joke&#8221; is believed to have originated from the final movement, which incorporates a series of playful musical jokes, such as a mock conclusion and an unexpected outburst of powerful chords, which leave the listener with a feeling of joyful surprise.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="716" height="1024" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-716x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1302" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-716x1024.png 716w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-210x300.png 210w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-300x429.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-640x915.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40.png 747w" sizes="(max-width: 716px) 100vw, 716px" /></figure>



<p>Comprising four movements, the piece follows a a non-traditional structure. The first movement is composed in Sonata form, while the second, instead of being a Minuet and Trio, is a Scherzo and Trio. The third and fourth movements are both arranged as a Rondo.</p>



<p>The quartet opens with a delightful theme that is subsequently fragmented, manipulated, and reassembled in various ways. Personally, I found this movement to be lighthearted and fascinating, particularly as Haydn deftly plays with the theme, departing from and returning to it, as demonstrated in the following example.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="713" height="517" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.43.45.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1303" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.43.45.png 713w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.43.45-300x218.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.43.45-640x464.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 713px) 100vw, 713px" /></figure>



<p>The second movement caught my attention with the violin slides present in the Trio section. The movement has a dance-like quality to it, with the second violin intermittently interacting with the first violin. At the same time, the viola and cello provide a steady foundation for the piece.</p>



<p>The third movement presents a stark contrast, opening with the lower strings and at a slower tempo in a Largo style. I found the movement to be somewhat dramatic, particularly with the powerful forte chords played by all strings. An illustration of this effect is evident in the following example towards the end of the movement.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="453" height="295" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.57.43.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1307" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.57.43.png 453w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.57.43-300x195.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 453px) 100vw, 453px" /></figure>



<p>The Rondo in the fourth movement shows a catchy, memorable theme that is both danceable and owns a humorous character. The coda segment of the movement is surprising, as the expected recurrence of the theme is subject to hesitant pauses, creating a sense of suspense and uncertainty for the listener. The final pause builds a sense of anticipation, ultimately ending with a soft whisper that leaves the listener with an unresolved sense of closure.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Igor Stravinsky &#8211; Symphonies of Wind Instruments</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-igor-stravinsky-symphonies-of-wind-instruments/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 15:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1242</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[During my research on Debussy, I discovered that he and Stravinsky were close friends. Following Debussy&#8217;s death, Stravinsky&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="IGOR STRAVINSKY Symphonies of Wind Instruments (1947 version)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VyKTujyLie4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>During my research on Debussy, I discovered that he and Stravinsky were close friends. Following Debussy&#8217;s death, Stravinsky paid tribute by composing a serene chorale, which was later incorporated into the &#8220;Symphonies of Wind Instruments&#8221; in 1920. In 1945, Stravinsky revised the work, publishing it in 1947, and made alterations including the removal of the alto flute and alto clarinet, as well as reworking the musical score.</p>



<p>After listening to it the first time, I absolutely loved this piece. I keep finding Stravinsky&#8217;s work amazing and it&#8217;s one of the composers I most like to listen to, but at the same time is the one I find most difficult to analyze. In the next paragraphs I&#8217;ll try to understand what made me like this piece.</p>



<p>The first hint comes from the title. The &#8220;Symphonies of Wind Instruments&#8221; is a musical work with a title that alludes to the original definition of symphony (as opposed to the musical form) as a harmonious blending of instruments. That&#8217;s one of the characteristics of this piece that stroke me right away. The interplay between the different wind instruments, particularly in terms of the contrasting chromatic tones between the woodwinds and brass, is particularly striking. Stravinsky&#8217;s manipulation of the instruments, such as in bar 3 where he plays a Bb in the trumpet and a B in the clarinets, creates a unique sonic landscape that highlights the tonal differences between the instruments.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="774" height="900" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1243" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41.png 774w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41-258x300.png 258w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41-768x893.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41-300x349.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41-640x744.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 774px) 100vw, 774px" /></figure>



<p>The formal structure of the piece proves to be elusive and challenging to categorize. It frequently alternates between tempos, including 144, 108, and 72 beats per minute, which are related by a ratio of 2:3:4. The fluctuating time signature only adds to the impression of multiple distinct musical ideas being woven together in the composition.</p>



<p>From the beginning, Stravinsky introduces contrasting thematic materials, switching between joyful flutes, mournful full chords, and the chorale theme, which symbolizes Debussy&#8217;s death or funeral. Throughout the piece, there is no clear narrative or progression. The musical ideas seem to shift abruptly, giving the impression of a series of disconnected fragments.</p>



<p>The chorale theme, which recurs throughout the piece, serves as a unifying thread and provides the piece with a sense of direction. It becomes the focus of the conclusion, which is joyful and uplifting, spreading a sense of peace and resolution.</p>



<p> </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="111" height="1024" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.59.52-111x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1244"/></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
