<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Composing Music &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 07:28:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reflections on Assignment 4</title>
		<link>./../../../reflections-on-assignment-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 13:09:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://shocking-purpose.localsite.io/?p=590</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For part 4 of this unit, I had the opportunity to explore how a counterpoint composition can be&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For part 4 of this unit, I had the opportunity to explore how a counterpoint composition can be developed with the main subject as the focal point. Bach&#8217;s fugues proved to be of great importance here.</p>



<p>I also explored tuned percussion instruments for the first time. I found them varied and versatile. I will certainly explore composition with the timpani and the glockenspiel.</p>



<p>As a result of listening to Ragtime, I also developed a better understanding of rhythm and syncopation in some compositions.</p>



<h3 id="about-assignment-4">About Assignment 4</h3>



<p>So far, this assignment has been the most challenging. The assignment was difficult for me for a number of reasons, but I suspect it was the challenge of writing something different that I placed on myself.</p>



<p>In general, I am not pleased with the composition. It has some parts that I like, especially the motif and some rhythmic details in section C, but as a whole, it doesn&#8217;t appeal to me as much as some of my other compositions.</p>



<p>Despite being aware that a university is a place where people take chances, I will attempt to create something I&#8217;m more familiar with in the next assignment to increase my self-confidence.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 4</title>
		<link>./../../../assignment-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 10:07:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://shocking-purpose.localsite.io/?p=582</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In assignment 4, I had to compose an imitative counterpoint for around 3 minutes using woodwinds and tuned&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In assignment 4, I had to compose an imitative counterpoint for around 3 minutes using woodwinds and tuned percussion.</p>



<p>You can find the final score <a href="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-43-Full-Score.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-43-Full-Score.pdf" target="_blank">here</a> and listen to it below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-4.mp3"></audio></figure>



<h2 id="the-idea-theme" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108541003 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Idea / Theme</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Having felt that my previous assignments were a bit on the safe side, I decided to incorporate the element of surprise into this assignment. It was important for me to try things I hadn&#8217;t done before. I wanted to go to places that made me uncomfortable and use my ingenuity to see if I could surprise myself.</p>



<p>Regarding the theme, along with the idea of surprise, this piece will be about a party, for instance, a wedding, where a dance will be performed by two voices. Then something goes wrong between these two voices, maybe an argument or an altercation that completely changes the mood. Ultimately, both parties reach an agreement and get back to dancing.</p>



<h2 id="the-structure" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108659753 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Structure</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The idea largely determines the structure. This turns the structure into an A-B-C-A-B. I envision this piece beginning with an intro (A section) that will be in the same key, but rhythmically different from the B section. When we move from the B section to the C section, there will be a change in key, time signature, tempo, and dynamics to create a full contrast. After this section, we return to the intro and then the B section.</p>



<p>The A section will be in a minor key, the B section in a major key, and the C section in a minor key. In this piece, I will start in the key of E minor, then move to its relative major key of G major. In the C section, I will use the key of B minor, which is a fifth from the key of E minor, because I want to create some contrast without sounding too abrupt.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-regular cnvs-block-core-table-1628498574118"><table><thead><tr><th>Theme</th><th>Section &amp; Triad</th><th>Duration / Tempo</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>The instruments present themselves and get in the mood for the party</td><td>A &#8211; E minor</td><td>~20 seconds at 75 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They party and dance together with one instrument initiating the dance and the other following</td><td>B &#8211; G major</td><td>~50 seconds at 95 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>Tension builds up and there&#8217;s a fight</td><td>C &#8211; B minor</td><td>~40 seconds at 80 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They come into agreement and return to get themselves in the mood for part</td><td>A&#8217; &#8211; E minor</td><td>~20 seconds at 75 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They slowly return to the dance and party until the end</td><td>B&#8217; &#8211; G major</td><td>~50 seconds at 95 bpm </td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 id="the-motifs" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108877461 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Motifs</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>As I was playing around with the piano, I came up with a motif (in red) that started short and developed into a bigger subject.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="252" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-1024x252.png" alt="" class="wp-image-595" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-1024x252.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-300x74.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-768x189.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-1536x378.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-2048x504.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-640x157.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-960x236.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432.png 2172w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h2 id="the-instruments" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110169912 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Instruments</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Having reviewed a recent video from Philharmonia, I decided to choose the vibraphone because of the sustained sound it produces.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Instruments: Percussion" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-lJctvybAJ8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Philharmonia Orchestra (London, UK), 2013. Instruments: Percussion. Available at:&lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-lJctvybAJ8&gt; [Accessed 15 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>I decided to go with the bassoon for the woodwind instrument again because I am finding it to be much more versatile than I had anticipated.</p>



<p>The combination of these instruments seemed unusual to me, and I was not wrong. Youtube and Spotify returned few results, but I found this performance of a piece by Alexandre Ouzounoff that encouraged me to continue experimenting with these two instruments.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Alexandre Ouzounoff: Cependant, la lune se lève pour basson et vibraphone (2013)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vo1Fgqq8-Kw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>University of Michigan Bassoon Studio, 2015.&nbsp;Alexandre Ouzounoff: Cependant, la lune se lève pour basson et vibraphone (2013). Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vo1Fgqq8-Kw&gt; [Accessed 15 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<h2 id="the-composition" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110414281 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The composition</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><strong>Section A</strong> Bars 1-6</p>



<p>As an introduction to the piece, I composed a short section with both instruments presenting themselves in different moods: the bassoon is strong and sustained, and the vibraphone is fast and harmonious.</p>



<p>I was inspired by Stravinsky&#8217;s bassoon solo in Rite Of Spring to start the piece on a high sustained note.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Stravinsky&#039;s Rite Of Spring Bassoon solo by Gustavo Nunez" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xfg9IIXhcPk?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Nick B., 2007.&nbsp;<em>Stravinsky&#8217;s Rite Of Spring Bassoon solo by Gustavo Nunez</em>. Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xfg9IIXhcPk&gt; [Accessed 15 November 2021].<br></figcaption></figure>



<p>This introduction ends abruptly to convey the main idea of a piece with surprise elements.</p>



<p><strong>Section B</strong> Bars 7-26</p>



<p>Here, the time signature changes and the bassoon plays the main subject, copied by the vibraphone. With the bassoon playing a countersubject in E in bar 13, the vibraphone is now free to play the main subject in G, which now is a major third.</p>



<p>In bar 20, the bassoon returns to the main theme but starts in C, which is a major 4th of G. The vibraphone continues to fill the room with ascending and descending notes.</p>



<p>Both instruments start ascending melodies in bar 23, which leads to a climax and the end of this section.</p>



<p><strong>Section C</strong> Bars 27-40</p>



<p>The section begins with a low dynamic and just the vibraphone playing. Although the key changes to B minor, I wanted to create another level of surprise and ambiguity, so I played an F major chord on the high notes, while the low notes created dissonance.</p>



<p>This section motif is then played by the bassoon, accompanied by a steady rhythm played by the vibraphone. Sometimes the vibraphone completes a triad, such as the A major in bar 28, but sometimes it just plays dissonant tones.</p>



<p>In the absence of harmony between the instruments, the tension rises with minor triads and the tempo increases.</p>



<p>At Bar 36, both instruments play staccato, and the tempo is the fastest in the entire piece. The vibraphone continues with its ascending and descending melody, while the bassoon is more steady in its notes.</p>



<p>At the end, in bar 40, they are both tired of the previous part and rest in minim notes before concluding with a B major triad.</p>



<p><strong>Section A&#8217;</strong> Bars 41-43</p>



<p>The section starts with a chord in G major, marking a key change, and proceeds into a version of the intro.</p>



<p><strong>Section B</strong>&#8216; Bars 44-67</p>



<p>In this section, a bassoon augmented subject is played while the vibraphone plays the motif, followed by a counterpoint.</p>



<p>In bar 56, the bassoon plays an inversion of the subject while the vibraphone plays parts of the motif and triads.</p>



<p>In bar 62, the bassoon plays the main motif, which is quickly repeated by the vibraphone in increasing tones until they both end in a G.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-4.mp3" length="3017582" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Bach&#8217;s Fugues</title>
		<link>./../../../listening-to-bachs-fugues/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 02:58:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=541</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 8 in D-Sharp Minor, BWV 853 I felt this fugue was&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h4 id="the-well-tempered-clavier-book-1-fugue-no-8-in-d-sharp-minor-bwv-853"><meta charset="utf-8">The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 8 in D-Sharp Minor, BWV 853</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 8 in D-Sharp Minor, BWV 853" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZG8LVgUzSc0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Gould, G., 2015.&nbsp;<em>The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 8 in D-Sharp Minor, BWV 853</em>. Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZG8LVgUzSc0&gt; [Accessed 12 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>I felt this fugue was really lovely, especially because I enjoyed the theme and Bach used it frequently throughout this composition. In fact, I thought this fugue was quite theme-centric, with the theme inverted, augmented, and rhythmically varied. It’s also worth noting that this fugue goes from a straightforward exposition to a three-voiced narrative.</p>



<p>To be clear, some sources indicate that this fugue is in Eb minor; nevertheless, the prelude is in Eb minor, but the fugue is in D# minor in most scores I discovered. Although I don’t believe it matters, I’ll keep mentioning that this fugue is in D# minor.</p>



<p>This fugue begins with the first voice exposition of the theme, while the second voice (in red) imitate it. Right away, the lowest voice repeats it a second time. Bach repeats this three-bar theme four times in the first 14 bars, which shows how important this theme is to him.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="614" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-1024x614.png" alt="" class="wp-image-544" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-1024x614.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-300x180.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-768x461.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-1536x921.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-640x384.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-960x576.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1.png 1884w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>In order to emphasize the theme-centric nature of the fugue, the theme is repeated five times from bar 19 to bar 29, before there is an inversion (in blue). I was interested to see if the inversion is an exact mirror of the theme. I got my answer right away: no. The very first note, D#, goes to an A#, the perfect fifth. However, the inversion goes down a perfect fourth. Following these first notes, everything is mirrored.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="573" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-1024x573.png" alt="" class="wp-image-545" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-1024x573.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-300x168.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-768x430.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-1536x859.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-640x358.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-960x537.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32.png 1888w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Afterwards, the lower voice plays an augmentation of the theme (in green) at double speed. In my opinion, this is where the piece begins to climax and become more complex.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="396" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-1024x396.png" alt="" class="wp-image-546" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-1024x396.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-300x116.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-768x297.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-1536x593.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-640x247.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-960x371.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14.png 1934w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>It is difficult for me to follow and analyze without assistance from here. I noticed that the theme is imitated and reversed as well as amplified and augmented throughout the entire piece, making it a complex and engaging ending.</p>



<h4 id="the-well-tempered-clavier-book-i-fugue-no-14-in-f-sharp-minor-bwv-859">The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book I: Fugue <meta charset="utf-8">No. 14 in F-sharp minor, BWV 859</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 14 in F-Sharp Minor, BWV 859" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uzeucBPHi00?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Gould, G., 2015.&nbsp;<em>The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 14 in F-Sharp Minor, BWV 859</em>. Available at: &lt;https://youtu.be/uzeucBPHi00&gt; [Accessed 12 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>I found this fugue to be slow, sorrowful, but at the same time, I found it to sometimes be beautifully harmonious. Contrary to other fugues I have heard, I believe this could be played in a church, with the long notes resonating in the long walls. Alternatively, a choral group could perform it.</p>



<p>The theme (in red) and countertheme (in brown) are presented in the first six bars of this fugue, which is interesting. The theme’s long notes are precisely counterbalanced by the countertheme’s quavers, allowing both to be heard clearly. When the third voice is added in the lower bass, it sounds really lovely to me. This produces a really fascinating and recognizable sound that binds all of the voices together.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1008" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-1024x1008.png" alt="" class="wp-image-548" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-1024x1008.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-300x295.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-768x756.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-80x80.png 80w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-640x630.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-960x945.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>I was curious as to how Bach composed the theme and counter-theme to work together so beautifully, so I decided to investigate further. One thing I observed is that both melodies, especially the countertheme, move in a step-by-step manner, only leaping in the finish. This, I believe, allows the intervals to move from fifths to thirds, as seen at the start of bar 5. In addition, the opposing motion in the first two bars, when one of the melodies rises (in red) and the other falls (in blue), generates a lovely contrast and tension, which is released in the last two bars, when both move in the same direction.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="678" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-1024x678.png" alt="" class="wp-image-549" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-1024x678.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-300x199.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-768x508.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-640x424.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-960x635.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43.png 1496w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>When I previously stated that I considered this piece to be quite harmonic at moments, I was making reference to bars 13 and 14. All melodies, I suppose, have the same function here: to set the stage for the return of the theme and countertheme, but this time in a more powerful form. The theme is mostly played by the two upper voices with the thirds. This brings the piece to a close with a mini-climax.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1001" height="1024" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-1001x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-550" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-1001x1024.png 1001w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-293x300.png 293w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-768x786.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-1501x1536.png 1501w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-300x307.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-640x655.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-960x982.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10.png 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1001px) 100vw, 1001px" /></figure>



<p>Something new appears later, at the conclusion of bar 20. The motif has been inverted (in blue). This inversion is accompanied by lower voice quavers that sound like the countertheme. I believe this is employed to have a familiar sound with this new inversion theme.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="724" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-1024x724.png" alt="" class="wp-image-551" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-1024x724.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-300x212.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-768x543.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-1536x1087.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-640x453.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-960x679.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16.png 1668w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>One last thing I’d like to mention is something I don’t recall hearing in previous fugues. When two voices play similar melodies while the other two wait their time to play identical tunes. As with prior examples, most of this is done using the third interval. All of this builds up to the final theme and countertheme section.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="355" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-1024x355.png" alt="" class="wp-image-552" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-1024x355.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-300x104.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-768x267.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-1536x533.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-2048x711.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-640x222.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-960x333.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33.png 2328w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project 12: Two-Part Invention</title>
		<link>./../../../project-12-two-part-invention/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 07:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=610</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the first exercise for a two-part experience, I aimed to compose something similar to what I heard&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the first exercise for a two-part experience, I aimed to compose something similar to what I heard from Bach and a more &#8220;traditional&#8221; invention. After reading about invention, I gathered some process rules that allow to write an invention.</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Write a motif in one voice</li><li>The second voice repeats the motif in another octave</li><li>The first voice imitates the motif on the dominant</li><li>The second voice imitates the motif it played before but this time on the dominant</li><li>Then use parts or the whole motif in augmented, diminuted or inversed version while the other voice plays counterpoint</li><li>End in the tonic</li></ul>



<p>Although I know these are not stric rules, I tried to apply the process here to help me compose faster and with fewer elements. I must say I liked this process. I started with a motif that is played in both voices on the tonic and on the dominant. I then passed to both voices playing a diminuted version of the motif and ending with the oboe playing a inversion while the bassoon plays a augmented motif. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="722" height="1024" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1-722x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-611" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1-722x1024.png 722w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1-212x300.png 212w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1-768x1089.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1-1083x1536.png 1083w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1-1445x2048.png 1445w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1-300x425.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1-640x907.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1-960x1361.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/project-12-1.png 2222w" sizes="(max-width: 722px) 100vw, 722px" /></figure>



<p>In my second exercise, I tried to apply a more rhythmic invention while using the marimba. As in the first exercise, I created a motif that is repeated and imitated by both voices. I didn&#8217;t feel the need to augment the motif since I got the sense that I would lose the rhytm of it, so I used an diminuted version of the motif in the marimba while the flute plays an inversion.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="928" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Project-12-2-1024x928.png" alt="" class="wp-image-612" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Project-12-2-1024x928.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Project-12-2-300x272.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Project-12-2-768x696.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Project-12-2-1536x1392.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Project-12-2-2048x1856.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Project-12-2-640x580.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Project-12-2-960x870.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Project-12-2.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Joseph Bologne, Chevalier de Saint-Georges &#8211; Violin Concerto No. 9 in G Major, Op. 8</title>
		<link>./../../../listening-to-joseph-bologne-chevalier-de-saint-georges-violin-concerto-no-9-in-g-major-op-8/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 04:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There are black composers who don&#8217;t get the attention they deserve, and Joseph Bologne is one of them&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="key-takeaways" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1632458688251 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Key takeaways </span>
	</span>
</h2>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled-positive"><li>There are black composers who don&#8217;t get the attention they deserve, and Joseph Bologne is one of them</li><li><span style="font-size: var(--cnvs-list-styled-font-size); color: var(--cs-color-primary); font-family: var(--cs-font-base-family), sans-serif; font-style: var(--cs-font-base-style); font-weight: var(--cs-font-base-weight); letter-spacing: var(--cs-font-base-letter-spacing);">I couldn&#8217;t fiind an African inspired sound in his works, maybe because of his European education</span></li><li><span style="font-size: var(--cnvs-list-styled-font-size); color: var(--cs-color-primary); font-family: var(--cs-font-base-family), sans-serif; font-style: var(--cs-font-base-style); font-weight: var(--cs-font-base-weight); letter-spacing: var(--cs-font-base-letter-spacing);">I find descending notes pleasing, once again </span></li></ul>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Violin Concerto Op.8 No.2 in G Major by Joseph Bologne Le Chevalier de Saint-Georges:Classical Music" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eiLPZCUaHEA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Badass Joseph Saint-Georges, 2020. <em>Violin Concerto Op.8 No.2 in G Major by Joseph Bologne Le Chevalier de Saint-Georges:Classical Music</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eiLPZCUaHEA> [Accessed 27 October 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>One thought occurred to me while I was searching for music to listen to. What is the reason for the scarcity of well-known African classical composers? I couldn&#8217;t think of one, and a quick Google search reveals that the first dozen names that come up are all white men. I recognize that my lack of knowledge stems primarily from my western culture, so I set out to find black composers, which I am glad I did.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="179" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-1024x179.png" alt="" class="wp-image-556" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-1024x179.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-300x52.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-768x134.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-1536x268.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-2048x357.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-640x112.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-960x167.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27.png 3028w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>One of the articles I read was from classicfm.com entitled <a href="https://www.classicfm.com/discover-music/black-composers-who-made-classical-music-history/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.classicfm.com/discover-music/black-composers-who-made-classical-music-history/" target="_blank">&#8220;9 Black composers who changed the course of classical music history&#8221;.</a> The first featured composer is Joseph Bologne, Chevalier de Saint-Georges.</p>



<p>Joseph Bologne was born to a wealthy plantation owner and his Senegalese slave mistress in Basse-Terre, Guadaloupe, in 1745. He received the best education his father could afford during the family&#8217;s move to France and grew into an exceptionally gifted student. He had professional training, as evidenced by his extensive work list, which includes a number of comedic operas, symphonies and concertos, as well as chamber works (Banat, 2001).</p>



<p>Despite his pejorative nickname of The Black Mozart (also known as The Other Mozart), I find myself wondering if it shouldn&#8217;t be the other way around. Joseph Bologne is regarded as one of the greatest composers of the 18th century, according to Marlon Daniel. He was known to frequent salons as a guest of the French nobility, including those of queen Marie Antoinette, who was an accomplished singer herself. He influenced Franz Joseph Haydn, François-Joseph Gossec, Carl Stamitz, and, most notably, Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, making him a leader rather than a follower of trends in the musical evolution of his century (Daniel, 2021).</p>



<p>His work was innovative since his earlier compositions, according to a New York Times article. &#8220;The six-string quartets of his Opus 1 were among the first in that genre to be written in France. His three sonatas for keyboard and violin (Op. 1a) feature those instruments as equals, breaking away from the Baroque tradition of basso continuo, which was still very much in vogue&#8221; (Balter, 2020).</p>



<p>Despite how innovative Bologne&#8217;s work may have sounded after listening to his violin concertos, my mind constantly tells me that he sounds a lot like some of his contemporaries. This, I believe, is a case of knowledge bias.</p>



<p>His Violin Concerto No. 9 in G Major, Op. 8 is one of my favourite works. I was struck by the three movements&#8217; energy and rhythm, as well as the motifs he created. I couldn&#8217;t find a free score for this piece, but they can easily compete with other well-known motifs, in my humble and naive opinion. Why hasn&#8217;t his music been used in an advertisement commercial?</p>



<p>The second movement, Largo, is one of my favourites. Despite the fact that it is a slower movement, I consider it to be a continuation of the first movement&#8217;s accentuated rhythm. The syncopation provides a solid sound of descending notes in the first minute, which I find pleasing. In fact, I find this movement to be quite contemporary. While listening to him, I noticed parallels with Nicolas Britell&#8217;s, in my opinion, amazing Succession Tv Show soundtrack, particularly the Adagio in C Minor I show below.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Spotify Embed: Adagio in C Minor" width="100%" height="80" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2hdBC9gUzlb0mpzDFOWv8n?si=ec602f74e4074406&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>In the end, I was thrilled about this discovery. I&#8217;m not qualified to say whether Joseph Bologne was a better composer than Mozart, but after hearing some of his works, I believe he deserves at least more credit.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1635310066343 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Banat, G., 2001. Saint-Georges [Saint-George], Joseph Bologne, Chevalier de.. [online] Oxford University Press. Available at: <a href="https://www-oxfordmusiconline-com.ucreative.idm.oclc.org/grovemusic/view/10.1093/gmo/9781561592630.001.0001/omo-9781561592630-e-0000024316">https://www-oxfordmusiconline-com.ucreative.idm.oclc.org/grovemusic/view/10.1093/gmo/9781561592630.001.0001/omo-9781561592630-e-0000024316</a> [Accessed 27 October 2021].</p>



<p>Daniel, M., 2021. THE MUSIC OF JOSEPH BOLOGNE CHEVALIER DE SAINT-GEORGES. [ebook] Tafelmusik. Available at: <a href="https://www.tafelmusik.org/downloads/Tafelmedia/joseph-bologne-digital-booklet.pdf">https://www.tafelmusik.org/downloads/Tafelmedia/joseph-bologne-digital-booklet.pdf</a> [Accessed 27 October 2021].</p>



<p>Balter, M., 2020. His Name Is Joseph Boulogne, Not ‘Black Mozart’. [online] Nytimes.com. Available at: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/22/arts/music/black-mozart-joseph-boulogne.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/22/arts/music/black-mozart-joseph-boulogne.html</a> [Accessed 27 October 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project 11 &#8211; Inventing free counterpoint</title>
		<link>./../../../project-11-inventing-free-counterpoint/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 10:27:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=519</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[During this project, I had to practice composing counterpoints for two instruments. There were two parts to the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>During this project, I had to practice composing counterpoints for two instruments. There were two parts to the brief. With exercises 1 and 2, one of the instruments is already provided in the briefing, and the challenge is to compose a counterpoint for it. The task in exercises 3 and 4 is to compose two tunes with contrasting characters.</p>



<p>The workbook states that any tuning percussion instrument and woodwind instrument may be used. In order to get more familiar with tuned percussion, I decided to use them in all exercises.</p>



<h4 id="exercise-1">Exercise 1</h4>



<p>With this exercise, the top melody was provided and I was asked to compose the bottom melody. As I looked at the written melody for the first time, I noticed that it had long notes, mirims, and crochets, so I decided to use mostly quavers and semiquavers to have a nice rhythmic contrast. I also took advantage of the opportunity to contrast the dynamics, sometimes having the vibraphone play higher than the flute.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="329" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-1024x329.png" alt="" class="wp-image-521" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-1024x329.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-300x96.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-768x246.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-1536x493.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-2048x657.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-640x205.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-960x308.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1.png 2163w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h4 id="exercise-2">Exercise 2</h4>



<p>Here, the bottom part was given, and I composed the top melody. With the first three bars of my melody, I worked with the staccato from the flute by adding semiquavers, resulting in an interaction between the two instruments. In the next three bars, I made the marimba melody follow the descending flute melody, but with fast notes to emphasize the different melodies. The marimba contrasts with the flute in the last three bars by going up while the flute continues to go down.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="577" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-1024x577.png" alt="" class="wp-image-522" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-1024x577.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-300x169.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-768x433.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-1536x866.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-2048x1154.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-640x361.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-960x541.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2.png 2166w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h4 id="exercise-3">Exercise 3</h4>



<p>In the third exercise, I followed the workbook&#8217;s suggestion and started one melody later than the other, so the listener could more easily pick out the different voices. I developed a little theme that begins with the flute, then the tubular bells accompany it. Following this repetition, however, both melodies drift away. With a wave-shaped melody, the flute is more unstable, with a descending melody in bar 3 and an ascending melody until bar 5. In the meantime, the tubular bells are more stable, using almost always the same rhythm except for bar 7 when they take the opportunity of the calmer flute to express themselves.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="662" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-1024x662.png" alt="" class="wp-image-523" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-1024x662.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-300x194.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-768x497.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-1536x994.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-2048x1325.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-640x414.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-960x621.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h4 id="exercise-4">Exercise 4</h4>



<p>Similarly to the previous exercise, I tried to start one melody after another, while the instruments followed a similar theme. I could see how this theme could be used in different ways if it were a longer composition. Thus, for example, the xylophone plays two notes on the first part of the theme while the bassoon plays staccato over the same notes. However, after this repetition, the melodies go the opposite way. Generally, they move oppositely, except in the last bar when both move down and up to the final F.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="681" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-1024x681.png" alt="" class="wp-image-524" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-1024x681.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-300x199.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-768x511.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-1536x1021.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-2048x1361.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-640x425.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-960x638.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4.png 2222w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reflections on Assignment 3</title>
		<link>./../../../reflections-on-assignment-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 12:50:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Round, descants, polyphony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=510</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Moving from monophonic to polyphonic music, in my opinion, was a significant step forward in terms of both&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Moving from monophonic to polyphonic music, in my opinion, was a significant step forward in terms of both complexity and creativity.</p>



<p>I had the opportunity to write for three instruments in this assignment, which proved to be more difficult than I anticipated, especially considering I had to write separate melodies for each of them. I can now better appreciate how great composers like Bach were able to compose in masterful harmony when they used 4 or more voices.</p>



<p>My hearing and analysis of rounds, descants, and, especially, polyphony, I believe, aided me in better understanding how voices might be written in harmony but with differing melodies.</p>



<h3 id="about-assignment-3">About Assignment 3</h3>



<p>As I previously stated, I found this task to be far more challenging than the prior two. Considering three instruments, each with their distinct melodies and &#8220;personalities,&#8221; brought a level of difficulty I hadn&#8217;t anticipated. However, I believe that this additional complexity will be advantageous in the long run as assignment tasks become longer and include more instruments.</p>



<p>In terms of notation, I made an effort to avoid some of the faults I made in earlier assignments, such as rhythmic spelling, correct beaming, and phrasing.</p>



<p>My ability to construct a two-minute composition and transpose the concepts I had in my head to a score surprised me. I wanted to compose a piece that put polyphony to work for the music rather than the other way around. The repeated theme and various small melodies throughout the music, I believe, made this polyphonic composition both familiar and fresh at the same time.</p>



<p>Being self-critical, I think this piece contains too many elements. As a result, I feel that I could turn this into a 4-minute musical piece that develops some of the ideas I wanted to include.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 3</title>
		<link>./../../../assignment-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Round, descants, polyphony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=467</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My third task was to compose a work for three woodwind instruments in a mostly polyphonic approach. This&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>My third task was to compose a work for three woodwind instruments in a mostly polyphonic approach. This composition should last about two minutes and follow a predetermined structure (seen below), in which one begins with a triad, moves to another, and concludes with another.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="358" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-1024x358.png" alt="" class="wp-image-473" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-1024x358.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-300x105.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-768x268.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-640x224.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-960x336.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47.png 1190w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>You can find the final score <a href="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V2-Full-Score.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V2-Full-Score.pdf" target="_blank">here</a> and listen to it below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V2.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p><meta charset="utf-8">I had few questions after seeing example 45. Should the first triad last several bars? (If that&#8217;s the case, I&#8217;ll have to use different chords in the meanwhile, or it&#8217;ll sound stuck). Or is the example intended to be regarded as a chord progression that should be used throughout the piece?</p>



<p>My tutor assisted me with these questions by directing me to consider these triads as harmonic centres for the music.</p>



<p>With this in mind, I decided to use three triads, each representing a different essence of the music, resulting in a piece of music with three parts.</p>



<h2 id="the-idea-theme" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108541003 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Idea / Theme</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>After reflecting on my polyphonic studies, I came up with the idea for this composition. I listened to polyphonic music in three different styles: Renaissance, Baroque, and African/Polynesian polyphony. Because the assignment&#8217;s predetermined structure required three triads, I challenged myself to write a piece of music in three parts, each inspired by a different style of polyphonic music.</p>



<p>About the theme, this piece will be about a love triangle involving three instruments. After meeting and dancing in an African<meta charset="utf-8">/Polynesian section, they progressed to the baroque section, where they fell in love, then finalized the dance with a passionate and harmonious section (Renaissance), showcasing their love for one another.</p>



<h2 id="the-structure" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108659753 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Structure</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The structure was mostly determined upon the development of the idea. This would be a straightforward story in which A leads to B, which leads to C. I wanted the music to begin rhythmically as if the instruments were dancing together and each had its own individuality. Then, in a more melodic section, the instruments repeat the motif as though they discover something in common and fall in love. Ending in harmony and love, each instrument repeats the same motif but then each plays its own melodic line while respecting the harmony of the others.</p>



<p>I decided to produce a piece in the key of C# major after studying pentatonic scales. The other triads and keys were chosen based on the least amount of note change between them.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-regular cnvs-block-core-table-1628498574118"><table><thead><tr><th>Theme</th><th>Section &amp; Triad</th><th>Duration / Tempo</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>The instruments meet and dance together, each with its own personality</td><td>A &#8211; B major</td><td><meta charset="utf-8">~30 seconds at 110 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They fall in love, repeating the same motif</td><td>B &#8211; C# major</td><td><meta charset="utf-8">~30 seconds at 70 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They live happily ever after, each with their own motif but harmonically</td><td>C &#8211; Ab major</td><td>~60 seconds at 70 bpm</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 id="the-motifs" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108877461 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Motifs</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>As I had done with prior projects and assignments, I began playing around with the piano, hoping to find a theme that sounded good to me and would serve as a catapult for this composition. After a time, I came upon a motif that I really loved and decided to go a little deeper into it.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="75" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-1024x75.png" alt="" class="wp-image-480" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-1024x75.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-300x22.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-768x57.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-1536x113.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-2048x151.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-640x47.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-960x71.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5.png 2171w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Because the song is divided into three distinct sections, I thought it would be fascinating if the same motif appeared in each section, but was played differently and by different instruments. This way, something would connect all three pieces.</p>



<p>This motif is performed subtly in semiquavers in the A section by the oboe.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="238" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-1024x238.png" alt="" class="wp-image-476" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-1024x238.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-300x70.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-768x178.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-1536x356.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-2048x475.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-640x149.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-960x223.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1.png 2172w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The B section is played more explicitly and with quavers by the flute.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="100" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-1024x100.png" alt="" class="wp-image-478" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-1024x100.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-300x29.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-768x75.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-1536x151.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-2048x201.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-640x63.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-960x94.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3.png 2171w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The motif is performed by the bassoon nearly in the background with crochets in the C section.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="64" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-1024x64.png" alt="" class="wp-image-479" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-1024x64.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-300x19.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-768x48.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-1536x96.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-2048x127.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-640x40.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-960x60.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4.png 2171w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>This division was quite helpful in enabling me to start writing each section quicker.</p>



<h2 id="the-instruments" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110169912 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Instruments</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Flute, oboe, and bassoon were my natural choices for a woodwind trio. I chose these three instruments because I believe they complement each other in terms of timbre while remaining distinct enough for the listener to hear each one&#8217;s melody.</p>



<p>I listened to three pieces to gain a sense of how a trio of woodwinds works together and how other composers used these instruments.</p>



<p>One of the first instances I found of the three I selected to work with was Antonio Vivaldi&#8217;s Concerto for Flute, Oboe, and Bassoon in G Minor, RV 103. This composition didn&#8217;t particularly appeal to me, but it did teach me how much prominence the flute can have at times, as well as how the oboe and flute can sound good together without clashing, with the flute in a high register and the oboe in a middle and low register.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Antonio Vivaldi - Concerto for Flute, Oboe, and Bassoon in G Minor, RV 103" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cMptoH6bo-I?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>The Trio for Flute, Oboe, and Bassoon, Op. 86 by Röntgen was an excellent illustration of what I was attempting. Each instrument&#8217;s identity is respected alongside the melody, yet they also repeat each other. This adds a lot of depth to the music.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Röntgen - Trio for Flute, Oboe and Bassoon, Op. 86" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9ke2oCFJatM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Pastorale for Wind Trio, Op. 147 by Darius Milhaud omits the flute but includes the clarinet. I was especially inspired by how wonderfully polyphony worked beginning in bar 24.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Darius Milhaud - Pastorale for Wind Trio, Op. 147 (1935) [Score-Video]" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TMctPXaihD8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<h2 id="the-composition" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110414281 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The composition</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><meta charset="utf-8"><strong>Section A</strong> Bars 1-9</p>



<p>I intended to portray more rhythmic and fast-paced music in this section. As a result, I employed semiquavers in all three instruments and staccato most of the time.</p>



<p>This section is in the key of B major, although it begins with a D#m triad. The B major triad is present in the second beat of the first bar to create the home triad.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="376" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-1024x376.png" alt="" class="wp-image-481" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-1024x376.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-300x110.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-768x282.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-1536x564.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-2048x752.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-640x235.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-960x352.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23.png 2218w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The oboe and flute begin by playing nearly the identical melody with a 3rd, 5th, or 6th interval, but at bar 4 the flute begins to move from a quick staccato to a slower legato. Meanwhile, the bassoon plays a more danceable melody.</p>



<p>This section has the most triad changes, with the majority being B major, D# minor, F# major and G# minor.</p>



<p>This section ends with a VI &#8211; I, reintroducing the home triad and leading to the next triad.</p>



<p><strong>Section B</strong> Bars 10-20</p>



<p>The music here shifts to a more elaborate yet slower paced approach. The speed is reduced to 70 quaver beats per minute, and the notes are predominantly quavers. In bar 11, the flute plainly states that the key signature has changed to C# major.</p>



<p>The home triad, like the first section, is played right at the start to express the feeling of the new home triad. This time, I stuck with the home triad for a little longer than in&nbsp;the first section, with inversions of the triad lasting two bars and the primary motif repeated by the three instruments.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="360" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-1024x360.png" alt="" class="wp-image-483" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-1024x360.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-300x106.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-768x270.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-1536x540.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-2048x720.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-640x225.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-960x338.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6.png 2218w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>In contrast to the preceding section, this one contains a clearly defined chord progression: I &#8211; IV &#8211; iii &#8211; V.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="771" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-1024x771.png" alt="" class="wp-image-484" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-1024x771.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-300x226.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-768x578.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-1536x1156.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-2048x1541.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-640x482.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-960x722.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7.png 2222w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>It ends with an I &#8211; IV, which leads to the next triad, that is expected to be the V: G# major.</p>



<p><strong>Section C</strong> Bars 21-40</p>



<p>Despite the fact that the tempo remains constant, I wanted the music to feel slower and more harmonized. As a result, I utilized a lot of crochets, minims, and semibreves.</p>



<p>This section is in the key of Ab major. I wanted it to be in G# major scale, but I learned that G# major isn&#8217;t commonly used because it&#8217;s too complex for practical use, and that Ab major is a better option.</p>



<p>In contrast to the other sections, I do not explicitly tell the listener of the key change. Though I begin with the Ab major triad, it isn&#8217;t until the third beat of the second bar of this section (bar 22) that I reach an Ab major triad.</p>



<p>In the final part of this section I wanted to express pure polyphony, with each instrument adding their own melody one at a time, culminating with all three instruments playing distinct melodies until they rise to end in Ab major triad.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V2.mp3" length="2567231" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening &#038; Researching Polyphony</title>
		<link>./../../../listening-researching-polyphony/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 06:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Round, descants, polyphony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=451</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Polyphonic music is when two or more melodies are played at the same time, each with the same&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="key-takeaways" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634272317962 wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span><meta charset="utf-8">Key takeaways </span>
	</span>
</h2>



<ul type="video" class="wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio is-style-cnvs-list-styled-positive"><li>Polyphonic music is when two or more melodies are played at the same time, each with the same relevance</li><li>It is not just a Western concept; it is found in a variety of cultures, each of which is distinct</li><li><span style="font-size: var(--cnvs-list-styled-font-size); color: var(--cs-color-primary); font-family: var(--cs-font-base-family), sans-serif; font-style: var(--cs-font-base-style); font-weight: var(--cs-font-base-weight); letter-spacing: var(--cs-font-base-letter-spacing);">Polyphonic music is more difficult to listen to than monophonic or homophonic music. Using a recurring theme through the voices is one method to make it easier to listen to</span></li><li><span style="font-size: var(--cnvs-list-styled-font-size); color: var(--cs-color-primary); font-family: var(--cs-font-base-family), sans-serif; font-style: var(--cs-font-base-style); font-weight: var(--cs-font-base-weight); letter-spacing: var(--cs-font-base-letter-spacing);">When there are more than 5 voices and melodies, it&#8217;s nearly impossible to distinguish them, and the experience becomes an aural one</span></li></ul>



<p>Before I could listen to polyphonic music, I needed to define polyphony. There are three types of music textures: monophonic, homophonic, and polyphonic (Copland, Rich and Slatkin, 2011).</p>



<p>So far, I&#8217;ve largely studied monophonic music, which is music composed using a single tune. It does not imply that the music is limited to a single instrument or vocal. Monophonic music can feature percussion and many lines, but they all play the same melody at the same time.</p>



<p>Today&#8217;s contemporary popular music is predominantly homophonic. It means that a principal melody is accompanied by a chordal accompaniment. Generally, it is more pleasant to hear than monophonic music because the harmony is played in a way that elevates the main melody.</p>



<p>Polyphony is more challenging than the preceding two. It occurs when two or more melodies happen at the same moment but are unrelated to one another. One of the most distinguishing characteristics of polyphony is that it is difficult to discern which melody is the primary one because each has its own prominence.</p>



<p>I was reminded of a pop tune that contains all three types of musical textures. Come On Eileen by Dexys Midnight Runners makes it simple to understand the three principles. The song begins with a single violin playing in a monophonic texture. The sound then shifts to a homophonic texture, primarily in the chorus. Finally, in the bridge portion, all voices join together in a polyphonic texture with up to three melodies, as far as I can tell.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Come On Eileen" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GbpnAGajyMc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>dexysofficial, 2019.&nbsp;<em>Come On Eileen</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GbpnAGajyMc&gt; [Accessed 1 October 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>Proceeding to my listening of polyphonic music, I decided that it will consist of as many listenings as there are melodies, plus one. To do this, I will try to listen to each melody separately and then all of them together in one final listening.</p>



<h4 id="thomas-morley-april-is-in-my-mistress-face">Thomas Morley – April Is In My Mistress’ Face</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="April is in my Mistress&#039; face – Thomas Morley" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/o4vE2lZWZVU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Frank, D., 2009.&nbsp;<em>April is in my Mistress&#8217; face – Thomas Morley</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o4vE2lZWZVU&gt; [Accessed 1 October 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>This is a polyphonic composition of music for four voices (Soprano, Alto, Tenor, Bass), and it is one of the shortest English madrigals, published in 1594.</p>



<p>After a first listen, this music seems to me like a Christmas carol, despite the fact that there is nothing in the lyrics that leads in that direction except the &#8220;cold December&#8221; section. Speaking of the lyrics, this is not a cheerful love poem, and I believe the music reflects the protagonist&#8217;s disappointment.</p>



<p>The song starts with gentle rhythms but ascending melodic lines when describing April and June as metaphors for her beauty and the warmth of her eyes.</p>



<p>But as the song progresses towards the colder months, it becomes a little melancholy and deeper, with the vocals becoming lower in pitch and dynamics. September has lengthier notes and the melodies are more similar.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.22.33-1024x905.png" alt="" class="wp-image-456" width="320" height="282" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.22.33-1024x905.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.22.33-300x265.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.22.33-768x679.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.22.33-640x566.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.22.33-960x849.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.22.33.png 1054w" sizes="(max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" /></figure>



<p>The most memorable section of the music occurs in December when the tune of &#8220;But in her heart&#8221; is repeated several times by all voices. This is foreshadowing the protagonist&#8217;s disappointment when he discovers she is as cold as December, and all voices get quieter and slower.</p>



<p>For me, the most exciting part is when the voices interact, and you can hear one voice starting at one point and another voice following up where the first left. This example below exemplifies how Thomas Morley considered this, employing quavers to interact amongst the voices, crotchets, and minims when the melodies are independent. This results in a lovely soundscape.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.03.10.png" alt="" class="wp-image-453" width="382" height="252" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.03.10.png 992w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.03.10-300x198.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.03.10-768x508.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.03.10-640x423.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-12.03.10-960x635.png 960w" sizes="(max-width: 382px) 100vw, 382px" /></figure>



<p>Although it is polyphonic music with individual melodies, there is some round counterpoint, as shown in the examples above and below. This can demonstrate that the composer is not limited to a single style.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.58.09.png" alt="" class="wp-image-452" width="334" height="300" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.58.09.png 686w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.58.09-300x270.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.58.09-640x577.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 334px) 100vw, 334px" /></figure>



<h4 id="thomas-tallis-spem-in-alium">Thomas Tallis &#8211; Spem in Alium</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Tallis - Spem in alium (a 40) - Harry Christophers - Live Concert - HD" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QmH1nZSGIyY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>AVROTROS Klassiek, 2013.&nbsp;<em>Tallis &#8211; Spem in alium (a 40) &#8211; Harry Christophers &#8211; Live Concert &#8211; HD</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QmH1nZSGIyY&gt; [Accessed 1 October 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>Because this is a 40-part motet, I did not follow the guideline of listening to it as many times as there are voices. </p>



<p>It was written about 1570 by Thomas Tallis for eight choirs of five voices each and is regarded as the greatest piece of English early music by certain commentators.</p>



<p>Writing polyphonic compositions is a complex job for the composer and a demanding one for the listener who tries to follow each melody alone. This is especially true for music with more than three or four melodies, so one can only imagine how impressive it is to write for 40 voices and over 11 minutes. An example of Tallis&#8217;s incredible work can be seen in the example below.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="691" height="1024" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.52.52-691x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-459" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.52.52-691x1024.png 691w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.52.52-202x300.png 202w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.52.52-768x1138.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.52.52-1037x1536.png 1037w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.52.52-300x445.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.52.52-640x948.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.52.52-960x1423.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-01-at-11.52.52.png 1154w" sizes="(max-width: 691px) 100vw, 691px" /></figure>



<p>Concentrating on individual melodies proved difficult in this situation, so I just listened to Spem in Alium as a whole choir song. I must add that it greatly surprised me and gave me a hypnotic sense due to the aural movements of the choirs. Though it is widely assumed that Tallis intended his choirs to be placed in a horseshoe form, I can only imagine how magnificent it would be to hear it live, with all eight choirs positioned in a circle around you, creating a 360º experience.</p>



<p>This piece, in my opinion, can be separated into three parts.</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>The first choir begins with just a few voices being formed together, then the other chorus joins them in turn. It almost sounds like a round.</li><li>Then, after a brief time when all 40 voices are singing together, we see an inverted movement from the opening section, in which the choirs follow each other in reverse order.</li><li>It is in the final section, which is more like a conversation between choirs, where this piece makes full use of its complexity, jumping between voices as it moves from choir to choir until it ends with all choirs singing together.</li></ul>



<p>Even though I didn&#8217;t find it boring, I thought the music was a bit longer than I would find interesting. Listening to it live would probably transmit the power and the spatial interactivity Tallis intended and keep it interesting for the whole 11 minutes of this piece.</p>



<h4 id="bach-prelude-and-fugue-no-17-in-ab-major-bwv-862">Bach: Prelude and Fugue No.17 in Ab major, BWV 862</h4>



<p>I was interested to listen how the polyphonic music developed from the renaissance era to the baroque. After reading some articles I found that Bach would be a great example of polyphonic baroque music, so I listened to a few of his fugues. The No.17 in Ab major was one the I liked most.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Richter plays Bach: WTC1 No. 17 in A flat major BWV 862" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gCL5Zvnt0TU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>The polyphony of the late Baroque differed from that of the Renaissance: It was rooted in tonal harmony and characterized by an energetic, metrically conceived, driving rhythm (Hylton, 2005).</p>



<p>The start of the prelude really interested me because it was such a great way of opening a piece. It reminded me of some rock and heavy metal songs that start with triads in one guitar and a melody in another. </p>



<p>The theme of the prelude is repeated several times by both voices. Since polyphony can be hard to listen, this repetition of the main theme in one voice makes it sound familiar, while the other voice delivers a new and unexpected sound, making it fresh at the same time.</p>



<p>Even from the start is easy to find the differences from renaissance polyphony. More rhythm and more complexity. </p>



<p>Moving to the fugue, the new theme is clearly stated by repetition of the 4 voices, two in Ab major and two in Eb major.</p>



<p>I really like how the voices keep playing the main theme, specially when they rise for a perfect 4th or 5th as in the example below. It gives a really fresh and climatic tone to the music.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="983" height="1024" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2-983x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-500" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2-983x1024.png 983w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2-288x300.png 288w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2-768x800.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2-1474x1536.png 1474w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2-1965x2048.png 1965w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2-300x313.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2-640x667.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2-960x1000.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled-2.png 2165w" sizes="(max-width: 983px) 100vw, 983px" /></figure>



<p>Also interesting is that in bar 11 starts a new melody that is repeated by three voices, separating by a perfect 5th and a perfect 4th. This adds again a freshness to the music, and Bach makes sure that although this piece is polyphonic and complex, there is always a familiar tune to be listened.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="962" height="1024" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2-962x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-498" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2-962x1024.png 962w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2-282x300.png 282w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2-768x818.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2-1443x1536.png 1443w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2-1924x2048.png 1924w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2-300x319.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2-640x681.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2-960x1022.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled2_0001-2.png 2165w" sizes="(max-width: 962px) 100vw, 962px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="470" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled21-1024x470.png" alt="" class="wp-image-497" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled21-1024x470.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled21-300x138.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled21-768x353.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled21-1536x705.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled21-2048x940.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled21-640x294.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled21-960x441.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled21.png 2165w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>I find this type of polyphony more interesting than the previous examples I listened, perhaps because I find that the complexity of notes and rhythms add more colour and interest to the piece.</p>



<h4 id="polyphony-of-dorze-people">Polyphony of Dorze People</h4>



<p>While researching polyphony, I came across this statement in the &#8216;Why do people sing?&#8217; book.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote is-style-solid-color"><blockquote><p>SubSaharan Africa is the largest and the most active region of distribution of vocal polyphony in the world.</p><cite>(Jordania, 2011)</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>Therefore, I decided to listen to some polyphony singing from the Dorze tribe in Ethiopia to see and understand the main differences between them and western polyphony.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Ethiopia - Polyphony of Dorze People" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0SJnYos3ksQ?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>ArsX, 2015.&nbsp;<em>Ethiopia &#8211; Polyphony of Dorze People</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0SJnYos3ksQ&gt; [Accessed 1 October 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>There are two songs on this recording that I listened to:</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Ritual song by young boys</li><li>Spinning song by young girls</li></ul>



<p>The first one had a drone-like effect in one of the voices while the other voices sang a repeated theme. It&#8217;s a pretty rhythmic tune, but it&#8217;s also incredibly repetitive, with the same theme running throughout.</p>



<p>The second song appears to be a three-part polyphony, with one high-pitched solo melody, another group melody, and a low-pitched rhythmical melody. This one appears to be more sophisticated than the last one and more enjoyable to listen to.</p>



<p>The biggest difference between this song and the ones I previously evaluated is that each voice is sung with a specific function in mind, such as a rhythmic voice or a harmonising voice.</p>



<h4 id="tautai-taora-ofrai-leeward-islands"><meta charset="utf-8">Tautai Taora Ofrai (Leeward Islands)</h4>



<p>Little did I know that Polynesia was one of the first places on earth to develop polyphonic music. Europeans discovered Polynesia&#8217;s long tradition of polyphonic music in the 18th century. This discovery was a shocking one for European musicians, who believed that polyphony, as an attribute of a more advanced musical civilization, could have been only a product of the Christian monastery (Jordania, 2011).</p>



<p>This is one of the examples of recorded Polynesian polyphony.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Music of Polynesia" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/82DpqbRLPAw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I got the same feeling after listening to Tautai Taora Ofrai as I did after listening to Dorze People&#8217;s polyphony. It&#8217;s a song with a lot of rhythms, but it&#8217;s also very repetitive.</p>



<p>Apart from that, I found this music to have a structure, with three parts separated by a drone from one of the voices.</p>



<p>Another difference I noticed between the two listenings is that there are more voices (at least four different melodies) and that they don&#8217;t appear to have a specific role, but rather their own melodies that are distinct from the other voices.</p>



<p></p>



<p>Finally, I&#8217;d want to share one anti-polyphony viewpoint that startled me. As in the video below, polyphony was described by Vincenzo Galilei as &#8220;a big mess of incoherent imperfections&#8221;. Despite the fact that I believe these statements to be harsh, I can see why Vicenzo Galilei wrote them. Polyphony is difficult to listen to and, if not properly done, can quickly devolve into a big mess.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Vincenzo Galilei VS Polyphony and Word Painting" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jSxBXPlDSwE?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634219014963 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Copland, A., Rich, A. and Slatkin, L., 2011. What to listen for in music. New York, N.Y: Signet Classic.</p>



<p>Jordania, J., 2011. Why do people sing?. Tbilisi [Georgia]: Logos, p.20.</p>



<p>Hylton, J., 2005. Comprehensive choral music education. Taipei: Pearson Education Taiwan Ltd.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project 10 &#8211; A contrapuntal trial</title>
		<link>./../../../project-10-a-contrapuntal-trial/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 05:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Round, descants, polyphony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=513</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The goal of this project was to create three different melodic lines that combined to make a little&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The goal of this project was to create three different melodic lines that combined to make a little polyphony. The same triad chord should be used to begin and end the song.</p>



<p>I started with three flutes, as one of the coursework examples suggested, but after experimenting with different melodies, I realized the three voices would sound too similar, so I switched to a woodwind trio of Flute, Oboe, and Bassoon.</p>



<p>This little polyphony was written in a different way from the rest of my projects. I composed vertically, which means I worked on all three melodies at the same time, one bar at a time. I began by deciding on a key (G minor), then came up with a chord progression that I liked: Gm &#8211; Eb – Bb &#8211; Gm. With these factors in mind, I began each bar with the triads of each chord and designed the melodies in each bar to connect the triads.</p>



<p>This way of work was interesting since I didn&#8217;t have a sense of a final melody while I worked, but when I got to the end, I could clearly hear the many melodies. I then made some adjustments to ensure that the voices don&#8217;t clash when played simultaneously, particularly with the 2nd and 7th intervals, which sound dissonant.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="914" src="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-10-1024x914.png" alt="" class="wp-image-515" srcset="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-10-1024x914.png 1024w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-10-300x268.png 300w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-10-768x686.png 768w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-10-1536x1371.png 1536w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-10-2048x1829.png 2048w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-10-640x571.png 640w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-10-960x857.png 960w, ./../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-10.png 2222w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
