<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Part 1 Exploring rhythm &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 11:13:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reflection on Assignment 1</title>
		<link>./../../../../reflection-on-assignment-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 07:41:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=206</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Prior to this, I had never written music in notation, had no experience with Sibelius, and my only&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="i-started-this-course-two-months-ago-and-already-feel-like-ive-come-a-long-way" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628924741753 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-2 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>I started this course two months ago and already feel like I&#8217;ve come a long way.</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Prior to this, I had never written music in notation, had no experience with Sibelius, and my only understanding of percussion instruments was limited to those found in a rock drum kit.</p>



<p>During these two months, I read various books and watched videos to better grasp how to notate music, how to listen to music, and how different instruments sound. Among my sources are:</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Black, D. and Gerou, T., 2005.&nbsp;<em>Essential Dictionary of Orchestration</em>. 3rd ed. Los Angeles, CA: Alfred Music.</li><li>Solomon, S., 2002.&nbsp;<em>How to write for percussion</em>. 1st ed. New York: SZSolomon.</li><li>Blatter, A. and Blatter, A., 1997.&nbsp;<em>Instrumentation and orchestration</em>. New York: Schirmer Books.</li><li>Adler, S., 2002. The study of orchestration. 3rd ed. New York: W.W. Norton.</li><li>Holland, J., 2005.&nbsp;<em>Practical percussion</em>. Lanham, Md.: Scarecrow Press.</li><li>Byrne, D., 2013.&nbsp;<em>How music works</em>. McSweeney’s, San Francisco.</li><li>Youtube.com. n.d.&nbsp;<em>Vic Firth Company</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/c/VicFirthCompany&gt;.</li><li>Youtube.com. n.d.&nbsp;<em>Black Swamp Percussion</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/c/BlackSwampPercussion&gt;.</li></ul>



<h2 id="about-assignment-1" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628923998205 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>About Assignment 1</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Following the finishing of the composition, I&#8217;m quite satisfied with the outcome, despite the fact that it took me longer than I anticipated. But I have to admit that making a plan ahead of time helped me stay focused and save time. This is an important lesson to remember for future projects.</p>



<p>As with all challenges, there were some parts that were easier than others.</p>



<p>Because of my professional background, I found the narrative section to be the most straightforward to write, therefore it was the first thing I did. Another thing that came naturally to me was writing themes depending on the story I wanted to tell.</p>



<p>Working with unpitched instruments was the most difficult part for me, and I often felt like I needed a pitched instrument to make a melody. Along the way, I discovered that employing various sounding percussion instruments might help in the creation of a melody. That&#8217;s what I sought to achieve with my composition.</p>



<p>Another challenge I faced was figuring out how to use the rests. Mostly, because most percussion instruments have such a short decay that the note&#8217;s duration is irrelevant and should be stated in an easy-to-read notation (Blatter and Blatter, 1997). I tried to make it simple for the players to read the rests by using the strong beat.</p>



<p>Overall, my ability to construct a 2-minute composition exceeded my expectations. The use of the variable meter has especially&nbsp;impressed me. I found it really beneficial in transmitting the devils&#8217; sense of disorder, and I ended up using it a lot more than I expected. On the other side, I believe I could do a better job of not using too many notes, or complicating things too much.</p>



<p>The key takeaway from this composition is that creating music in notation allows me to think more slowly about each section of the song and to delve deeper into each particular instrument.</p>



<p>As I previously stated, this was my first time using just percussion and non-pitched instruments, and my aim is that it will provide me with the foundations to write with a variety of instruments, specially tuned ones.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628923848042 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Blatter, A. and Blatter, A., 1997.&nbsp;<em>Instrumentation and orchestration</em>. New York: Schirmer Books, p.194.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 1</title>
		<link>./../../../../assignment-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 07:40:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=194</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The first assignment&#8217;s brief is really exciting: to complete an unfinished ballet score called Wild Dance, of which&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="assignment-1-a-composition-for-a-group-of-untuned-percussion" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628920059263 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-2 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Assignment 1: A composition for a group of untuned percussion</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The first assignment&#8217;s brief is really exciting: to complete an unfinished ballet score called Wild Dance, of which only the first 14 bars have been completed and the sole indication is: Curtain rises &#8211; enter a group of demons. The goal is to create a complete composition with unpitched percussion that lasts between 2 and 3 minutes.</p>



<p>I looked deeper into the composition and made a few tweaks to the concept after<a href="/project-4-about-structure/" data-type="URL" data-id="/project-4-about-structure/" target="_blank"> the plan I developed in Project 4</a>. The most notable difference is in the narrative, which has an impact on the structure.</p>



<p>You can find the score <a href="https://bit.ly/pedroassignment1" data-type="URL" data-id="https://bit.ly/pedroassignment1" target="_blank">here</a> and listen to it below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Assignment-1-Wild-dance-Kontakt.mp3"></audio></figure>



<h2 id="theme-story" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628867810567 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Theme /Story</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Do you know how you feel when you&#8217;re about to do something that makes you uncomfortable? Maybe the first time you kissed a person you loved? Or when you&#8217;re taking an exam that you haven&#8217;t prepared for? Or every time you perform in front of a large crowd?</p>



<p>A lot of things happen in your head: adrenaline rushes, you feel dizzy, and your mind is filled with conflicting thoughts. &#8220;I can&#8217;t do it,&#8221; &#8220;What if everything goes wrong?&#8221; &#8220;I&#8217;m not prepared,&#8221; &#8220;I think I can do it!&#8221; and &#8220;I&#8217;ll do it!&#8221;<br>Inside your head, it&#8217;s like a war between demons and angels.</p>



<p>This is the subject of this piece. Sometimes the angels prevail, and other times your anxieties triumph. Demons win in this one.</p>



<h2 id="structure" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628867818771 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Structure</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>I constructed a structure for the piece using the &#8220;Wild Dance&#8221; as a starting point, with the form: A B C B&#8217; A&#8217;.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-regular cnvs-block-core-table-1628498574118"><table><thead><tr><th>Theme</th><th>Section</th><th>Duration / Tempo</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>A &#8211; A horde of demons appear on stage, dancing around the angels and provoking them. The angels are standing calmly nearby.</td><td>Introduction</td><td>~30 seconds at 153 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>B &#8211; The demons strike strongly and rhythmically, but with hesitation, insecurity, and anxiety. They get tired in the end.</td><td>Principal</td><td>~40 seconds at 153 bpm</td></tr><tr><td>C &#8211; The angels continue to live in peace. They are serene, self-assured, and wise. They don&#8217;t desire war, so they demonstrate this by dancing slowly and peacefully.</td><td>Subsidiary</td><td>~40 seconds at 85 bpm</td></tr><tr><td>B&#8217; &#8211; The demons retaliate, but they are stronger and more aggressive. They used the angels&#8217; passiveness to gain strength.</td><td>Reprise</td><td>~20 seconds at 153 bpm</td></tr><tr><td>A&#8217; &#8211; The demons win. Now it&#8217;s their time to make their happy dance, similar to the one in the beginning, but slower and more confident.</td><td>Closing</td><td>~20 seconds at 120 bpm</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 id="composition" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1628867829203 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Composition</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><strong>Part A</strong> Bars 1 &#8211; 30</p>



<p>This section serves as an introduction, introducing the demons. I decided to keep the provided piece and extend it until the 30th Bar. The provided score begins with a motif that I utilized to introduce the demons. I used the same instruments as the demons: cymbals, tambourine, snare, and bass drum.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39.png" alt="" class="wp-image-188" width="234" height="291" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39.png 500w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39-241x300.png 241w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39-300x373.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 234px) 100vw, 234px" /></figure>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Bars 15-16 are the repetition of bars 3-4.</li><li>Bars 17-18 the tambourine is silenced for the first bar, and the 7/8 time signature is introduced to offer some variety to the dance.</li><li><meta charset="utf-8">Bars 19-20 are the repetition of bars 3-4.</li><li>Bar 21 the tambourine comes to a halt to give the rhythm a break.</li><li><meta charset="utf-8">Bars 22-23 are the repetition of bars 3-4.</li><li>Bars 24-26 the tambourine increases the strokes towards the end of the first part.</li><li>Bars 27-30 the bass drum and snare drum mimic each other until the end. </li></ul>



<p><strong>´</strong></p>



<p><strong>Part B </strong>Bars 31 &#8211; 77</p>



<p>Here we have the attack of the demons. Although the tempo is the same, the intensity is bigger with the snare having more prominence than in the introduction, giving the feeling of a faster section. I kept the variable meter from the introduction, as it passes the sense of nervousness. </p>



<p>I thought of an attack motif as an inversion of the time signature of the introduction, 3/8 &#8211; 5/8 instead of 5/8 &#8211; 3/8, to give some familiarity while maintaining the 3 2 3. This motif ends with a small pause since I want to give the listener the feeling of hesitation. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43.png" alt="" class="wp-image-197" width="244" height="302" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43.png 684w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43-242x300.png 242w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43-300x372.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.18.43-640x793.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 244px) 100vw, 244px" /></figure>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled has-regular-font-size"><li>Bar 31 the Part B starts with a wink to Part A, with the crescendo working as the launch of the attack. I repeat it several times to work as the launch of each attack. </li><li>Bars 32-41 the snare establishes the motif. </li><li>Bars 42-46 are the repetition of bars 31-35 with some modifications.</li><li>Bars 47-57 the tambourine substitutes the snare and derives from the motif.</li><li>Bars 58-67 the motif continues and the cymbal strikes more often, reaching the climax.</li><li>Bars 68-71 the first part of the motif is repeated to reach the climax and end the Part B</li><li>Bars 72-77 the ritardando is used to transmit the demons&#8217; tiredness and build a bridge to Part C, with the Tam-Tam and Bass Drum (Bar 76) ending it.</li></ul>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Part C</strong> Bars 78 &#8211; 98</p>



<p>Part C is devoted to the angels. This section contrasts with the previous ones by being slower and with fewer instrument strikes. I want the listener to breathe from the previous strikes and to prepare for the following ones. For the angels&#8217; instruments, I picked Finger Cymbals &#8211; Cabasa &#8211; Bongos &#8211; Bass Drum. The motif came after I watched the tremolo Finger Cymbal technique in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dt6nyCLf45s" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dt6nyCLf45s" target="_blank">this Zildjian video</a>. I liked how spacial it sounded. Then I thought that the cabasa would be a good fit for the Finger Cymbals, so I researched some playing techniques and ended up finding <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UAwVq2VbBbc" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UAwVq2VbBbc" target="_blank">this video</a> showing the player hitting the cabasa and shaking it, which sounded perfect for me. The Bass drum provides the base rhythm and the Bongos provide the dance rhythm.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10.png" alt="" class="wp-image-199" width="253" height="298" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10.png 740w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10-254x300.png 254w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10-300x354.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-12-at-10.29.10-640x756.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px" /></figure>



<p>The time signature is always 5/8 &#8211; 5/8 &#8211; 6/8 to keep it simple and predictable.</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Bars 78-80 establishes the motif, ending in a kind of delay sound for the cabasa.</li><li>Bars 81-94 are the repetition of the motif but with the bongos providing the danceable rhythm.</li><li>Bars 95-98 the repetition and the acceleration of the snare brings us a new attack, to the B&#8217; part.</li></ul>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Part B&#8217;</strong> Bars 99 &#8211; 120</p>



<p>This reprise is a shortened version of Part B, where the motif is repeated at first, but then the tambourine joins the snare in a new pattern to gain force in this last attack. In the end, they defeat the angels.</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Bars 99-103 are the repetition of the 32-35 bars.</li><li>Bars 104-116 we can hear the last attack, the tambourine joins the snare and the cymbal joins the bass drum. All instruments grow in presence.</li><li>Bars 117-120 are a passage to the closing. The claves enter to make a celebratory dance, very childish and naive, but very simple. Only later I noticed it sounds like the intro of Rage Against The Machine&#8217;s Killing In The Name.</li></ul>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Part C&#8217;</strong> Bars 121 &#8211; 136</p>



<p>The dance ends as it started, but is slower. Since the demons won, they don&#8217;t need to make all the rush they did at the beginning, but can make a slow and confident victory dance. Ending with the same motif from the beginning makes a full circle, meaning that like the demons in your head, they always come and go, and this is not an isolated battle.</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Bars 121-128 are the repetition of bars 3-10, with the little addition of bass drum to add more base sound, because of the slower tempo.</li><li>Bars 129-130 the repetition continues but with the increase of the cymbal and snare.</li><li>Bars 131-136 the cymbal has a little motif of 5 consecutive strokes with all the other instruments increasing in strokes until the end.</li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Assignment-1-Wild-dance-Kontakt.mp3" length="3224994" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project 4 &#8211; About Structure</title>
		<link>./../../../../project-4-about-structure/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2021 14:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/?p=166</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The goal of this final project, which comes before the first assignment, is to create a plan for&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The goal of this final project, which comes before the first assignment, is to create a plan for the assignment composition, which should last between 2 and 3 minutes and begin with the specified composition.</p>



<p>One thing I noticed is that it is suggested that the plan begins with the structure before deciding on the content. However, when I look at Assignment 1, I find that it begins with a group of demons entering the scene. As a result, I&#8217;m reluctant to separate the idea from the structure. So I decided to start with the idea/story and then go on to the structure.</p>



<h2 id="the-idea" class="wp-block-heading">The Idea</h2>



<p>When I first read &#8220;Curtain Rises, enter a group of demons&#8221; at the start of assignment 1, I immediately thought of the devils that pop into your head from time to time. Particularly when you&#8217;re going to do something that makes you feel uneasy. For example, for me, it was when I began writing music in notation, which I had never done before. All of your demons begin to rush through your head in the form of doubts such as &#8220;will I be able to do this?&#8221; and &#8220;why did I even start this course?&#8221;</p>



<p>For this piece, I decided to explore the battle between spirits (doubts, anxieties, self-censorship) and demons (confidence, tranquillity, wisdom) that happen inside your head when you&#8217;re about to do something uncomfortable.</p>



<h2 id="the-structure" class="wp-block-heading">The Structure</h2>



<p>Starting with the given Wild Dance composition, I opted to utilize the specified tempo (153 bpm) as the demons tempo since it conveys a sense of haste and chaos. By contrast, the angels will move at a slower pace, conveying a sense of tranquillity. </p>



<p>As I previously stated, my composition will be about a clash&nbsp;in which demons arrive and attack, angels defend, demons counter-attack and the angels ultimately triumph. I want the audience to sense this conflict, which will be reflected in the speed and instrument shifts.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-regular cnvs-block-core-table-1628498574118"><table><thead><tr><th>Theme</th><th>Section</th><th>Duration / Tempo</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>A &#8211; A horde of demons appear on stage, dancing around the angels and provoking them. The angels are standing calmly nearby.</td><td>Principal</td><td>~30 seconds at 153 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>B &#8211; The demons strike with hesitation, insecurity, and anxiety.</td><td>Principal</td><td>~40 seconds at 153 bpm</td></tr><tr><td>C- The angels continue to live in peace. They are composed, self-assured, and wise. They don&#8217;t desire war, so they demonstrate this by dancing slowly and peacefully.</td><td>Subsidiary</td><td>~40 seconds at 85 bpm</td></tr><tr><td>B&#8217;-The demons retaliate, but they&#8217;re growing nervous.</td><td>Reprise</td><td>~20 seconds at 153 bpm</td></tr><tr><td>C&#8217;-The angels grow in strength and distance themselves from the demons.</td><td>Closing</td><td>~20 seconds at 153 bpm</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 id="the-motifs" class="wp-block-heading">The motifs</h2>



<p>I developed some themes for each section. The first one will serve as an introduction and the example is already delivered, which heavily uses the tambourine.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39.png" alt="" class="wp-image-188" width="270" height="336" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39.png 500w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39-241x300.png 241w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.02.39-300x373.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 270px) 100vw, 270px" /></figure>



<p>In the B section, I imagined the demons&#8217; strike to be powerful, but with a slight hesitation at the end.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.00.31.png" alt="" class="wp-image-189" width="277" height="346" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.00.31.png 508w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.00.31-240x300.png 240w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.00.31-300x374.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 277px) 100vw, 277px" /></figure>



<p>The angels in the C portion are calm, assertive, and peaceful. It will contrast with the prior two motifs&#8217; warlike snare.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.01.45.png" alt="" class="wp-image-190" width="281" height="323" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.01.45.png 514w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.01.45-261x300.png 261w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-10-at-15.01.45-300x344.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 281px) 100vw, 281px" /></figure>



<h2 id="the-instruments" class="wp-block-heading">The instruments</h2>



<p>For the demons parts, I chose the given instruments (Bass Drum, Snare Drum, Tambourine, Cymbal) because I believe they convey the sense of urgency and aggression I want to portray. In addition to the Bass Drum, a rhythmic instrument, the angels will also use the Bongos, Cabasa, and Finger Cymbals.</p>



<p>For simplicity, I retained four instruments for each part, and since I want it to be played by four musicians, they only have to switch between two instruments.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Carlos Chávez &#8211; Toccata for Percussion</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-carlos-chavez-toccata-for-percussion/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 18:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=216</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The backstory surrounding the Toccata is fascinating. Carlos Chávez was commissioned by John Cage to create a piece&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="when-i-came-across-this-piece-on-youtube-i-was-expecting-a-latin-rhythm-percussion-piece-probably-because-the-composer-was-mexican" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1629007147368 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-2 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>When I came across this piece on Youtube, I was expecting a Latin rhythm percussion piece. Probably because the composer was Mexican.</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><meta charset="utf-8"></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Carlos Chávez: Toccata" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Smrbcl_klQM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Fox, J., 2014. <em>Carlos Chávez: Toccata</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Smrbcl_klQM> [Accessed 5 August 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>The backstory surrounding the Toccata is fascinating. Carlos Chávez was commissioned by John Cage to create a piece for the percussion ensemble with which he was travelling. As a result, the <meta charset="utf-8">Toccata for Percussion was created. The sad part is that <meta charset="utf-8">Cage&#8217;s ensemble was unable to execute the opening movement, which requires all members to play long, continuous drum rolls, and the piece was never played. The Toccata was not performed until 1948 (Hall, 2008).</p>



<p>The moral of this story, in my opinion, is that there is a fine line between what the composer wants and what the players are capable of playing. In my compositions, I&#8217;ll try to keep this in mind.</p>



<p>This is a three-movement work composed entirely of percussion instruments, the majority of which are unpitched (or indefinite-pitched). I was expecting Latin percussion instruments, but, with the exception of the Indian Drum, all of the other instruments are standard orchestral instruments, not exotic ones.</p>



<p>After a first listen, I discovered that Chávez divided the piece into Membranes and Metalic instruments, with a few wooden instruments thrown in the mix. The wooden instruments, I believe, are used for melody and the other for rhythm.</p>



<p>In terms of the first movement, I found it to be highly interactive. Instruments can be heard playing the passing theme at different times. Other times, as in the example below, the sound shifts from low to high pitch.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="448" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-11.58.59-1024x448.png" alt="" class="wp-image-218" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-11.58.59-1024x448.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-11.58.59-300x131.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-11.58.59-768x336.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-11.58.59-1536x671.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-11.58.59-2048x895.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-11.58.59-640x280.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-11.58.59-960x420.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-11.58.59.png 2558w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>This first movement is characterized by the eight notes, that create some of the motifs of this part.</p>



<p>When I got to the end of this movement, I realized it ended the same way it started: with a roll. Actually, rolls are present in all music and may be the Toccata&#8217;s most prominent feature. When I got to the end of the movement, I realized it ended with a roll, just like it had begun.  Because Chávez wrote these final rolls without diminuendo, I believe it will be difficult for players to keep the roll while changing the strength of strokes at the same time.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="469" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.17.19-1024x469.png" alt="" class="wp-image-220" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.17.19-1024x469.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.17.19-300x138.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.17.19-768x352.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.17.19-1536x704.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.17.19-2048x939.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.17.19-640x293.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.17.19-960x440.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.17.19.png 2452w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>With the exception of the xylophone, the instruments in the second movement are all metallic. This movement seemed more mysterious to me, perhaps because of the sound of the metallic instruments and the slower tempo. But, thanks to the xylophone and glockenspiel, it&#8217;s also the most melodic of the movements. I found it particularly fascinating when all of the instruments imitated one another, resulting in a unique timbre.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.12.25-991x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-219" width="423" height="437" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.12.25-991x1024.png 991w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.12.25-290x300.png 290w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.12.25-768x794.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.12.25-300x310.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.12.25-640x661.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.12.25-960x992.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-12.12.25.png 1318w" sizes="(max-width: 423px) 100vw, 423px" /></figure>



<p>The third movement is more complex, and I finally found the Latin rhythms I was looking for at the beginning. We return to membrane instruments in this movement, with the glockenspiel, maracas, and claves added later. This movement appears to use more sixteenth notes than the previous ones, making it feel faster. The third movement continues to be interactive, with some instruments passing the motif from one instrument to the next, like the example below.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="450" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-13.30.36-1024x450.png" alt="" class="wp-image-221" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-13.30.36-1024x450.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-13.30.36-300x132.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-13.30.36-768x338.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-13.30.36-1536x675.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-13.30.36-2048x900.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-13.30.36-640x281.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-13.30.36-960x422.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/08/Screenshot-2021-08-15-at-13.30.36.png 2548w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>On a personal note, I found the Toccata for Percussion to be a fascinating composition in which I was able to acquire a feel of how different percussion instruments may be used to convey both rhythm and melody.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1629005686283 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>HALL, J.R., 2008.&nbsp;<em>Development of the percussion ensemble through the contributions of the Latin American composers Amadeo Roldán, José Ardévol, Carlos Chávez, and Alberto Ginastera</em>, The Ohio State University, p. 61.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project 3 &#8211; Three and more instruments</title>
		<link>./../../../../project-3-three-and-more-instruments/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 09:02:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/?p=145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This project&#8217;s goal is to create two studies using at least three untuned percussion instruments. Despite the fact&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This project&#8217;s goal is to create two studies using at least three untuned percussion instruments. Despite the fact that I could have used some of the examples provided as a starting point for my work, I chose to build them from scratch.</p>



<p>While I thought using more instruments would be easier, the variety of instruments available and the techniques for each instrument were overwhelming. I often worked on a single instrument and then realized it didn&#8217;t fit well with the others, forcing me to rewrite it. That took longer than I anticipated.</p>



<p>A characteristic that I noticed about some of the percussion compositions I listened to is that they are coupled with dance or body movements. Therefore, the central focus of both of my studies is on expressive dance and bodily movement.</p>



<h2 id="study-1" class="wp-block-heading">Study 1</h2>



<p>My professional background is in advertising, and as I started thinking about this first research, I remembered an old Lacoste commercial called The Leap. This video shows a couple sitting at a coffee table, with the boy preparing to kiss the girl for the first time. The film then turns to a metaphor for what&#8217;s going on inside his head: a massive leap into the unknown. I immediately thought of my <a href="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/2021/07/project-1-percussion-solos" target="_blank">first study of Taiko</a> and how it is linked to breathing rhythm. Due to this, I chose the video and the Taiko as the basis for my initial study.</p>



<p>I decided Taiko was the foundation of this composition, the heart, and then I added instruments that I thought might be able to bring the breath rhythm to life. Wood Blocks first function as an echo of the heart (Taiko) and then as the rush of the mind. The snare brings a marching strength that reminds me of running. The tam-tam is used as a reminder of the character&#8217;s great action&#8217;s danger. Cabasas are merely used to cause confusion and dizziness.</p>



<p>When I was looking for information on instrument techniques, I came upon <a href="https://philharmonia.co.uk/resources/instruments/percussion/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://philharmonia.co.uk/resources/instruments/percussion/" target="_blank">Philharmonia&#8217;s excellent webpage</a> on percussion instruments. There, I examined the tam-tam and one unique technique in which the musician rubs a triangular stick against the tam-tam&#8217;s edge&nbsp;to produce a harsh sound. If the player rubbed it gently enough, it could simulate the sound of the wind.</p>



<p>There are three parts to this piece:</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>The acceleration of breathing</li><li>The suspension of jumping</li><li>The unpredictability of the first kiss</li></ul>



<p>As much as possible, I tried to make it concise and interesting while staying true to the main idea. My 3rd section used a time change from 5/4 to 3/4 in order to help create some confusion. The ending was inspired by my first <a href="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/2021/06/listening-to-arthur-honegger-cello-sonata-h-20-iii-presto" target="_blank">listening of Honegger</a>, with the ending feeling incomplete (just like every first kiss, you want more from the moment) in a 4/4 bar rather than a 5/4 bar.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-3_0001.png" alt="" class="wp-image-158"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-3_0002-708x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-157"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-3_0003-708x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-156"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-3_0004-707x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-155"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-3_0005-707x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-154"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-3_0006-708x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-153"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-3.mp3"></audio></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-video"><video controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Lacoste-The-Big-Leap.mov"></video></figure>



<h2 id="study-2" class="wp-block-heading">Study 2</h2>



<p>This study was inspired by flamenco dances I watched as a kid. There were times when a male and female dancer alternated. The idea behind this song is to create a classic storyline in which a girl meets a boy and in the end, they dance together.</p>



<p>I have divided this piece into three parts:</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>The girl is introduced</li><li>The boy is introduced</li><li>They both dance together</li></ul>



<p>I attempted to use some Latin instruments, but because some of them were unfamiliar to me, I had to do some additional research into their techniques.</p>



<p>The Cajon and Tambourine offer the rhythm&#8217;s foundation. I looked at Vic Firth&#8217;s tutorials for the tambourine, particularly the usage of the thumb roll as a gentle and long roll that could fit this rhythm. Because I couldn&#8217;t find a standardized method to notate the Cajon, I created a two-line stave with the low strokes on the bottom line and the high strokes on the top line.</p>



<p>The girl is represented by the Castanets and the Guiro. For me, the Guiro was a whole new instrument. After seeing and listening to Guiro rhythms, I decided to keep it basic and only provide some context for the Castanets.</p>



<p>Bongos and Claves symbolize the boy. Cajon&#8217;s low pitch led me to choose Bongos instead of Congas since they are higher pitched. It is written in two-line Bongo notation.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-Beguine_0001-1024x877.png" alt="" class="wp-image-152"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-Beguine_0002-1024x773.png" alt="" class="wp-image-151"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-Beguine_0003-1024x773.png" alt="" class="wp-image-150"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-Beguine_0004-1024x742.png" alt="" class="wp-image-149"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-Beguine_0005-1024x742.png" alt="" class="wp-image-148"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-Beguine_0006-1024x773.png" alt="" class="wp-image-147"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-Beguine.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-3.mp3" length="1093402" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Lacoste-The-Big-Leap.mov" length="6279762" type="video/quicktime" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-3-Percussion-ensemble-Beguine.mp3" length="911067" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Boris Blacher &#8211; Variations On A Theme of Paganini</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-boris-blacher-variations-on-a-theme-of-paganini/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 23:51:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/?p=135</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I listened to all 16 variations from Boris Blacher&#8217;s Variations On A Paganini Theme, but I was curious&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="variations-rhythm-and-all-that-jazz" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1626071306105 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-3 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Variations, rhythm and all that jazz.</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>I listened to all 16 variations from Boris Blacher&#8217;s Variations On A Paganini Theme, but I was curious how it sounded and looked in a concert, so I watched a performance by the Frankfurt Radio Symphony.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Blacher: Paganini-Variationen ∙ hr-Sinfonieorchester ∙ Andrés Orozco-Estrada" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/l8GVvL-wW8c?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>hr-Sinfonieorchester – Frankfurt Radio Symphony, 2018.&nbsp;<em>Blacher: Paganini-Variationen ∙ hr-Sinfonieorchester ∙ Andrés Orozco-Estrada</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l8GVvL-wW8c&gt; [Accessed 12 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>The Paganini Caprice theme fades away after a few seconds, and Blacher&#8217;s variants come to life on their own. There&#8217;s a little resemblance to it now and then, but it&#8217;s really subtle. Another thing I noticed is that Blacher strives to showcase all instruments through the variations, starting with strings, then on to woodwinds, and finally to brass. Percussion continues to come and go as the variants change. Despite the fact that I believe most of the variants to be quite vibrant rhythmically, there is no variation dedicated only to percussion.</p>



<p>I couldn&#8217;t find a score, and despite the fact that different time signatures were used between variations, I couldn&#8217;t figure out if Variable Metre was used at all.</p>



<p>For me, the second&nbsp;and last two&nbsp;variations were the most intriguing. The second variation features a bluesy oboe with blue notes, which I adore (and it looks like the player from the performance I posted does too). The 15th and 16th have a jazzier flavour to them, and they remind me of big bands. That was a fantastic conclusion. &#8220;Dominant rhythm and abrupt ends are Blacher hallmarks,&#8221; (Simon, 2003) I realized after learning more about Blacher.</p>



<p>All of this jazz influence, and how he changed it into an orchestral sound, piqued my curiosity in Blacher, and I&#8217;m likely to listen to him more in the future, and perhaps include some of his influences into my works.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>Side Note about Variations. I had no clue what variations were, let alone how popular Paganini&#8217;s theme was. Basically, variation form is when you take a song&#8217;s theme and investigate, mine, twist, and transform it into a new piece of art (Hough, 2013). It appears to me to be a creative exercise rather than the construction of completely new work. I enjoy the idea of variations, and I&#8217;m curious as to why there aren&#8217;t any big musicians that do variations of other artists&#8217; songs. This reminds me that some DJs are experimenting with several versions of the same song like Stereossauro did with Carlos Paredes&#8217; Verdes Anos.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Stereossauro - Verdes Anos | Eléctrico | Antena 3" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/v7A1pmlePDA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Stereossauro, 2019.&nbsp;<em>Stereossauro &#8211; Verdes Anos | Eléctrico | Antena 3</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v7A1pmlePDA&gt; [Accessed 9 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1626070536852 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Simon, J. (2003) &#8216;Chasing the blahs with Blacher. (On Music)&#8217;, The New Leader, 86(2), 34+, available: https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A100544790/ITOF?u=ucca&amp;sid=summon&amp;xid=a718ba22 [accessed 12 Jul 2021].</p>



<p>Hough, S., 2013. On the art of variation: why Paganini&#8217;s theme is so popular. [online] the Guardian. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/2013/jul/05/how-paganini-became-pop [Accessed 9 July 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project 2 &#8211; Percussion Duets</title>
		<link>./../../../../project-2-percussion-duets/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 06:37:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/?p=121</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Composing for two instruments should have been easy for me, but it turned out to be more difficult.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Composing for two instruments should have been easy for me, but it turned out to be more difficult. Beyond the obvious snare and bass drum, I had a hard time deciding which instruments should make a duet. Then I had difficulties getting it to function beyond the basic concept; I constantly felt like one instrument was missing.</p>



<p>The purpose of this project is to write four short compositions with at least eight bars each for two untuned instruments. The conversation between the instruments should be explored in the first two parts. The latter two should experiment with unusual time signatures &#8211; five and seven beats per bar, respectively.</p>



<h2 id="snare-drum-bass-drum" class="wp-block-heading">Snare Drum &amp; Bass Drum</h2>



<p>For the first study, I chose the one that was most comfortable for me. I&#8217;m familiar with the snare and bass drum&#8217;s characteristics, so I sought to create a piece that would explore a dialogue between the two. The goal is for each participant to &#8220;talk&#8221; in turn until they are both in unison. The second section of this composition was inspired by a scene from Carmen Suite (that I reviewed <a href="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/2021/07/listening-to-rodion-shchedrin-carmen-suite" target="_blank">here</a>), in which the Marimba and Vibrafono had a little dialogue.</p>



<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1625973391243 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625973391270" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="rodion-shchedrin-carmen-suite" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">Rodion Shchedrin – Carmen Suite</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Screenshot-2021-07-03-at-22.47.39-1024x321.png" alt="" class="wp-image-122"/></figure>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625973391274" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
			</div>
</div>

</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Snare-Bass-Drum-745x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-123"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Snare-Bass-Drum.mp3"></audio></figure>



<h2 id="shaker-wood-block" class="wp-block-heading">Shaker &amp; Wood Block</h2>



<p>In this work, I had a concept of a conversation, but it&#8217;s one of those where one side does the majority of the talking while the other simply attempts to say something but finds it nearly impossible and eventually becomes frustrated. If I&#8217;m being frank, I think the shaker can be irritating if used frequently. I discovered George Crumb&#8217;s Music For a Summer Evening when researching the shaker. The use of the shaker piqued my interest, and it led me to conclude the conversation in bar 7.</p>



<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1625974329757 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625974329805" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="g-crumb-music-for-a-summer-evening-makrokosmos-iii" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">G. Crumb: Music for a Summer Evening (Makrokosmos III)</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="G. Crumb: Music for a Summer Evening (Makrokosmos III)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Et8pUMm0VE8?start=119&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Shpachenko, N., 2014.&nbsp;<em>G. Crumb: Music for a Summer Evening (Makrokosmos III)</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Et8pUMm0VE8&gt; [Accessed 11 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625974329810" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="-2" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
			</div>
</div>

</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Shaker-Wood-Block-1024x622.png" alt="" class="wp-image-125"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Shaker-Wood-Block.mp3"></audio></figure>



<h2 id="castanets-tambourine" class="wp-block-heading">Castanets &amp; Tambourine</h2>



<p>When I was listening to Carmen Suite, I noticed how the castanets were used to create a more danceable rhythm. I looked into what approaches could be used in the castanets for my third composition, but in the end, the flamenco dancers who hit their shoes on the floor to mark the rhythm inspired me more.</p>



<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1625975001948 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625975002122" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="john-parks-castanet-performance-tips" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">John Parks: Castanet Performance Tips</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="John Parks: Castanet Performance Tips" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jXqFEx-S0hw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Black Swamp Percussion, 2017.&nbsp;<em>John Parks: Castanet Performance Tips</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jXqFEx-S0hw&gt; [Accessed 11 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625975002149" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="melina-najjar-flamenco-dance-farruca-with-yazan-ibrahim" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">Melina Najjar- Flamenco dance Farruca with Yazan Ibrahim</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Melina Najjar- Flamenco dance Farruca with Yazan Ibrahim" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eIBCd4zmPDA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Najjar, M., 2020.&nbsp;<em>Melina Najjar- Flamenco dance Farruca with Yazan Ibrahim</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eIBCd4zmPDA&gt; [Accessed 11 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>

	</div>
</div>

</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Castanets-Tambourine-1-1024x933.png" alt="" class="wp-image-129"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Castanets-Tambourine.mp3"></audio></figure>



<h2 id="triangle-cymbal" class="wp-block-heading">Triangle &amp; Cymbal</h2>



<p>With the last one, I wanted to go darker. In my perspective, the cymbal has either a massive marking when struck hard or a mystery marking when slammed softly. After seeing Vic Firth&#8217;s video with the suspended cymbal, I decided to use the Marimba Mallet&#8217;s deeper tone. However, because it is preferable to describe the desired sound rather than the mallet (Solomon, 2002), I put &#8220;dark.&#8221;</p>



<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1625981577123 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625981577173" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="suspended-cymbal-1-selection-and-techniques-vic-firth-percussion-101" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">Suspended Cymbal 1: Selection and Techniques / Vic Firth Percussion 101</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Suspended Cymbal 1: Selection and Techniques / Vic Firth Percussion 101" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/m51seFRRal0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Firth, V., 2012.&nbsp;<em>Suspended Cymbal 1: Selection and Techniques / Vic Firth Percussion 101</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m51seFRRal0&gt; [Accessed 11 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625981577178" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="-3" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
			</div>
</div>

</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Triangle-Cymbal-2-1024x674.png" alt="" class="wp-image-127"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Triangle-Cymbal-2.mp3"></audio></figure>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1625981826194 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Solomon, S., 2002. How to write for percussion. 1st ed. New York: SZSolomon, p.42.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Snare-Bass-Drum.mp3" length="572520" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Shaker-Wood-Block.mp3" length="376602" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Castanets-Tambourine.mp3" length="445565" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-2-Percussion-solos-Triangle-Cymbal-2.mp3" length="635214" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Researching Variable Metre</title>
		<link>./../../../../researching-variable-metre/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 17:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/?p=118</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It&#8217;s amusing that a quick Google search for [Variable Metre Boris Blacher] yields nearly exclusively results from OCA&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It&#8217;s amusing that a quick Google search for [Variable Metre Boris Blacher] yields nearly exclusively results from OCA students&#8217; blogs. Are we the only ones who have written on Variable Metre?</p>



<p>I&#8217;m not going to provide an entire biography of Boris Blacher here (an excellent summary can be found in Simon, 2003), but I did discover that he studied architecture before becoming a renowned composer. Probably that is why he developed the Variable Metre, which is made up of &#8220;patterns, certainly, but used as expressive building blocks&#8221; (Matthew-Walker 2003, p.24).</p>



<p>But first, let&#8217;s look at the formal definition of Variable Metre from The Oxford Dictionary of Music:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">[a rhythmical process] whereby systematic changes of metre are planned according to mathematical relationships.</p><cite>(Kennedy, Kennedy and Rutherford-Johnson, 2013)</cite></blockquote>



<p>I believe that it is simpler to say that Variable Metre is when a piece of music with a continual shift in time signature based on a numeric pattern. This pattern can have a mathematical relationship, but I don&#8217;t believe it is always true. It&#8217;s also easier to understand if you look at it:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://drive.google.com/uc?export=download&amp;id=1fZQ6vsTcWMsSif1J3uHEMJGXZ2JLKa2I" alt=""/></figure>



<p>Numbers below the tempo marker indicate the time signature, while dots indicate incremental changes to the next value.</p>



<p>Although some sources claim he did not invent Variable Metre (Quinn, 2005), he was most likely the one who developed it most.</p>



<p>I must admit that when I initially read the definition of Variable Metre, I was sceptical about whether or not I would enjoy hearing it. I agreed with critics who claimed that this method was more like eye-music than ear-music (Matthew-Walker 2003, p.24). My opinion changed when I heard his Piano Concerto No.2.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Boris Blacher - Piano Concerto No.2 Op.42" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/00QddeqyE5U?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>fyrexianoff, 2012.&nbsp;<em>Boris Blacher &#8211; Piano Concerto No.2 Op.42</em>. [image] Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=00QddeqyE5U&gt; [Accessed 11 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>After hearing it multiple times and assessing which sections I loved the most and which parts I didn&#8217;t believe Variable Metre made a significant difference, I realized that this technique works best when the notes are&nbsp;repeated. In Konzert für Klavier und Orchester, No. 2: I. Allegro, this happens. You&#8217;re listening to the same thing over and over, but each time the time changes, a new puzzle piece is added. As if a block is being added to a building to make it more stunning. This enables the creation of anticipation and disruption. I believe these two qualities are&nbsp;appealing to the ear.</p>



<p>In conclusion, I believe it was worthwhile to learn about Variable Metre, but I find it difficult to think of it as anything more than a creative exercise if it is not utilized with repetition.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1626070536852 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Simon, J. (2003) &#8216;Chasing the blahs with Blacher. (On Music)&#8217;, <em>The New Leader</em>, 86(2), 34+, available: https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A100544790/ITOF?u=ucca&amp;sid=summon&amp;xid=a718ba22 [accessed 09 Jul 2021].</p>



<p>Kennedy, M., Kennedy, J. and Rutherford-Johnson, T., 2013.&nbsp;<em>The Oxford dictionary of music</em>. 6th ed. Oxford: Oxford Univ. Press.</p>



<p>Matthew-Walker, R. 2003, Boris Blacher, Musical Opinion Limited, 126, pp. 24.</p>



<p>Quinn, I., 2005. Blacher: Paganini Variations; Ornament; Pianissimo Study; Fantasy: The Record Connoisseur&#8217;s Magazine. American Record Guide, 68(5), pp. 79.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Rodion Shchedrin &#8211; Carmen Suite</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-rodion-shchedrin-carmen-suite/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2021 04:45:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/?p=105</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I was researching the tambourine, I came across Rodion Shchedrin&#8217;s Carmen Suite for string orchestra and percussion&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="it-doesnt-hurt-trying-to-do-something-new" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1625410855934 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-3 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>It doesn&#8217;t hurt trying to do something new.</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>When I was researching the tambourine, I came across Rodion Shchedrin&#8217;s Carmen Suite for string orchestra and percussion (1967). </p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Bizet / Shchedrin : Carmen Suite" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QysD8zCfGTs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>France Musique, 2020.&nbsp;<em>Bizet / Shchedrin: Carmen Suite</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QysD8zCfGTs&gt; [Accessed 4 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>A little backstory. When Shchedrin&#8217;s wife, Maya Plisetskaya, asked Shostakovich to write a new Carmen ballet, he &#8220;gently but firmly refused.&#8221; &#8220;I&#8217;m afraid of Bizet.&#8221; After that, she asked her husband, who agreed. Shostakovich&#8217;s response demonstrates Shchedrin&#8217;s bravery. After its debut performance, the Carmen Suite was deemed &#8220;disrespectful&#8221; to Bizet&#8217;s opera and was banned by the Soviet leadership. (Plisetskaya, 2001)</p>



<p>I feel that percussion, such as tubular bells, cymbals and castanets, are used throughout Shchedrin&#8217;s score to emphasize rhythms. Although he pays homage to the original material, he frequently pushes the music in unexpected ways, heightening the atmosphere and drama.</p>



<p>On&nbsp;the&nbsp;other&nbsp;side,&nbsp;I&nbsp;find&nbsp;the&nbsp;presence&nbsp;of&nbsp;percussion&nbsp;to&nbsp;be&nbsp;rather&nbsp;comic&nbsp;at&nbsp;times, such&nbsp;as&nbsp;when&nbsp;the&nbsp;timpani&nbsp;glissando&nbsp;is&nbsp;used&nbsp;or&nbsp;when&nbsp;the&nbsp;strings&nbsp;provide&nbsp;distinctive&nbsp;effects. </p>



<p>Overall, I think the experiment of using percussion to replace other instruments was a great success, and the end result was quite entertaining. If it&#8217;s superior to the original? I don&#8217;t believe it is necessary to respond.</p>



<p>It reminded me of Johnny Cash&#8217;s Hurt version. It was a risky move for producer Rick Rubin to persuade Johnny Cash to record a version of Nine Inch Nail&#8217;s Hurt. Cash refused to sing the song, which was widely regarded as one of NIN&#8217;s best. It wasn&#8217;t until he read the lyrics that Cash realized he could make his own version of the song. Finally, the singer and producer managed to create a masterpiece from a masterpiece. It wasn&#8217;t better or worse than the original; rather, it was unique. Instead of being a song about drugs and self-destruction, they transformed it into an acoustic song about the epilogue of an eventful life.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Johnny Cash - Hurt (Official Music Video)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8AHCfZTRGiI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Cash, J., 2021.&nbsp;<em>Johnny Cash &#8211; Hurt (Official Music Video)</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8AHCfZTRGiI&gt; [Accessed 4 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>Like NIN/Cash&#8217;s Hurt, Bizet/Shchedrin&#8217;s Carmen can exist in the music world indefinitely as two different but interconnected works that don&#8217;t have to be judged against each other.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1625412893497 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Plisetskaya, M., 2001.&nbsp;<em>I, maya plisetskaya</em>. [Place of publication not identified]: Yale Univ Press.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to System Of A Down &#8211; Chop Suey!</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-system-of-a-down-chop-suey/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 10:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=708</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As I was working on project 1, System Of A Down&#8217;s Chop Suey! began playing on my Spotify.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As I was working on project 1, System Of A Down&#8217;s Chop Suey! began playing on my Spotify. Although I have always enjoyed this song, I never paid close attention to it.</p>



<p>Chop Suey! is the first single from the Los Angeles band&#8217;s second studio album, Toxicity, it&#8217;s one of the most recognizable songs in the Nu-Metal genre and it was voted the greatest metal song of the 21st century by Metal Hammer magazine (Metal Hammer, 2021).</p>



<p>While System Of A Down is an American heavy metal band, all of its members are of Armenian descent, being either the children of Armenian immigrants or immigrants themselves from Armenia. This contributes to the novel sound that they brought to the Heavy Metal scene, which is especially apparent in Chop Suey!.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="System Of A Down - Chop Suey! (Official HD Video)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CSvFpBOe8eY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>System Of A Down, 2009.&nbsp;<em>System Of A Down &#8211; Chop Suey! (Official HD Video)</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CSvFpBOe8eY&gt; [Accessed 2 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>One reason this song is so enjoyable is that it is both familiar and experimental at the same time. “It has this very experimental side that wasn’t like anything the radio was playing at the time, but also a really melodic side that really caught people,” says the band&#8217;s guitarist Daron Malakian (Everley, 2021).</p>



<p>Initially, we hear an acoustic guitar with a danceable rhythm, followed by bass and drums. The intro leads to the heavy part with heavily distorted electric guitar and open hi-hats on the drums. After that, the novel part begins.</p>



<p>The voice, guitar, bass, and drums are all unified in the verse. They all have the same rhythm, the same rests, and the same notes. It&#8217;s confusing, unexpected, and a nod to rap music. For me, this is the most memorable part of the song because it is almost like a staccato in a heavy metal song.</p>



<p>After the verse, the song moves flawlessly to the chorus. This is a melodic and calm part. The two voices are in harmony, the guitar is playing a simpler arpeggio and the drums are just sustaining the rhythm. This is another interesting take on this song, because instead of the chorus being the climax and the most memorable part of the song, as it usually is, here is the relaxing part that makes a bridge between the chaotic verse.</p>



<p>The song repeats the pre-verse riff, then the verse and chorus again before moving to the bridge. Here, the chaos returns with the distorted guitars and intense drums is combined with a new melody sung by Gregorian chant-like harmonies. Once again, an unexpecting twist makes this song even more memorable.</p>



<p>The bridge moves almost unnoticeably to the chorus but with few changes in melody and in the guitar, keeping it fresh but familiar at the same time until the end of the song.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1640873187970 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Metal Hammer. 2021.&nbsp;<em>System Of A Down&#8217;s Chop Suey! has been voted the greatest metal song of the 21st century</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://www.loudersound.com/news/system-of-a-downs-chop-suey-has-been-voted-the-greatest-metal-song-of-the-21st-century&gt; [Accessed 2 July 2021].</p>



<p>Everley, D., 2021.&nbsp;<em>The Story Behind The Song: System Of A Down’s Chop Suey!</em>. [online] Metal Hammer. Available at: &lt;https://www.loudersound.com/features/system-of-a-down-chop-suey-story-behind-the-song&gt; [Accessed 2 July 2021].</p>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project 1: Percussion Solos</title>
		<link>./../../../../project-1-percussion-solos/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 07:41:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/?p=71</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Composing exclusively for percussion is something new for me. In fact, composing in notation is also a first&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="i-have-never-composed-for-percussion-before" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1624948072250 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-3 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>I have never composed for percussion before</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Composing exclusively for percussion is something new for me. In fact, composing in notation is also a first for me. Usually, I just sit at the piano and compose. I believe that creating in this way took me longer, but that time allowed me to go deeper into the instruments and better understand what I could do with them.</p>



<p>The lack of a standard for notating percussion instruments was the first hurdle I faced (Black and Gerou, 2005). As a result, to have a consistent notation, I used the Essential Dictionary of Orchestration. Also, because some percussion instruments have little or no natural resonance, I chose to change the note-length in order to have fewer rests, which keeps the piece from becoming cluttered and difficult to read (Solomon, 2002). </p>



<p>The&nbsp;goal&nbsp;for&nbsp;this&nbsp;project&nbsp;was&nbsp;to&nbsp;compose&nbsp;four&nbsp;short&nbsp;pieces&nbsp;for&nbsp;untuned&nbsp;instruments&nbsp;of&nbsp;my&nbsp;choice. I chose the Triangle, the Snare Drum, the Taiko and the Tambourine.</p>



<h2 class="has-huge-font-size wp-block-heading" id="the-triangle">The Triangle</h2>



<p>Because this is my first time composing for percussion, I chose to work with the triangle. Eric Hopes wrote it best when he said: &#8220;The truth is that anyone can play the triangle. It is one of the most basic musical instruments.&#8221; (How to Be a Professional Triangle Player | Musicians of the Utah Symphony, n.d.). To test it out, I started writing in a simple time signature, and it sounded good. A section of this work was influenced by Antonín Dvořák&#8217;s Symphony No. 9 in E minor (3rd movement), of which I discovered a performance of the triangle on Youtube.</p>



<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1624949067525 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1624949067564" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="bsp-orchestral-sessions-triangle-dvorak-symphony-9-mvt-iii" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"><em>BSP Orchestral Sessions: Triangle / Dvorak Symphony #9 Mvt. III</em>.</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="BSP Orchestral Sessions: Triangle / Dvorak Symphony #9 Mvt. III" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RrvTZWxk4vs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Black Swamp Percussion, 2021.&nbsp;<em>BSP Orchestral Sessions: Triangle / Dvorak Symphony #9 Mvt. III</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RrvTZWxk4vs&gt; [Accessed 29 June 2021].</figcaption></figure>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1624949067573" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
			</div>
</div>

</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="403" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle-1024x403.png" alt="" class="wp-image-792" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle-1024x403.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle-300x118.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle-768x302.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle-1536x604.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle-2048x805.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle-640x252.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle-960x377.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p></p>



<h2 class="has-huge-font-size wp-block-heading" id="the-snare-drum">The Snare Drum</h2>



<p>For me, the snare drum was an obvious option because it is the percussion instrument with which I am most familiar. Chop Suey! by System Of A Down began playing on my Spotify while I was composing this piece. I interpreted it as both a divine sign and a challenge. Could this song&#8217;s verse serve as inspiration for a snare solo? Yes, I believe so.</p>



<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1624949278903 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1624949278939" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="system-of-a-down-chop-suey" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">System Of A Down &#8211; Chop Suey!</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Spotify Embed: Chop Suey!" width="100%" height="80" style="[object Object]" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2DlHlPMa4M17kufBvI2lEN?si=f0c52e1e3e8140b3&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div><figcaption>System Of A Down, 2001.&nbsp;<em>Chop Suey!</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://open.spotify.com/track/2DlHlPMa4M17kufBvI2lEN?si=a09b43b598914518&gt; [Accessed 29 June 2021].</figcaption></figure>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1624949278943" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="-2" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
			</div>
</div>

</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="550" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare-1024x550.png" alt="" class="wp-image-790" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare-1024x550.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare-300x161.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare-768x413.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare-1536x826.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare-2048x1101.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare-640x344.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare-960x516.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p></p>



<h2 class="has-huge-font-size wp-block-heading" id="the-taiko">The Taiko</h2>



<p>Because I knew nothing about this instrument, I did some research and discovered the principle of &#8220;breath rhythm,&#8221; in which a piece&#8217;s metrical markers are sensed and played as the rhythm of breath (Powell, 2012). This inspired me to set the tempo to 64 because an adult breath rhythm is around 16 breaths per minute, multiplied by four equals 64. This piece, I believe, can translate your breathing before doing something exciting, such as fighting in a war or kissing someone for the first time. Your breathing quickens, you hold your breath for a brief moment, and then it&#8217;s all adrenaline.</p>



<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1624949578282 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1624949578325" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="this-is-japanese-taiko-drum-o-taiko-by-master-eitetsu-hayashi" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"><em>This is Japanese Taiko Drum! (O-taiko by master Eitetsu Hayashi)</em></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="This is Japanese Taiko Drum! (O-taiko by master Eitetsu Hayashi)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ub195aGvfXQ?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>tmme1234, 2016.&nbsp;<em>This is Japanese Taiko Drum! (O-taiko by master Eitetsu Hayashi)</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ub195aGvfXQ&gt; [Accessed 29 June 2021].</figcaption></figure>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1624949578329" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="-3" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
			</div>
</div>

</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="700" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2-1024x700.png" alt="" class="wp-image-793" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2-1024x700.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2-300x205.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2-768x525.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2-1536x1051.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2-2048x1401.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2-640x438.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2-960x657.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2.png 2260w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p></p>



<h2 class="has-huge-font-size wp-block-heading" id="the-tambourine">The Tambourine</h2>



<p>For me, this was not an obvious choice. I&#8217;d never given the tambourine much thought before, but when I was looking for instruments, I came across Edoardo Giachino&#8217;s video of him playing it and was inspired to use it in this project.</p>



<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1625122579406 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625122579457" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="edoardo-giachino-mr-tambourine-man-tamburello-basco" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">Edoardo Giachino Mr Tambourine Man Tamburello Basco</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Edoardo Giachino Mr Tambourine Man Tamburello Basco" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xbhk5yYgUxI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Giachino, E., 2015.&nbsp;<em>Edoardo Giachino Mr Tambourine Man Tamburello Basco</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xbhk5yYgUxI&gt; [Accessed 1 July 2021].</figcaption></figure>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1625122579463" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="-4" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#"></a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
			</div>
</div>

</div>



<p>What I like about the tambourine is that it reminds me of Spanish/Latin sounds that I&#8217;m familiar with. Particularly in Bizet&#8217;s Carmen, which I may review later in my listening log. I attempted to create some fanfare in this piece. Fanfares are typically performed for brass or brass and percussion instruments (Florek, 2015), so I figured why not a tambourine fanfare?</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="403" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine-1024x403.png" alt="" class="wp-image-794" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine-1024x403.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine-300x118.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine-768x302.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine-1536x604.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine-2048x805.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine-640x252.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine-960x377.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1624950766200 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Black, D. and Gerou, T., 2005.&nbsp;<em>Essential Dictionary of Orchestration</em>. 3rd ed. Los Angeles, CA: Alfred Music, p.183.</p>



<p>Solomon, S., 2002.&nbsp;<em>How to write for percussion</em>. 1st ed. New York: SZSolomon, p.42.</p>



<p>Musiciansutahsymphony.com. n.d.&nbsp;<em>How to Be a Professional Triangle Player | Musicians of the Utah Symphony</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://musiciansutahsymphony.com/how-to-become-a-professional-triangle-player/&gt; [Accessed 29 June 2021].</p>



<p>Spaces.oca.ac.uk. 2020.&nbsp;<em>My Listening and Learning Log for Music 1: Composing Music</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://spaces.oca.ac.uk/anthonycomposingmusic/category/coursework/part-1/project-1/&gt; [Accessed 29 June 2021].</p>



<p>Powell, K., 2012. Composing Sound Identity in Taiko Drumming.&nbsp;<em>Anthropology &amp; Education Quarterly</em>, [online] 43(1), pp.101&#8211;119. Available at: &lt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/41410159&gt; [Accessed 29 June 2021].</p>



<p>FLOREK, P.J., 2015.&nbsp;<em>Modern forms of an ancient art: a selection of contemporary fanfares for multiple trumpets demonstrating evolutionary processes in the fanfare form</em>, University of North Texas, p.14.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Triangle.mp3" length="389141" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Snare.mp3" length="431982" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Taiko-2.mp3" length="605435" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Project-1-Percussion-solos-Tambourine.mp3" length="305549" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Arthur Honegger &#8211; Cello Sonata, H. 20: III. Presto</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-arthur-honegger-cello-sonata-h-20-iii-presto/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 07:52:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/?p=32</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My&#160;first&#160;listening&#160;log&#160;was&#160;an&#160;assignment&#160;in&#160;which&#160;I&#160;was&#160;given&#160;a&#160;list&#160;of&#160;composers&#160;to choose&#160;from. I chose Honegger because I have never listened to him before. I&#8217;m glad I did. I&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="honegger-showed-me-that-we-are-on-the-road-to-nowhere" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1623907804669 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-3 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Honegger showed me that we are on the road to nowhere</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Spotify Embed: Cello Sonata, H. 20: III. Presto" width="100%" height="80" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3bk7txJoz14H5HLW0Lwm28?si=83277edda9ca4516&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Honegger, A., Bertsch, B. and Weber, M., 2003.&nbsp;<em>Cello Sonata, H. 20: III. Presto</em>. [Streaming] Available at: &lt;https://open.spotify.com/track/3bk7txJoz14H5HLW0Lwm28?si=f55b4198c69f4b59&gt; [Accessed 17 June 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>My&nbsp;first&nbsp;listening&nbsp;log&nbsp;was&nbsp;an&nbsp;assignment&nbsp;in&nbsp;which&nbsp;I&nbsp;was&nbsp;given&nbsp;a&nbsp;list&nbsp;of&nbsp;composers&nbsp;to choose&nbsp;from. I chose Honegger because I have never listened to him before. I&#8217;m glad I did.</p>



<p>I listened to Cello Sonata, H.20 and I was surprised when the III. Presto started. The music starts with a sharp cello that immediately took me to Tango sounds. I was not expecting that. But that feeling lasted for a second because the music immediately takes a rhythm that is nothing like Tango. It goes with a very paced rhythm, almost mechanical, marked by the cello and followed by the piano. Then, is the piano that marks the rhythm. For me, this is done in a very subtle but interesting way. </p>



<p>The music becomes more melodious toward the finish, and it appears that it is becoming calmer, but I believe Honegger is deceiving us. The mechanical rhythm is constant, and the apotheosis is approaching until it abruptly ends. Instead of ending in a D, as you might expect, the cello and piano end a B and a B#, respectively. That was incredible.</p>



<p>Another thing I found fascinating was listening to multiple musicians perform this piece and seeing how they approached the finish in quite different ways. Some clearly marked it, indicating that it had come to an end. Others failed to create the surprise that Honegger envisioned. But, in my perspective, Bertsch and Webber did an excellent job.</p>



<p>One last thought.</p>



<p>Because my mind was still expecting a finish, this finale remained stuck in my thoughts. The&nbsp;thing&nbsp;is,&nbsp;you&#8217;ve&nbsp;been&nbsp;rushing&nbsp;somewhere&nbsp;for&nbsp;more&nbsp;than&nbsp;3&nbsp;minutes,&nbsp;but&nbsp;you&#8217;ve&nbsp;arrived&nbsp;nowhere. Is this song about life? About being born in an instant, living your life at full speed, and having it abruptly end?</p>



<p>That reminds me of the hit tune &#8220;Road to Nowhere&#8221; by Talking Heads. I&#8217;m not suggesting David Byrne was influenced by Honegger, but the mechanically striking snare throughout the song makes you feel like you&#8217;re on your way somewhere. But as David sings, you&#8217;re not. And that is alright.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Spotify Embed: Road to Nowhere - 2005 Remaster" width="100%" height="80" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2co8fDyaVmxv8xruQWORnC?si=eb525b83a94d4259&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Talking Heads, 2021.&nbsp;<em>Road to Nowhere</em>. [Streaming] Available at: &lt;https://open.spotify.com/track/2co8fDyaVmxv8xruQWORnC?si=eb525b83a94d4259&gt; [Accessed 17 June 2021].</figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Sound Of Revolution</title>
		<link>./../../../../the-sound-of-revolution/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jun 2021 05:23:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Exploring rhythm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://pedrovintem.000webhostapp.com/?p=15</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I remember going to a football stadium for the first time when I was six years old to&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="thinking-about-percussion-led-me-to-a-revolution" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1623902327817 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-2 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Thinking about percussion led me to a revolution.</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>I remember going to a football stadium for the first time when I was six years old to see a game at the Sport Lisboa and Benfica stadium. A large concrete stadium with a capacity of roughly 120.000 spectators. The score was 0-0 at halftime, and the fans were growing concerned. Then something happened that I had never experienced before. The concrete benches began to shake, a rumbling sound grew louder, and it felt like an earthquake. It was the supporters&#8217; feet that stomped on the ground. Thousands of people making a rhythmic sound altogether. It was frightening, powerful and incredible. It was my first experience with live percussion. Benfica won by 3-0.</p>



<p>Beginning my music degree with a study of rhythm and percussion prompted me to look into the history of percussion instruments and their role in music. I ended up viewing Steven Schick&#8217;s presentation. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="On the Bridge: The Beginnings of Contemporary Percussion Music with Steven Schick -- To Be Musical" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-lkAOZC1w3g?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>University of California Television (UCTV), 2013.&nbsp;<em>On the Bridge: The Beginnings of Contemporary Percussion Music with Steven Schick &#8212; To Be Musical</em>.  Available at: &lt;http://University/ of California Television (UCTV)&gt; [Accessed 17 June 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>The presentation was entertaining and light while yet being instructive. One thing he said remained with me out of all the things he mentioned. His definition of percussion instruments.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-default"><p>&#8220;[Percussion instruments] are simple objects that make sound by striking them.&#8221;</p><cite>University of California Television (UCTV), 2013.&nbsp;<em>On the Bridge: The Beginnings of Contemporary Percussion Music with Steven Schick &#8212; To Be Musical</em>.  Available at: &lt;http://University/ of California Television (UCTV)&gt; [Accessed 17 June 2021].</cite></blockquote>



<p>It&#8217;s really that simple. It&#8217;s so simple that I believe anyone, regardless of musical knowledge, can play a percussion instrument. And I believe that is why percussion is at the very beginning of this course. It&#8217;s simple, doable and fun. And yet it&#8217;s so powerful.</p>



<p>Steven Schick also mentions a quote by John Cage.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>&#8220;Percussion music is revolution.&#8221;</p><cite>Cage, J., 1973.&nbsp;<em>Silence</em>. Middletown: Wesleyan University Press, p.87.</cite></blockquote>



<p>John Cage, I believe, meant that percussion allowed musicians to break away from the constraints imposed by classical composers who used the same sounds. Percussion provided an opportunity for exploration. Anything that generated a sound when struck may be included in the music. And the terms &#8220;percussion&#8221; and &#8220;revolution&#8221; immediately brought José Afonso&#8217;s Grândola Vila Morena to mind. Since it was utilized as the start of the Portuguese revolution, this is one of the most emblematic Portuguese songs. Only voice and the sound of marching feet on gravel can be heard during the entire song. And it caused a revolution, politically and musically speaking. For me, that was because of percussion. Isn&#8217;t it percussion if you hit the gravel with your feet? It makes sound by striking them, right?</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Spotify Embed: Grândola vila morena" width="100%" height="380" allowtransparency="true" frameborder="0" allow="encrypted-media" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4YTZhbzc5dV87hhup8HVuo?si=9ece3bec8c6d4058"></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
