<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignments &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 14:49:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Revision of Assignment 5 after tutor&#8217;s feedback</title>
		<link>./../../../../../revision-of-assignment-5-after-tutors-feedback/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 20:46:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1466</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This assignment provided me with significant learning outcomes, enriching my understanding of the piece and expanding my research&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="revision-and-reflection" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1683751774139 is-style-default halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Revision and Reflection</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>This assignment provided me with significant learning outcomes, enriching my understanding of the piece and expanding my research skills. Given my background in writing, I find it more comfortable and efficient to compose an essay rather than a musical piece. Once again, I found the word limit somewhat restrictive for what I wanted to write, but I recognize that such constraints serve to ensure the essay remains focused on essential aspects.</p>



<p>Regarding my research method, I began by listening to the Symphony, using my ears to identify themes, sections, key changes, and other musical elements. Then I researched books and articles to gain a historical understanding of the piece. Finally, I applied a method of analysis I used before, identifying the form, themes, and keys, outlining the structure, establishing how the transitions of keys and sections are made and analysing how themes are built and used throughout the piece.</p>



<p>The feedback from my tutor proved pivotal in transforming what the tutor described as &#8220;a very good start to your analytical writing&#8221; into what I believe to be a well-structured and cohesive essay. Each comment offered new perspectives that hadn&#8217;t occurred to me before, which led to extensive revisions and additions to the essay.</p>



<p>The most important comment was to structure the essay around a central theme, accompanied by a suitable title and introduction. Although this advice seemed obvious upon reading it, it hadn&#8217;t initially occurred to me. Initially, I attempted to provide a comprehensive overview of the piece, resulting in numerous questions. With the help of my tutor, I selected one of those questions and reoriented my essay around the concept of Tone-painting or the &#8220;expression of a feeling.&#8221;</p>



<p>Furthermore, the feedback provided valuable guidance on areas to focus on during my research. For instance, the comment and question raised by my tutor regarding my strangeness when I found the brief key change to a minor key in the development section prompted further investigation into the sonata form, leading me to discover the book &#8220;Elements of Sonata Theory.&#8221; This reference provided answers to that particular question and others I had.</p>



<p>In conclusion, this assignment stands out as one of the most impactful learning experiences I have encountered thus far.</p>



<h2 id="tone-painting-or-the-expression-of-a-feeling-beethovens-sixth-symphony-first-movement" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1684317223172 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Tone-painting or the &#8220;expression of a feeling&#8221;? Beethoven&#8217;s Sixth Symphony, First Movement</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>This essay explores the historical and musical aspects that help understand the nuanced connection between tone-painting and emotional expression in Beethoven&#8217;s Sixth Symphony, Op. 68 “Pastoral”. Through an analysis of the 1st movement of the Symphony, this essay aims to demonstrate how Beethoven masterfully blends these two concepts to create a musical composition that is both vibrant and sensitively emotive.</p>



<p>The Pastoral Symphony, composed between 1807 and 1808, falls within the middle of Beethoven&#8217;s second phase, which was influenced by the turbulent sociopolitical events of the Enlightenment era, personal struggles such as the onset of his deafness, and its cultural context as part of the transition from the Classical to Romantic music period.</p>



<p>Premiered in Vienna on December 22nd 1808, during a concert at which several of other major works by the composer were premiered including his 5th Symphony, the Pastoral Symphony is written for a typical orchestra of that period: piccolo, two flutes, two oboes, two clarinets, two bassoons, two horns, two trumpets, two trombones, timpani and strings (The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1998a). </p>



<p>Since they both premiered at the same concert and were composed at around the same time, the contrast between the 5th Symphony and 6th Symphony is worth noting. The 5th is vigorous and varied, while the 6th is calm and repetitive, with programmatic titles illustrating rural life. Also, unlike the 5th Symphony, Beethoven gave his 6th an epithet: &#8220;Pastoral&#8221;.</p>



<p>In order to understand why Beethoven decided to use the Pastoral as the theme for this Symphony, one must consider the intersection of his personal history and the historical context in which he was creating. On the personal side, according to Allen (2017), Beethoven had a profound love for nature and often sought refuge from the bustle of urban life by retreating to the countryside. But in a historical context, Will (1994:166) states that the pastoral theme was the most common subject in programmatic symphonies during the Classical Period, and although there were earlier works such as Justin Heinrich Knecht&#8217;s 1784 symphony &#8220;Le portrait musical de la nature,&#8221; which shares a similar programmatic intent with Beethoven&#8217;s 6th Symphony, Beethoven might have found inspiration in Haydn&#8217;s great oratorios The Creation (1799) and The Seasons (1801) (Lockwood, 2015). However, in opposition to other programmatic symphonies, Beethoven intended this work to be “more the Expression of Feeling than Tone-Panting”.</p>



<p>Distinguishing between tone-painting and expression of feeling is crucial. According to Will (2002:130), expression involves imitating emotions, while painting involves replicating the sounds or movements of physical objects. The debate surrounding tone-painting in music gained significant attention in the late 18th century, leading to criticism from various English and German writers, including arguments such as &#8220;painting violates the true spirit of music, which ought to express the sentiments of feeling, not convey ideas of inanimate objects&#8221; (Sulzer 1792–94, II: 357 cited in Will, 2002:131).</p>



<ol start="6">
<li></li>
</ol>



<p>Two reviews from 1810, published in Allgemeine musikalische Zeitung (AmZ) and Zeitung für die elegante Welt, shed light on the debate surrounding tone-painting and expression of feeling in Beethoven&#8217;s Pastoral Symphony. While initially denouncing it as &#8220;the utmost in tastelessness,&#8221; the AmZ review later justifies Beethoven&#8217;s use of tone-painting to represent emotions, rather than physical objects.  (Will, 1994:158-160). Similarly, the review published in the Zeitung für die elegante Welt acknowledges that the symphony portrays emotions associated with the pastoral but it goes further to argue that it is more than a generic representation of such emotions. Rather, the scenes depicted are specific episodes from the composer&#8217;s own experiences in the countryside, imbued with his personal emotions. (Will, 1994:161).</p>



<p>Both reviews share a common acknowledgement of Beethoven&#8217;s utilization of tone-painting in his Pastoral Symphony, evident in instances like the storm in the 4th movement and the depiction of birds in the 2nd movement. However, they both consider Beethoven&#8217;s tone-painting to be of secondary significance, with the primary emphasis placed on its ability to convey emotions associated with the pastoral theme.</p>



<p>The pastoral style, as discussed by Adolf Sandberger and stated by Frank Eugene Kirby (1970:612-613), incorporates various elements such as &#8220;bird-call themes, hunting-horn themes, shepherds&#8217; pipes&#8230; and shepherds&#8217; calls&#8230;, country dances, &#8230; and&#8230; the bagpipe with its drone bass.&#8221; He also states that &#8220;the lilting dotted rhythm of the siciliano was frequently associated with the representation of the pastoral, as were flutes, oboes, and horns. Melodic motion in parallel thirds was also common&#8221;. </p>



<p>Robert Hatten (2004:83) highlights the historical precedent for the formal treatment of the pastoral theme through distinctive musical elements such as &#8220;greater consonance, simpler harmonies, pedal points, more-flowing melodic lines&#8221; and also rocking compound accompaniment, harmonic stasis, and melody in parallel thirds.</p>



<p>While each movement of Beethoven&#8217;s Symphony can be analyzed to understand how Beethoven used the music to convey the pastoral theme and elicit associated emotions, Lockwood (2015) defends that the 1st movement &#8220;exemplifies what Beethoven meant when he wrote “More the expression of feelings than tone-painting.”</p>



<p>The 1st movement of the Symphony, titled &#8220;Awakening of Cheerful Feelings upon Arrival in the Country,&#8221; serves as a joyful prelude, devoid of explicit programmatic features found in other movements. It features simple melodies and a light rhythm, with homophonic orchestration and primarily major keys, creating an atmosphere that transmits a cheerful pastoral quality. To depict the tranquillity of awakening in nature, Beethoven minimizes unexpected shifts, employs extensive repetitions, and only briefly uses a minor key.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><a href="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32.png"><img decoding="async" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1419" width="997" height="418" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32.png 1994w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-300x126.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-1024x429.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-768x322.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-1536x644.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-640x268.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-960x402.png 960w" sizes="(max-width: 997px) 100vw, 997px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Figure 1: Structural analysis of the first movement. Click to amplify.</figcaption></figure>



<p>The first movement follows the sonata form structure, as illustrated in Figure 1. Set in the key of F major, this choice holds a significant historical association with compositions inspired by nature, as noted by Geck (2017:105).</p>



<p>The introduction starts with a theme, that can be considered the first theme of the first subject area. This theme may have been inspired by a Serbian folk song called &#8220;Sirvonja&#8221; (Geck, 2017:107). The initial four bars come to a halt by means of the fermata over a sustained C major chord, dominant of F major.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-05-23-at-10.51.57.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1489" width="424" height="423" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-05-23-at-10.51.57.png 848w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-05-23-at-10.51.57-300x299.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-05-23-at-10.51.57-150x150.png 150w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-05-23-at-10.51.57-768x766.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-05-23-at-10.51.57-80x80.png 80w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-05-23-at-10.51.57-640x638.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 424px) 100vw, 424px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The first theme of the first subject area played by the strings at bars 1-4</figcaption></figure>



<p>In the first 4 bars, there are several musical elements that convey the pastoral theme: folk-like melody, drone bass, greater consonance, (briefly) melody in thirds and the key of F.</p>



<p>By bar 5, the second theme belonging to the first subject area is introduced in the violas, accompanied by the violins that employ pre-existing motific material from the first theme. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><a href="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804.png"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1400" width="324" height="106" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804.png 648w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804-300x98.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804-640x209.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 324px) 100vw, 324px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The second theme of the first subject area played by the violas at bars 5-7</figcaption></figure>



<p>Within the initial 12 bars of the movement, Beethoven introduces the two principal themes that will serve as a significant guide throughout the piece, in addition to some hints of the motif&#8217;s development.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1401" width="487" height="471" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24.png 974w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24-300x290.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24-768x743.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24-640x619.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24-960x928.png 960w" sizes="(max-width: 487px) 100vw, 487px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The first violins play a motific variation and the strings play the second theme of the first subject area at bars 8-12</figcaption></figure>



<p>At bar 16 comes an unexpected repetition on the strings. The first violins play the same rhythm as the second bar of the first theme, which lasts for 13 bars. The sole variation lies in the dynamics. This provides an indication of Beethoven&#8217;s approach to the symphony, characterized by repetitions and harmonic stasis, which is another feature of the pastoral theme (Hatten, 2004:98).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="265" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-1024x265.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1402" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-1024x265.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-300x78.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-768x199.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-1536x398.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-640x166.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-960x249.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33.png 1692w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The repetition on the violins at bars 17-22</figcaption></figure>



<p>At bar 29, the exposition section starts with a subdued presentation of the first theme initiated by the oboe, with the cellos and horns providing support. This theme is subsequently passed through the orchestra going through the clarinets and bassoons and finally with the strings. Notably, a sense of repetition is evident, as the same rhythm of the third bar of the first theme is repeated in the woodwinds and violins. However, the dynamics make all the difference in not making it seem stale.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-1024x131.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1403" width="768" height="98" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-1024x131.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-300x38.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-768x98.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-640x82.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-960x123.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29.png 1342w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Violins playing the same rhythm as the third bar of the first theme at bars 43-48 </figcaption></figure>



<p>At bar 46, Beethoven employs his first instance of tone-painting in the symphony, with the flutes performing a birdsong. This technique, however, is used sparingly throughout the first movement, with only one other occurrence observed during the recapitulation.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.08.05.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1404" width="555" height="107" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.08.05.png 740w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.08.05-300x58.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.08.05-640x123.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 555px) 100vw, 555px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Birdsong on the flutes at bars 46-48</figcaption></figure>



<p>Suddenly, at bar 53, a change in texture occurs as the clarinets and bassoons, followed by the horns, introduce a triplet theme, played over the rhythm of the first bar of the first theme.   </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-1024x258.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1405" width="640" height="161" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-1024x258.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-300x76.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-768x194.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-640x161.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-960x242.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53.png 1364w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The horns play triples while the first violins play a variation of the first theme at bars 55-62</figcaption></figure>



<p>At bar 67, a traditional sonata change to the dominant key of C marks the beginning of the second subject area. The first theme is introduced by the first violin and subsequently transferred to all string instruments, followed by all woodwinds. This part brings a “rocking accompaniment” in the strings which is one of the pastoral’s general qualities, as stated before.</p>



<p>In bar 93, Beethoven introduces the second theme of the second subject area, which is characterized by a clear question-and-answer structure between the strings and woodwinds. The dynamics employed in this structure are noteworthy, as the question is played f while the answer is played p.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-1024x241.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1407" width="640" height="150" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-1024x241.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-300x71.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-768x181.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-640x151.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-960x226.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58.png 1375w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The oboe provides an answer to the first violins question at bars 93-99</figcaption></figure>



<p>Bar 111 marks the return of the triplets, providing a sense of a faster rhythm and subsequently leading to a prolonged repetition over a C pedal tone, another pastoral feature. The first two bars of the first theme of the first subject area are then repeated, which results in a substantial build-up of tension.</p>



<p>The development section starts at bar 151, marked by the modulation to Bb Major and the reappearance of the triplet rhythm, along with a slightly varied part of the second bar of the first theme of the first subject area. Notably, the development section is an unconventional deviation from the traditional expectation of dramatic and innovative contrast to the exposition. Instead, it features a static and repetitive section transposed into different keys. It actually reminded me of the Prelude in Wagner&#8217;s Das Rheingold, which builds in the intensity of dynamics and instrumentation while maintaining a constant motif.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-1024x631.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1409" width="512" height="316" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-1024x631.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-300x185.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-768x473.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-1536x946.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-640x394.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-960x591.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17.png 1734w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The strings repetition at bars 154-159</figcaption></figure>



<p>Bar 237 marks a key change to A Major where both the first and second themes from the first subject area make an appearance. The second theme is subsequently repeated, leading to a brief modulation to the minor key at bar 255, and finally to C Major at bar 263. While some might contend that the brief modulation to the minor key gives the development section the expected dramatism, it is, in fact, brief and it&#8217;s not repeated again.</p>



<p>Hepokoski and Darcy (2011:197) state that in major mode sonatas, it is common for the development sections to incorporate shifts towards more &#8220;dramatic&#8221; minor mode regions. However, it can be inferred that Beethoven intentionally avoided such expressive contrasts in the development of this movement, as it would have contradicted the serene and pastoral atmosphere he sought to create.</p>



<p>At bar 282, the music reaches a moment of pause, with only the violin playing a trill, suggesting the arrival of the recapitulation and the return of the first theme. However, the second theme from the first subject area reappears, leaving the listener uncertain about whether the development section has ended. There&#8217;s a sense of false start, through persistent repetition that builds in dynamics, until the first theme from the first subject is ultimately played by all the instruments of the orchestra featured in the movement at bar 312, thereby indicating the start of the recapitulation.</p>



<p>The recapitulation goes back, as expected in classical sonata form, to both subject areas but in the tonic key of F Major. Notably, Beethoven chooses to initiate this section with a ff dynamic, rather than following the softer dynamic of the exposition, thereby contradicting the expectations. In the final stages of the recapitulation, the dynamics and texture gradually decrease, leading to a reduced level of tension as the music moves towards the coda.</p>



<p>The coda starts in bar 418 with a modulation to Bb Major, the subdominant, which was common in Beethoven (Hepokoski and Darcy, 2011:285), before bringing it back to the tonic in measure 440. Beethoven utilizes dynamics that range from pp to ff, which creates a sense of uncertainty regarding the music&#8217;s conclusion, as he plays with the audience&#8217;s expectations. This leaves uncertainty about the end of the music until the orchestra ends playing in a soft and comforting F major chord. </p>



<p>Engel, in his brilliant insight on the matter, proposes the idea that &#8220;painting is expression.&#8221; (Will, 2002:136). This concept explores the harmonious alignment between our inner emotions and the external world, opening the door to an aesthetic validation of tone-painting. This inherent duality implies that Beethoven could not effectively convey pastoral sentiments without employing some form of tone-painting. Particularly in the first movement, he skillfully incorporates musical techniques and occasional imitations of natural sounds, enabling listeners to recognize and appreciate the pastoral feelings within the composition. Ultimately, the true essence of Beethoven&#8217;s Sixth Symphony lies beyond an imitation of nature. Instead, it embodies a deep longing for the inner peace and serenity that nature invokes.</p>



<p>Word Count: 2185 words.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1682538096360 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Allen, A. S. (2017) “Beethoven’s Natures,” in Ecological Thought in German Literature and<br>Culture, edited by Gabriele Dürbeck, Urte Stobbe, Hubert Zapf, and Evi Zemanek (Lexington<br>Books, 2017), pp. 371-386.</p>



<p>Geck, M. (2017) <em>Beethoven’s Symphonies: Nine Approaches to Art and Ideas</em>. University of Chicago Press.</p>



<p>Kirby (1970) “BEETHOVEN’S PASTORAL SYMPHONY AS A SINFONIA CARACTERISTICA,” <em>The Musical Quarterly</em>, LVI(4), pp. 605–623. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1093/mq/lvi.4.605.</p>



<p><em>Leonard Bernstein Discussing Beethoven’s 6th and 7th Symphony</em> (2011) [Online Video] At: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OuYY1gV8jhU (Accessed: April 24, 2023).</p>



<p>Lockwood, L. (2015) <em>Beethoven’s Symphonies: An Artistic Vision</em> [Ebook]. W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</p>



<p>Hatten, R.S. (2004) <em>Musical Meaning in Beethoven: Markedness, Correlation, and Interpretation</em>. Indiana University Press.</p>



<p>Hepokoski, J. and Darcy, W. (2011) <em>Elements of Sonata Theory: Norms, Types, and Deformations in the Late-Eighteenth-Century Sonata</em>. Oxford University Press.</p>



<p>Rogers, J.R. (1919) “THE THREE BEETHOVENS,” <em>The Musical Quarterly</em>, V(4), pp. 505–512. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1093/mq/v.4.505 (Accessed: April 26, 2023).</p>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (1998a) <em>Instrumentation &#8211; The Classical period</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/art/instrumentation-music/The-Classical-period (Accessed: April 28, 2023).</p>



<p>Will, R.J. (1994) <em>Programmatic symphonies of the Classical Period</em>. [Doctorate Thesis] Cornell University. At: https://www.proquest.com/docview/304104826/fulltextPDF/AF1AED13E40146D7PQ/ (Accessed: April 26, 2023)</p>



<p>Will, R. J. (2002) <em>The Characteristic Symphony in the Age of Haydn and Beethoven</em>. Cambridge University Press.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 5</title>
		<link>./../../../../../assignment-5/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 13:40:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1390</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It has been widely accepted since Lenz&#8217;s 1852 Beethoven biography that his musical journey can be distinguished into&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It has been widely accepted since Lenz&#8217;s 1852 Beethoven biography that his musical journey can be distinguished into three distinct phases. In the first phase (1782-1802), he imitated Mozart and Haydn to fit the aesthetic of the time. The second phase (1803-1812) marked a period of stylistic evolution and the creation of his third to eighth symphonies. The third and final phase began around 1813 and involved experimentation with innovative sonorities. (Rogers, 1919).</p>



<p>The Pastoral Symphony, composed between 1807 and 1808, falls within the middle of Beethoven&#8217;s second phase, which was heavily influenced by the events explained in more detail <a href="./../../../../../research-point-5-0/index.html" data-type="post" data-id="1317">here</a>, such as artistic innovations, political revolutions, wars, but also personal struggles such as the onset of his deafness. </p>



<p>Premiered in Vienna, Austria, on December 22nd, 1808, during a concert at which several of his works were premiered, including his 5th Symphony, the Pastoral Symphony is written for a typical orchestra of that period: piccolo, two flutes, two oboes, two clarinets, two bassoons, two horns, two trumpets, two trombones, timpani and strings (The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1998a). </p>



<p>Since they both premiered at the same concert and were composed at around the same time, the contrast between Symphony No. 5 and Symphony No. 6 is a remarkable aspect worth noting. No. 5 is vigorous and varied, while No. 6 is calm and pastoral, with programmatic titles illustrating rural life as a refuge. Was this contrast deliberate on Beethoven&#8217;s part? Why did he choose to compose a programmatic symphony? And why a pastoral theme?</p>



<p>In order to answer the last question, one must consider the intersection of his personal history and the historical context in which he was creating. On the personal side, according to Allen (2017), Beethoven had a profound love for nature and often sought refuge from the bustle of urban life by retreating to the countryside. But in a historical context, Will (1994:166) analyses, the pastoral theme was the most common subject in programmatic symphonies during the Classical Period, and Beethoven might have found inspiration in earlier works such as Justin Heinrich Knecht&#8217;s 1784 symphony &#8220;Le portrait musical de la nature,&#8221; which shares a similar programmatic intent with Beethoven&#8217;s 6th Symphony. However, in opposition to other programmatic symphonies, Beethoven intended this work to be “more the Expression of Feeling than Tone-Panting”.</p>



<p>The question of tone-painting in Beethoven&#8217;s Pastoral Symphony has sparked much debate and was subject to extensive criticism in two reviews in 1810, published in AMZ 12 and Zeitung für die elegante Welt 10. These reviews provide valuable insights into the contemporary perception of tone-painting. While initially denouncing it as &#8220;the utmost in tastelessness,&#8221; the AMZ review later justifies Beethoven&#8217;s use of tone-painting to represent emotions, rather than physical objects. The continues stating that theorists of expression saw superficiality as one of the greatest faults of tone-painting (Will, 1994:158-160).</p>



<p>The review published in Zeitung provides further insight into the perception of the Pastoral Symphony&#8217;s tone-painting. The reviewer acknowledges that the symphony portrays emotions associated with the pastoral but goes on to argue that it is more than a generic representation of such emotions. Rather, the scenes depicted are specific episodes from the composer&#8217;s own experiences in the countryside, imbued with his personal emotions. Consequently, the reviewer deems tone-painting to be of secondary importance, with the focus instead on the power of the composer&#8217;s personality (Will, 1994:161).</p>



<p>In my opinion, the reviews made a clear effort to dismiss tone-painting and focus on how Beethoven conveyed emotions (personal or generic) revealing that both this symphony and the cultural environment of its time were undergoing a discernible transition from the classicist period to the romantic era, exhibiting traits and preferences that spanned both styles. This is a reminder that such transitions are not time-bound but rather an organic and gradual process marked by overlaps. </p>



<p>Ultimately, this raises questions that remained unresolved in my research. Specifically, as Beethoven transitioned from the patronage system to a broader audience-based system, did he prioritize the opinions of critics with regard to tone-painting? Additionally, what was his stance regarding the proposition that tone-painting was a manifestation of tastelessness? Could this potentially explain why this is his only symphony?</p>



<h5 id="6th-symphony-movements" class="wp-block-heading">6th Symphony Movements</h5>



<p>Pastoral Symphony&#8217;s first movement, &#8220;Awakening of Cheerful Feelings upon Arrival in the Country,&#8221; serves as a joyful prelude. It features simple melodies and light rhythm, with homophonic orchestration and primarily major keys. Beethoven minimizes unexpected shifts by repeating motifs and only briefly uses a minor key.</p>



<p>The second movement, titled &#8220;Scene by the Brook,&#8221; is a serene and peaceful composition that is free of the typical Germanic tension often associated with Beethoven&#8217;s music. The movement begins with a lilting rhythmic motion that is said to sound like the flowing of a brook.</p>



<p>The third movement, titled &#8220;Merry Gathering of the Country Folk,&#8221; is a Scherzo in ABA form, with the main theme having a rustic feel. The trio section has a particularly country dance feel, with a constant emphasis on the downbeat of each bar. The movement ends with a curtailed return to the main theme, followed by a faster presto section and a transition into the next movement.</p>



<p>The fourth movement, entitled &#8220;Thunderstorm,&#8221; is a dramatic and tension-filled episode that deviates from the overall tranquil character of the symphony. The storm is portrayed through the depiction of thunder and thunderclaps, and the movement ultimately subsides, coinciding with the gradual fading of the storm.</p>



<p>Continuing without interruption, the fifth and final movement of the symphony is entitled &#8220;Shepherd&#8217;s Song, happy and thankful feelings after the storm.&#8221; It is a delightful and evocative music that utilizes a gentle and rhythmic theme that is repeated throughout the rondo form of the movement. The movement ends with a quiet and prayerful coda as if wishing farewell to the countryside before returning to the city.</p>



<h5 id="analysis-of-the-1st-movement" class="wp-block-heading">Analysis of the 1st Movement</h5>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32.png"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="429" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-1024x429.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1419" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-1024x429.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-300x126.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-768x322.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-1536x644.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-640x268.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32-960x402.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-28-at-12.41.32.png 1994w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Figure 1: Structural analysis of the first movement. Click to amplify.</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<p>The first movement of the composition is in the sonata form, as exemplified in Figure 1. The introduction starts with a theme, that can be considered the first theme of the first subject area. The initial four bars come to a halt by means of the fermata over a sustained C major chord, dominant of F major.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-20.44.52-1024x243.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1398" width="512" height="122" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-20.44.52-1024x243.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-20.44.52-300x71.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-20.44.52-768x182.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-20.44.52-1536x365.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-20.44.52-640x152.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-20.44.52-960x228.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-20.44.52.png 1592w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The first theme of the first subject area played by the first violins at bars 1-3</figcaption></figure>



<p>By bar 5, the second theme belonging to the first subject area is introduced in the violas, accompanied by the violins that employ pre-existing motific material from the first theme. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><a href="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804.png"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1400" width="486" height="159" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804.png 648w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804-300x98.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.19.49-e1682682783804-640x209.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 486px) 100vw, 486px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The second theme of the first subject area played by the violas at bars 5-7</figcaption></figure>



<p>Within the initial 12 bars of the movement, Beethoven introduces the two principal themes that will serve as a significant guide throughout the piece, in addition to some hints of the motif&#8217;s development.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1401" width="487" height="471" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24.png 974w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24-300x290.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24-768x743.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24-640x619.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-26-at-21.31.24-960x928.png 960w" sizes="(max-width: 487px) 100vw, 487px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The first violins play a motific variation and the strings play the second theme of the first subject area at bars 8-12</figcaption></figure>



<p>At bar 16 comes an unexpected repetition on the strings. The first violins play the same rhythm as the second bar of the first theme, which lasts for 13 bars. The sole variation lies in the dynamics. This provides an indication of Beethoven&#8217;s approach to the symphony, characterized by repetitions, reutilization of motific material and a marked emphasis on dynamics.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="265" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-1024x265.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1402" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-1024x265.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-300x78.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-768x199.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-1536x398.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-640x166.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33-960x249.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-09.47.33.png 1692w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The repetition on the violins at bars 17-22</figcaption></figure>



<p>At bar 29, the exposition section starts with a subdued presentation of the first theme initiated by the oboe, with the cellos and horns providing support. This theme is subsequently passed through the orchestra going through the clarinets and bassoons and finally with the strings. Notably, a sense of repetition is evident, as the same rhythm of the third bar of the first theme is repeated in the woodwinds and violins. However, the dynamics make all the difference in not making it seem stale.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-1024x131.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1403" width="768" height="98" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-1024x131.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-300x38.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-768x98.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-640x82.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29-960x123.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.06.29.png 1342w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Violins playing the same rhythm as the third bar of the first theme at bars 43-48 </figcaption></figure>



<p>At bar 46, Beethoven employs his first instance of tone-painting in the symphony, with the flutes performing a birdsong. This technique, however, is used sparingly throughout the first movement, with only one other occurrence observed during the recapitulation. This brings back the question of Beethoven&#8217;s intention with respect to tone painting. Was he conflicted between differing views on the technique, or was he experimenting with it in a playful or provocative manner, perhaps testing the reactions of audiences and critics?</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.08.05.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1404" width="555" height="107" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.08.05.png 740w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.08.05-300x58.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.08.05-640x123.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 555px) 100vw, 555px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Birdsong on the flutes at bars 46-48</figcaption></figure>



<p>Suddenly, at bar 53, a change in texture occurs as the clarinets and bassoons, followed by the horns, introduce a triplet theme, played over the rhythm of the first bar of the first theme. Once again, Beethoven employs repetition to great effect, inducing heightened tension as the triplet motif interrupts the expected continuation of the primary theme.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-1024x258.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1405" width="640" height="161" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-1024x258.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-300x76.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-768x194.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-640x161.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53-960x242.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-10.44.53.png 1364w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The horns play triples while the first violins play a variation of the first theme at bars 55-62</figcaption></figure>



<p>At bar 67, a traditional sonata change to the dominant key of C marks the beginning of the second subject area. The first theme is introduced by the first violin and subsequently transferred to all string instruments, followed by all woodwinds. Beethoven employs the same technique of repeating the theme, marked by a dynamic and instrumental buildup.</p>



<p>At bar 93, Beethoven introduces the second theme of the second subject area, which is characterized by a clear question-and-answer structure between the strings and woodwinds. The dynamics employed in this structure are noteworthy, as the question is played f while the answer is played p.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-1024x241.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1407" width="640" height="150" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-1024x241.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-300x71.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-768x181.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-640x151.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58-960x226.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-11.32.58.png 1375w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The oboe provides an answer to the first violins question at bars 93-99</figcaption></figure>



<p>Bar 111 marks the return of the triplets, providing a sense of a faster rhythm and subsequently leading to a prolonged repetition over a C pedal tone. The first two bars of the first theme of the first subject area are then repeated, which results in a substantial buildup of tension.</p>



<p>Based on my analysis, the development section starts at bar 151, marked by the modulation to Bb Major and the reappearance of the triplet rhythm, along with a slightly varied part of the second bar of the first theme of the first subject area. Notably, the development section is an unconventional deviation from the traditional expectation of dramatic and innovative contrast to the exposition. Instead, it features a static and repetitive section transposed into different keys. It actually reminded me of the Prelude in Wagner&#8217;s Das Rheingold, which builds in the intensity of dynamics and instrumentation while maintaining a constant motif.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-1024x631.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1409" width="512" height="316" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-1024x631.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-300x185.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-768x473.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-1536x946.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-640x394.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17-960x591.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/04/Screenshot-2023-04-27-at-13.06.17.png 1734w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The strings repetition at bars 154-159</figcaption></figure>



<p>Bar 237 marks a key change to A Major where both the first and second themes from the first subject area make an appearance. The second theme is subsequently repeated, leading to a brief modulation to the minor key at bar 255, and finally to C Major at bar 263. While some might contend that the brief modulation to the minor key gives the development section the expected dramatism, it is, in fact, brief and it&#8217;s not repeated again.</p>



<p>At bar 282, the music reaches a moment of pause, with only the violin playing a trill, suggesting the arrival of the recapitulation and the return of the first theme. However, the second theme from the first subject area reappears, leaving the listener uncertain about whether the development section has ended. There&#8217;s a sense of false start, through persistent repetition that builds in dynamics, until the first theme from the first subject is ultimately played by all the instruments of the orchestra featured in the movement at bar 312, thereby indicating the start of the recapitulation.</p>



<p>The recapitulation goes back, as expected by classical sonata form, to both subject areas but in the tonic key of F Major. Notably, Beethoven chooses to initiate this section with a ff dynamic, rather than following the softer dynamic of the exposition, thereby contradicting the expectations. In the final stages of the recapitulation, the dynamics and texture gradually decrease, leading to a reduced level of tension as the music moves towards the coda.</p>



<p>The coda starts in bar 418 with a modulation to Bb Major, which I found unexpected. However, this modulation is brief, as it modulates back to F Major in measure 440. Beethoven utilizes dynamics that range from pp to ff, which creates a sense of uncertainty regarding the music&#8217;s conclusion, as he plays with the audience&#8217;s expectations. This leaves uncertainty about the end of the music until the orchestra ends playing.</p>



<p>After my research and analysis, my opinion is that Beethoven found himself composing this Symphony in times of change, where he was balancing his classical influences with a desire to establish himself as a disruptive composer and build the pavement for the romantic era. Beethoven&#8217;s use of traditional sonata form, such as the question/answer construction and the modulations in the development section, reflect his attachment to the classical principles of order and balance, while his exploration of static harmony for long periods and the repetition of a motif while exploring dynamics and timbres demonstrates his forward-thinking approach.</p>



<p>Additionally, Beethoven was also grappling with the concept of tone-painting and trying to appeal to a broader audience, which may have influenced his decision to use the natural world as a thematic focus in this symphony. Furthermore, the composer&#8217;s personal struggles with increasing deafness likely added a layer of complexity to his creative process and may have impacted his artistic choices in this work. </p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1682538096360 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Allen, A. S. (2017) “Beethoven’s Natures,” in Ecological Thought in German Literature and<br>Culture, edited by Gabriele Dürbeck, Urte Stobbe, Hubert Zapf, and Evi Zemanek (Lexington<br>Books, 2017), pp. 371-386.</p>



<p><em>Leonard Bernstein Discussing Beethoven’s 6th and 7th Symphony</em> (2011) [Online Video] At: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OuYY1gV8jhU (Accessed: April 24, 2023).</p>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (1998a) <em>Instrumentation &#8211; The Classical period</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/art/instrumentation-music/The-Classical-period (Accessed: April 28, 2023).</p>



<p>Rogers, J.R. (1919) “THE THREE BEETHOVENS,” <em>The Musical Quarterly</em>, V(4), pp. 505–512. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1093/mq/v.4.505 (Accessed: April 26, 2023).</p>



<p>Will, R.J. (1994) <em>Programmatic symphonies of the Classical Period</em>. [Doctorate Thesis] Cornell University. At: https://www.proquest.com/docview/304104826/fulltextPDF/AF1AED13E40146D7PQ/ (Accessed: April 26, 2023)</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
