<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignment &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 21:08:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Assignment 5</title>
		<link>./../../../../../assignment-5-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 22:53:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1974</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This assignment compares the Missa Brevis by two composers, Palestrina and Zoltán Kodály. Additionally, it examines Max Richter&#8217;s&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This assignment compares the Missa Brevis by two composers, Palestrina and Zoltán Kodály. Additionally, it examines Max Richter&#8217;s reinterpretation of Vivaldi&#8217;s Four Seasons in his work, Vivaldi Recomposed.</p>



<h5 id="part-1" class="wp-block-heading">Part 1</h5>



<p>To compare the Missa Brevis by Palestrina and Zoltán Kodály, I listened to The Tallis Scholars&#8217; recording of Palestrina&#8217;s Mass, directed by Peter Phillips, and to the Warsaw Philharmonic Choir&#8217;s performance of Kodály&#8217;s Mass directed by Bartosz Michałowski.</p>



<p>Palestrina&#8217;s Missa Brevis exemplifies the Renaissance style. Composed for four voices sometime in the mid-16th century, it adheres to the principles of counterpoint, with melodic lines weaving together seamlessly. The focus is on vocal clarity and a sense of serenity. Palestrina&#8217;s textures are predominantly smooth, with a balance between polyphony and homophony, usually manifesting at the final cadence. The overall effect is one of meditative beauty, drawing the listener into a realm of introspection. Palestrina&#8217;s works were typically performed with no accompaniment in large, resonant spaces, allowing the polyphonic textures to blend and create a sense of reverence and spaciousness.</p>



<p>Kodály&#8217;s Missa Brevis for solo voices, chorus, and organ, was composed during World War II (1942-44), reflecting a contrasting world. It is imbued with significance, having premiered in the cloakroom of Budapest&#8217;s Opera House. Subtitled “in tempore belli” (“in times of war”), it was written, at least in part, during the Budapest siege. This sense of despair is infused in the composition through the use of dissonances and the interaction between the voices. Kodály&#8217;s Missa Brevis is more outward-looking, with a sense of energy and drama that contrasts with Palestrina&#8217;s introspective nature. It also distances itself from Palestrina&#8217;s Mass by incorporating more rhythmic vitality and a greater emphasis on the expressive potential of the human voice.</p>



<p>In terms of tonality, it is centred on D and its structure forms an arch, a nineteenth-century structural principle (Pickar, 1985), with extensive use of thematic transformation: the Adagio ‘Qui tollis’ from the Gloria returns at the start of the Agnus Dei. A variation of the entire Kyrie is employed for the ‘Dona nobis pacem’. The cadences feel more unexpected than those found in Palestrina&#8217;s compositions.</p>



<p>Despite their stylistic differences, both composers share a common core. They adhere to the traditional structure of the Mass Ordinary, comprising sections like Kyrie, Gloria, Credo, Sanctus, Benedictus, and Agnus Dei, although Kodály adds an introductory section (Introitus) and a final section (Ite, Missa Est). They also employ the traditional Latin text of the Mass. Kodály&#8217;s Missa Brevis features plainchant-style melodies similar to Palestrina but mixed with modal keys reminiscent of the Hungarian folk tradition.</p>



<p>Being passionate about WWII history, Kodály&#8217;s Mass naturally feels more interesting to me. Its historical importance attracted me right away, but so did the sound of it. It feels more explorative than Palestrina&#8217;s, even while following an established structure. The beginning of Gloria is a great example of unexpected fanfare-like figures. The interaction between the voices, almost like a dialogue, appeals to me more. The drama, the use of dissonance, and the unexpected cadences also draw me toward Kodály&#8217;s Mass.</p>



<p>Ultimately, I feel that Kodaly&#8217;s Mass is rooted in tonality and isn&#8217;t as challenging to the ear as other contemporary musical pieces, such as Bartók&#8217;s. This made me appreciate the music more. Perhaps it was Kodaly&#8217;s background as a music educator that led him to make a more accessible Mass, or maybe he aimed to create a Mass that would reach a broader audience and bring peace and hope in a post-war setting.&#8221;</p>



<p>Word: 548</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1710969819900 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Pickar, C. (1985) &#8216;An analytical process applied to Kodály’s ‘Missa Brevis’ on JSTOR,&#8217; <em>The Choral Journal</em>, 26(3), pp. 7–12. https://www.jstor.org/stable/23546905.</p>



<p>Stevens, H. (1968) &#8216;THE CHORAL MUSIC OF ZOLTÁN KODÁLY,&#8217; <em>The Musical Quarterly</em>, LIV(2), pp. 147–168. https://doi.org/10.1093/mq/liv.2.147.</p>



<h5 id="part-2" class="wp-block-heading">Part 2</h5>



<p>Vivaldi Recomposed is a piece composed by Max Richter in 2011, where he proposed to pick up the essence of Vivaldi’s Four Seasons and imbue it with a contemporary sound (Vivaldi’s The Four Seasons recomposed by Max Richter [Streaming], 2014). But rather than merely rearranging Vivaldi’s composition to mirror the modern aesthetic, Richter deconstructs the original piece. He isolates its fundamental elements—themes, harmonies, and rhythms—and reassembles them, allowing the work to resonate deeply with today’s audiences. This analysis examines the Winter Concerto to understand how Richter creates a fresh sound while using earlier material.</p>



<p>Before looking into the piece, it’s crucial to understand that Richter, like any composer, did not create in isolation. His work is a product of the 21st-century context. This implies that both he and his audience are familiar with Vivaldi’s Four Seasons since it is one of the most popular classical pieces in the world. Moreover, composers who emerged after Vivaldi introduced new techniques and sounds, influencing Richter’s compositions.</p>



<p>This influence is evident in the first segment of Winter 1. The first 22 bars mirror exactly Vivaldi’s Winter First Movement. However, Richter introduces a new technique. He instructs all the strings to use Ponticello, see Fig. 1, generating a shivering and harsh sound. While Ponticello was used occasionally in the Baroque period, it was only during the Romantic Period that Ponticello evolved into a significant expressive tool, rather than merely a unique sound effect (Greenfield, 2017). The effect is particularly pronounced in the solo violin, which produces a sound that is significantly colder and more glass-like than Vivaldi’s.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="598" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.11.14-1-1024x598.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1979" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.11.14-1-1024x598.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.11.14-1-300x175.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.11.14-1-768x448.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.11.14-1-1536x897.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.11.14-1-640x374.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.11.14-1-960x561.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.11.14-1.png 1627w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Fig 1 (Max Richter&#8217; Vivaldi Recomposed: Winter 1. Bars 1-4)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Richter’s usage of dynamics also diverges from Vivaldi’s. Where Vivaldi maintains a constant mezzo-forte until the crescendo for a forte before the main them, Richter engages in a dynamic fluctuation, repeatedly crescendo from pianissimo to mezzo-forte or forte, see Fig. 2, before each of solo violin line. This manipulation of dynamics enhances the overall texture and emotional depth of the piece, underpinning Richter’s vision.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="352" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.24.01-1024x352.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1981" style="width:640px;height:auto" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.24.01-1024x352.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.24.01-300x103.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.24.01-768x264.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.24.01-1536x528.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.24.01-2048x704.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.24.01-640x220.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.24.01-960x330.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.24.01.png 2142w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Fig 2 (Max Richter&#8217; Vivaldi Recomposed: Winter 1. Bars 9-13)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Perhaps the most thrilling aspect of Richter&#8217;s Winter 1 is his approach to reconfiguring Vivaldi’s most recognisable passage of the movement. Richter decided to extract a beat from the main theme, transitioning from a 4/4 to a 7/16 time signature, see Fig. 3. This imparts an unexpected sound to a familiar part of the music. It renders the music rapid, restless, and somewhat sloppy, effectively conveying the sensation of someone running on ice and occasionally slipping.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="897" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.25.23-1024x897.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1982" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.25.23-1024x897.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.25.23-300x263.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.25.23-768x673.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.25.23-1536x1346.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.25.23-640x561.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.25.23-960x841.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.25.23.png 1616w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Fig 3 (Max Richter&#8217; Vivaldi Recomposed: Winter 1. Bars 21-24)</figcaption></figure>



<p>The rest of the first movement repeats this progression and rhythm until the end. The constant repetition of Vivaldi&#8217;s selected material is a hallmark of Richter&#8217;s recomposition, which one can understand comes from his minimalistic roots. Or perhaps it is so the work is more appealing to modern ears. In this case, in particular, he repeats the chord progression that moves in 4ths, see Fig 4. (which Vivaldi already used). This is a progression that has been extensively used in modern pop music, and the repetition likely satisfies the sensibilities of contemporary audiences.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="398" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.29.49-1024x398.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1983" style="width:640px;height:auto" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.29.49-1024x398.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.29.49-300x117.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.29.49-768x299.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.29.49-1536x597.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.29.49-640x249.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.29.49-960x373.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.29.49.png 1954w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Fig 4 (Max Richter&#8217; Vivaldi Recomposed: Winter 1. Bars 39-46)</figcaption></figure>



<p>The second movement, &#8220;Winter 2,&#8221; is impressive in its simplicity and coldness. Here, Richter utilizes two of Vivaldi&#8217;s original materials &#8211; the melody, which is almost the same as the original except for some additional tremolos and brief skipping of notes, and the drone of the viola, which he multiplies across all the strings. This seems a Richter stylistic trace, reminiscent of his piece &#8220;A Sudden Manhattan of the Mind,&#8221; where a drone harmony (played by synths in this case) creates a soundscape for the violin to display its melody.</p>



<p>The harmonic inaction evokes a sensation of stillness, coldness, and sadness, which contrasts with Vivaldi&#8217;s programmatic feeling of pleasure in getting warm inside through a crackling fire. This is perhaps the most impressive feature of Richter&#8217;s recomposition &#8211; using almost identical material (in this case, the melody and drone) to convey a completely different, and in fact, opposing emotional experience.</p>



<p>Allowing for an almost static harmony gives solo performers significant creative expression, particularly in live performances, where the tempo can be stretched or reduced without impacting the accompaniment. This aspect hints at Richter’s dedication to continue Vivaldi’s legacy of showcasing musical virtuosity.</p>



<p>In Winter 3 there’s Richter&#8217;s signature style of stability, defined by Ross (2023), when he writes “Richter’s pieces usually wind up not far from where they began”. This movement evokes a sense of a vast, seemingly unchanging landscape, subtly layered with the introduction of individual elements, one at a time, without any dramatic harmonic or rhythmic shifts. This aligns perfectly with Szabo&#8217;s definition of minimalism: &#8220;uniform, predictable, and understated music; lacking in abrupt changes of instrumentation or volume, devoid of harmonic or rhythmic surprises&#8221; (Ross, 2023). Here, Richter unquestionably embraces a minimalist approach to Vivaldi’s material.</p>



<p>He steers away from Vivaldi&#8217;s programmatic movement, creating an enigmatic soundscape that feels perpetually unsettled. While a subtle programmatic hint lingers through the repeated descending scales in the violas, in red in Fig. 5, suggesting a sensation of constant falling, the solo violin&#8217;s unending ostinatos (green) and contrabass drone (blue) establish an ethereal atmosphere that defies a strictly programmatic interpretation.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="411" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.40.57-1024x411.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1984" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.40.57-1024x411.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.40.57-300x120.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.40.57-768x308.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.40.57-1536x617.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.40.57-2048x822.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.40.57-640x257.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.40.57-960x385.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-29-at-22.40.57.png 3024w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Fig 4 (Max Richter&#8217; Vivaldi Recomposed: Winter 3. Bars 49-60)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Another noteworthy distinction is Richter&#8217;s omission of the unexpected pauses and changes of mood employed by Vivaldi in his third movement. Here, the rhythm persists uniformly throughout, further emphasising the minimalist avoidance of rhythmic surprises.</p>



<p>The ending of the movement fades out rather than resolving with a definitive cadence, a technique prevalent in many popular songs, particularly those from the latter half of the 20th century (Weir, 2014). This is particularly intriguing for a piece&#8217;s final resolution. One traditionally anticipates a conclusive ending, mirroring Vivaldi&#8217;s approach. Here, however, Richter offers a gentle, introspective, and open-ended conclusion.</p>



<p>Upon revisiting Vivaldi Recomposed, it becomes evident that Richter&#8217;s process involved more than simply layering new material upon Vivaldi&#8217;s foundation. Notably, Richter introduces no entirely new melodies. Instead, he employs a technique of repetition, similar to looping and sampling – a decidedly modern soundscape. Through this approach, Richter creates a piece that bridges the centuries, fostering a dialogue between an old work and the present day. This strategy allows Richter to both preserve and redefine Vivaldi&#8217;s composition, ensuring its continued relevance and connection with contemporary audiences.</p>



<p>Word: 1024</p>



<h2 id="references-2" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1711750096547 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Ross, A. (2023) &#8216;The doleful minimalism of Max Richter,&#8217; <em>The New Yorker</em>, 10 April. https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2023/04/17/max-richter-music-review.</p>



<p>How I wrote… Vivaldi’s Four Seasons Recomposed &#8211; Max Richter (2014). https://www.classicfm.com/composers/richter/news/vivaldi-recomposed-interview/.</p>



<p><em>Vivaldi’s The Four Seasons recomposed by Max Richter</em> [Streaming] (2014). Isis Productions for Deutsche Grammophon. https://edu-medici-tv.rpa.sccl.org/en/documentaries/vivaldi-the-four-seasons-recomposed-by-max-richter-the-berlin-concert-george-scott.</p>



<p>Weir, W. (2014) &#8216;The sad, gradual decline of the Fade-Out in popular music,&#8217; <em>Slate Magazine</em>, 15 September. https://slate.com/culture/2014/09/the-fade-out-in-pop-music-why-dont-modern-pop-songs-end-by-slowly-reducing-in-volume.html.</p>



<p>Greenfield, L. (2017) <em>Extended string techniques and special effects in Arnold Schoenberg’s string Quartet No. 1 and its significance in chamber music literature</em>. Dissertation Prepared for the Degree of DOCTOR OF MUSICAL ARTS. University of North Texas. https://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc1011750/m2/1/high_res_d/GREENFIELD-DISSERTATION-2017.pdf.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="reflective-account" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1711832443517 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Reflective Account</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The Renaissance and Baroque eras are not my favorite musical periods. While I recognise their importance to music history, the complexity of the contrapuntal music and the strict adherence to forms are two aspects that put me off. However, I found it extremely useful to gain knowledge of forms, instruments, techniques and composers of these eras.</p>



<p>One particular sound that doesn’t appeal to me in these periods is sacred music, especially because of its stillness, slow rhythms, and the echoing polyphony of the voices. I&#8217;ve tried to listen to several pieces, and this unit was helpful in that regard as well, but I still struggle to find pleasure in listening to them. That was until I listened to Kodály’s Missa Brevis. That was a real pleasure to listen to. Although it had the same slowness of a Renaissance style, it had a lot of dissonance that I felt adds a lot more drama and spice.</p>



<p>Reflecting and researching dissonance was interesting to the point that I’ve been much more drawn to dissonant sounds since I started my degree than ever before. I now appreciate dissonance as a spice in food. Too much can distract from the main flavours (meaning harmony and melody), but too little can make it bland and predictable. In the case of Kodály’s Missa Brevis, I felt that the dissonances were just right in making serene music sound more dramatic.</p>



<p>I feel that this unit’s assignment was when I explored more of one of the things I love most about the arts, and music in particular. I love to explore how modern artists are influenced by past artists, especially in popular music. I find a special pleasure in identifying little influences in modern compositions that can relate directly to previous artists and understanding how contemporary artists add to that. But to do this, it&#8217;s better to have a deep understanding of music history as a whole, and that’s how I found this unit to be so useful.</p>



<p>Reflecting and understanding musical patronage was another topic I found very interesting in this unit. I find it especially important right now, in a moment when there’s a big discussion about payment models for artists, since streaming services pay so little and music publishers seem to favor those artists who are profitable in terms of live music. This leaves emerging artists out of the way to have financial support to pursue their music.</p>



<p>Although I like the historical and theoretical part of music, I miss composition a lot. I believe that this unit, and this course in general, would benefit from having a strong mix of theory and practical composition throughout the units.</p>



<p>I end this unit still mixing up a little between the eras. It’s much easier and intuitive for me to discern between Classical and Romantic than it is to discern Classical from Baroque and Renaissance. I believe I should work more on this in future units during my degree.</p>



<p>Overall, this unit helped a lot to contextualise music historically and idiomatically, although I believe I need further studying in order to gain a deep understanding of each musical era.</p>



<p>Word: 522</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
