<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 22:43:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Beethoven &#8211; Symphony No. 1 in C major, Op. 21</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-beethoven-symphony-no-1-in-c-major-op-21/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 22:11:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1925</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As the lovely and gradual introduction in the first movement gets underway, the anticipation for a strong cadence&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As the lovely and gradual introduction in the first movement gets underway, the anticipation for a strong cadence builds and builds, but it doesn&#8217;t arrive. The music is constantly leaving you on a hook and, just when you think it can&#8217;t get any more energetic, the strings drop into tune and the winds have a moment of stillness. At last, the cadence arrives but the pace never lets up throughout the movement, toying with your expectations throughout. It&#8217;s a back-and-forth of suspense and surprise, the whole way up to a glorious conclusion that couldn&#8217;t leave you in any doubt of the music&#8217;s full force.</p>



<p>The second movement has the feel of classical formality, with a subject and then periods of rest. At first, the emotional restraint in this movement might make it less engaging, but the dramatic volume level gives the music layers of interest that will keep you listening.</p>



<p>Beethoven scores more points with dynamic change and strong contrast in the third movement. These are hallmarks of his style, and you can see why people, like me for example, just really enjoy listening to his music.</p>



<p>The symphony&#8217;s final movement starts dramatically and commands attention immediately. Throughout this movement, it feels like Beethoven is deliberately playing with the listener&#8217;s expectations again, creating moments where the orchestra resembles a choir and leading the listener to anticipate a conclusion, only to defy those expectations. The movement maintains a sense of suspense and anticipation, keeping the listener engaged until the very end.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Clementi &#8211; Sonata Op. 26 No. 2</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-clementi-sonata-op-26-no-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 22:02:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1918</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This was the first Clementi work I listened to, and I found it to have great emotive depth.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This was the first Clementi work I listened to, and I found it to have great emotive depth. It featured intricate harmonies and masterful variation writing, offering a compelling listening experience. The slow movement is particularly poignant, with its evocative expression, providing a glimpse into Clementi&#8217;s musical prowess and his ability to convey powerful emotions.</p>



<p>One of the striking aspects of this piece is the technical usage of the pianoforte. The work progressively presents challenges for the performer, showcasing Clementi&#8217;s understanding of piano technique while exploring imaginative variations. This balance between technical demands and musical depth makes this work intriguing for listeners, allowing them to appreciate the potential of the keyboard.</p>



<p>The unexpected plot twists in the opening movement demonstrate the fusion of technical complexity with expressive musicality. The torrents of notes and sudden, dramatic contrasts make it an impressive movement both in technicality and musicality.</p>



<p>In the final movement, I notice a connection between Clementi&#8217;s writing and that of Beethoven, particularly in the strong dynamic contrasts. However, the rapid arpeggios that set the mood remind me more of a Romantic movement, suggesting that Clementi might have been an influential composer for future generations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Clementi &#8211; Piano Duet in C Major, Op. 6 No. 1</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-clementi-piano-duet-in-c-major-op-6-no-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 23:24:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1921</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This was a truly enjoyable piece to listen to, similar to a vibrant chat between two close friends.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This was a truly enjoyable piece to listen to, similar to a vibrant chat between two close friends. It takes you on a journey through varying moods.</p>



<p>The piece begins with a lively movement, filled with cascading scales and playful tunes. It&#8217;s intriguing how it feels familiar yet different, not a composition from a known composer. The two piano parts intertwine beautifully, creating a delightful blend of friendly rivalry and harmony. The joy in their back-and-forth interactions is palpable, with one piano seemingly predicting the other&#8217;s phrases, building anticipation.</p>



<p>The second movement provides an expectable contrast. The melody becomes more introspective, featuring long, flowing lines that feel like a shared moment of reflection. The tenderness with which the two pianos merge into a single voice creates a sense of closeness and connection.</p>



<p>The final movement reintroduces the energy and excitement. The music surges forward with swift scales and virtuosic passages, a cascade of notes that carries the listener along. There&#8217;s a playful defiance in this movement, a celebration of the sheer joy of creating music.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Chopin &#8211; Nocturne Eb major Op. 9 no. 2 </title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-chopin-nocturne-eb-major-op-9-no-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 22:39:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1873</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As one of Chopin&#8217;s most famous piano works, I&#8217;ve heard this lovely Nocturne many times before but listened&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As one of Chopin&#8217;s most famous piano works, I&#8217;ve heard this lovely Nocturne many times before but listened to it closely again recently. True to the nocturne style, it&#8217;s a short, simple piece with a straightforward structure centred on a lovely, almost naive melody that is instantly accessible and deeply romantic. The focus is absolutely on the long-lined vocal quality of the melody rather than complex harmonies, which remain mostly diatonic throughout. </p>



<p>While there&#8217;s not much harmonic tension, the interest comes from Chopin&#8217;s ornamentation that showcases the piano&#8217;s ability to quickly change notes, including trills, turns, and appoggiaturas. Despite its simplicity, or perhaps because of it, this nocturne is profoundly emotional to me. The famous melody is so classically romantic and intimate, that it&#8217;s no wonder it has moved listeners for almost 200 years.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Brahms &#8211; Piano Concerto No. 2 in B-flat major Op. 83</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-brahms-piano-concerto-no-2-in-b-flat-major-op-83/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 22:09:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1879</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I listened to Yuja Wang&#8217;s performance of this concerto, I was drawn into a musical conversation. The&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When I listened to Yuja Wang&#8217;s performance of this concerto, I was drawn into a musical conversation. The piano starts quietly, making small talk with the orchestra. But soon it shows a bold personality, interrupting the orchestra strongly.</p>



<p>There&#8217;s something remarkably compelling when the piano interrupts the orchestra. It&#8217;s like the small piano is shouting against the group. These interruptions give the concerto a sense of struggle and triumph that adds to the piece&#8217;s drama.</p>



<p>Sometimes it sounds like the piano and orchestra are having a dynamic conversation, taking turns. Other times they angrily argue, competing for attention. This conversation keeps changing from calm to passionate. The piano brings thoughtful melody and skill, balancing the orchestra&#8217;s powerful sections.</p>



<p>In the second movement, the dramatic piano storms against the mellow orchestra. The orchestra sometimes responds mildly, creating a vivid contrast that heightens the overall excitement of the movement.</p>



<p>The gentle third movement has a flowing lyricism, with the cello spinning a beautiful song. This movement is rich and sumptuous. It&#8217;s a peaceful contrast from all the arguments before.</p>



<p>But it is the final movement that leaves an indelible mark. Here, the piano shifts from gracious to loud and forceful. The piano showcases its full range of expression. This movement captures the whole spirit of the concerto &#8211; starting peacefully and ending spectacularly.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Schumann &#8211; Carnaval, op. 9</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-schumann-carnaval-op-9/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2024 22:06:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1868</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to Schumann&#8217;s Carnaval, took me into a grand masquerade, where masked partygoers come together to celebrate the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to Schumann&#8217;s Carnaval, took me into a grand masquerade, where masked partygoers come together to celebrate the festivities of Carnival. Even Chopin appeared at this fictitious party. This piano suite, composed between 1834 and 1835, consists of 21 short movements, each representing a character or caricature from the carnival scene.</p>



<p>Schumann turned this piece into a storytelling breathing life into the characters. Pierrot, the sad clown, dances poignantly, while Harlequin, the mischievous trickster, bounds with infectious energy.</p>



<p>At times, the technical challenges posed by Carnaval seemed daunting, even overwhelming. Yet as I studied the piece more deeply, I developed a greater understanding of Schumann&#8217;s composition. Learning about his mental health struggles and how they may have shaped this music gave me new insight. I realized that the complex and shifting emotions woven throughout Carnaval serve to enhance its overall poignant effect. Every musical detail—each note, chord, melodic twist and turn—contributes to this emotional impact.</p>



<p>It is not the kind of work that I would love to listen to repeatedly. Still, I get the sense that it is a work that is important to establish the piano as an extremely expressive instrument and will continue to captivate listeners.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Marta Pereira da Costa &#8211; Tiny Desk Concert</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-marta-pereira-da-costa-tiny-desk-concert/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 22:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1812</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I happened to catch this concert and decided to listen since it featured a Portuguese artist playing the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I happened to catch this concert and decided to listen since it featured a Portuguese artist playing the Portuguese guitar, something you don&#8217;t often see on international channels.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Marta Pereira da Costa: Tiny Desk Concert" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wzlZ68ts-IU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I hadn&#8217;t heard of Marta Pereira da Costa before, although I knew her name. She&#8217;s the world&#8217;s first and only professional female Portuguese guitar player in Fado music.</p>



<p>Right away the sound reminded me of Carlos Paredes, a legendary Portuguese guitarist, but with a fresher vibe, mainly from the percussion. Traditionally the Portuguese guitar is accompanied by two guitars, but here it&#8217;s one guitar plus percussion, bringing a modern twist which I enjoy.</p>



<p>I&#8217;m biased since I love the Portuguese guitar, but Marta&#8217;s playing conveys so much expression and goes beyond mellow tunes. Even faster, danceable songs have a singing, soaring quality from her guitar.</p>



<p>Another thing I enjoyed was how Marta lets the other instruments shine, especially in the last song. The interplay of bass and treble, each with its moment, creates a really beautiful, rich sound.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@nprmusic"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Classical and Romantic</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-classical-and-romantic/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 21:36:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1815</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Beethoven&#8217;s first piano sonata (No. 1 in F minor, Op 2) displays the hallmarks of the Classical style.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Beethoven&#8217;s first piano sonata (No. 1 in F minor, Op 2) displays the hallmarks of the Classical style. It contains a straightforward sonata form structure, opening with a lively first movement dotted with playful melodies. The middle movements provide contrast &#8211; a peaceful Adagio followed by a brisk dance-like section similar to a minuet. The finale introduces a vigorous theme. Throughout the piece, Beethoven focuses on balanced phrases and graceful melodies, supported by conventional harmony and rhythms &#8211; all trademarks of the Classical period.</p>



<p>In contrast, his final piano sonata (No. 32 in C minor, Op 111) exhibits innovations that push toward Romanticism. While still structured into movements, the form is more ecstatic, especially in the mystical opening movement. In this sonata, I hear many more chromatic harmonies and elastic rhythms and feel there&#8217;s an emotional range from brooding melancholy to joyful jubilation. The enriched harmonic palette and depth of expression represent the early Romantic style. </p>



<p>My research, in general, supports my feelings.</p>



<p>In the Opus 2 sonatas of his early period, Beethoven hews more closely to the balanced elegance of Mozart and Haydn. But flashes of his revolutionary voice emerge even then in the intense, turbulent passages. It contains a straightforward sonata form structure, opening with a lively first Molto Allegro movement characterized by accelerating small phrases leading to mini-climaxes, followed by pauses for theatrical effect. The middle Adagio movement offers the only overtly &#8216;pretty&#8217; music in the whole sonata &#8211; simple, serene melodies decorated with lavish ornamentation. The Allegretto finale features a slightly anxious minute tune pieced together from repeated fragments, counteracted by a smoother, more elegant major-mode Trio section.</p>



<p>The Op. 111 is regarded as one of Beethoven&#8217;s best piano compositions. It is a departure from previous sonatas, having only two movements, which led his publisher to question if it wasn&#8217;t a mistake. The sonata is described as powerful, passionate and inventive. For example, Beethoven transforms a simple and singable theme into five variations, ending in a serene and transcendent mood. Yet the animated fugue demonstrates Beethoven&#8217;s contrapuntal mastery cultivated in the Classical tradition. This piano sonata encapsulates Beethoven&#8217;s musical evolution from formal lucidity toward mystical, subjective soundscapes, prefiguring Romantic ideals.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1701123445593 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Tayama, M. (2022) <em>Beethoven Piano sonata in F minor (Op. 2 No. 1)</em>. https://practisingthepiano.com/beethoven-piano-sonata-no-1-in-f-minor/.</p>



<p>G. Gíslason, D. (2022) <em>Sonata No. 1 in F minor&nbsp; Op. 2 No. 1 Archives &#8211; Vancouver Recital Society</em>. https://vanrecital.com/tag/sonata-no-1-in-f-minor-op-2-no-1/.</p>



<p>Pizarro, A. (no date) <em>BBC &#8211; Radio 3 &#8211; Beethoven Piano Sonata No. 1 in F minor, Op. 2 No. 1</em>. https://www.bbc.co.uk/radio3/classical/pizarro/sonata1.shtml.</p>



<p>Kramer, L. (1993b) <em>Music as Cultural Practice, 1800-1900</em>. Univ of California Press.</p>



<p>Vrs (2019) <em>Sonata in C minor Op. 111 Archives &#8211; Vancouver Recital Society</em>. https://vanrecital.com/tag/sonata-in-c-minor-op-111/.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Antonio Vivaldi &#8211; Piccolo Concerto in C Major, RV 443</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-antonio-vivaldi-piccolo-concerto-in-c-major-rv-443/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 21:01:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1808</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Antonio Vivaldi wrote three concertos for a small, high-pitched instrument called the &#8220;flautino&#8221;. The exact instrument Vivaldi intended&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Antonio Vivaldi wrote three concertos for a small, high-pitched instrument called the &#8220;flautino&#8221;. The exact instrument Vivaldi intended is unknown, but scholars believe it was either the sopranino recorder or the flageolet. In the 18th century, the transverse flute replaced both the recorder and flageolet and a new edition of Vivaldi&#8217;s concerto was published for the piccolo, a member of the flute family. This is the version that is typically performed today and it was the one I listened to.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="A. Vivaldi - Piccolo Concerto in C major (RV443)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FBNq-F80uFc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>As soon as the orchestra begins the opening Allegro molto, the piccolo enters with a joyful, singing melody in the upper octave that immediately grabs my attention. The piccolo part requires technical agility as it features fast runs and trills, but the melodies flow so naturally that the difficulty is masked and it looks easy.</p>



<p>The calm and emotional middle Largo movement offers a lovely change from the faster outer movements. The piccolo carries a gorgeous, flowing melody above soft strings, reminiscent of a soulful operatic aria. It&#8217;s my favourite part—a moment where the piccolo&#8217;s expressiveness truly shines.</p>



<p>The concluding Allegro brings back the cheerful mood, with the piccolo presenting new melodic material over the orchestra&#8217;s constant, pulsing motion. The themes are fragmented with trills, creating a perpetually moving, spinning sensation. The cadenza features more rapid runs that showcase the soloist&#8217;s skill.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Tchaikovsky &#8211; The Nutcracker&#8217;s Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-tchaikovsky-the-nutcrackers-dance-of-the-sugar-plum-fairy/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2023 21:46:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1804</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Of course, I already knew the melody of the Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy, since it is&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Of course, I already knew the melody of the Dance of the Sugar Plum Fairy, since it is one of the most used melodies in Christmas ads. But at this time I listened to it closely. In the beginning, I was immediately struck by the beauty of the music. The melody is light and airy and has a childish magical quality that transports you to another world. The use of the celesta gives the music a unique, ethereal and enchanting sound.</p>



<p>The presence of the bass clarinet is brief but it is truly remarkable. It brings a new tone and colour that adds depth to the beginning of the piece. The choice of the bass clarinet seems to bring a warm, mellow and rounded sound in contrast to the brighter, crystalline tones of the celesta. This elevates the overall feeling of the fantastical and mysterious setting.</p>



<p>Overall, it evokes a profound sense of innocent joy and wonder for me. The music exudes a youthful spirit of fantasy and imagination. It&#8217;s a timeless piece that brings out the inner child in me. Every listen renews feelings of wide-eyed enchantment and marvel.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Samuel Barber &#8211; Adagio For Strings</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-samuel-barber-adagio-for-strings/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Nov 2023 20:46:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1771</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Last night I had the pleasure of attending a live performance of Mozart&#8217;s Requiem. When the conductor stepped&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Last night I had the pleasure of attending a live performance of Mozart&#8217;s Requiem. When the conductor stepped up, he surprised us all by announcing they would open with Samuel Barber&#8217;s Adagio for Strings before moving into the Requiem. Though I knew the piece from movies and commercials, I had never truly listened closely before. I found it profoundly moving.</p>



<p>The opening immediately establishes a heavy, mournful mood brimming with emotional weight. It&#8217;s easy to understand why this piece is often played at funerals, including Einstein&#8217;s.</p>



<p>The main theme is deceptively simple &#8211; just three notes ascending. Yet the aching slowness, the dragging tempo, creates the sense of struggling to lift upwards only to fall back down. I loved how the stately, elongated melody passes from the violins to the violas and finally, the cellos, maintaining its emotional power throughout.</p>



<p>To me, it sounded extremely beautiful, but the melody alone doesn&#8217;t convey the full emotional impact. That comes from the harmony of the other strings, which inspire the melody with all its feelings. The rich harmonies and colours of the string orchestra add emotive depth. </p>



<p>This piece perfectly captures the universality of grief, transcending time and place. Though it was composed in 1936, it speaks profoundly to the shared human experience across cultures and generations. Little did Barber know what the world was about to witness and how this song would be embraced as an expression of mourning, remembrance, and hope.</p>



<p>In the end, it proved the perfect prelude to Mozart&#8217;s Requiem. Well-chosen, maestro.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Harry Partch &#8211; Sonata Dementia</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-harry-partch-sonata-dementia/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 20:01:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1728</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I must admit, prior to this, I was unfamiliar with Partch so this is my initial experience listening&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ul></ul>



<p>I must admit, prior to this, I was unfamiliar with Partch so this is my initial experience listening to any of his compositions. Partch was indeed a uniquely creative artist, as he was known for not only inventing his own musical instruments but also scoring his compositions for a 43-tone scale unique to these instruments.</p>



<p>Despite being created over 70 years ago (1950), this piece remains surprisingly fresh and innovative. The composition is marked by its distinct sound, thanks to the use of Partch&#8217;s own instruments like the Bass Marimba and the Hypobass.</p>



<p>Although the microtonal melodies and harmonies of the piece often sounded to me as dissonant and jarring, it&#8217;s the unsettling sound contrasted with the comical visual of the instruments that makes it so unique. The sonata is a satirical work going into themes of madness, delusion, and paranoia.</p>



<p>This composition thoroughly blends humour and lightness with hints of darker territories. The lyrics of the piece might seem nonsensical on the surface, but they carry potential interpretations concerning the human condition.</p>



<p>Listening to &#8216;Sonata Dementia&#8217; is a challenging experience. The microtonality might initially seem daunting, but it may not be as intricate as expected. The initial dissonance from the 43-tone scale, which might seem hard to accept at first, gradually becomes more harmonic and natural as the pieces develop.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Harry Partch: SONATA DEMENTIA (1950)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qZybJAEPu18?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Harry Partch &#8211; King Oedipus</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-harry-partch-king-oedipus/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 21:36:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1731</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I recently listened to some parts of King Oedipus, an opera composed by Harry Partch. I was drawn&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I recently listened to some parts of King Oedipus, an opera composed by Harry Partch. I was drawn to listen to it because of the information about how Partch started to dive into microtonality, as it more closely resembles the natural human voice. This actually makes total sense for opera. People don&#8217;t speak in 12 semitones, but actually in hundreds of microtones and opera relies heavily on the expression of the voice. As I listened to King Oedipus, I noticed how the voices sounded more like speech than singing.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Partch&#8217;s music for King Oedipus is a unique blend of microtonality, percussion, and spoken word. The voices sound more natural, not sung, but spoken. The instruments follow the vocals and strangely don&#8217;t sound as strange as they do in other microtonal pieces by Partch. The microtonality allows the voices to more closely match natural speech patterns, rather than conforming to the 12 notes of standard Western music. I enjoyed listening to King Oedipus, even though I did not hear the whole opera. It was a refreshing and stimulating experience that opened my ears to new possibilities of musical expression.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="HARRY PARTCH - King Oedipus 1952 (Audio)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/V2jHtfk2ljM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Julian Carrillo &#8211; Seis casi-sonatas en cuartos de tono para violoncello solo</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-julian-carrillo-seis-casi-sonatas-en-cuartos-de-tono-para-violoncello-solo/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2023 21:13:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1754</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Julian Carrillo&#8217;s Seis casi-sonatas en cuartos de tono para violoncello solo, performed by Gerardo Gimenez Cacho, offers a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Julian Carrillo&#8217;s Seis casi-sonatas en cuartos de tono para violoncello solo, performed by Gerardo Gimenez Cacho, offers a fascinating glimpse into the expressive potential of microtonal music. As someone accustomed to the familiar 12-tone equal temperament of Western classical music, I found these quarter-tone sonatas surprisingly easy to listen to and appreciate. The solo cello format helps make the microtones feel intimate rather than jarring.</p>



<p>With these sonatas, I could understand how dividing the octave into smaller intervals can open up new sonic palettes and colours. Microtonality provides the performer access to the &#8220;cracks between the keys&#8221; &#8211; those poignant notes that float between our conventional Western pitches. The cello seems to emote in ways that would be impossible with merely 12 notes.</p>



<p>I cannot imagine how difficult these pieces must be to perform well, given the challenge of precisely nailing pitches outside of the equal temperament celloists spend years mastering. The skill demonstrated in this recording is hugely impressive.</p>



<p>Occasionally the quarter tones sound somewhat unsettling, but more often I found they enhanced the cello&#8217;s innate expressiveness. For example, the aching melody in the third movement of Sonata No. 4 attains an extra sadness from its microtonal sounds. The result is something simultaneously familiar and novel.</p>



<p>The quarter tones may initially sound like &#8220;out of tune&#8221; notes, but one&#8217;s ear quickly adjusts, and their emotional resonance becomes apparent. Julian Carrillo has created a compelling showcase for the cello as an instrument of uncommon subtlety. Even for listeners new to microtonality, these Casi-sonatas offer an accessible and rewarding introduction.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Jacob Collier &#8211; In The Bleak Midwinter</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-jacob-collier-in-the-bleak-midwinter/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 20:37:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1748</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to Jacob Collier&#8217;s &#8220;In The Bleak Midwinter&#8221; was an enlightening experience for me as I researched microtonality&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to Jacob Collier&#8217;s &#8220;In The Bleak Midwinter&#8221; was an enlightening experience for me as I researched microtonality in modern music. As one of the most talented young musicians today, Collier&#8217;s ingenious use of microtones immediately drew me in. The track begins deceivingly simple but slowly builds in complexity. At one point, Collier modulates to what sounds like a G#. However, with microtonal inflexions, he has actually modulated to the key of G half-sharp major &#8211; something I did not detect on the first listen! The modulation is brilliantly executed, such that the music flows seamlessly.  I had to understand how he modulated and David Bruce helped me on that.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="How to Modulate to G 1/2 Sharp (Jacob Collier-style)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xd54l8gfi7M?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>As I re-listened and focused on the microtonal shift, I better appreciated Collier&#8217;s technical mastery and innovative musicality. &#8220;In The Bleak Midwinter&#8221; proves he is not just one of the best musicians of our time, but one boldly expanding the boundaries of Western music.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="In The Bleak Midwinter - Jacob Collier" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mPZn4x3uOac?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Radiohead &#8211; How to Disappear Completely</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-radiohead-how-to-disappear-completely/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 20:17:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1745</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Radiohead is not a band that I particularly enjoy listening to, but I decided to listen to How&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Radiohead is not a band that I particularly enjoy listening to, but I decided to listen to How to Disappear Completely to hear its use of microtonality. </p>



<p>The song starts off with a simple guitar and Thom Yorke&#8217;s falsetto vocals, nothing too unusual for a Radiohead track. The lyrics are vague and ambiguous, but they convey a sense of detachment and dissociation from reality. The song gradually builds up with layers of orchestral strings, guitar effects, and electronic sounds, creating a rich and complex sonic landscape. About two-thirds of the way through, the strings come in playing microtonal intervals that clash with the conventional instrumentation. These non-standard pitches on the strings create an unsettling, tense atmosphere contrasting with the dreamy opening section. The microtonal strings sound almost like they&#8217;re playing a separate song altogether, weaving an anxious counter-melody against the main chords. </p>



<p>This incoherent effect highlights Yorke&#8217;s lyrics about feeling disconnected from reality. While Radiohead isn&#8217;t my go-to band, I found &#8220;How to Disappear Completely&#8221; an interesting song with the use of microtonality to convey emotional dissociation in music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Charles Ives &#8211;  Three Quarter Tone Pieces for Two Pianos</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-charles-ives-three-quarter-tone-pieces-for-two-pianos/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 20:56:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1740</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I enjoyed Ives&#8217; Three Quarter Tone Pieces for Two Pianos more than Hába&#8217;s quarter-tone sonata. The interplay between&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I enjoyed Ives&#8217; Three Quarter Tone Pieces for Two Pianos more than Hába&#8217;s quarter-tone sonata. The interplay between the two pianos tuned a quarter tone apart, creates an intriguing sense of conversation. One piano is tuned to standard western 12-tone equal temperament, while the other uses quarter tones. At first, they both sound out of tune, which has a quirky, childlike quality. But at moments they harmonize in an unconventional way that sounds oddly &#8220;in tune.&#8221;</p>



<p>As I kept listening, I began to familiarize myself with the microtonal language. The quarter tones initially sound discordantly unfamiliar, but gradually become interesting as my ears adapt. Although the microtonal effect hasn&#8217;t become conventionally pleasing to my ears accustomed to the 12-note scale, I can recognize the inventive nature and derive pleasure from the music on its own merits.</p>



<p>Overall, the quarter-tone pieces demonstrate that microtonality is an acquired taste that requires time to appreciate. The outcome is a captivating sound that I can find enjoyable, even though it hasn&#8217;t fully convinced me.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="IVES Three Quarter Tone Pieces for Two Pianos w/ TMC Fellows" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wwj8mTiZi8o?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Alois Hába &#8211;  Sonata for quarter-tone piano, op.62</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-alois-haba-sonata-for-quarter-tone-piano-op-62/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 20:14:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1736</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Strange is the first word that comes to my mind when listening to Hába&#8217;s Sonata for Quarter-Tone Piano,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Strange is the first word that comes to my mind when listening to Hába&#8217;s Sonata for Quarter-Tone Piano, Op. 62. After researching microtonality, I&#8217;ve come to enjoy the concept and composers&#8217; reasons for exploring it. But the truth is my ears are so accustomed to the 12-semitone scale that I initially find microtonal music weird. Recent examples in rock and jazz, like King Gizzard and Jacob Collier, are growing on me. Yet even in the slower, more lyrical second movement of Hába&#8217;s sonata, I struggle to fully appreciate the quarter tones. </p>



<p>Making an effort to keep an open mind, I can sense the pioneering spirit of discovery in Hába’s quarter-tone innovations. They impart an otherworldly, dreamlike quality as my ear gradually adjusts. But my long familiarity with 12-tone equal temperament means microtones continue to sound strange at first, even as I recognize their creative possibilities. However, after listening to it more carefully, I started to notice there&#8217;s some beauty and subtlety of the quarter tones. The sonata has a lot of variation and contrast that I can see me appreciating it the more I listen to it.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Alois Hába: Sonata for quarter tone piano, op.62 (1946/1947)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FDs7ve1uGbg?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p><a href="https://bard.google.com/" target="_blank"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Greta Van Fleet &#8211; Light My Love</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-greta-van-fleet-light-my-love/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 20:20:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1751</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As a Led Zeppelin fan, I was eager to check out the band Greta Van Fleet after a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As a Led Zeppelin fan, I was eager to check out the band Greta Van Fleet after a friend&#8217;s recommendation. While I enjoyed several of their retro-rock tracks that pay homage to Zeppelin&#8217;s classic sound, the song &#8220;Light My Love&#8221; stood out as my favourite.</p>



<p>The piano melody at the start sets up an interesting intro, but after a few bars, the song explodes into a full-on rock explosion. The lead singer, Josh Kiszka, has a voice that sounds remarkably similar to the legendary Robert Plant &#8211; soaring and crystalline one moment, then shifting into joyful wails that drive the energy ever higher.</p>



<p>Though the chorus repeats in typical pop fashion, the anthemic sound of guitars and drums keeps it from being repetitive. Kiszka unleashes some spectacular high screams that electrify the lyrics. Overall, while Greta Van Fleet wears their influences proudly, &#8220;Light My Love&#8221; shows they can also craft an exhilarating retro-rock song that stands on its own. For a Led Zeppelin fan like me, it left me eager to hear more from this talented young band.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Public Service Broadcasting &#8211; Broadcasting House</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-public-service-broadcasting-broadcasting-house/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 21:40:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1630</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I recently discovered Public Service Broadcasting when I heard their music performed by the 88-piece BBC Symphony Orchestra,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I recently discovered Public Service Broadcasting when I heard their music performed by the 88-piece BBC Symphony Orchestra, conducted by Jules Buckley. I liked it from the start and have been listening to it repeatedly.</p>



<p>I enjoyed how the music remains mostly the same but gradually adds different instruments and textures in a big build-up. </p>



<p>The most surprising aspect for me was the blend of drums and orchestra. I think exploring drums in an orchestral context adds a modern rhythmic element. I also liked the mix of pre-recorded sounds, electronic, and acoustic instruments. They fit together seamlessly, making it hard to distinguish between them.</p>



<p>Overall, it&#8217;s a perfect fusion of pop and classical music, with experimental elements that I appreciate.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to contemporary music styles</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-contemporary-music-styles/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 21:06:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1618</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Religious composers (holy minimalism) John Tavener &#8211; The LambI liked this song. I didn&#8217;t know John Tavener until&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 id="religious-composers-holy-minimalism" class="wp-block-heading">Religious composers (holy minimalism)</h3>



<p><strong>John Tavener &#8211; The Lamb<br></strong>I liked this song. I didn&#8217;t know John Tavener until today, and I was very impressed by this choral piece. It was peaceful, calm, and it seemed to be written to enjoy the echo of a church. This means that I didn&#8217;t feel sudden changes in the voices. Instead, they seemed to float on their own and slowly fade out.</p>



<p><strong>Arvo Pärt &#8211; Spiegel im Spiegel<br></strong>Another piece that I enjoyed, and I didn&#8217;t know the composer. The piano is very simple, but I think its purpose is to allow the violin to express long sustained notes. I can imagine this being played at a church, and the sound echoing through the walls. I have the desire to understand how deeply rooted this song is in Estonian traditional music.</p>



<p><strong>Henryk Górecki &#8211; Symphony No 3<br></strong>The music seems very peaceful but mournful at the same time, especially in the middle of the first movement when the soprano starts singing. I liked that the first half of the first movement seems like it is building up for a big explosion, but it never arrives. Overall, I think this symphony could be a soundtrack for a movie or documentary. I believe Zimmer thought so too.</p>



<h3 id="minimalism" class="wp-block-heading">Minimalism</h3>



<p><strong>Steve Reich &#8211; Music for 18 Musicians<br></strong>I find this type of music harder to enjoy. The simple sound and repetitive nature with subtle changes are not my preference. I understand the exploration of sounds, similar to Ravel&#8217;s Bolero, and can appreciate it to some extent. However, the length of the repetition is too much for me. Listening to it as a whole might induce a trance-like feeling and it made me wonder if this kind of music could also be used for religious purposes.</p>



<p><strong>Terry Riley &#8211; In C<br></strong>I tried to listen attentively to the entire piece, but once again, aside from the interesting exercise, I don&#8217;t find this art form truly enjoyable. What stood out to me was how the introduction of new sounds and instruments took the music on different paths. This was more noticeable when I skipped ahead a few minutes from time to time. I understand that the composer probably didn&#8217;t intend his music to be listened to this way, but for me, it provided a more interesting experience.</p>



<p><strong>Philip Glass &#8211; Glassworks<br></strong>I found this album much easier to appreciate than the previous two. Although there is still repetition, there is a sense of progression. It feels like the music is going somewhere. Some moments reminded me of Radiohead, which added another layer of interest. Another notable aspect of Glass&#8217;s music is the varied tempo compared to the previous pieces, creating interesting contrasts between songs.</p>



<h3 id="new-complexity" class="wp-block-heading">New complexity</h3>



<p><strong>Brian Ferneyhough &#8211; Exordium<br></strong>It&#8217;s difficult for me to write about this piece. I felt uncomfortable at times and wasn&#8217;t sure if I liked it or not. It seemed highly complex and lacked direction after my initial hearing. It felt more like an exploration of sounds rather than a cohesive composition. While I acknowledge that there is certainly thought behind this piece, I couldn&#8217;t fully grasp it.</p>



<h3 id="choral-music-tonality" class="wp-block-heading">Choral music/tonality</h3>



<p><strong>John Rutter &#8211; Requiem<br></strong>All of Rutter&#8217;s Requiem felt accessible to me. Even though I wasn&#8217;t familiar with the artist, there was a sense of déjà vu while listening to the pieces. It reminded me of Górecki, and I could imagine it as a movie soundtrack. The harmonies are simple, and the instrumentation is understated. However, this simplicity doesn&#8217;t diminish the emotional impact. For example, Agnus Dei felt mysterious and sombre to me.</p>



<p><strong>Eric Whitacre &#8211; Cloudburst<br></strong>The introduction was surprising and bewildering, with the gradual rise of all the sounds. I couldn&#8217;t determine if it was purely vocal or if other instruments were involved. I enjoyed how the voices floated at times, each having its own line, but I was even more captivated when they harmonized and created a powerful sonority.</p>



<h3 id="microtonality-and-spectralism" class="wp-block-heading">Microtonality and spectralism</h3>



<p><strong>Tristan Murail &#8211; Allegories<br></strong>I have limited knowledge of microtonality and spectralism, so this is a new experience for me. This particular piece left me uncertain about my feelings by the end. I attempted to identify recurring elements, but I struggled to do so. Instead, I found myself focusing on the electronic sounds and trying to differentiate them from the acoustic sounds. It was challenging for me to discern between the two. I couldn&#8217;t help but wonder if this blurring of sounds was intentional on the part of the composer.</p>



<p><strong>Gérard Grisey – Les Espaces Acoustiques<br></strong>The overall pace of the music is slow, but it has a captivating effect. The first piece starts with a beautiful melody played by the viola which I really enjoyed. It had a certain pattern that kept coming back, and I couldn&#8217;t help but focus on it. As the piece progressed, more instruments joined in, which I found less interesting than the solo instrument.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Tchaikovsky &#8211; The Seasons</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-tchaikovsky-the-seasons/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 21:24:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1461</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tchaikovsky&#8217;s Seasons is probably the less known &#8220;seasons&#8221; of major composers. My opinion is that, because they were&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Tchaikovsky&#8217;s Seasons is probably the less known &#8220;seasons&#8221; of major composers. My opinion is that, because they were composed for a bigger audience, including amateurs, they lack the virtuosity and complexity that pianists prefer in order to showcase their skills.</p>



<p>The collection was composed between November 1875 and May 1876 and commissioned by Nikolay Matveyevich Bernard, the publisher of Le Nouvelliste, a monthly music magazine in St. Petersburg. The intention of the publisher was to release one piece per month, but Tchaikovsky wrote the majority of the pieces between April and May 1876.</p>



<p>In opposition to Vivaldi&#8217;s &#8220;The Four Seasons&#8221;, Tchaikovsky&#8217;s seasons are composed of 12 pieces, each one dedicated to each month of the year, showcasing a glimpse of something characteristic of the month, for example, Carnival (February), The Harvest (August) or Christmas (December).</p>



<p>I would not say that this romantic work is programmatic, but one cannot definitely distance himself from the theme of each piece and hear it as absolute music.</p>



<p>My thoughts after listening to each piece:</p>



<ul>
<li>January: Warm, cosy, and familiar, Evokes a feeling of being at home with the cold outside, warmed by a fireplace and surrounded by loved ones.</li>



<li>February: Playful, cheery, festive. Just like Carnival should be.</li>



<li>March: Melancholic and distant, evoking a sense of reflection for the cold month of March.</li>



<li>April: Charming and optimistic. The end of winter means the start of spring.</li>



<li>May: Serene and tranquil, but warm just like the nights of May.</li>



<li>June: There&#8217;s a certain melancholy in this piece that I find beautiful. It looks like a very romantic piece.</li>



<li>July: The summer spirit is present with a catchy and cheerful tone.</li>



<li>August: The initial and final sections of this piece weren&#8217;t to my liking. It feels chaotic and excessively flourishing for my taste.</li>



<li>September: Majestic and spirited. It resembles a fanfare that complements the eerie ambience of this time of year.</li>



<li>October: Among the pieces in this set, this one evokes a particularly somber mood, but is my favourite. Winter is coming.</li>



<li>November: Somehow, the beggining, reminds me of impressionist pieces. It showcases familiar tunes and notable variations.</li>



<li>December: A refined and courteous waltz-like composition, that brings a warm and festive sensation.</li>
</ul>



<p>Ultimately, I think Tchaikovsky successfully captured the essence of each month, while also preserving a sense of coherence throughout the entire composition. It was a fantastic initial listening, and I eagerly anticipate revisiting it in the future.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Erik Satie &#8211; Gymnopédie No.1</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-erik-satie-gymnopedie-no-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 13:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1544</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Composed in 1888, Gymnopédie No. 1 is one of three piano pieces. The term &#8220;gymnopédie&#8221; refers to a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Composed in 1888, Gymnopédie No. 1 is one of three piano pieces. The term &#8220;gymnopédie&#8221; refers to a dance performed by young men in ancient Greece, characterized by their nudity. Satie&#8217;s music beautifully captures a sense of ethereal beauty and melancholic nostalgia.</p>



<p>As I learned in my previous studies, Satie influenced Debussy in rejecting the conventions and rules of the era. Gymnopédie No. 1 holds great historical significance as it marked a departure from the prevailing Romantic style of that time.</p>



<p>The composition revolves around a single musical idea, depicted in the image below. To me, it resembles a steady heartbeat that pervades the entire piece, setting its rhythm and atmosphere. Throughout the composition, I anticipated an eruption or a contrasting texture, like in Debussy&#8217;s Clair de Lune, but it never arrived. Even the melody lacks such contrast, with the only variety stemming from the harmony.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="285" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-1024x285.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1545" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-1024x285.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-300x83.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-768x213.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-640x178.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-960x267.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00.png 1346w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Interestingly, upon initial listening, the melody seems simplistic and somewhat predictable, while the harmonies are surprisingly unexpected. Although I couldn&#8217;t find a tonal centre, the music appears to shift between D Major and G Major, introducing delightful contrasts, such as the A minor.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-1024x565.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1547" width="512" height="283" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-1024x565.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-300x166.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-768x424.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-640x353.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-960x530.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42.png 1228w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /></figure>



<p>After several listens, I find the music to be ethereal, creating a contemplative and soothing experience. The choice of the piano as the instrument contributes to this sensation, as it conveys tranquillity more effectively than an orchestra, such as Debussy&#8217;s orchestration. The absence of a narrative or progression in the music makes me wonder whether Satie paved the way for ambient music.<br></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
