<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 20:54:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Public Service Broadcasting &#8211; Broadcasting House</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-public-service-broadcasting-broadcasting-house/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 21:40:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1630</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I recently discovered Public Service Broadcasting when I heard their music performed by the 88-piece BBC Symphony Orchestra,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I recently discovered Public Service Broadcasting when I heard their music performed by the 88-piece BBC Symphony Orchestra, conducted by Jules Buckley. I liked it from the start and have been listening to it repeatedly.</p>



<p>I enjoyed how the music remains mostly the same but gradually adds different instruments and textures in a big build-up. </p>



<p>The most surprising aspect for me was the blend of drums and orchestra. I think exploring drums in an orchestral context adds a modern rhythmic element. I also liked the mix of pre-recorded sounds, electronic, and acoustic instruments. They fit together seamlessly, making it hard to distinguish between them.</p>



<p>Overall, it&#8217;s a perfect fusion of pop and classical music, with experimental elements that I appreciate.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to contemporary music styles</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-contemporary-music-styles/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 21:06:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1618</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Religious composers (holy minimalism) John Tavener &#8211; The LambI liked this song. I didn&#8217;t know John Tavener until&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 id="religious-composers-holy-minimalism" class="wp-block-heading">Religious composers (holy minimalism)</h3>



<p><strong>John Tavener &#8211; The Lamb<br></strong>I liked this song. I didn&#8217;t know John Tavener until today, and I was very impressed by this choral piece. It was peaceful, calm, and it seemed to be written to enjoy the echo of a church. This means that I didn&#8217;t feel sudden changes in the voices. Instead, they seemed to float on their own and slowly fade out.</p>



<p><strong>Arvo Pärt &#8211; Spiegel im Spiegel<br></strong>Another piece that I enjoyed, and I didn&#8217;t know the composer. The piano is very simple, but I think its purpose is to allow the violin to express long sustained notes. I can imagine this being played at a church, and the sound echoing through the walls. I have the desire to understand how deeply rooted this song is in Estonian traditional music.</p>



<p><strong>Henryk Górecki &#8211; Symphony No 3<br></strong>The music seems very peaceful but mournful at the same time, especially in the middle of the first movement when the soprano starts singing. I liked that the first half of the first movement seems like it is building up for a big explosion, but it never arrives. Overall, I think this symphony could be a soundtrack for a movie or documentary. I believe Zimmer thought so too.</p>



<h3 id="minimalism" class="wp-block-heading">Minimalism</h3>



<p><strong>Steve Reich &#8211; Music for 18 Musicians<br></strong>I find this type of music harder to enjoy. The simple sound and repetitive nature with subtle changes are not my preference. I understand the exploration of sounds, similar to Ravel&#8217;s Bolero, and can appreciate it to some extent. However, the length of the repetition is too much for me. Listening to it as a whole might induce a trance-like feeling and it made me wonder if this kind of music could also be used for religious purposes.</p>



<p><strong>Terry Riley &#8211; In C<br></strong>I tried to listen attentively to the entire piece, but once again, aside from the interesting exercise, I don&#8217;t find this art form truly enjoyable. What stood out to me was how the introduction of new sounds and instruments took the music on different paths. This was more noticeable when I skipped ahead a few minutes from time to time. I understand that the composer probably didn&#8217;t intend his music to be listened to this way, but for me, it provided a more interesting experience.</p>



<p><strong>Philip Glass &#8211; Glassworks<br></strong>I found this album much easier to appreciate than the previous two. Although there is still repetition, there is a sense of progression. It feels like the music is going somewhere. Some moments reminded me of Radiohead, which added another layer of interest. Another notable aspect of Glass&#8217;s music is the varied tempo compared to the previous pieces, creating interesting contrasts between songs.</p>



<h3 id="new-complexity" class="wp-block-heading">New complexity</h3>



<p><strong>Brian Ferneyhough &#8211; Exordium<br></strong>It&#8217;s difficult for me to write about this piece. I felt uncomfortable at times and wasn&#8217;t sure if I liked it or not. It seemed highly complex and lacked direction after my initial hearing. It felt more like an exploration of sounds rather than a cohesive composition. While I acknowledge that there is certainly thought behind this piece, I couldn&#8217;t fully grasp it.</p>



<h3 id="choral-music-tonality" class="wp-block-heading">Choral music/tonality</h3>



<p><strong>John Rutter &#8211; Requiem<br></strong>All of Rutter&#8217;s Requiem felt accessible to me. Even though I wasn&#8217;t familiar with the artist, there was a sense of déjà vu while listening to the pieces. It reminded me of Górecki, and I could imagine it as a movie soundtrack. The harmonies are simple, and the instrumentation is understated. However, this simplicity doesn&#8217;t diminish the emotional impact. For example, Agnus Dei felt mysterious and sombre to me.</p>



<p><strong>Eric Whitacre &#8211; Cloudburst<br></strong>The introduction was surprising and bewildering, with the gradual rise of all the sounds. I couldn&#8217;t determine if it was purely vocal or if other instruments were involved. I enjoyed how the voices floated at times, each having its own line, but I was even more captivated when they harmonized and created a powerful sonority.</p>



<h3 id="microtonality-and-spectralism" class="wp-block-heading">Microtonality and spectralism</h3>



<p><strong>Tristan Murail &#8211; Allegories<br></strong>I have limited knowledge of microtonality and spectralism, so this is a new experience for me. This particular piece left me uncertain about my feelings by the end. I attempted to identify recurring elements, but I struggled to do so. Instead, I found myself focusing on the electronic sounds and trying to differentiate them from the acoustic sounds. It was challenging for me to discern between the two. I couldn&#8217;t help but wonder if this blurring of sounds was intentional on the part of the composer.</p>



<p><strong>Gérard Grisey – Les Espaces Acoustiques<br></strong>The overall pace of the music is slow, but it has a captivating effect. The first piece starts with a beautiful melody played by the viola which I really enjoyed. It had a certain pattern that kept coming back, and I couldn&#8217;t help but focus on it. As the piece progressed, more instruments joined in, which I found less interesting than the solo instrument.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Tchaikovsky &#8211; The Seasons</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-tchaikovsky-the-seasons/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 21:24:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1461</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tchaikovsky&#8217;s Seasons is probably the less known &#8220;seasons&#8221; of major composers. My opinion is that, because they were&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Tchaikovsky&#8217;s Seasons is probably the less known &#8220;seasons&#8221; of major composers. My opinion is that, because they were composed for a bigger audience, including amateurs, they lack the virtuosity and complexity that pianists prefer in order to showcase their skills.</p>



<p>The collection was composed between November 1875 and May 1876 and commissioned by Nikolay Matveyevich Bernard, the publisher of Le Nouvelliste, a monthly music magazine in St. Petersburg. The intention of the publisher was to release one piece per month, but Tchaikovsky wrote the majority of the pieces between April and May 1876.</p>



<p>In opposition to Vivaldi&#8217;s &#8220;The Four Seasons&#8221;, Tchaikovsky&#8217;s seasons are composed of 12 pieces, each one dedicated to each month of the year, showcasing a glimpse of something characteristic of the month, for example, Carnival (February), The Harvest (August) or Christmas (December).</p>



<p>I would not say that this romantic work is programmatic, but one cannot definitely distance himself from the theme of each piece and hear it as absolute music.</p>



<p>My thoughts after listening to each piece:</p>



<ul>
<li>January: Warm, cosy, and familiar, Evokes a feeling of being at home with the cold outside, warmed by a fireplace and surrounded by loved ones.</li>



<li>February: Playful, cheery, festive. Just like Carnival should be.</li>



<li>March: Melancholic and distant, evoking a sense of reflection for the cold month of March.</li>



<li>April: Charming and optimistic. The end of winter means the start of spring.</li>



<li>May: Serene and tranquil, but warm just like the nights of May.</li>



<li>June: There&#8217;s a certain melancholy in this piece that I find beautiful. It looks like a very romantic piece.</li>



<li>July: The summer spirit is present with a catchy and cheerful tone.</li>



<li>August: The initial and final sections of this piece weren&#8217;t to my liking. It feels chaotic and excessively flourishing for my taste.</li>



<li>September: Majestic and spirited. It resembles a fanfare that complements the eerie ambience of this time of year.</li>



<li>October: Among the pieces in this set, this one evokes a particularly somber mood, but is my favourite. Winter is coming.</li>



<li>November: Somehow, the beggining, reminds me of impressionist pieces. It showcases familiar tunes and notable variations.</li>



<li>December: A refined and courteous waltz-like composition, that brings a warm and festive sensation.</li>
</ul>



<p>Ultimately, I think Tchaikovsky successfully captured the essence of each month, while also preserving a sense of coherence throughout the entire composition. It was a fantastic initial listening, and I eagerly anticipate revisiting it in the future.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Erik Satie &#8211; Gymnopédie No.1</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-erik-satie-gymnopedie-no-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 13:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1544</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Composed in 1888, Gymnopédie No. 1 is one of three piano pieces. The term &#8220;gymnopédie&#8221; refers to a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Composed in 1888, Gymnopédie No. 1 is one of three piano pieces. The term &#8220;gymnopédie&#8221; refers to a dance performed by young men in ancient Greece, characterized by their nudity. Satie&#8217;s music beautifully captures a sense of ethereal beauty and melancholic nostalgia.</p>



<p>As I learned in my previous studies, Satie influenced Debussy in rejecting the conventions and rules of the era. Gymnopédie No. 1 holds great historical significance as it marked a departure from the prevailing Romantic style of that time.</p>



<p>The composition revolves around a single musical idea, depicted in the image below. To me, it resembles a steady heartbeat that pervades the entire piece, setting its rhythm and atmosphere. Throughout the composition, I anticipated an eruption or a contrasting texture, like in Debussy&#8217;s Clair de Lune, but it never arrived. Even the melody lacks such contrast, with the only variety stemming from the harmony.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="1024" height="285" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-1024x285.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1545" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-1024x285.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-300x83.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-768x213.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-640x178.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00-960x267.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.35.00.png 1346w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Interestingly, upon initial listening, the melody seems simplistic and somewhat predictable, while the harmonies are surprisingly unexpected. Although I couldn&#8217;t find a tonal centre, the music appears to shift between D Major and G Major, introducing delightful contrasts, such as the A minor.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-1024x565.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1547" width="512" height="283" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-1024x565.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-300x166.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-768x424.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-640x353.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42-960x530.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/06/Screenshot-2023-06-13-at-14.40.42.png 1228w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /></figure>



<p>After several listens, I find the music to be ethereal, creating a contemplative and soothing experience. The choice of the piano as the instrument contributes to this sensation, as it conveys tranquillity more effectively than an orchestra, such as Debussy&#8217;s orchestration. The absence of a narrative or progression in the music makes me wonder whether Satie paved the way for ambient music.<br></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
