<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 20:07:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Jamie Lidell and Fer Isella &#8211; Transcendence</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-jamie-lidell-and-fer-isella-transcendence/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 20:48:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 4: Composing for Solo Voice]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=322</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As a listener familiar with Jamie Lidell&#8217;s work, this song is a surprising and intriguing departure from his usual style. The song creates a dreamlike, ethereal atmosphere that seems to keep up to its title....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As a listener familiar with Jamie Lidell&#8217;s work, this song is a surprising and intriguing departure from his usual style. </p>



<p>The song creates a dreamlike, ethereal atmosphere that seems to keep up to its title.  What I liked most about this piece is the connection between Lidell&#8217;s deep, resonant voice and the piano lines. The piano mirrors the vocal melody, creating an interesting contrast between the two timbres. The vocal performance is particularly noteworthy for its &#8220;dragging&#8221; quality &#8211; he extends and stretches the melodic phrases, lending a meditative, deeply sensitive character to the music. This technique enhances the contemplative nature of the piece and draws the listener into its hypnotic atmosphere.</p>



<p>While minimalistic in their application, the electronic elements play a crucial role in shaping the song&#8217;s character. They provide a foundation that deepens the overall sound, expanding beyond what would be possible with just piano and voice. These subtle electronic textures contribute significantly to the dreamlike quality of the piece, reinforcing the theme of transcendence suggested by the title. </p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Iron &#038; Wine and Fiona Apple &#8211; All In Good Time</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-iron-wine-and-fiona-apple-all-in-good-time/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2024 21:04:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 4: Composing for Solo Voice]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=324</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The song immediately creates a satisfying emotional journey, building tension before resolving into the repeated phrase &#8220;all in good time.&#8221; This reminded me of Eibhlín a Rún listening I did previously. This structure creates a...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The song immediately creates a satisfying emotional journey, building tension before resolving into the repeated phrase &#8220;all in good time.&#8221; This reminded me of Eibhlín a Rún listening I did previously. This structure creates a powerful sense of resolution that is both pleasing and emotionally fulfilling. The overall style evokes traditional folk music that I feel its meant to be sung in a group, repeating the &#8220;all in good time&#8221; part all together.</p>



<p>Another feature of the piece is the interplay between the male and female voices. Iron &amp; Wine and Fiona Apple&#8217;s vocal collaboration follows a traditional approach of conversation-style singing, where the two voices create an engaging contrast. This back-and-forth dynamic adds depth and interest to the song.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Charles Mingus &#8211; Moanin</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-charles-mingus-moanin/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 20:44:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 4: Composing for Solo Voice]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=320</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The piece immediately got my attention with its opening baritone saxophone line &#8211; a riff that is both catchy and bluesy. This memorable theme serves as more than just an introduction; it becomes the binding...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The piece immediately got my attention with its opening baritone saxophone line &#8211; a riff that is both catchy and bluesy. This memorable theme serves as more than just an introduction; it becomes the binding element that holds together the entire seven-minute composition. It was both accessible and easy to follow the piece.</p>



<p>What makes this song engaging is how the band uses this catchy opening theme throughout the piece. As the composition progresses, different instruments take their turns in the spotlight, but the original theme is never far away. The soloists occasionally offer hints or fragments of the main theme, creating a sense of anticipation in the listener. This technique of teasing the return of the main theme keeps the audience engaged throughout the extended duration of the piece.</p>



<p>I like how this creates a satisfying tension between the known (the theme) and the unknown (the improvisations).</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Dervish &#038; Friends &#8211; Eibhlín a Rún</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-dervish-friends-eibhlin-a-run/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 21:57:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 4: Composing for Solo Voice]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=302</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I found this piece while working on the exercise about writing piano accompaniment for a folk song. I didn&#8217;t know the song, so I researched it on YouTube, where this performance by Dervish &#38; Friends...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I found this piece while working on the exercise about writing piano accompaniment for a folk song. I didn&#8217;t know the song, so I researched it on YouTube, where this performance by Dervish &amp; Friends stood out.</p>



<p>When I first heard the song, I was struck by its beautiful melody and minimalistic instrumentation. The way it&#8217;s arranged lets you really feel the emotion in the song, making it a powerful experience to listen to. The song is slow and careful, which adds to its sad mood. Each singer adds their own twist to the melody, making it even more emotional. </p>



<p>One thing that really stood out was how the singers ornamented the melody, which reminds me of Arabic and Indian singing traditions. The use of microtones in these embellishments adds expressiveness to the melody.</p>



<p>The song uses repetition in a clever way, especially with the phrase &#8220;Eibhlín a Rún.&#8221; This repeated line feels like a group of people calling out together. As the song goes on, more voices join in, making it feel stronger and more emotional. This builds a sense of togetherness that really adds to the song&#8217;s impact.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
