<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 20:07:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Robert Schumann &#8211; Intermezzo from Faschingsschwank aus Wien, Op. 26</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-robert-schumann-intermezzo-from-faschingsschwank-aus-wien-op-26/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 22:26:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Developing Orchestration Skills]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=519</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The contrast between the flowing accompaniment and the slower, expressive melody creates a sense of emotional push and pull, as if the music is caught between longing and unrest. There is something almost poetic about...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The contrast between the flowing accompaniment and the slower, expressive melody creates a sense of emotional push and pull, as if the music is caught between longing and unrest. There is something almost poetic about the way the melody unfolds, and I am particularly drawn to how Schumann maintains a sense of melancholy even in moments of intensity.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to João Gilberto &#8211; Estate</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-joao-gilberto-estate/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 22:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Developing Orchestration Skills]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=517</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[At first, I wasn’t sure what language João Gilberto was singing in. His Brazilian accent makes the Italian lyrics sound unique. Once I realized it was Italian, it made perfect sense. The piece feels like...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>At first, I wasn’t sure what language João Gilberto was singing in. His Brazilian accent makes the Italian lyrics sound unique. Once I realized it was Italian, it made perfect sense. The piece feels like a fusion of Ennio Morricone’s cinematic style and the relaxed sophistication of bossa nova. I love how the orchestral elements create a dreamy atmosphere, while the guitar keeps it grounded in a more intimate style. </p>



<p>The piece begins with an orchestral introduction, featuring what sounds like a saxophone and flute, supported by rich, flowing strings. This creates a smooth, cinematic atmosphere. When the acoustic guitar enters, it immediately adds the tone, bringing the familiar syncopated rhythm and warm chord voicings of bossa nova. The contrast between the orchestral backdrop and the guitar makes the texture feel both sophisticated and intimate.</p>



<p>The timbre is warm and smooth, with the strings providing a velvety foundation while the saxophone and flute add a light, airy touch. The acoustic guitar’s soft, rhythmic strumming brings a sense of familiarity and warmth, grounding the piece in the bossa nova tradition. João Gilberto’s voice, with its signature breathy quality adding to the song’s nostalgic and reflective mood.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to The Stranglers &#8211; Golden Brown</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-the-stranglers-golden-brown/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 17:31:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Developing Orchestration Skills]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=515</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I find Golden Brown, released in 1981, fascinating because of how it blends different styles. The harpsichord gives the song a unique baroque-inspired touch, setting it apart from typical rock and new wave tracks of...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I find <em>Golden Brown</em>, released in 1981, fascinating because of how it blends different styles. The harpsichord gives the song a unique baroque-inspired touch, setting it apart from typical rock and new wave tracks of the time. While the shifting time signatures make it rhythmically intriguing. Although the song doesn’t develop much harmonically, the subtle changes in texture and instrumentation keep it engaging. The echoing vocals at the end, in particular, create a haunting and atmospheric effect that lingers after the song finishes.</p>



<p>The combination of the harpsichord’s bright, metallic tone with the warmer sounds of the bass and guitar creates an interesting contrast. The overall sound is rich yet understated, avoiding any harsh or overly dramatic elements.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Céline Dion &#8211; J&#8217;attendais</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-celine-dion-jattendais/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 17:27:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Introduction to Orchestration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Developing Orchestration Skills]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=513</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This song is a beautiful example of Céline Dion’s ability to convey deep emotion through subtle musical changes. The intimate beginning drew me in, and the gradual build-up makes the final modulation feel even more...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This song is a beautiful example of Céline Dion’s ability to convey deep emotion through subtle musical changes. The intimate beginning drew me in, and the gradual build-up makes the final modulation feel even more powerful. The contrast between the rising vocal line and the return to calm at the end is what makes this song interesting.</p>



<p>The song begins with a sparse arrangement, featuring Céline Dion’s voice at the forefront, accompanied only by a soft synth. This creates an intimate and delicate atmosphere. As the song progresses, an acoustic guitar enters during the chorus, adding warmth and depth. In the second section, bass and drums join in, but the texture remains relatively light, allowing the focus to stay on Dion’s expressive vocals.</p>



<p>The melody follows a gentle rise and fall, characteristic of Dion’s ballads. The song builds gradually, giving a sense of emotional progression. The first section is soft and restrained, with Dion’s voice almost whisper-like. As more instruments are introduced, the intensity grows, but never becomes overwhelming.  gradual layering of instruments enriches the sound without overshadowing the vocals.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
