<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignments &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 17:59:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Revision of Assignment 4 after tutor feedback</title>
		<link>./../../../../../revision-of-assignment-4-after-tutor-feedback/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 14:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=764</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My reviewed score can be viewed here. In my revision, I developed the C and A&#8217; sections since&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>My reviewed score can be viewed <a href="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Assignment-4-Revision-Full-Score.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Assignment-4-Revision-Full-Score.pdf" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>



<p>In my revision, I developed the C and A&#8217; sections since the tutor pointed out that they were the most characteristic passages. In my composition, I explored and developed the uncommon harmonies and the contrapuntal section.</p>



<p>My tutor pointed out that both instruments had a number of challenging passages. As for the bassoon, these passages aren&#8217;t impossible to play and their musical sonority justifies them. The vibraphone, however, had some difficult passages, particularly fast chords of three notes. I changed most of the three-note chords to two-note chords without losing the sonority I intended.</p>



<p>As for the notation, I rearranged the order of the instruments, because the bassoon should be above the vibraphone. Additionally, I deleted the bracket in the vibraphone, changed the font for tempo, and adjusted the layout so that the gaps between the instruments are consistent.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reflections on Assignment 4</title>
		<link>./../../../../../reflections-on-assignment-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 13:09:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://shocking-purpose.localsite.io/?p=590</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For part 4 of this unit, I had the opportunity to explore how a counterpoint composition can be&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For part 4 of this unit, I had the opportunity to explore how a counterpoint composition can be developed with the main subject as the focal point. Bach&#8217;s fugues proved to be of great importance here.</p>



<p>I also explored tuned percussion instruments for the first time. I found them varied and versatile. I will certainly explore composition with the timpani and the glockenspiel.</p>



<p>As a result of listening to Ragtime, I also developed a better understanding of rhythm and syncopation in some compositions.</p>



<h3 id="about-assignment-4" class="wp-block-heading">About Assignment 4</h3>



<p>So far, this assignment has been the most challenging. The assignment was difficult for me for a number of reasons, but I suspect it was the challenge of writing something different that I placed on myself.</p>



<p>In general, I am not pleased with the composition. It has some parts that I like, especially the motif and some rhythmic details in section C, but as a whole, it doesn&#8217;t appeal to me as much as some of my other compositions.</p>



<p>Despite being aware that a university is a place where people take chances, I will attempt to create something I&#8217;m more familiar with in the next assignment to increase my self-confidence.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 4</title>
		<link>./../../../../../assignment-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 10:07:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://shocking-purpose.localsite.io/?p=582</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In assignment 4, I had to compose an imitative counterpoint for around 3 minutes using woodwinds and tuned&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In assignment 4, I had to compose an imitative counterpoint for around 3 minutes using woodwinds and tuned percussion.</p>



<p>You can find the final score <a href="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-43-Full-Score.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-43-Full-Score.pdf" target="_blank">here</a> and listen to it below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-4.mp3"></audio></figure>



<h2 id="the-idea-theme" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108541003 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Idea / Theme</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Having felt that my previous assignments were a bit on the safe side, I decided to incorporate the element of surprise into this assignment. It was important for me to try things I hadn&#8217;t done before. I wanted to go to places that made me uncomfortable and use my ingenuity to see if I could surprise myself.</p>



<p>Regarding the theme, along with the idea of surprise, this piece will be about a party, for instance, a wedding, where a dance will be performed by two voices. Then something goes wrong between these two voices, maybe an argument or an altercation that completely changes the mood. Ultimately, both parties reach an agreement and get back to dancing.</p>



<h2 id="the-structure" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108659753 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Structure</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The idea largely determines the structure. This turns the structure into an A-B-C-A-B. I envision this piece beginning with an intro (A section) that will be in the same key, but rhythmically different from the B section. When we move from the B section to the C section, there will be a change in key, time signature, tempo, and dynamics to create a full contrast. After this section, we return to the intro and then the B section.</p>



<p>The A section will be in a minor key, the B section in a major key, and the C section in a minor key. In this piece, I will start in the key of E minor, then move to its relative major key of G major. In the C section, I will use the key of B minor, which is a fifth from the key of E minor, because I want to create some contrast without sounding too abrupt.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-regular cnvs-block-core-table-1628498574118"><table><thead><tr><th>Theme</th><th>Section &amp; Triad</th><th>Duration / Tempo</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>The instruments present themselves and get in the mood for the party</td><td>A &#8211; E minor</td><td>~20 seconds at 75 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They party and dance together with one instrument initiating the dance and the other following</td><td>B &#8211; G major</td><td>~50 seconds at 95 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>Tension builds up and there&#8217;s a fight</td><td>C &#8211; B minor</td><td>~40 seconds at 80 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They come into agreement and return to get themselves in the mood for part</td><td>A&#8217; &#8211; E minor</td><td>~20 seconds at 75 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They slowly return to the dance and party until the end</td><td>B&#8217; &#8211; G major</td><td>~50 seconds at 95 bpm </td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 id="the-motifs" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108877461 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Motifs</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>As I was playing around with the piano, I came up with a motif (in red) that started short and developed into a bigger subject.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="1024" height="252" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-1024x252.png" alt="" class="wp-image-595" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-1024x252.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-300x74.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-768x189.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-1536x378.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-2048x504.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-640x157.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-960x236.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432.png 2172w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h2 id="the-instruments" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110169912 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Instruments</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Having reviewed a recent video from Philharmonia, I decided to choose the vibraphone because of the sustained sound it produces.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Instruments: Percussion" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-lJctvybAJ8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Philharmonia Orchestra (London, UK), 2013. Instruments: Percussion. Available at:&lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-lJctvybAJ8&gt; [Accessed 15 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>I decided to go with the bassoon for the woodwind instrument again because I am finding it to be much more versatile than I had anticipated.</p>



<p>The combination of these instruments seemed unusual to me, and I was not wrong. Youtube and Spotify returned few results, but I found this performance of a piece by Alexandre Ouzounoff that encouraged me to continue experimenting with these two instruments.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Alexandre Ouzounoff: Cependant, la lune se lève pour basson et vibraphone (2013)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vo1Fgqq8-Kw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>University of Michigan Bassoon Studio, 2015.&nbsp;Alexandre Ouzounoff: Cependant, la lune se lève pour basson et vibraphone (2013). Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vo1Fgqq8-Kw&gt; [Accessed 15 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<h2 id="the-composition" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110414281 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The composition</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><strong>Section A</strong> Bars 1-6</p>



<p>As an introduction to the piece, I composed a short section with both instruments presenting themselves in different moods: the bassoon is strong and sustained, and the vibraphone is fast and harmonious.</p>



<p>I was inspired by Stravinsky&#8217;s bassoon solo in Rite Of Spring to start the piece on a high sustained note.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Stravinsky&#039;s Rite Of Spring Bassoon solo by Gustavo Nunez" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xfg9IIXhcPk?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Nick B., 2007.&nbsp;<em>Stravinsky&#8217;s Rite Of Spring Bassoon solo by Gustavo Nunez</em>. Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xfg9IIXhcPk&gt; [Accessed 15 November 2021].<br></figcaption></figure>



<p>This introduction ends abruptly to convey the main idea of a piece with surprise elements.</p>



<p><strong>Section B</strong> Bars 7-26</p>



<p>Here, the time signature changes and the bassoon plays the main subject, copied by the vibraphone. With the bassoon playing a countersubject in E in bar 13, the vibraphone is now free to play the main subject in G, which now is a major third.</p>



<p>In bar 20, the bassoon returns to the main theme but starts in C, which is a major 4th of G. The vibraphone continues to fill the room with ascending and descending notes.</p>



<p>Both instruments start ascending melodies in bar 23, which leads to a climax and the end of this section.</p>



<p><strong>Section C</strong> Bars 27-40</p>



<p>The section begins with a low dynamic and just the vibraphone playing. Although the key changes to B minor, I wanted to create another level of surprise and ambiguity, so I played an F major chord on the high notes, while the low notes created dissonance.</p>



<p>This section motif is then played by the bassoon, accompanied by a steady rhythm played by the vibraphone. Sometimes the vibraphone completes a triad, such as the A major in bar 28, but sometimes it just plays dissonant tones.</p>



<p>In the absence of harmony between the instruments, the tension rises with minor triads and the tempo increases.</p>



<p>At Bar 36, both instruments play staccato, and the tempo is the fastest in the entire piece. The vibraphone continues with its ascending and descending melody, while the bassoon is more steady in its notes.</p>



<p>At the end, in bar 40, they are both tired of the previous part and rest in minim notes before concluding with a B major triad.</p>



<p><strong>Section A&#8217;</strong> Bars 41-43</p>



<p>The section starts with a chord in G major, marking a key change, and proceeds into a version of the intro.</p>



<p><strong>Section B</strong>&#8216; Bars 44-67</p>



<p>In this section, a bassoon augmented subject is played while the vibraphone plays the motif, followed by a counterpoint.</p>



<p>In bar 56, the bassoon plays an inversion of the subject while the vibraphone plays parts of the motif and triads.</p>



<p>In bar 62, the bassoon plays the main motif, which is quickly repeated by the vibraphone in increasing tones until they both end in a G.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-4.mp3" length="3017582" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
