<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignments &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2022 12:28:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Assignment 2</title>
		<link>./../../../../../assignment-2-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2022 12:28:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1037</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Richard Strauss (1864-1949), a child prodigy with exceptional musical aptitude, composed two symphonies and concertos for horn and&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsibles cnvs-block-collapsibles-1669374898215 cnvs-block-collapsibles-2" >
	
<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1669374898270" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="click-to-read-the-briefing" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">Click to read the briefing</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<p>Listen to Richard Strauss’ Don Juan for orchestra and read the score. </p>



<p>Write an essay or around of 1500 words discussing this piece.</p>



<p>Among other things, you may wish to include:</p>



<ul>
<li>some background information on the composer</li>



<li>an overview of the story on which the composition is based and a discussion of how the music conveys the story</li>



<li>a discussion of the piece’s Romantic properties</li>



<li>the instrumentation and observations on how the orchestra is used</li>



<li>other musical observations which connect with topics covered in this chapter.</li>
</ul>



<p>Include musical examples as appropriate. Find a balance between the ‘facts’ surrounding the piece and your personal views.</p>

	</div>
</div>


<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible cnvs-block-collapsible-1669374898271" >
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-title">
		<h6 id="richard-strauss-don-juan-op-20-1954-rca-recording-with-the-chicago-symphony-and-fritz-reiner" class="cnvs-block-collapsible-heading">
			<a href="#">Richard Strauss Don Juan, OP.20, 1954 RCA recording with the Chicago Symphony and Fritz Reiner</a>
		</h6>
	</div>
	<div class="cnvs-block-collapsible-content">
		

<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Don Juan, Op. 20 - Redbook Stereo" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/7mNOSNp8sa0wGYGzjwfuc0?si=46f949317cb74fa7&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>

	</div>
</div>

</div>



<p>Richard Strauss (1864-1949), a child prodigy with exceptional musical aptitude, composed two symphonies and concertos for horn and violin by the time he was twenty years of age. He hailed from Munich and was the son of Franz Strauss, a celebrated horn player who held Mozart, Beethoven, and Haydn in high esteem as his &#8220;musical trinity&#8221; (Kennedy, 2006).</p>



<p>In 1874, he attended the Ludwigsgymnasium where he studied music theory with Friedrich Wilhelm Meyer, conductor of the Munich Court Orchestra. During his studies with Meyer, Strauss learned about Mozart, Beethoven, Schubert, Mendelssohn and other classical composers.</p>



<p>By the time Strauss was 18, he had already written around 150 pieces in a conservative style that resembled Mozart, Beethoven and Schubert. But at 21, he began to rebel against this traditional sound.</p>



<p>In 1885, he moved to Meiningen to work with Hans von Bülow, a renowned conductor. He learnt about opera from Brahms and perfected his conducting technique, while being exposed to the two main currents of Germanic music at the time. Those advocating &#8220;pure music&#8221; (e.g., Joachim, Hanslick) hailed Brahms&#8217; music and opposed those who propagated &#8220;music of the future&#8221; (e.g., Berlioz, Liszt and Wagner) (Malheiros dos Santos, 2018).</p>



<p>Strauss met Alexander Ritter (1833-1896), a composer and violinist in the Meiningen Orchestra, who had an immense influence on him. An avid follower of Wagner, Ritterer shifted Strauss&#8217; focus from abstract works towards modern orchestral works inspired by literature. This was despite his father&#8217;s disapproval of Wagner&#8217;s music. In 1889, Strauss completed his first mature masterpiece Don Juan (Dotsey, 2019).</p>



<p>The idea behind composing Don Juan was born in 1885, during a performance of Paul Heyse&#8217;s Don Juans Ende in Frankfurt. However, Strauss&#8217; direct source was an incomplete poem from 1851 written by Nicolaus Lenau. In contrast to the classic conception of Don Juan as a rake and impostor, Lenau portrayed him as an idealist searching for ultimate love, eventually becoming discontented with himself.</p>



<p>In his composition of Don Juan, Strauss focused on the individual pursuit of an idealised form of love that perpetually eludes him. This is expressed musically through a continuous rise and fall in emotion that culminates in the protagonist&#8217;s demise by duel.</p>



<p>Strauss wrote Don Juan for a large instrumental ensemble consisting of 3 flutes (3rd doubling piccolo), 2 oboes and English horn, 2 clarinets, 2 bassoons and contrabassoon, 4 horns, 3 trumpets, 3 trombones, tuba, timpani, triangle, cymbals, glockenspiel, harp, and strings.</p>



<p>Strauss&#8217; structure of Don Juan mirrors the story told by Nikolaus Lenau, beginning with a presentation of the protagonist, followed by two episodes of love affairs and an orgiastic scene which leads to a duel with Don Pedro resulting in his (assumed) death.</p>



<p>At the outset of this piece, Strauss employs the whole orchestra to create a boisterous, heroic rising pattern which adds vigour and propulsion to the main theme.</p>



<p>The initial scene (beginning at 00:56 of the recording I listened to) appears to be the introduction of Don Juan&#8217;s initial conquest and romantic relationship with a woman. There is a duet between the violins (woman) and horns and cello (Don Juan), that culminates in a very interesting and surprising dark climax at G.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="456" height="1024" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-11.51.08-456x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1057" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-11.51.08-456x1024.png 456w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-11.51.08-134x300.png 134w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-11.51.08-300x674.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-11.51.08.png 624w" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" /></figure>



<p>The second scene (at 05:32) appears to be another conquest by Don Juan, suggesting a greater emotional connection this time. The plaintive flute and especially the endearing oboe melody are employed to convey the ardour of his love. This sentiment ultimately reaches a triumphant high point as the horns play the heroic theme.</p>



<p>The carnival scene (at 10:27) functions as a transitional section as it spirals out of control. It starts with tranquil strings, but quickly gains intensity and creates an intense atmosphere. As the scene progresses, Strauss juxtaposes various iterations of Don Juan&#8217;s theme on top of one another.</p>



<p>The fight scene (at 15:00) maintains the tension built in the preceding scene, ending suddenly to echo Don Juan&#8217;s death at the hands of Don Pedro.</p>



<p>The death scene (at 15:37) is an understated and sorrowful conclusion with the bassoons giving Don Juan a final breath.</p>



<p>Listening to the full piece is clear that Strauss uses the full orchestra and its individual timbres to express Don Juan&#8217;s emotional journey to the audience. At the start, he is portrayed as audacious and confident through sweeping arpeggios and complex orchestration. His love stories are tender and romantic, with Strauss employing range, colour and instrumentation to illustrate the character&#8217;s humanity. He accentuates Don Juan&#8217;s boldness through powerful instruments such as brass while utilising woodwinds to depict his insecurities.</p>



<p>Strauss&#8217; use of dynamics is a notable feature in his composition of Don Juan. As an example, it ranges between ff and fff only for woodwinds, horns, and strings in the A. Another example is the beautiful slow movement in L, which ranges from p to ppp. In addition to conveying the storyline to the listener, this creates an interesting contrast that prevents the music from becoming monotonous.</p>



<p>The exact structure of Don Juan has been a source of detective work for the past century, with the piece being described by some as a free sonata and by others as either a rondo or a fusion between the two (Hepokoski, 1997). Nonetheless, it is clear that Strauss wanted to move away from conventional structures.</p>



<p>Romantic-era composers sought more open ways to express their musical ideas, instead of the strict forms used by classical composers (i.e. Haydn&#8217;s sonata form). With this newfound freedom, they could employ melody, harmony and texture to evoke a narrative, a character or an atmosphere; thus new genres such as Programme Music, Concert Overture and Symphonic Poem were created.</p>



<p>In the collection of his thoughts, Recollections and Reflections, edited by biographer Willi Schuh, Strauss voiced his support for these novel orchestral forms. He stated that “New ideas must seek out new forms for themselves: the basic principle adopted by Liszt in his symphonic works, in which the poetic idea really did act simultaneously as the structural element, became from then onwards the guideline for my own symphonic works.” (Strauss and Schuh, 1974).</p>



<p>Strauss was aware of the pioneering progressions in Programme Music from Liszt, a pianist who revolutionised programme music with his novel genre, the symphonic poem.</p>



<p>The term &#8216;symphonic poem&#8217; describes a programmatic work composed for an orchestra which draws inspiration from a range of outside sources, such as poems, stories and artwork. This style of composition was adopted to meet nineteenth-century aesthetic objectives; by relating music to something non-musical, allowing multiple movements to be combined into one section and raising instrumental program music up to the same level as opera (Macdonald, 2001).</p>



<p>In addition, composers of symphonic poems had the freedom to alter the stories and characters, as Strauss appears to do with Don Juan. It remains uncertain whether he is faithful to Lenau&#8217;s representation, or if he uses melodic themes and orchestral colouring to suggest a character who is more actively engaged with life rather than one who is jaded. This could be described as the enchantment of romanticism in art, expressed by their search for unlimited possibilities in composition which allows listeners to enter into a realm of introspection and imagination rather than being restricted by form.</p>



<p>Strauss also drew much influence from Wagner, particularly in terms of chromaticism, harmonic structures, and the use of leitmotifs. In his composition of Don Juan, this is evident through the varied orchestration and gradual evolution of motifs to evoke drama and emotion. These musical ideas effectively convey the psychological nature of its characters.</p>



<p>It wasn’t just the piece’s structure and the use of the motifs that made Don Juan innovative. The piece demands great technical virtuosity from its performers in terms of range, breath control and virtuosic execution, as in A. This is emblematic of the Romantic era which sought to develop great technical virtuosity.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="486" height="1024" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-12.08.58-486x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1058" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-12.08.58-486x1024.png 486w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-12.08.58-142x300.png 142w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-12.08.58-300x632.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-12.08.58-640x1348.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Screenshot-2022-12-05-at-12.08.58.png 658w" sizes="(max-width: 486px) 100vw, 486px" /></figure>



<p>In summary, Richard Strauss&#8217;s Don Juan is a remarkable example of Program Music from the Romantic era. It displays his aptitude in utilizing various musical elements to convey the protagonist’s inner world whilst simultaneously stirring emotions in its listeners. Through the incorporation of leitmotifs, chromaticism and technically challenging orchestral parts, Strauss has produced a sophisticated and powerful composition that reflects music’s capacity to narrate stories.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1669375583098 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Kennedy, M. (2006) <em>Richard Strauss: Man, musician, Enigma</em>. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</p>



<p>Malheiros dos Santos, P.S. (2018) <em>Don Juan, op. 20</em>. Available at: https://www.filarmonica.art.br/educacional/obras-e-compositores/obra/don-juan-poema-sinfonico-op-20/ (Accessed: 29 November 2022).</p>



<p>Dotsey, C. (2019) <em>Insatiable: Strauss’s Don Juan</em>. Available at: https://houstonsymphony.org/strauss-don-juan/ (Accessed: 29 November 2022).</p>



<p>Meltzer, K. (2020) <em>Strauss, Richard: Don Juan, Tone Poem after Nikolaus Lenau, Opus 20</em>. Available at: https://fwsymphony.org/program-notes/strauss-richard-don-juan-tone-poem-after-nikolaus-lenau-opus-20 (Accessed: 29 November 2022).</p>



<p>Weinstein, L. (1959) <em>The Metamorphoses of Don Juan</em>. Stanford University Press.</p>



<p>Hepokoski, J. (1997) <em>Fiery-Pulsed Libertine or Domestic Hero? Strauss’s Don Juan Reinvestigated</em> [Book], <em>Richard Strauss: New Perspectives on the Composer and His Work (Sources of Music &amp; Their Interpretation S)</em>. Duke University Press Books, pp. 135–175.</p>



<p>Strauss, R. and Schuh, W. (1974) <em>Recollections and Reflections</em>. First English Edition. Amsterdam, Netherlands: Amsterdam University Press.</p>



<p>Macdonald, H. (2001)  <em>Symphonic poem.</em> Available at: https://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/grovemusic/view/10.1093/gmo/9781561592630.001.0001/omo-9781561592630-e-0000027250 (Accessed: 5 December 2022).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
