<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignments &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 21:17:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reflection</title>
		<link>./../../../../../reflection-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 09:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1860</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Studying Part Three was a real mix of feelings for me. I love the Romantic era in music&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Studying Part Three was a real mix of feelings for me. </p>



<p>I love the Romantic era in music – it’s my favourite. Especially because I like seeing how history has shaped today&#8217;s music and this era was particularly impactful in today&#8217;s music. During the Romantic era, people started to see musicians as heroes which is reflected in today&#8217;s famous artists. Music and songs became a way for them to share deep feelings. I also enjoyed learning about how music started to reach more people, making it easier for regular folks to enjoy and play. It was a time for the democratisation of music. </p>



<p>The exploration of Romantic-era music ignited this fascination with the concept of musical evolution. How composers drew inspiration from their predecessors, adapted styles to suit their creative vision, and eventually paved the way for new musical forms was truly inspiring.</p>



<p>But, even though I liked studying this period in music, I also missed doing the compositional part of my course: writing and making music is what excites me. That hands-on part is something I look forward to and wish I had more of now.</p>



<p>Similar to my experience with the previous parts of my learning, I encountered challenges in managing my time effectively. However, the support and guidance from my tutor played a great role in keeping me motivated and determined to make progress, no matter how slow it may have seemed. I&#8217;ve come to realize that the journey of learning is not always about speed, but about the steady and dedicated progress one makes, regardless of the pace.</p>



<p>One part I feel good about is my assignment on how pianos changed in the Romantic era. I spent a lot of time researching and it paid off. I wrote a well-structured text that shows how the piano became key to all kinds of music.</p>



<p>Despite the challenges, I felt a sense of accomplishment as I progressed through Part Three. The time and effort invested were worth it, as I had gained a deeper understanding of the Nineteenth century&#8217;s music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 3</title>
		<link>./../../../../../assignment-3-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 08:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Nineteenth-century innovations]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1853</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lately, I’ve been interested in the piano as a player and listener. Therefore, I decided to research its&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Lately, I’ve been interested in the piano as a player and listener. Therefore, I decided to research its development during the Romantic era. A new emphasis on powerful emotion, individualism and expressiveness in the arts characterised this period. As opposed to the reason and order valued during the Enlightenment, Romantic artists sought to explore the full range of human emotion and experience. Music was profoundly impacted by this philosophical shift, with composers experimenting with passionate, dramatic works to evoke strong sentiments from audiences. The piano emerged during this period as a revolutionary instrument that epitomised the Romantic spirit.</p>



<p>Gill Green&#8217;s &#8220;History of Piano Tuning&#8221; (2020) discusses the nineteenth-century upheaval and innovation in the piano industry, highlighting the rapid advancements during that time. The main innovation was the ability of this instrument to vary tone and volume based on touch, unlike the fixed volume of the harpsichord. Implementing metal and heavier wooden frames allowed for increased string tension and enhanced the piano&#8217;s capacity for thunderous fortissimo and delicate pianissimo voicings. The new double escapement action enabled rapid repeated notes through its responsive key return and hammer resetting mechanisms. Also, the expanded keyboard range of over seven octaves permitted a wider spectrum of tonal colour.</p>



<p>Ultimately, the new piano&#8217;s capabilities made the Romantic era paying audiences, especially the middle class, captivated by its ability to channel profound personal expression. This demand fuelled the prominence of new miniature genres and forms such as short piano compositions which perfectly showcased the piano&#8217;s expressive versatility.</p>



<p>Conversely, composers started exploiting the piano&#8217;s rich harmonies, creating melodies and dynamic gradations to conjure passion, conflict, intimacy and all shades of Romantic experience.</p>



<p>For example, Chopin&#8217;s nocturnes, such as his famous Nocturne Op. 9 No.2, spotlight the instrument&#8217;s singing lyricism and range of colouristic voicings to evoke moods from brooding melancholy to gentle bliss. Also, his études and preludes for solo piano, the Prelude Op. 28, no. 4 in E minor and no. 20 in C minor being two great examples for me, capturing shifting qualities of emotion through intense passages and lyrical melodies.  Chopin brought the bel canto to the piano, redefining its expressive capabilities and influencing generations of pianists and composers to come. </p>



<p>The piano&#8217;s expanding expressive powers also began to influence the sound and direction of Romantic orchestral music. No longer confined to a supporting continuo role, the piano emerged as a prominent solo voice within the rich orchestral texture, providing a contrasting intimate quality. Composers increasingly incorporated the piano as a soloist in concertos and symphonic works, juxtaposing its unique timbre and dynamic fluctuations against the grand orchestral forces.</p>



<p>For example, Brahms’ Second Piano Concerto integrates the solo piano part as an equal partner in dialogue with the orchestra, accompanying or contrasting with its passages. The most beautiful parts are when the piano adds a dimension of lyrical sensitivity and virtuosity to balance the orchestra&#8217;s imposing, expansive passages. Similarly, Tchaikovsky’s First Piano Concerto exploits the piano&#8217;s capacity for thunderous bravura and whisper-soft poeticism, especially in the third movement. It transitions from soft, to playful, to a raging force, enlivening the dramatic trajectory of the piece.</p>



<p>The piano&#8217;s small size and versatility had a significant impact backstage and may have contributed to the development of large-scale works such as ballet. According to Parakilas (1999), the rehearsal of operas, ballets, oratorios, orchestral works, and masses, was greatly influenced by the piano, as one instrument could stand in for an entire orchestra during rehearsals. This allowed singers, dancers, and solo performers to practice more affordably and efficiently.</p>



<p>The piano provided an ideal creative canvas for Romantic composers to explore new musical forms that departed from Classical norms. Short and personal forms emerged during the Romantic era as vehicles for piano solo composition such as rhapsody, nocturne, and song cycle. They all showcased the composer as well as the pianist’s virtuosity. Audiences were drawn to the drama and excitement of watching pianists conquer seemingly impossible passages and spark deep emotions through their playing. The spectacle of the virtuoso at the keyboard cultivated a “cult of genius” surrounding renowned pianist-composers. Their impassioned expressions of Romanticism struck a chord with middle-class audiences, who saw these artists as visionaries unveiling profound truths through music.</p>



<p>Liszt in particular cultivated an ultra-Romantic ideal of meritocracy, encapsulated in his quote “My talent ennobles me,” as noted by Greenberg (2013) in his analysis of Romantic era composers. Liszt became a hugely famous star, admired by audiences for his virtuosic piano skills. The poet Heinrich Heine coined the term &#8220;Lisztomania&#8221; to describe the frenzy surrounding Liszt&#8217;s celebrity and performances, which were known for dazzling technical displays. His prowess at the piano made him an iconic embodiment of the Romantic ethos of the artist-hero. His Piano Sonata in B Minor showcases how he could compose extremely technically demanding passages, pushing the boundaries of what was considered possible on the piano.</p>



<p>In addition to Liszt&#8217;s virtuosity, Clara Schumann, one of the female pianists to enjoy acclaim during this male-dominated era, set new standards for performance by playing recitals and concertos from memory, being a skilled improviser who brought creativity to her performances, and promoting contemporary composers like her husband Robert Schumann and Johannes Brahms.</p>



<p>Character pieces for piano also flourished during the Romantic period. These brief works captured a single mood, place, person or situation through music. Titles like Chopin’s “Raindrop” Prelude, Mendelssohn’s “Song Without Words” and Schumann’s “Scenes from Childhood” gave clues to the miniatures’ poetic aims. This genre allowed experimentation with new harmonies, textures and forms within a condensed timeframe ranging from just one to ten minutes in length typically.</p>



<p>The condensed scope, alongside the small size of the piano and the development of publishing, made character pieces quite accessible to amateur pianists. These short piano works proliferated in musical salons and amateur recitals alongside the more ambitious sonatas and concertos aimed at virtuoso performers. Even complex programmatic cycles like Schumann’s Carnaval incorporated character pieces as movements. The character piece&#8217;s brevity and focus suited the more casual playing of non-professionals in home settings. With the rise of sheet music distribution, amateurs could readily acquire these bite-sized impressionistic works to perform for their own enjoyment or for small gatherings of friends and family.</p>



<p>This also led to the development of art songs, with composers sometimes organising songs with similar themes into collections called song cycles. Schubert notably created song cycles like “The Fair Maid of the Mill” and “Winter Journey,” based on the poems of German poet Muller, both evoking feelings of sadness.</p>



<p>As the piano became more accessible, art songs became a popular genre for home music-making, providing women in the 19th century a unique opportunity. This led to an increase in compositions by women composers, unprecedented in previous centuries, resulting in their rise to fame. Fanny Mendelssohn Hensel, for example, composed about 500 musical pieces, including approximately 120 for piano and many art songs (Lieder), such as the elegant piece “Warum sind den die Rosen so blass.”</p>



<p>By cultivating these innovative genres for solo piano, Romantic composers ensured the instrument remained at the heart of mainstream middle-class musical culture. Whether expressed through compact character sketches or sprawling sonata structures, the piano gave Romantic composers their ideal canvas to paint bold new musical narratives filled with drama, poetry and intimacy previously unexplored in past eras. </p>



<p>The instrument shaped both listening habits and amateur music-making for generations to come. Its influence has been so profound that it is now the only instrument that features across all popular Western musical genres, including jazz, hip-hop, EDM, and rock.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1706305140689 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Green, G. (2020) <em>The history of piano tuning</em>. In: PTA News 04/2020 p.10.</p>



<p>Parakilas, J. (1999) <em>Piano roles: Three Hundred Years of Life with the Piano</em>. Yale University Press.</p>



<p>Greenberg, R. and Courses, T.G. (2013) <em>How to Listen to and Understand Great Music, 3rd Edition</em>. The Great Courses.</p>



<p>Hall, D. (2022) <em>Chapter 15: Music of the Romantic Era</em>. https://louis.pressbooks.pub/exploringarts/chapter/575/.</p>



<p>White, W.B. (2022) <em>Theory and practice of piano construction: With a Detailed, Practical Method for Tuning</em>.</p>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (2023a)  <em>Romanticism | Definition, characteristics, artists, history, art, poetry, literature, &amp; music</em>. https://www.britannica.com/art/Romanticism/Music.</p>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (2023a) <em>Fanny Mendelssohn | Romantic era, female composer, piano works</em>. https://www.britannica.com/biography/Fanny-Mendelssohn.</p>



<p><em>Get to know: Clara Schumann | LA Phil</em> (no date). https://www.laphil.com/about/watch-and-listen/get-to-know-clara-schumann.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
