<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 21:14:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Assignment 1: Reflection</title>
		<link>./../../../../assignment-1-reflection/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 20:28:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=604</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[At this point in the course, I find myself in a state of exciting tension. At the same time, I&#8217;m drawn to and apprehensive about the possibilities of collaborative creative practice. This duality reminds me...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>At this point in the course, I find myself in a state of exciting tension. At the same time, I&#8217;m drawn to and apprehensive about the possibilities of collaborative creative practice. This duality reminds me of my past experiences in a band. While I was excited about creating music with others, that feeling was often undermined by the energy drain that comes with my introverted nature. I&#8217;m not antisocial at all, but being around people drains my energy reserves quickly, which created a challenging dynamic during those musical collaborations.</p>



<p>Looking back, my response to this energy limitation might have been counterproductive. In an attempt to make the most of our limited time together, I would arrive with pre-formed ideas, essentially bypassing the open creative process that makes collaboration valuable. </p>



<p>From the exercises, what excited me most now was the example of Dubois and her work with the French Space Agency. Her ability to take collaboration to an entirely new level, creating work that has not only an artistic impact but also a personal transformation, represents the kind of ambitious creative partnership I aspire to explore.</p>



<p>This connects to my growing interest in exploring collaborations beyond the music field entirely. While my initial instinct was to work with other musicians, the readings and discussions with my tutor have opened my thinking to partnerships with people from completely different disciplines.</p>



<p>One of the most compelling opportunities I see is the potential for collaboration to address what I recognise as my greatest creative weakness: my tendency to generate many ideas without following through to completion. I have countless starting points that never develop into finished work. Collaboration could provide not only the external accountability of deadlines but also the peer pressure to think more deeply about these initial sparks.</p>



<p>However, this opportunity is shadowed by a fear: having to compromise my vision and accept others&#8217; ideas that don&#8217;t align with my creative instincts. I know myself well enough to recognise that I typically avoid conflict, which could lead to acceptance of directions that don&#8217;t follow my vision. This creates a paradox: I need collaboration to push my ideas forward, but I worry that the collaborative process itself might dilute what makes those ideas interesting to me. But despite my concerns, I am genuinely open to listening and trying completely different approaches. This openness could be my greatest asset in collaborative relationships.</p>



<p>My ambition is to find collaborative partnerships that function more like the Dubois model, where different forms of expertise genuinely enhance each other&#8217;s work rather than requiring compromise. The risk, of course, is that such partnerships are rare and require not only compatible working styles but also aligned levels of commitment and vision. There&#8217;s also the risk that my energy management challenges could limit the depth of collaboration I&#8217;m capable of sustaining.</p>



<p>Moving forward, I see collaboration as finding ways to expand my creativity through a partnership that honours both my introverted nature and my curiosity about what becomes possible with collaboration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 3: Reflecting on Your Experiences</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-3-reflecting-on-your-experiences/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 20:36:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=602</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My feelings about collaboration are mixed, but I can define them as cautious excitement. My introverted nature means I thrive on independent work, and I&#8217;ve found my creative output is most productive when I have...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>My feelings about collaboration are mixed, but I can define them as cautious excitement. My introverted nature means I thrive on independent work, and I&#8217;ve found my creative output is most productive when I have space to myself. The idea of sharing ownership of a project with someone else, and having to constantly articulate my thought process, feels like a potential source of energy draining.</p>



<p>On the other side, the idea of collaboration is exciting. I believe that working with another artist could challenge my assumptions and lead to completely new ideas that I wouldn&#8217;t have discovered on my own. I&#8217;m particularly excited about the possibility of exploring a different creative approach or even a new medium. I feel I need support in the initial stages of a collaboration, specifically in defining clear roles and boundaries so that the creative process doesn&#8217;t become chaotic or unfocused.</p>



<p>I don&#8217;t have that much prior experience with artistic collaboration in a formal sense. However, I have learned from my experiences in other group projects. I&#8217;ve found that when roles are clearly defined and each person has a specific, independent task, the work is more successful. This allows for individual deep work, with periodic check-ins to ensure everyone is on the same page. This model avoids the kind of &#8220;ideas all over the place&#8221; dynamic that I find stifling. In the future, I would approach a collaboration with a conversation about these preferences upfront, and I would be proactive in suggesting a structured working method to ensure a productive and positive experience for everyone involved.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Task 3: Collaborations and Ethics</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-task-3-collaborations-and-ethics/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 21:25:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=600</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Effective collaboration isn&#8217;t just a matter of working together; it requires specific skills and strategies. One of the most important aspects is defining the collaboration itself. Partnerships can range from simple contributing to a shared...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Effective collaboration isn&#8217;t just a matter of working together; it requires specific skills and strategies. One of the most important aspects is defining the collaboration itself. Partnerships can range from simple contributing to a shared output to more involved co-construction or socially-engaged projects. It&#8217;s essential to define what you can offer, who you need to work with, and the scale of the project. For example, a small project might be an &#8220;intimate to-and-fro with one other person,&#8221; while a larger one might involve a wider community.</p>



<p>A key part of working effectively is understanding group dynamics. The Tuckman model identifies five stages of group development: Forming, Storming, Norming, Performing, and Adjourning. Acknowledging these stages can help in managing potential conflicts and finding a productive working rhythm. Effective collaborators should be open-minded, adaptable, and possess good communication and negotiation skills. It is also important to establish clear parameters and a process for decision-making at the start of a project to prevent issues later on.</p>



<p>Ethical considerations are an integral part of creative projects, ensuring they are undertaken safely, with care and honesty. The ethics process involves identifying potential risks and planning measures to mitigate them. These risks can be physical, psychological, financial, or reputational. The Risk Exposure Rating can help assess risks by evaluating the likelihood and consequences of an event. Any risks rated as &#8220;high&#8221; or &#8220;extreme&#8221; need especially careful consideration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to The Kills &#8211; The Last Goodbye</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-the-kills-the-last-goodbye/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 13:16:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=608</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have been interested in piano music recently, focusing on how a single instrument can carry such depth. Though The Last Goodbye has a simple arrangement, the power of it immediately impressed me. The piece...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I have been interested in piano music recently, focusing on how a single instrument can carry such depth. Though <em>The Last Goodbye</em> has a simple arrangement, the power of it immediately impressed me. The piece opens directly with the piano accompaniment, setting a 3/4 tempo that establishes the ballad character.</p>



<p>The instrumentation here is simple: piano and voice. What stood out to me most was the timbre of the singe&#8217;s voice. It has this slightly rough, lower register quality, almost a whisper at times, which keeps the music from becoming too lyrical. When the vocal enters, it is conversational, resting above the piano. The overall texture is thin, giving the song an intimate sound. </p>



<p>While the musical setting, the slow, waltz-like rhythm, creates melancholy, her voice introduces a paradoxical sense of peace. It is not a crying-out sadness; rather, it is a calm, reflective resignation. I felt like I was listening to someone quietly accept an inevitable loss. This contrast, where the sadness of the music is met with a relaxed tone, makes the piece memorable. This simplicity makes the emotion feel real.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 2: What Makes a Successful Collaboration?</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-2-what-makes-a-successful-collaboration/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 21:07:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=598</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I find myself to be both a creative and a rational person. While I enjoy the spontaneity of creation, my rational side needs a sense of order within the creative chaos. For me, a successful...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I find myself to be both a creative and a rational person. While I enjoy the spontaneity of creation, my rational side needs a sense of order within the creative chaos. For me, a successful collaboration is one that respects this need while also challenging me to grow.</p>



<p>Based on this, my criteria for a successful collaboration can be broken down into three main points:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Clarity and Defined Roles:</strong> A collaboration must begin with a clear understanding of the project&#8217;s goals and each partner&#8217;s role. As an introvert who thrives on structure, a successful partnership would have defined responsibilities from the outset. This would prevent the kind of unfocused creative freedom that leads to many ideas but no concrete action. By knowing my specific task, I can focus my energy and avoid the overwhelm that can dampen my productivity.</li>



<li><strong>Balance of Independent and Shared Work:</strong> A successful collaboration would respect my need for a dedicated time to work alone. We would establish a rhythm that allows both partners to work independently on their respective parts, followed by scheduled check-ins to integrate our work, share feedback, and make collective decisions.</li>



<li><strong>Mutual Benefit and Discovery:</strong> Ultimately, a successful collaboration must lead to mutual growth. I would hope to engage in a process that challenges my current thinking and helps me discover new approaches and ideas. By working with a partner, I am exposed to a different skill set and way of thinking that I couldn&#8217;t develop on my own. The project’s success would be measured by how much both of us grew as practitioners because of the experience.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 1: Identifying Working Styles</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-1-identifying-working-styles/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 20:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=596</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My working style is deeply tied to my personality as an introvert. I get my energy from being alone, and while I love being with others and am a social person, my energy can be...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>My working style is deeply tied to my personality as an introvert. I get my energy from being alone, and while I love being with others and am a social person, my energy can be quickly drained, even in online settings. For this reason, my creative process thrives when I am working independently. </p>



<p>I like to have boundaries and constraints. I find that I am most productive when given a clear task to focus on, as I prefer to avoid the overwhelm of a blank page. Another good constraint on this process is time. Deadlines create a necessary pressure that helps me move past a desire for unachievable perfection and instead focus on getting the work done. This balance of quiet, focused work with a clear goal is where I am most effective.</p>



<p>Given my style, I have learned that collaboration is most successful for me when it has clear roles. When roles are undefined, creative freedom can get in the way of focus, leading to a lot of ideas but no concrete action. This lack of structure can dampen my productivity.</p>



<p>My ideal approach to collaboration is to have a defined role that allows for independent work. For example, on a writing project, I would thrive on being responsible for a specific chapter or section. I would do my research and writing alone, then meet with my partner to integrate our work, edit, and discuss the overall flow. This approach allows me to bring my best independent work to the project while still benefiting from the ideas and skills of a partner.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Joy Crookes &#8211; Skin</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-joy-crookes-skin/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 13:09:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=606</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I first hear &#8220;Skin,&#8221; I am struck by its immediate, almost cinematic quality, which is rooted in its instrumental texture. The introduction is marked by a deliberate and stately piano line, establishing a gentle...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When I first hear &#8220;Skin,&#8221; I am struck by its immediate, almost cinematic quality, which is rooted in its instrumental texture. The introduction is marked by a deliberate and stately piano line, establishing a gentle but firm rhythmic pulse in a ballad tempo. This immediately gives the piece a meditative, perhaps melancholic, quality.</p>



<p>The instrumentation and texture are what really make this piece captivating for me. It is a soul-jazz ballad, but it is elevated by the use of orchestral elements. As the first verse begins, Crookes&#8217; voice, with a smoky, rich timbre, is front and center. Underneath the vocal melody, the texture is sparse, dominated by a simple piano. However, it is the entrance of the string section that acts as the primary structural marker. The strings bring a warm lush, rising counter-melody, adding a grandiosity that contrasts beautifully with the intimacy of the piano.</p>



<p>The overall emotional interpretation I take from the piece is one of tender, yet strong, reassurance. The music speaks of resilience and self-acceptance. It is not a song of dramatic conflict, but rather a reflective thought. It makes me wonder about the specific person Crookes was thinking of, and how much a simple, beautiful melody can carry the weight of life&#8217;s biggest struggles.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Task 2: Reflecting on Examples</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-task-2-reflecting-on-examples/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 21:12:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=594</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Kitsou Dubois example particularly stuck with me because it represents such a bold leap into unknown territory. I find it particularly interesting how Dubois kept her identity as an artist and researcher while working...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Kitsou Dubois example particularly stuck with me because it represents such a bold leap into unknown territory. I find it particularly interesting how Dubois kept her identity as an artist and researcher while working outside of traditional dance spaces.</p>



<p>This is an example of Complementary Collaboration within John-Steiner&#8217;s model, as each party contributed specific knowledge that enhanced the other&#8217;s work. In 1990, Dubois, a choreographer and dance researcher, became the first artist to experience weightlessness in a parabolic flight with the French Space Agency. This partnership meant her expertise in movement complemented the scientific knowledge of microgravity.</p>



<p>The partnership led to new discoveries. The collaboration showed how weightlessness can extend the expressive moment of a dance to infinity. Dubois also created dance protocols that helped astronauts combat space sickness, giving her work scientific value. The work did have challenges. It required bridging different languages, adapting her practice to safety protocols, and translating her movement experiences into data.</p>



<p>This case study has made me think about my own hesitation to collaborate. I work independently, partly for creative control, but I am also beginning to realise it&#8217;s from a fear of having to explain my processes to people from other fields.</p>



<p>Dubois&#8217;s example suggests that collaboration does not require giving up your identity or artistic vision. Instead, it can expand how you realise that vision. The key is to find collaborators whose needs align with your interests, rather than forcing connections.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Task 1: Typology of Collaboration</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-task-1-typology-of-collaboration/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 20:59:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=592</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Creative partnerships thrive when individuals complement each other in style, temperament, disciplinary training, and specific vision. The expression &#8220;revealing mirrors&#8221; resonated with me because it suggests that these partnerships have the power to show both...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Creative partnerships thrive when individuals complement each other in style, temperament, disciplinary training, and specific vision. The expression &#8220;revealing mirrors&#8221; resonated with me because it suggests that these partnerships have the power to show both complementary and at the same time, antagonistic points of view. It&#8217;s almost like a special sum of 1+1=3 because the gains from a creative partnership extend to both individual solo works and the joint project. This is a powerful reminder. My natural inclination might be to seek out collaborators who share my exact vision or working method, assuming it will lead to smoother progress. But in reality, someone completely different from me can unleash a powerful result.</p>



<p>The idea that struck me most was that creativity springs solely from an individual is a &#8220;debilitating myth.&#8221; This resonates strongly. I frequently find myself battling the internal pressure to do it all myself. This myth can isolate me and limit my potential. I need to consciously acknowledge that my creative output can be much more influenced by mentors, peers, and the broader creative community.</p>



<p>But collaboration requires significant joint thought and understanding. There must be an openness for critique, judgment, and the allowance for different personalities to momentarily suspend their individual artistic or professional persona.</p>



<p>The types of collaboration are a novel concept for me, which leads me to wonder: before embarking on a new project, should I reflect on which type of collaboration I&#8217;m aiming for? Is it important to think about whether I&#8217;m looking for efficient output and a synergistic combination of distinct skills (complementary)? Or am I striving for a deeper, more transformative fusion of minds that might redefine an artistic or intellectual paradigm (integrative)? Or should creative partnerships be allowed to flourish naturally? I still don&#8217;t have an answer, but I hope to find it during my unit.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
