<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 12:29:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Franz Liszt &#8211; Les Préludes</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-franz-liszt-les-preludes/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 13:43:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1039</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Les Préludes is a symphonic poem composed by Franz Liszt and premiered in 1854. His symphonic poem is&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Les Préludes (Franz Liszt)  Daniel Barenboim mit Berlin Philharmoniker - Staatsoper Berlin (1998)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jb2bkVQwtBs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Les Préludes is a symphonic poem composed by Franz Liszt and premiered in 1854. His symphonic poem is one of his most famous compositions and is often seen as a paradigmatic example of the genre. This work is based on a poem by Alphonse de Lamartine of the same name that explores ideas of fate and destiny. Liszt uses a variety of musical devices to illustrate Lamartine&#8217;s poem, including changes in tempo and dynamics, harmonic shifts, and orchestral colour.</p>



<p>Liszt&#8217;s use of thematic transformation in Les Préludes is one of the most striking aspects of the work. Thematic transformation is a compositional technique whereby a musical theme is altered or transformed in order to create a distinct idea or mood. In Les Préludes, Liszt uses this technique to significant effect, transforming the main theme of destiny into several different musical ideas that represent different aspects of the poem.</p>



<p>Beginning with three notes (C-B-E), the piece is a dreamy introduction. In a thematic transformation, this motif will be repeated throughout the work. Using this single motif, the music moves from a dawn of enchantment to a tumultuous battle to a triumphant ending.</p>



<p>My first experience listening to Liszt&#8217;s Les Préludes was incredibly moving. Liszt&#8217;s use of thematic transformation made me feel the tension he had created, although sometimes it was challenging to discern where the main theme was. I really like this piece of music.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1669815713034 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><em>Les Préludes | work by Liszt</em> (2013). Available at: https://www.britannica.com/topic/Les-Preludes (Accessed: 30 November 2022).</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Luís de Freitas Branco &#8211; Suite Alentejana No. 1</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-luis-de-freitas-branco-suite-alentejana-no-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 15:11:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1063</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Luís de Freitas Branco was a Portuguese composer, musicologist, and professor of music who played a pre-eminent part&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Suite alentejana No.1: III. Finale: Allegro" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/0XB5x9beMMdC11MLxJh6Ps?si=f3a82eba5a5c40f8&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Luís de Freitas Branco was a Portuguese composer, musicologist, and professor of music who played a pre-eminent part in developing Portuguese music in the first half of the 20th century. He wrote over 150 pieces of music, including orchestral works, chamber music and works for the stage, as well as songs and choral works. Suite Alentejana No. 1 is one of his most famous works and is known for its energetic rhythms, colourful orchestration and vibrant melodies.</p>



<p>The piece is written for a large orchestra with 3 flutes, 2 oboes, Cor Anglais, 2 clarinets, bass clarinet, 2 bassoons, 4 trumpets, 3 trombones, tuba, timpani, bass drum, cymbals, triangle, castanets and harp, as well as strings.</p>



<p>Luís de Freitas Branco&#8217;s Suite Alentejana No. 1, written in 1919, is a celebrated work demonstrating his preference for Portugal&#8217;s Alentejo region. Personally, the third and final movement, known as the Fandango, stands out for its vibrant energy and eloquent orchestration. It is written for orchestra with elements of folk music from Alentejo such as a binary-metered rhythm and castanets incorporated into the piece. The form of the piece is tripartite (A-B-A), with a Cor Anglais solo leading to a choral section in between two energised sections featuring returning themes. As we close the Fandango brilliantly, the exuberance and vigour of the first section return.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Georg Philipp Telemann &#8211; Sonata in D Major, TWV 44:1</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-georg-philipp-telemann-sonata-in-d-major-twv-441/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 14:36:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1043</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sonata in D Major, TWV 44:1 is a piece of Baroque music composed by the German composer Georg&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Georg Philipp Telemann - Trumpet Sonata in D major, TWV 44:1. Trumpet: Maurice André." width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iUhXRvEPuC4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Sonata in D Major, TWV 44:1 is a piece of Baroque music composed by the German composer Georg Philipp Telemann (1681-1767). It combines elements of concerto and suite genres and is composed for trumpet, strings, and basso continuo.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Three movements make up the piece, each with its own distinctive character. In Sinfonia Spirituoso, the opening trumpet fanfare presents a lively and energetic start. The second movement, Largo, displays two violins in intimate harmony with the basso continuo. With its lively tempo and energetic tone, the closing movement Vivace brings the piece to a triumphant conclusion.</p>



<p>I found it to be a captivating work of Baroque music with an interesting and multifaceted composition. The opening fanfare immediately captivated me with its bold and triumphant sound.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to The Pharcyde &#8211; Runnin</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-the-pharcyde-runnin/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 13:28:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=984</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the last few weeks, I&#8217;ve been reading the book Dilla Time, about the life of James DeWitt&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the last few weeks, I&#8217;ve been reading the book Dilla Time, about the life of James DeWitt Yancey, better known as J Dilla and Jay Dee. He was an American record producer, drummer, rapper, songwriter, and rapper. It is Dilla&#8217;s &#8220;drunk&#8221;, and &#8220;laid back&#8221; time-feel that makes his work unique and difficult to interpret, define, or translate. His production style has inspired some of the world&#8217;s most renowned pop, hip-hop, and jazz musicians &#8212; achieved, in part, because he didn&#8217;t quantize his music (Fitzpatrick, 2011).</p>



<p>While I don&#8217;t listen to a lot of hip-hop, I was intrigued by his stories and how he blew everyone away with his eccentric rhythms, so I decided to check out some of the music he produced or composed (Stadnicki, 2017). My favourite was Running by The Pharcyde, released in 1995.</p>



<p>It begins with a simple maracas sample from James Moody, followed by acoustic guitar from Luiz Bonfá. As I listen to these samples, I realize that the tempo is not always right. I start to understand why people talk about J Dilla when the drums start playing. It seems like the kick drum is rushing (perhaps running?) while the snare is dragging after the hi-hats. This results in strangely relaxed music, with an endless forward motion.</p>



<p>These kinds of not quantized drum sounds are somehow normal nowadays and explored by a lot of musicians, but I can imagine how refreshing it was to listen to such a relaxed and “humanized” beat after listening to so much on-tempo electronic music from the late ’80s and early ’90s.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1667471184588 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Fitzpatrick, R. (2011) <em>J Dilla: The mozart of hip-hop</em>, <em>The Guardian</em>. Guardian News and Media. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/2011/jan/27/j-dilla-suite-ma-dukes (Accessed: November 3, 2022).</p>



<p>Stadnicki, D.A. (2017) “Play like jay: Pedagogies of drum kit performance after J Dilla,” <em>Journal of Popular Music Education</em>, 1(3), pp. 253–280. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1386/jpme.1.3.253_1.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Aaron Copland &#8211; Letter from Home</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-aaron-copland-letter-from-home/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 15:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1049</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[“Letter from Home” is a composition by American composer Aaron Copland, written in 1944 and commissioned as a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Letter from Home" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4BmuwW29smvsvayXpXD0uo?si=338fb8e5c25f456f&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>“Letter from Home” is a composition by American composer Aaron Copland, written in 1944 and commissioned as a patriotic work by Paul Whiteman for his Radio Hall of Fame Orchestra. The piece is a reflection on the experiences of soldiers returning home from war, and the changes that they have undergone during their time away. The piece is written in the style of a letter from a soldier to his family and conveys the bittersweet emotions of coming home after having seen the horrors of war.</p>



<p>The piece begins with a sombre, reflective melody, as the soldier reflects on his experiences and considers the changes that have taken place in his life since departing. The music slowly builds to a more upbeat, hopeful tone, as the soldier finds comfort in the thought of being reunited with his family and friends. The piece ends with a triumphant, joyous melody, as the soldier celebrates the joy of being home. The instrumentation is sparse and haunting, evoking a sense of loneliness and longing.</p>



<p>Ultimately, “Letter from Home” is a powerful and poignant tribute to the soldiers who have sacrificed so much for their country. Through its emotional intensity and evocative musical language, Copland captures the complex emotions of a soldier returning home.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Keith Jarrett &#8211; My Song</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-keith-jarrett-my-song/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 13:48:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1046</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Keith Jarrett is a celebrated American jazz musician and composer. He has been active since the 1960s and&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: My Song" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1fZWZxwDpzMw9qkGv17d4c?si=ba376f2beb304fd8&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Keith Jarrett is a celebrated American jazz musician and composer. He has been active since the 1960s and has released several acclaimed albums, such as My Song, which came out in 1978. His music often features a sublime simplicity and directness that has made it a favorite among jazz enthusiasts.</p>



<p>The title track of Keith Jarrett&#8217;s 1978 album, My Song, is a timeless piece featuring the collaborative efforts of the European Quartet. The melody is introduced by a pensive piano movement that is soon joined by Jan Garabek&#8217;s saxophone and Jon Christensen&#8217;s percussion, which uses shakers and cymbals to create a soft and muted backdrop. Over the years, My Song has become a popular standard among jazz musicians, with Pat Metheny being one of its most notable interpreters.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Jörg Widmann &#8211;  Viola Concerto</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-jorg-widmann-viola-concerto/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 22:45:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=974</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It was while researching Berlioz&#8217;s Harold in Italy that I came across an article by French violist Antoine&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It was while researching Berlioz&#8217;s Harold in Italy that I came across an article by French violist Antoine Tamestit. This article stated, in 2015, when he played Harold with John Eliot for the first time, he told German composer Jörg Widmann how delighted he was with the piece. Therefore, Widmann composed a viola concerto filled with narration, journeys and interactions with multiple orchestral instruments.</p>



<p>Based on this description, I decided to watch Tamestit&#8217;s performance with the Frankfurt Radio Symphony conducted by Andrés Orozco-Estrada.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Widmann: Viola Concerto ∙ hr-Sinfonieorchester ∙ Antoine Tamestit ∙ Andrés Orozco-Estrada" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_5WraTt_l_U?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>My overall reaction was one of awe and I still don&#8217;t know if I liked it or not. However, I believe that was the purpose of this concerto. In one interview, Tamestit explains that this piece is intended to disorient the listener (Todes, 2021). While I sometimes understood what the composer was saying, other times I felt disoriented and I wondered if it wasn&#8217;t just too much theatrical for show&#8217;s sake.</p>



<p>In the same interview, Tamestit talks about how the instrumentation is unusual. This concerto, for instance, requires the soloist to scream throughout and requires the pianist to hold a whiskey glass.</p>



<p>I wasn&#8217;t expecting such a theatrical performance with such an emphasis on the viola soloist. But as an homage or follow-up to Berlioz&#8217;s symphony, Widmann seemed to want to keep the viola at the center of this performance.</p>



<p>The viola is the focus of this piece, for me. As it takes the listener through the viola&#8217;s different sounds, blending and clashing with other instruments, and finding its place within the orchestra.</p>



<p>Berlioz&#8217;s symphony and this concerto have many connections, but for me, the biggest one is the instrument&#8217;s representation. In Harold in Italy, the viola embodied Harold, here the instrument symbolized itself. As I realized, Widmann attempted to meta-characterize the viola. And that was a brilliant idea.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1666218709706 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Todes, A. (2021) <em>&#8216;it is in my blood&#8217;: Antoine Tamestit on Jörg Widmann&#8217;s Viola Concerto</em>, <em>London Symphony Orchestra</em>. Available at: https://lso.co.uk/whats-on/alwaysplaying/read/1473-it-is-in-my-blood-antoine-tamestit-on-jorg-widmann-s-viola-concerto.html (Accessed: October 19, 2022).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
