<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignment &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 22:44:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Assignment 4</title>
		<link>./../../../../../assignment-4-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 21:50:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1909</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For this assignment, I listened to the recording of Prokofiev’s ‘Classical’ Symphony by the Frankfurt Radio Symphony conducted&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For this assignment, I listened to the recording of Prokofiev’s ‘Classical’ Symphony by the Frankfurt Radio Symphony conducted by Alondra de la Parra (2020) and the recording of Pulcinella (1920) by Stravinsky played by the Orchestre Philharmonique de Radio France conducted by Barbara Hannigan (2021).</p>



<p>From a historical perspective, the premiere of &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; in 1920 and the &#8220;Classical Symphony&#8221; in 1918 allows one to situate both works squarely in the aftermath of World War I. This was a period of cultural change that moved against the Romantic era, marked by emotional expressivity and complex harmonic language. After the apocalyptic experience of World War I, people started to favour practicality and realism in art and philosophy, instead of abstract and metaphysical concepts (Taruskin, 2010). In music, as Burkholder et al. (2014:798) state, this led to a move away from intense emotions, irrationality, yearning, individualism, and nationalism, towards a return to the values of an earlier, seemingly more civilised era, such as the Classical style.</p>



<p>When addressing the apparent paradox of twentieth-century composers employing eighteenth-century Classical idioms, it is helpful to leverage the concept of &#8220;Neoclassicism.&#8221; This term, as Burkholder et al. (2014:798) explains, denotes a deliberate evocation of the principles and forms associated with the music of pre-Romantic music, including Baroque. Neoclassicism in music emphasised simplicity, polished textures, and refined melodies, emphasising instrumental over vocal, standardising orchestras and forms like sonata and rondo. Both Stravinsky and Prokofiev can be found within this neoclassical framework, yet they applied these influences in uniquely individual ways.</p>



<p>The exploration of Igor Stravinsky’s &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; unveils an interesting journey through musical experimentation mixed with homage to the musical past. Composed between 1919 and 1920, and premiered as a ballet in May 1920, &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; emerged during a period when Stravinsky began to divert from his earlier Russian nationalist style, characterised by works like &#8220;The Rite of Spring,&#8221; to what would later be labelled as his neoclassical phase. In &#8220;Pulcinella,&#8221; Stravinsky recasts the music attributed to 18th-century composer Giovanni Battista Pergolesi and his contemporaries with a contemporary touch, embodying the initial states of neoclassicism in the early 20th century (Leitão, n.d.).</p>



<p>Although it is considered a hallmark in Stravinsky’s production, as a turning point in the composer’s style, there is no consensus about whether &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; truly fits the neoclassical label. Unlike typical neoclassical compositions, where the borrowed material is often reworked to fit a more modern style, Stravinsky keeps much of the original material in &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; unchanged. For Cross (2003:110), his additions seem more like an elegant enhancement or gloss on the existing material instead of a complete re-composition.</p>



<p>I respectfully diverge from Cross’ perspective. While I acknowledge that Stravinsky reproduces certain movements largely in their original form (such as the Overture, Serenata and Gavotta), I argue that he engages in substantial recomposition in other sections (e.g. Allegro assai and Vivo). It is imperative to go into specific examples to illustrate this further.</p>



<p>Listening to the overture, it is clear that there’s a classical sound to it. The memorable theme being played immediately at the beginning is a Gallant trait and a repetition with a slight change, resembling, for example, Mozart’s Eine Kleine Nachtmusik, K. 525. This theme undergoes variations throughout the piece, showcasing the classical hallmark of Ritornello, a musical device extensively utilised during the Baroque and classical periods.</p>



<p>The Sinfonia&#8217;s melody-dominated homophony and the contrapuntal exchange between bassoon and oboe work reinforce the Baroque feel (bars 7-9).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="165" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-1024x165.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1910" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-1024x165.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-300x48.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-768x123.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-1536x247.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-2048x329.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-640x103.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-960x154.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39.png 2452w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 6-9 of Overture: Allegro moderato </figcaption></figure>



<p>The classical feeling is further reinforced by the presence of traditional voice leading and the utilisation of perfect cadences. Ratner (1956) argues that in the Gallant style, full cadences are much more frequent and can be employed not only at the end but also within the composition. This is evident, for example, in the straightforward D major perfect cadence (bar 15).</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="674" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-1024x674.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1911" style="width:340px;height:auto" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-1024x674.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-300x198.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-768x506.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-640x421.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-960x632.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33.png 1312w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bara 15-17 of Overture: Allegro moderato</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Despite these classical hallmarks, subtle hints of modernity begin to emerge, such as the strategic use of dynamics to create a dramatic interpretation.</p>



<p>Stravinsky employs a similar compositional approach in the Serenade movement, adhering substantially to the original classical style of the piece while subtly integrating select modernist elements. The melody retains the lyrical, cantabile quality and thin homophonic accompaniment texture characteristic of the original composition. However, Stravinsky introduces hints of 20th-century harmonic practices such as the dissonant harmonisation supporting the sustained vocal note (bar 17-18).</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="847" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-1024x847.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1912" style="width:501px;height:auto" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-1024x847.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-300x248.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-768x635.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-1536x1271.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-640x530.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-960x794.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08.png 1622w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 17-19 of Serenata: Larghetto: &#8220;Mentre l&#8217;erbetta&#8221;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>This manipulation of the traditional harmonic language can often be subtle, cushioned within the familiar cadences of the classical style, as we’ve seen before. Yet at times, it can be unsettling, particularly when he introduces dissonant vertical sonorities, resembling The Rite of Spring, that challenge the listener’s expectations steeped in the conventions of tonal music. A notable instance is the Allegro assai, where a dissonant C minor 6th is repeated 21 times at the beginning and 33 times at the end, each time at Fortississimo. This kind of dissonant intensity diverges from the norms of the 18th century, where dissonances were promptly resolved.</p>



<p>The choice of instrumentation in the Vivo movement, specifically the pairing of contrabass and trombone, allows for striking timbral effects and contrasts that are far from a classical choice of instrumentation.</p>



<p>Furthermore, the choice of only wind instruments in the Gavotte is a deviation from the traditional classical orchestration, further explored by Stravinsky with the melodic line frequently alternating between the oboe and flute, with the lower register instruments also periodically assuming the melody. This is a clear deviation from typical Baroque era roles of clear melody versus accompaniment.</p>



<p>Looking at the suite as a whole, Stravinsky&#8217;s innovations emerge gradually. At first, the work resembles a straightforward orchestration of an 18th-century piece. As it continues, hints of Stravinsky&#8217;s style periodically appear, becoming increasingly obvious. The transformation culminates in the jazzy ending that foreshadows the sound Copland would later develop.</p>



<p>This oscillation between conformity and defiance of classical norms encapsulates the dual nature of &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; that could be seen explored by Prokofiev two years before.</p>



<p></p>



<p>Prokofiev tried a different approach for what would later be understood as his first (if not the first ever) Neoclassical work. In his Symphony No. 1 in D major, Op. 25, commonly referred to as the &#8220;Classical&#8221; Symphony, instead of reworking pre-existing material from the classical era, he created a composition with original material but “in the style of Haydn” &#8211; Prokofiev, as cited in Robinson (1987: 130).</p>



<p>In this symphony, which premiered in 1918, Prokofiev consciously adopted classical forms for each movement of the symphony, such as the sonata form for the first movement, a slow lyrical second movement, a gavotte replacing the conventional minuet and trio for the third, and a lively Sonata for the finale. In each of these movements, Prokofiev maintained the hallmark of Classical music: brief, restrained, symmetrical, transparent and scored for a small Haydnesque ensemble (Robinson, 1987:185). The light and elegant texture created by the modest orchestration of two flutes, two oboes, two clarinets, two bassoons, two horns, two trumpets, timpani and strings employs a classical ambient to the overall sound.</p>



<p>On top of the classical four-movement structure as we’ve seen before, harmonically, the use of D major in the first, third, and fourth movements, with the second set in the dominant key, A major, reflects the Classical practice of tonal organisation.</p>



<p>The melodies are brought forward and are discernible. The thematic and melodic elements are employed economically, reminiscent of classical composition, transitioning across instrumentation to create timbral contrast. One clear example can be found in the second theme of the first movement, presented in bars 19-20, and explored in the subsequent measures.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="428" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-1024x428.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1913" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-1024x428.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-300x126.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-768x321.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-1536x643.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-2048x857.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-640x268.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-960x402.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39.png 2218w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 16-20 of First Movement &#8211; Allegro</figcaption></figure>



<p>Within the third movement&#8217;s Gavotte, a brief interplay of counterpoint arises. The middle segment maintains a homophonic texture dominated by a distinct melody; however, with the entrance of a counter melody in the solo oboe (bar 21), a two-part counterpoint emerges, reflecting an influence of the Baroque era.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="763" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-1024x763.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1914" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-1024x763.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-300x223.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-768x572.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-1536x1144.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-2048x1526.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-640x477.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-960x715.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11.png 2062w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 19-23 of Third Movement &#8211; Gavotte</figcaption></figure>



<p>In addition to form and melody, Prokofiev incorporates specific techniques linked to Haydn and Mozart. The sudden bursts in the opening bars of the first movement recall the famed Mannheim Rocket figures that Haydn adopted. The extra silent bar at the end of the exposition is a grand pause, another Mannheim trait meant to stress the sonata form&#8217;s architecture.</p>



<p>However, Prokofiev also differs from the Classical style. There are many unexpected key changes and distant modulations. For example, in the first movement he surprisingly, and almost provocatively, shifts from D major to C major.</p>



<p>Additionally, Prokofiev adds complex, syncopated rhythms beyond the Classical norm. Specifically in the development section in the first movement, the orchestra falls out of rhythmic alignment, introducing highly modern syncopations.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="531" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-1024x531.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1915" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-1024x531.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-300x156.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-768x398.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-1536x796.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-2048x1062.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-640x332.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-960x498.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37.png 2434w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 131-135 of First Movement &#8211; Allegro</figcaption></figure>



<p>Finally, Prokofiev’s playful mixing of themes, witty contrasts and overall humour align more with the modernist inclination toward irony and satire than with the earnestness of the Classical symphonic tradition. His provocative modulations, such as initiating the recapitulation of the first movement in an unrelated C major, can be seen as a playful critique or jest at the conventions of classical music. This approach underscores his unique style, which often challenges and reinterprets traditional norms.</p>



<p>While both composers adopted a neoclassical approach in their respective pieces, it&#8217;s fascinating to listen to how each infused their compositions with distinct personal traits. Stravinsky, for instance, introduced his characteristic abrupt dynamics, unsettling repetitions and pushing the boundaries of instrumentation. On the other hand, Prokofiev employed his signature modulations and unexpected key changes. Here lies the beauty of neoclassicism. Its ability to evoke a sense of familiarity yet is full of novel elements waiting to be explored.</p>



<p><em>Word Count: 1578</em></p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="reflective-account" class="wp-block-heading">Reflective Account</h2>



<p><br>Engaging with this unit on the classical era of music history helped me develop several new skills. Most notably, I gained a much deeper understanding of the musical concept of neoclassicism. While I was familiar with the term in the context of visual arts, studying its application to music in assignment 4 gave me new insight. Realizing how cyclical arts tend to be was also an interesting takeaway. Artists often look back in time for inspiration, not usually to the immediate past but rather to more distant eras. I see this happening currently as more musicians use musical ideas, samples, and lexicon from the 80s and 90s, similar to how composers in the 1920s neoclassical period were inspired by the 18th-century classical period.</p>



<p>This assignment also allowed me to solidify my personal preferences within the genre. The dramatic shifts, unsettling sounds, and instrumental experimentation present in Stravinsky&#8217;s work deeply resonate with me. What truly impresses me is his ability to infuse classical forms with his unique style, influencing music for years to come. Stravinsky&#8217;s work embodies the spirit of innovation within a traditional framework, making him a composer I&#8217;m particularly drawn to.</p>



<p>However, this journey wasn&#8217;t without its challenges. My enthusiasm for research sometimes overshadowed the pure act of listening. Getting bogged down in historical details and technical aspects occasionally prevented me from simply experiencing the music on an emotional level. Moving forward, I plan to strike a balance between intellectual exploration and pure listening pleasure.</p>



<p>The exercise I found most valuable in developing my skills was explaining the essence of Haydn’s Symphony No. 104 in simple, clear terms. Distilling complex musical ideas and history concisely takes practice and I believe this strengthened my ability. On the other hand, comparing period orchestras to modern ones was disappointing, as I did not perceive the contrast I expected in their sounds. Perhaps I would select a different piece to better highlight their differences.</p>



<p>Listening to lesser-known composers beyond the trio of Mozart, Beethoven and Haydn brought welcome new perspectives. I was particularly intrigued by Muzio Clementi and hope to explore more of his and other contemporaneous composers’ work in the future. If I were to undertake a similar exercise again, I would set aside more time to go more deeply into the biographical details and compositional outputs of more minor classical-period figures, especially women. Their contributions to the development of the era’s predominant musical style deserve more attention than I could give them here.</p>



<p>Overall, I found this an exciting first step in more fully studying Western classical music. The discoveries I made have motivated me to continue learning more about music history across different eras. Understanding context opens up a greater appreciation of the compositions themselves, so I am eager to keep developing a richer framework through which to enjoy the fruits of musical geniuses past and present.<br><br><em>Word Count: 480</em></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1709330599039 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Taruskin, R. (2010). Chapter 4 Extinguishing the “Petty ‘I’ ” (Transcendentalism, I). In Oxford University Press, Music in the Early Twentieth Century. New York, USA. Retrieved 19 Feb. 2024, from https://www.oxfordwesternmusic.com/view/Volume4/actrade-9780195384840-div1-004009.xml</p>



<p>Burkholder, J.P., Grout, D.J. and Palisca, C.V. (2014) A history of Western music. W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</p>



<p>Leitão, R.C. (n.d.) Pulcinella de Stravinsky &#8211; Metropolitana. https://www.metropolitana.pt/musicalia/pulcinella-de-stravinsky/ (Accessed: February 19, 2024).</p>



<p>Cross, J. (2003) <em>The Cambridge Companion to Stravinsky</em>, <em>Cambridge University Press eBooks</em>. https://doi.org/10.1017/ccol9780521663304.</p>



<p>Robinson, H. (1987) <em>Sergei Prokofiev: A Biography</em>. Northeastern University Press.</p>



<p>Ratner, L.G. (1956) <em>Eighteenth-Century Theories of Musical Period Structure</em>, The Musical Quarterly, XLII(4), pp. 439–454. https://doi.org/10.1093/mq/xlii.4.439.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
