<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 23:12:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Rosalía, Carminho – Memória</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-rosalia-carminho-memoria/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 22:19:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Designing Your Project]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=629</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The global success of Rosalía’s new album, Lux, made it impossible for me to ignore, so I finally sat down to listen. In my view, the record is a triumph because it is a conceptual...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The global success of Rosalía’s new album, Lux, made it impossible for me to ignore, so I finally sat down to listen. In my view, the record is a triumph because it is a conceptual work where a mainstream artist takes the liberty to create something entirely different from the formatted pop we hear today. Among the tracks, <em>Memória</em> stood out most. Partly because I am Portuguese and I adore Carminho, but also because of how it bridges two worlds.</p>



<p>To me, <em>Memória</em> captures a deep sense of saudade through its inherent sadness. The dramatic contrast between the quiet instruments and the intense, longing delivery of the lyrics creates a mood of profound introspection. It feels like a bridge between the past and the present, where the minimalist production allows the emotional weight of the Fado tradition to shine without being over-produced. I found the experience deeply moving, as it proves that mainstream music can still be surprising.</p>



<p>I adore how the minimalist texture, featuring a delicate interplay between harp and piano, replaces the traditional Portuguese guitar, pushing the sound toward an ethereal, dreamlike atmosphere rather than a standard folk style.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
