<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 04:48:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Beethoven &#8211;  Piano Concerto No.5 in Eb, Op.73 I. Allegro</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-beethoven-piano-concerto-no-5-in-eb-op-73-i-allegro/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 04:15:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Exploring harmony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=619</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Because of my research on Cadenza, I ended up listening to Beethoven&#8217;s Piano Concerto No. 5, specially the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Beethoven - Piano Concerto No. 5 in E-flat Major, op. 73 (Brendel, Rattle) - full score" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8K-eFmYXGh4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Victor Nikolaev, 2017. <em>Beethoven &#8211; Piano Concerto No. 5 in E-flat Major, op. 73 (Brendel, Rattle) &#8211; full score</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8K-eFmYXGh4> [Accessed 25 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>Because of my research on Cadenza, I ended up listening to Beethoven&#8217;s Piano Concerto No. 5, specially the first movement Allegro. In my opinion, this concerto is a perfect example of Beethoven&#8217;s ability to infuse rhythm, depth a power into music. </p>



<p>This first movement starts with a rather unusual presentation of the orchestra and the solo instrument, in this case the piano. The orchestra plays open chords while the piano plays  flourishes of arpeggios, trills, and scales.</p>



<p>Then comes the theme, which in my opinion is a very powerful and almost a fanfare. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/score/r/a/raziya37xna3jfo5ipe1h63ulbuere0/raziya37.png" alt="
\relative c' {
  \override TupletBracket #'stencil = ##f
  \override Score.BarNumber #'stencil = ##f
  \key es \major \set Score.tempoHideNote = ##t \tempo 4 = 120
  es2~\f es8 \times 2/3 { f16( es d) } es8-. f-. |
  g4( es c) bes8. bes16 |
  es2~\sf es8 \times 2/3 { f16( es d) } es8-. f-. |
  g4( es c) bes8. bes16 |
  d2\sf es8 r f r |
  g2\sf as4.\sf f8 |
  es4\p
}
"/></figure>



<p>The development shows all the creative genius of Beethoven, who created a stunning piece that contains a repeating themes and different elaborations of them by both the orchestra and the piano. </p>



<p>One thing I found interesting is the duality of the piano &#8211; orchestra, because from my listening I think that the piano is more experimental and spontaneous, while the orchestra tends to stay more predictable and harmonious. I believe this was a deliberate thought of Beethoven to create some tension and interest in this 20 minute movement.</p>



<p>The cadenza of Piano Concerto No. 5 a.k.a. Emperor Concerto is a very short part of this piece and it was written by Beethoven, probably because he was unable to perform it and wanted to control all the narrative of this concerto. Following this Emperor Concerto, writing the cadenzas became a common feature among contemporary composers (Lindeman, 1995).</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1637813517228 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Lindeman, S., 1995. <em>Formal novelty and tradition in the early romantic piano concerto</em>. Rutgers The State University of New Jersey &#8211; New Brunswick, p.32.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Researching Cadenza</title>
		<link>./../../../../../researching-cadenza/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 04:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Exploring harmony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One of the things I&#8217;m finding most interesting in this course is that I&#8217;m putting names and concepts&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>One of the things I&#8217;m finding most interesting in this course is that I&#8217;m putting names and concepts in things I loved about music. It happened with counterpoint and it happened now with cadenza.</p>



<p>Cadenza is, according to The Oxford Dictionary of Music, &#8220;a flourish (properly, improvised) inserted into the final cadence of any section of a vocal aria or a solo instr movement&#8221; (Kennedy, Kennedy and Rutherford-Johnson, 2012). This music usually culminates in an extended trill, after which the orchestra re-enters, bringing the movement to a speedy conclusion, more often than not without any further participation from the soloist.</p>



<p>The practice of cadenzas originated in vocal music where singers improvised at certain cadences within an aria. The general rule for vocal music was that the cadenza would last no longer than a breath. Composers preferred that performers keep their cadenzas short to prevent interference with the structure of the aria. Since Mozart and Beethoven were writing for their own performances, they felt no inclination to keep things and took this opportunity to show their flashy keyboard skills (Fuller, n.d.).</p>



<p> In other words, it can be described as a parenthesis in music, where the author (in the case of a written cadenza) or the player (in the case of an improvised cadenza) take the liberty of getting out of the structure of the music and create a new focal point of the piece  (Bribitzer-Stull, Matthew, 2006).</p>



<p>After hearing some cadenzas (shown below) I believe that the cadenza has two main purposes: one in itself and the other within the piece. The first is to showcase the singer/player skills; the second is to anticipate a climactic ending. </p>



<p>Going back to the beginning of this post, now I know what Freddie Mercury (one of my favourite composers) was doing when, for example, he used a little cadenza at the end of Barcelona (at minute 3:50) or a slightly bigger one at the end of the live performance of Somebody To Love (at minute 5:00). In both examples, he was showcasing the vocal skills of the singer (Montserrat Caballé&#8217;s skill in the first example, which can be thought of a melisma) and leading the music into an apotheotic ending. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Freddie Mercury &amp; Montserrat Caballé - Barcelona (Original David Mallet Video 1987 Remastered)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y1fiOJDXA-E?start=230&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Freddie Mercury Solo, 2012.&nbsp;<em>Freddie Mercury &amp; Montserrat Caballé &#8211; Barcelona (Original David Mallet Video 1987 Remastered)</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://youtu.be/Y1fiOJDXA-E&gt; [Accessed 23 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Queen - Somebody To Love - HD Live - 1981 Montreal" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aA2IRoPFIn0?start=300&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>AgoraVoxFrance, 2011.&nbsp;<em>Queen &#8211; Somebody To Love &#8211; HD Live &#8211; 1981 Montreal</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aA2IRoPFIn0&gt; [Accessed 23 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>Maybe there are other examples of cadenzas in more popular music, but I can&#8217;t find them. Below are the classical examples I listened to.</p>



<h5 id="wolfgang-amadeus-mozart-piano-concerto-no-20-in-d-minor-k-466-mvt-1-allegro">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart &#8211; Piano Concerto No. 20 in D minor, K. 466. Mvt. 1: Allegro</h5>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart - Piano Concerto No. 20 in D minor, K. 466" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3KHvNDn-o0s?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This is one of the most cited cadenzas I found through all articles I read. Probably because it joins the work of two geniouses: Mozart&#8217;s concerto and Beethoven&#8217;s cadenza. Mozart&#8217;s Piano Concerto was given its premiere in Vienna on 1785, with the composer at the piano, but sadly, Mozart&#8217;s own cadenza was lost. A few years later in 1809, Beethoven wrote his own. </p>



<p>It&#8217;s full of contrasts and unexpected twists and turns and a fantastic final stretched with a trill that lasts several bars before the orchestra comes in. I was expecting a more virtuosic challenge for the pianist, but what I believe Beethoven achieved was a more emotional and impassioned cadenza.</p>



<h5 id="beethoven-piano-concerto-no-5-in-e-flat-major-op-73">Beethoven &#8211; Piano Concerto No. 5 in E flat major op. 73</h5>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Alina Bercu performs Beethoven&#039;s Piano Concerto No. 5 in E flat major op. 73 (full)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3TiYGxOQDYw?start=1064&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This cadenza that appears near the end of the first movement, was written by the composer itself and it is a really short but elaborate part of this piece. What I found interesting about this cadenza is that it fits the whole movement very well. It comes from the main theme and makes the passage to another theme.</p>



<p>Before the cadenza, the orchestra plays the powerful dotted quaver &#8211; semi quaver &#8211; crochet chords while the piano anticipates a bit of the cadenza. Then the short cadenza starts full of rhythm but then gently eases back into the tutti by accompanying the end of the “cadenza” with a horn theme. </p>



<h5 id="brahms-violin-concerto-in-d-major-op-77">Brahms &#8211; Violin Concerto in D major, Op. 77</h5>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Brahms: Violinkonzert ∙ hr-Sinfonieorchester ∙ Hilary Hahn ∙ Paavo Järvi" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UFl9xuYP5T8?start=1085&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Brahms wrote one violin concerto and it was dedicated to Joseph Joachim. The cadenza appears in the end of Mvt.1 and I believe it is full of passion and melancholy at the same time. It explores the violin capabilites, which fits the purpose of a cadenza: to showcase the player&#8217;s and instrument virtuosities.</p>



<p>The dissonant notes and the strikes on the chords convey a bit of rage that I specially aprecciate. With the runs, I felt that it had some rock and metal sound I used to listen to. It brought me memories of the extended electric guitar solos that showcased the guitarist skills.</p>



<p>In the end, the entering of the orchestra is much smoother than the Mozart&#8217;s piano concerto, and I believe this creates a great contrast with the cadenza, almost like it is a resolution of the violin&#8217;s anger.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1637722906186 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Kennedy, J., Kennedy, M. and Rutherford-Johnson, T., 2012.&nbsp;<em>cadenza</em>. [online] The Oxford Dictionary of Music. Available at: &lt;https://www-oxfordreference-com.ucreative.idm.oclc.org/view/10.1093/acref/9780199578108.001.0001/acref-9780199578108-e-1488&gt; [Accessed 23 November 2021].</p>



<p>Fuller, M., n.d. BEAUTY of music | the classical cadenza &#8211; American Pianists Association. [online] Americanpianists.org. Available at: <a href="https://www.americanpianists.org/apa-blog/95-beauty-of-music-the-classical-cadenza" target="_blank">https://www.americanpianists.org/apa-blog/95-beauty-of-music-the-classical-cadenza</a> [Accessed 24 November 2021].</p>



<p>Bribitzer-Stull, Matthew, 2006. <em>The Cadenza as Parenthesis: An Analytic Approach.</em>&nbsp;Journal of Music Theory&nbsp;50, no. 2, 211–51. Available at: &lt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/40283099&gt; [Accessed 23 November 2021].</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
