<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 12:46:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Claude Bolling and Jean-Pierre Rampal &#8211; Baroque and Blue</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-claude-bolling-and-jean-pierre-rampal-baroque-and-blue/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2021 11:52:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Exploring harmony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=687</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It is possible to use classical instruments like the flute in other genders while maintaining their identity. Composers&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="key-takeaways" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1636018788468 wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Key takeaways </span>
	</span>
</h2>



<ul type="rich" class="wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio is-style-cnvs-list-styled-positive"><li>It is possible to use classical instruments like the flute in other genders while maintaining their identity.</li><li>Composers can use both traditional and experimental composition to create new and yet familiar sounds.</li><li>There are still a number of huge commercial successes I&#8217;m not aware of and I should look into finding more.</li></ul>



<p>After researching Bach&#8217;s fugues, I came across Suite for Flute and Jazz Piano by Claude Bolling and Jean-Pierre Rampal. The music on this album is an exciting combination of a classical flute and a jazz piano trio.</p>



<p>This album has a really simple story behind it. A French virtuoso jazz pianist, Bolling was Duke Ellington&#8217;s &#8220;spiritual son&#8221;. During his career, he was a pianist, composer and bandleader who wrote more than 100 film scores in a variety of styles (John, 2020). The ease with which he adapted to other musical environments led him to Jean-Pierre Rampal.</p>



<p>Rampal is known as one of the greatest flautists ever, having made the flute a concert instrument and showing how it can adapt to different forms of music (Britannica, 2021).</p>



<p>As Rampal listened to Bolling&#8217;s Sonata for Two Pianists, he asked him to come up with an album that would allow a musical dialogue between a classical flute and a jazz piano (Sklar, 2010). They then composed and recorded the album as a suite of seven movements in 1975, which was a huge commercial success and spent more than a decade on the Billboard classical albums chart.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Suite for Flute - Bolling and Rampal - Baroque and Blue.mp4" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6r_2Qql4Qq8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Raul Martins, 2011.&nbsp;<em>Suite for Flute &#8211; Bolling and Rampal &#8211; Baroque and Blue.mp4</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6r_2Qql4Qq8&gt; [Accessed 24 December 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>One of the seven movements, Baroque and Blue, is the album&#8217;s first piece. Originally composed for flute, piano, double bass, and drums, this piece is exceptionally memorable after you listen to it for the first time. Rampal and Bolling combined two worlds the listener is used to in a way that seemed new and yet familiar at the same time.</p>



<p>Even though this isn&#8217;t my favourite track on the album, I feel that it is a good way for the listener to be ready to hear what is to come in the following tracks.</p>



<p>First, we hear the flute&#8217;s motif followed by an imitation of the piano, reminiscent of Bach&#8217;s fugues. Following some more imitation between the piano and the flute, a familiar jazz sound is introduced by the jazz trio. Here&#8217;s how the composers introduce the listener to the combination of jazz and classical music.</p>



<p>We hear a lighthearted, lively, and crisp dialogue between a traditional flute sound, which I feel does not quite capture the swing of jazz, and a jazz trio delivering cool riffs and a feeling of nightclub swing.</p>



<p>In the end, I have the impression that I&#8217;m listening to extremely virtuoso musicians who are trying something out of their comfort zone that, while not a masterpiece, is very enjoyable to listen to.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1640345882150 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>John, F., 2020.&nbsp;<em>Claude Bolling obituary</em>. [online] the Guardian. Available at: &lt;https://www.theguardian.com/music/2020/dec/31/claude-bolling-obituary&gt; [Accessed 24 December 2021].</p>



<p>Britannica, T., 2021.&nbsp;<em>Jean-Pierre Rampal | French musician</em>. [online] Encyclopedia Britannica. Available at: &lt;https://www.britannica.com/biography/Jean-Pierre-Rampal&gt; [Accessed 24 December 2021].</p>



<p>Sklar, P., 2010. <em>Claude Bolling: a living legend turns 80: Duke Ellington&#8217;s &#8220;spiritual son&#8221; talks about his pleasure with the success of his collaboration with Jean-Pierre Rampal, his musical influences, and his love of trains</em>, Flutist Quarterly, available: &lt;https://link.gale.com/apps/doc/A243799691/AONE?u=ucca&amp;sid=summon&amp;xid=db00a6d1&gt; [Accessed 24 December 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Kaija Saariaho &#8211; Vista</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-kaija-saariaho-vista/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 04:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Exploring harmony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=676</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Spectral music is about experimenting with sound through overtones and creating aural atmospheres through layering. Saariaho showed that&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="key-takeaways" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1636018788468 wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Key takeaways </span>
	</span>
</h2>



<ul type="rich" class="wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio is-style-cnvs-list-styled-positive"><li>Spectral music is about experimenting with sound through overtones and creating aural atmospheres through layering.</li><li>Saariaho showed that rules should be viewed as guidelines rather than restrictions.</li><li> A song does not need to depict a moving image. Music can depict a still moment, just like a painting.</li></ul>



<p>To gain a better understanding of what contemporary classical musicians are preoccupied with, my tutor challenged me to listen to more contemporary classical music. I chose Kaija Saariaho after reading that BBC Music Magazine named her the greatest living composer in 2019 (Fiilin, 2019) and the New York Times named her Composer of the Year 2021 (Barone, 2021).</p>



<p>Kaija Saariaho&#8217;s sound was completely new to me because I had never heard it before.</p>



<p>Finnish composer Kaija Saariaho, born in 1952, studied composition at Sibelius Academy and then moved to Germany to study at the Hochschule für Musik Freiburg. During this time she felt frustrated by all the forbidden things of post-serialist tradition. “You were not allowed to have a pulse, or tonally oriented harmonies, or melodies,” she said. “I don’t want to write music through negations. Everything is permissible as long as it’s done in good taste&#8221; (Posner, 2018).</p>



<p>In 1980, she first encountered spectral music in France, where she eventually settled. Throughout her career, her work has been influenced by themes that have circulated in French music for decades: melody and harmony derived from overtones, and the fusion of instrumental and electronic elements. IRCAM, which Pierre Boulez founded in 1977, has been an important part of her career (Ross, 2006).</p>



<p>Like Saariaho in 1980, I was unfamiliar with spectralism. The method of using overtones to examine sonorities was a different approach to music, although it isn&#8217;t completely novel in terms of music theory. Overtone series is the building block of Western music &#8211; the octave, the fourth, the fifth, and the major third. The beauty of spectral music lies in the way the different instruments explore and utilize the overtones without becoming dull and boring.&nbsp;</p>



<p>I chose Vista because it is a composition from 2021, and I was curious to know what a great composer is working on at the moment. I found this recording of the Helsinki City Orchestra conducted by Susanna Mälkki.</p>



<p><div class="yle_areena_player" data-id="1-50946353"></div><script src="https://player-v2.yle.fi/embed.js" defer=""></script></p>



<p>In my mind, music has always been like motion, like a slice of life imagined by the composer, or a scene from a film transcribed into music. However, I found that Saariaho&#8217;s music can be compared to a picture. In this still moment, all the acoustic nuances combine to create what I believe could be a musical photograph.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Vista, which has two parts &#8211; Horizons and Targets, left me with the impression that this was a scene that the composer had imagined. She describes this scene to the listener and how it made her feel.</p>



<p>The scene in Horizons is a very open one, perhaps a field or the sea. She couldn&#8217;t see the end of it, perhaps it was a very flat landscape. The scenery is serene, allowing you to enjoy nature&#8217;s beauty. I would love to see some paintings inspired by Horizons.</p>



<p>Although it uses the same instruments from the previous piece, Targets has a completely different soundscape. It is rough, dry, and turbulent. This looks like a mountainous landscape, with sharp geometric shapes everywhere you look. It&#8217;s not prettier or uglier than Horizons&#8217; landscape, but neither is it peaceful. Maybe it&#8217;s near a city and you can feel the stress.</p>



<p>I enjoyed listening to Vista because it opened up a new musical world to me. Also outstanding about this work is the score, which I found particularly interesting due to the detailed notation for the players.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-issuu wp-block-embed-issuu"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div data-url="https://issuu.com/scoresondemand/docs/vista_60023/4" style="width: 640px; height: 453px;" class="issuuembed"></div><script type="text/javascript" src="//e.issuu.com/embed.js" async="true"></script>
</div></figure>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1639632443177 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Fiilin, T., 2019.&nbsp;<em>Kaija Saariaho voted greatest living composer by BBC Music Magazine</em>. [online] Music Finland. Available at: &lt;https://musicfinland.com/en/news/kaija-saariaho-voted-greatest-living-composer-by-bbc-music-magazine&gt; [Accessed 10 December 2021].</p>



<p>Barone, J., 2021.&nbsp;<em>Best Classical Music of 2021</em>. [online] Nytimes.com. Available at: &lt;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/12/06/arts/music/best-classical-music.html&gt; [Accessed 10 December 2021].</p>



<p>Posner, H., 2018.&nbsp;<em>Du cristal (Kaija Saariaho)</em>. [online] Hollywood Bowl. Available at: &lt;https://www.hollywoodbowl.com/musicdb/pieces/1577/du-cristal&gt; [Accessed 10 December 2021].</p>



<p>Ross, A., 2006.&nbsp;<em>Birth</em>. [online] The New Yorker. Available at: &lt;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2006/04/24/birth&gt; [Accessed 10 December 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Astor Piazzola &#8211; Las Cuatro Estaciones Porteñas</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-astor-piazzola-las-cuatro-estaciones-portenas/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 04:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Exploring harmony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=673</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Trying to sound like famous composers can make you feel as though you are creating something of quality,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="key-takeaways" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1636018788468 wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Key takeaways </span>
	</span>
</h2>



<ul type="rich" class="wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio is-style-cnvs-list-styled-positive"><li>Trying to sound like famous composers can make you feel as though you are creating something of quality, but sounding like yourself will set you apart from others.</li><li>The tango rhythms are really simple, but if you play with tempo and melody, you can get a lot of variety. </li><li>In this work, the violins show that instruments can be just as expressive as the human voice.</li></ul>



<p>In researching Ragtime, I discovered that this music style resembled Tango in some ways. As it turns out, ragtime and tango share some rhythmic styles, such as bass syncopation (Berlin, 2013).</p>



<p>As a result, I learned more about Tango and one of its greatest composers: Astor Piazzolla. Although I had heard Piazzolla before, I hadn&#8217;t listened to his Four Seasons work. Consequently, I decided to listen to it.</p>



<p>Piazzolla was born in Mar del Plata, Argentina, on March 11, 1921. When he was eight years old, his family moved to New York, USA, from where he got his first bandoneon before moving back to Argentina and then again to the USA. As a result of all of this back and forth between Argentina and the US, he was influenced by Tango and Jazz in all of his work (Bach, 1991).</p>



<p>As a 12-year-old, he was already a prolific bandoneon player, until he met Carlos Gardel, one of his idols. He eventually became Gardel&#8217;s translator and bandoneon player as well.</p>



<p>In 1946, Piazzolla moved back to Argentina and formed his own orchestra. He then travelled to France for a Paris Conservatory scholarship. However, his secret goal on this trip to France was to meet Nadia Boulanger, one of the greatest music teachers to ever live (Burton-Hill, 2017). In response to a symphony he composed, she gave him some great advice:&nbsp;&#8220;Something is missing You sound like Ravel, Bartok, Stravinsky, Hindemith but you don&#8217;t sound like Piazzolla. Where is Astor Piazzolla in all this? What do you do!&#8221; (Bach, 1991).</p>



<p>Nadia Boulanger encouraged Piazzolla to pursue what would become known as the New Tango, a unique fusion of tango, jazz, and classical music. His favourite instruments for tango nuevo were the bandoneon, violin, bass, piano, and electric guitar.</p>



<p>I can hear all of these influences in his Buenos Aires Four Seasons, or in the original title Las Cuatro Estaciones Porteñas.</p>



<p>As opposed to Vivaldi&#8217;s Four Seasons, Piazzolla treated the four pieces separately rather than as a single suite. The summer was written in 1965, the winter in 1969, and the spring and autumn in 1970. However, he sometimes performed them together in concerts. In this composition, the four seasons are presented with the focus on Buenos Aires, meaning that each season is seen and heard through the eyes and ears of a city bursting with life and activity.</p>



<p>In 1998, Leonid Desyatnikov composed a new arrangement linked to Vivaldi&#8217;s work for solo violin and string orchestra. Instead of listening to this arrangement, I will listen to the original bandoneon arrangement played by Piazzolla.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Astor Piazzolla - Las cuatro estaciones porteñas (Compilado)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/x6Jv_JrjJIY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>It was generally very enjoyable, particularly the contrast between energetic and almost chaotic forces and subtle and gentle melodies. All of the &#8220;seasons&#8221; follow some kind of fast-slow-fast pattern, which makes them feel very different from what traditional tango used to be.</p>



<p>In traditional tango, the time signature is 4/4 and there are two simple rhythms: marcato, where there are four marks on the beat; and síncopa, where there is an off-beat pattern that includes a number of variations like the most famous Habanera. In Piazzolla&#8217;s&nbsp;Las Cuatro Estaciones Porteñas, I can hear both rhythms but particularly Autumn has a very interesting habanera rhythm.</p>



<p><strong>Spring</strong></p>



<p>The city is waking up from a rainy winter and moving towards sunny days in the spring. In a way, spring is the beginning of life. This is especially evident in this piece where the violin makes a sound that sounds almost like a shout of joy, at mark 01:00. People start moving out of their houses and partying on the streets.</p>



<p>Around 02:30, the calmer part begins and I believe this is a time for romance. As the Spring lovers appear and the seduction begins, Piazzolla demonstrates that Tango is not just about the party and energetic rhythms, it can also be about beautiful and tranquil melodies.</p>



<p>We return to the energetic motif at 03:20 because spring is about letting go of all the tension accumulated during the winter and enjoying the wonderful weather outside.</p>



<p><strong>Summer</strong></p>



<p>Summer in Buenos Aires is extremely hot, making it difficult to spend time outside during the day. I believe that&#8217;s why this piece is not as energetic as Spring. There is some repetition within the melody itself because that is what the heat does to you. Everything becomes more lethargic. The joy returns in the late afternoon and evening. During mark 09:30, we hear the same shouts of joy as in the Spring piece, as well as a hint of celebration and romance.</p>



<p>Piazzolla&#8217;s violin solo brings back the lethargy of the very hot and humid summer of Buenos Aires because perhaps in his mind the daytime has returned.</p>



<p>The joy returns at the end with a bit of joy and síncopa to help bring about a festive mood with the end of summer and colder days to come.</p>



<p><strong>Autumn</strong></p>



<p>While spring is the season for birth, Autumn brings a sense of death and tranquillity. Particularly at mark 17:00, the previous violin shouts have less power and sound almost sad. It brings melancholy to our ears with the nostalgia of spring and summer and the anticipation of a cold winter that comes slowly to us. I feel that by the end of this piece. There are huge, heavy steps of coming winter.</p>



<p><strong>Winter</strong></p>



<p>During the winter, the city moves indoors. Because everything is a little calmer and colder, the tango sounds a little warmer as if it could warm the heart of the dancers. In this piece, I believe Piazzolla envisioned couples dancing close to each other to this tango in order to warm each other and maybe have a little romance in the winter.</p>



<p>The electric guitar sound is quite dominant in this piece, which I believe is meant to emphasize the warm sound needed for the cold winter, just like a musical fireplace.</p>



<p>In the second half, the music starts to gain energy, probably trying to make the anticipation of the Spring to come.</p>



<p>Around mark 26:00, the sound shifts into classical, perhaps a nod to Vivaldi&#8217;s work.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1640084771597 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Berlin, E., 2013.&nbsp;<em>Ragtime</em>. [online] Grove Music Online. Available at: &lt;https://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/grovemusic/view/10.1093/gmo/9781561592630.001.0001/omo-9781561592630-e-1002252241&gt; [Accessed 4 December 2021].</p>



<p>Bach, Caleb, 1991. <em>Astor Piazzolla: a new-age score for the tango.</em> The Free Library. <meta charset="utf-8">Available at: &lt;https://www.thefreelibrary.com/Astor Piazzolla: a new-age score for the tango.-a011810151&gt; [Accessed 4 December 2021].</p>



<p>Burton-Hill, C., 2017.&nbsp;<em>The greatest music teacher who ever lived</em>. [online] Bbc.com. Available at: &lt;https://www.bbc.com/culture/article/20170308-the-greatest-music-teacher-who-ever-lived&gt; [Accessed 4 December 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Richard Wagner – Das Rheingold, Prelude</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-richard-wagner-das-rheingold-prelude/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 17:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Exploring harmony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=739</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One key can leave a lot of room for creativity. Repetition can be made more interesting by using&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="key-takeaways" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1636018788468 wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Key takeaways </span>
	</span>
</h2>



<ul type="rich" class="wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio is-style-cnvs-list-styled-positive"><li>One key can leave a lot of room for creativity.</li><li>Repetition can be made more interesting by using dynamics.</li><li>Leitmotifs are motifs that represent characters, objects, places, and specific emotions.</li></ul>



<p>This is a prelude from the first opera of Wagner&#8217;s mythic four-opera cycle, The Ring, composed in 1874. It begins on the Rhine, where the Rhinemaidens protect the precious Rheingold (Kay, n.d.). This is the scene that this Prelude establishes.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="DAS RHEINGOLD by Richard Wagner (Audio + Full Score) [RE-UPLOAD]" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VsR11uFzBJg?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>tomekkobialka, 2019.&nbsp;<em>DAS RHEINGOLD by Richard Wagner (Audio + Full Score) [RE-UPLOAD]</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VsR11uFzBJg&gt; [Accessed 2 December 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>Upon hearing it, my first reaction was that it was one of the most remarkable openings I have ever heard. Not because of its complexity or memorable themes, quite the opposite. This concept is actually very simple: an entire prelude made out of just one key, E flat major, that doesn&#8217;t go anywhere harmonically. Or maybe it moves to a perfect cadence after 136 bars, and E flat is the V of the A flat that starts the next scene.</p>



<p>In the Prelude to Das Rheingold, the double bass in E flat starts slowly and barely audibly rumbling. Later, the bassoon in B flat is added, followed by the rest of the instruments in a series of layers of repetitive sounds. As the piece progresses, simple notes played in a drone-like manner are accompanied by the increased and overlaid sounds of multiple instruments played without a clearly defined rhythm and downbeat.</p>



<p>The composer&#8217;s intention was to create a mood of birth, I believe. As in nature, the instruments multiply, much like the cells of a growing organism. Possibly here is the birth of the river Rhine, or even the whole universe as it sets up the Opera. When one listens to this piece with their eyes closed and thinks about the birth of anything, one can imagine it starting from something small and growing into something beautiful.</p>



<p>Researching this Prelude, I found that it is used at the beginning of the movie The New World when the English ship arrives in 1607 to establish Jamestown, an English colony in Virginia. This confirms my belief in the atmosphere created by this Prelude.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="The New World - Vorspiel" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lFkyAD9gS6g?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>tgureckis tgureckis, 2006.&nbsp;<em>The New World &#8211; Vorspiel</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lFkyAD9gS6g&gt; [Accessed 2 December 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>In researching this piece, I also came across the concept of Leitmotifs. With leitmotifs (leading motifs) Wagner represented characters, objects, places, and specific emotions. In this piece, there are three leitmotifs: nature or genesis, the river or Rhein and the waves (Trythall, n.d.).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1022" height="230" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.20.40.png" alt="" class="wp-image-741" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.20.40.png 1022w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.20.40-300x68.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.20.40-768x173.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.20.40-640x144.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.20.40-960x216.png 960w" sizes="(max-width: 1022px) 100vw, 1022px" /><figcaption>The nature or genesis leitmotif</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="388" height="138" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.23.01.png" alt="" class="wp-image-742" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.23.01.png 388w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.23.01-300x107.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 388px) 100vw, 388px" /><figcaption>The river or Rhein leitmotif</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="398" height="70" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.23.24.png" alt="" class="wp-image-743" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.23.24.png 398w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Screenshot-2022-01-17-at-22.23.24-300x53.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 398px) 100vw, 398px" /><figcaption>The waves leitmotif</figcaption></figure>



<p>My favourite thing about these leitmotifs is that they resemble waves whose intensity increases. In addition to being waves of sound, they can also be perceived as waves of a waking river &#8211; the Rhein. With these leitmotifs, Wagner, I believe, wanted the audience to feel that they were going down in a river and there was nothing they could do but go with the flow.</p>



<p>Having listened and investigated this piece, I now have a better understanding of the concept of leitmotifs, which was not created by Wagner, but taken up by him and developed to the highest level of musical expression in the four operas that make up Der Ring des Nibelungen (BBC Radio 3 &#8211; Opera on 3 &#8211; Wagner&#8217;s The Ring &#8211; Leitmotives, n.d.). From my perspective, this concept had a tremendous impact on music and influenced generations to come. Now, leitmotifs are a common occurrence in movie soundtracks. Think of Darth Vader&#8217;s theme or Jaw&#8217;s two-note suspense. Even advertising has benefited from the development of this concept since jingles have become leitmotifs for brands.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1642460265884 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Kay, G., n.d. BBC Radio 3 &#8211; Opera on 3 &#8211; Wagner&#8217;s The Ring &#8211; plot essentials. [online] BBC. Available at: <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/articles/3KgB2xl02TSCYYf0QkmZ8B0/wagners-the-ring-plot-essentials">https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/articles/3KgB2xl02TSCYYf0QkmZ8B0/wagners-the-ring-plot-essentials</a> [Accessed 2 December 2021].</p>



<p>Trythall, R., n.d.&nbsp;<em>UCCD2A Das Rheingold Leitmotifs</em>. [online] Richardtrythall.com. Available at: &lt;http://richardtrythall.com/UCCD2A.html&gt; [Accessed 2 December 2021].</p>



<p>BBC. n.d.&nbsp;<em>BBC Radio 3 &#8211; Opera on 3 &#8211; Wagner&#8217;s The Ring &#8211; Leitmotives</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/articles/5W3xDK5Y93WPlfbZj0s3LvS/wagners-the-ring-leitmotives&gt; [Accessed 2 December 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Beethoven &#8211;  Piano Concerto No.5 in Eb, Op.73 I. Allegro</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-beethoven-piano-concerto-no-5-in-eb-op-73-i-allegro/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 04:15:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Exploring harmony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=619</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Beethoven demonstrates how a theme can be repeated through a work and never become monotonous. Beethoven may hold&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="key-takeaways" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1636018788468 wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Key takeaways </span>
	</span>
</h2>



<ul type="rich" class="wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio is-style-cnvs-list-styled-positive"><li>Beethoven demonstrates how a theme can be repeated through a work and never become monotonous.</li><li>Beethoven may hold a large part of the credit for today&#8217;s concept of chorus in pop music.</li><li>Cadenzas can be improvised by the player or written by the composer.</li></ul>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Beethoven - Piano Concerto No. 5 in E-flat Major, op. 73 (Brendel, Rattle) - full score" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8K-eFmYXGh4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Victor Nikolaev, 2017.&nbsp;<em>Beethoven &#8211; Piano Concerto No. 5 in E-flat Major, op. 73 (Brendel, Rattle) &#8211; full score</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8K-eFmYXGh4&gt; [Accessed 25 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>Because of my research on Cadenza, I ended up listening to Beethoven&#8217;s Piano Concerto No. 5, especially the first movement Allegro. In my opinion, this concerto is a perfect example of Beethoven&#8217;s ability to infuse rhythm, depth a power into music. </p>



<p>This first movement starts with a rather unusual presentation of the orchestra and the solo instrument, in this case, the piano. The orchestra plays open chords while the piano plays flourishes of arpeggios, trills, and scales.</p>



<p>Then comes the theme, which in my opinion is very powerful and almost a fanfare. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/score/r/a/raziya37xna3jfo5ipe1h63ulbuere0/raziya37.png" alt="
\relative c' {
  \override TupletBracket #'stencil = ##f
  \override Score.BarNumber #'stencil = ##f
  \key es \major \set Score.tempoHideNote = ##t \tempo 4 = 120
  es2~\f es8 \times 2/3 { f16( es d) } es8-. f-. |
  g4( es c) bes8. bes16 |
  es2~\sf es8 \times 2/3 { f16( es d) } es8-. f-. |
  g4( es c) bes8. bes16 |
  d2\sf es8 r f r |
  g2\sf as4.\sf f8 |
  es4\p
}
"/></figure>



<p>The development shows all the creative genius of Beethoven, who created a stunning piece that contains repeating themes and different elaborations of them by both the orchestra and the piano. </p>



<p>One thing I found interesting is the duality of the piano &#8211; orchestra because from my listening I think that the piano is more experimental and spontaneous, while the orchestra tends to stay more predictable and harmonious. I believe this was a deliberate thought of Beethoven to create some tension and interest in this 20-minute movement.</p>



<p>The cadenza of Piano Concerto No. 5 a.k.a. Emperor Concerto is a very short part of this piece and it was written by Beethoven, probably because he was unable to perform it and wanted to control all the narrative of this concerto. Following this Emperor Concerto, writing the cadenzas became a common feature among contemporary composers (Lindeman, 1995).</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1637813517228 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Lindeman, S., 1995.&nbsp;<em>Formal novelty and tradition in the early romantic piano concerto</em>. Rutgers The State University of New Jersey &#8211; New Brunswick, p.32.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Researching Cadenza</title>
		<link>./../../../../../researching-cadenza/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 04:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Exploring harmony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One of the things I&#8217;m finding most interesting in this course is that I&#8217;m putting names and concepts&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>One of the things I&#8217;m finding most interesting in this course is that I&#8217;m putting names and concepts in things I loved about music. It happened with counterpoint and it happened now with cadenza.</p>



<p>Cadenza is, according to The Oxford Dictionary of Music, &#8220;a flourish (properly, improvised) inserted into the final cadence of any section of a vocal aria or a solo instr movement&#8221; (Kennedy, Kennedy and Rutherford-Johnson, 2012). This music usually culminates in an extended trill, after which the orchestra re-enters, bringing the movement to a speedy conclusion, more often than not without any further participation from the soloist.</p>



<p>The practice of cadenzas originated in vocal music where singers improvised at certain cadences within an aria. The general rule for vocal music was that the cadenza would last no longer than a breath. Composers preferred that performers keep their cadenzas short to prevent interference with the structure of the aria. Since Mozart and Beethoven were writing for their own performances, they felt no inclination to keep things and took this opportunity to show their flashy keyboard skills (Fuller, n.d.).</p>



<p> In other words, it can be described as a parenthesis in music, where the author (in the case of a written cadenza) or the player (in the case of an improvised cadenza) take the liberty of getting out of the structure of the music and create a new focal point of the piece  (Bribitzer-Stull, Matthew, 2006).</p>



<p>After hearing some cadenzas (shown below) I believe that the cadenza has two main purposes: one in itself and the other within the piece. The first is to showcase the singer/player skills; the second is to anticipate a climactic ending. </p>



<p>Going back to the beginning of this post, now I know what Freddie Mercury (one of my favourite composers) was doing when, for example, he used a little cadenza at the end of Barcelona (at minute 3:50) or a slightly bigger one at the end of the live performance of Somebody To Love (at minute 5:00). In both examples, he was showcasing the vocal skills of the singer (Montserrat Caballé&#8217;s skill in the first example, which can be thought of a melisma) and leading the music into an apotheotic ending. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Freddie Mercury &amp; Montserrat Caballé - Barcelona (Original David Mallet Video 1987 Remastered)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y1fiOJDXA-E?start=230&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Freddie Mercury Solo, 2012.&nbsp;<em>Freddie Mercury &amp; Montserrat Caballé &#8211; Barcelona (Original David Mallet Video 1987 Remastered)</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://youtu.be/Y1fiOJDXA-E&gt; [Accessed 23 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Queen - Somebody To Love - HD Live - 1981 Montreal" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aA2IRoPFIn0?start=300&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>AgoraVoxFrance, 2011.&nbsp;<em>Queen &#8211; Somebody To Love &#8211; HD Live &#8211; 1981 Montreal</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aA2IRoPFIn0&gt; [Accessed 23 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>Maybe there are other examples of cadenzas in more popular music, but I can&#8217;t find them. Below are the classical examples I listened to.</p>



<h5 id="wolfgang-amadeus-mozart-piano-concerto-no-20-in-d-minor-k-466-mvt-1-allegro" class="wp-block-heading">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart &#8211; Piano Concerto No. 20 in D minor, K. 466. Mvt. 1: Allegro</h5>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart - Piano Concerto No. 20 in D minor, K. 466" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3KHvNDn-o0s?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This is one of the most cited cadenzas I found through all articles I read. Probably because it joins the work of two geniouses: Mozart&#8217;s concerto and Beethoven&#8217;s cadenza. Mozart&#8217;s Piano Concerto was given its premiere in Vienna on 1785, with the composer at the piano, but sadly, Mozart&#8217;s own cadenza was lost. A few years later in 1809, Beethoven wrote his own. </p>



<p>It&#8217;s full of contrasts and unexpected twists and turns and a fantastic final stretched with a trill that lasts several bars before the orchestra comes in. I was expecting a more virtuosic challenge for the pianist, but what I believe Beethoven achieved was a more emotional and impassioned cadenza.</p>



<h5 id="beethoven-piano-concerto-no-5-in-e-flat-major-op-73" class="wp-block-heading">Beethoven &#8211; Piano Concerto No. 5 in E flat major op. 73</h5>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Alina Bercu performs Beethoven&#039;s Piano Concerto No. 5 in E flat major op. 73 (full)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3TiYGxOQDYw?start=1064&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This cadenza that appears near the end of the first movement, was written by the composer itself and it is a really short but elaborate part of this piece. What I found interesting about this cadenza is that it fits the whole movement very well. It comes from the main theme and makes the passage to another theme.</p>



<p>Before the cadenza, the orchestra plays the powerful dotted quaver &#8211; semi quaver &#8211; crochet chords while the piano anticipates a bit of the cadenza. Then the short cadenza starts full of rhythm but then gently eases back into the tutti by accompanying the end of the “cadenza” with a horn theme. </p>



<h5 id="brahms-violin-concerto-in-d-major-op-77" class="wp-block-heading">Brahms &#8211; Violin Concerto in D major, Op. 77</h5>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Brahms: Violinkonzert ∙ hr-Sinfonieorchester ∙ Hilary Hahn ∙ Paavo Järvi" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UFl9xuYP5T8?start=1085&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Brahms wrote one violin concerto and it was dedicated to Joseph Joachim. The cadenza appears in the end of Mvt.1 and I believe it is full of passion and melancholy at the same time. It explores the violin capabilites, which fits the purpose of a cadenza: to showcase the player&#8217;s and instrument virtuosities.</p>



<p>The dissonant notes and the strikes on the chords convey a bit of rage that I specially aprecciate. With the runs, I felt that it had some rock and metal sound I used to listen to. It brought me memories of the extended electric guitar solos that showcased the guitarist skills.</p>



<p>In the end, the entering of the orchestra is much smoother than the Mozart&#8217;s piano concerto, and I believe this creates a great contrast with the cadenza, almost like it is a resolution of the violin&#8217;s anger.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1637722906186 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Kennedy, J., Kennedy, M. and Rutherford-Johnson, T., 2012.&nbsp;<em>cadenza</em>. [online] The Oxford Dictionary of Music. Available at: &lt;https://www-oxfordreference-com.ucreative.idm.oclc.org/view/10.1093/acref/9780199578108.001.0001/acref-9780199578108-e-1488&gt; [Accessed 23 November 2021].</p>



<p>Fuller, M., n.d. BEAUTY of music | the classical cadenza &#8211; American Pianists Association. [online] Americanpianists.org. Available at: <a href="https://www.americanpianists.org/apa-blog/95-beauty-of-music-the-classical-cadenza" target="_blank">https://www.americanpianists.org/apa-blog/95-beauty-of-music-the-classical-cadenza</a> [Accessed 24 November 2021].</p>



<p>Bribitzer-Stull, Matthew, 2006. <em>The Cadenza as Parenthesis: An Analytic Approach.</em>&nbsp;Journal of Music Theory&nbsp;50, no. 2, 211–51. Available at: &lt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/40283099&gt; [Accessed 23 November 2021].</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
