<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 13:41:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to SZA &#8211; Kill Bill</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-sza-kill-bill/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 13:41:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1221</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Although I appreciate pop music, I&#8217;m usually turned away from songs that are too popular on the charts.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Kill Bill" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1Qrg8KqiBpW07V7PNxwwwL?si=0505b2005f2b4d8b&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Although I appreciate pop music, I&#8217;m usually turned away from songs that are too popular on the charts. But, when I stumbled upon SZA&#8217;s &#8220;Kill Bill&#8221; on the radio without knowing what it was, I was extremely surprised. The song really caught my attention. My impression was that the song never settled down, a feeling (a very good feeling) I also had when <a href="./../../../../listening-to-beach-boys-god-only-knows/index.html" data-type="post" data-id="531" target="_blank">listening to God Only Knows</a>.</p>



<p>The aspect that impressed me the most was the chorus vocal melody. It was straightforward yet stunning and flowed smoothly. Upon transcribing it, I discovered the song was in Ab Major, but the vocal melody only utilized the Ab once on the last note of the 4th beat, which was a rather weak one. There was also an A flat, a chromatic note just a half-step from the tonic, leading to a sense of uncertainty and incompletion.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="74" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1024x74.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1222" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1024x74.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-300x22.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-768x55.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1536x111.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-2048x148.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-640x46.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-960x69.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26.png 2578w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The chord progression also caught my attention. Throughout the song, it used the same progression: Bbm-Eb-Ab-F or ii-V-I-VI. This again contributed to a sense of instability as it started on ii and placed the I on the third bar, which is a weaker position for establishing the key. The final chord was a modulation to a chromatic chord of F Major, which was my favourite part of the chorus. It was playful, and daring, and complemented the lyrics perfectly (e.g. &#8220;Rather be in jail than alone&#8221;).</p>



<p>But right from the beginning, the song starts off sounding vague. There&#8217;s a distinct out-of-tune waver that is completely undefined. From that point, the song could head in any direction. Then, the drum beat enters and as with any typical pop song, you anticipate listening to a four-beat loop until the vocals begin. But the vocals come in on the fourth beat, like an anacrusis, unexpectedly.</p>



<p>Ultimately, I don&#8217;t think &#8220;Kill Bill&#8221; will be regarded as a masterpiece like &#8220;God Only Knows,&#8221; but in today&#8217;s landscape of overwhelming similar-sounding pop music, I found the song to be invigorating. I hope it serves as inspiration for other artists to create pop music that departs from standard harmonic and melodic structures.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Bach: Brandenburg Concerto No. 5 in D Major</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-bach-brandenburg-concerto-no-5-in-d-major/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 15:19:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1207</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reading &#8220;How to Listen to Great Music&#8221; by Robert Greenberg has been an invaluable resource in learning how&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Reading &#8220;How to Listen to Great Music&#8221; by Robert Greenberg has been an invaluable resource in learning how to listen to and analyze music. The author suggests listening to Bach&#8217;s Brandenburg Concerto No. 5 as a way to gain a deeper understanding of Baroque concertos, with a particular emphasis on the ritornello. The concerto, which is composed for flute, solo violin, harpsichord, and strings, presents several interesting features upon listening and studying the score.</p>



<p>Right from the start of the concerto, I noticed the ritornello theme, which was highlighted by Greenberg, and how it reappears in fragments throughout the movement before being repeated in the end after the harpsichord solo.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="547" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-1024x547.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1209" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-1024x547.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-300x160.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-768x410.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-640x342.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-960x513.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29.png 1292w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Ritornello Theme</figcaption></figure>



<p>As Greenberg explains in his book, the function of the ritornello theme is to create a sense of logical inevitability, providing a feeling of returning home and familiarity, even if only for a brief moment. This helps the listener relax and not be overwhelmed by constant new sounds.</p>



<p>It works similarly to a chorus in modern-day popular music. but it typically appears at the beginning and end of the movement, while choruses in contemporary music typically appear in the middle and end of songs. I am curious as to why composers have shifted the placement of this familiar theme from the beginning to the middle of their compositions.</p>



<p>The concerto is also notable for its use of the harpsichord as a solo instrument. The harpsichord, which was a relatively new instrument at the time, was often used as a continuo instrument to accompany other instruments. However, in this concerto, according to Greenberg, Bach was the first to elevate the harpsichord to the role of a true solo instrument, giving it an equal voice alongside the flute and violin. And this solo is extremely impressive and virtuoso.</p>



<p>This movement also stands out for its unique use of the harpsichord as a solo instrument. While it was often used as a continuo instrument in the past, Bach elevated its role to that of a true solo instrument, giving it equal importance alongside the flute and violin. According to Greenberg, this concerto marks a significant moment in music history as the harpsichord&#8217;s solo capabilities were truly showcased for the first time. </p>



<p>The second movement of the concerto is an affettuoso, characterized by its melodic singing between the flute and violin. As I listened, I noticed two features that I had previously encountered in Bach&#8217;s violin sonata &#8211; the use of long, melodic lines that persistently avoid resolving to a steady cadence (as exemplified by the flute&#8217;s quick movement to C), and the repetition of a rhythmic pattern (in this case, quaver-quaver-dotted semiquaver-demisemiquaver) throughout the entire movement.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.20.07.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1210" width="445" height="304" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.20.07.png 738w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.20.07-300x205.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.20.07-640x437.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 445px) 100vw, 445px" /></figure>



<p>The third movement starts with the exposition of a fugal theme by the violin, which is then repeated by the flute. However, as the movement progresses, the violin and flute often play in unison, rather than in counterpoint as is typical in a true fugue. Despite this, there is a significant use of polyphonic texture throughout the movement.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Bach: Sonata No. 4 for violin and harpsichord in C Minor, BMV 1017: 1. Siciliano</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-bach-sonata-no-4-for-violin-and-harpsichord-in-c-minor-bmv-1017-1-siciliano/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 16:22:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This sonata looks like a good example of Baroque music, characterized by its long melodic lines and ornamental&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Glenn Gould &amp; Yehudi Menuhin - Bach, Sonata No. 4 in C minor (OFFICIAL)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Boii0EA6hWo?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This sonata looks like a good example of Baroque music, characterized by its long melodic lines and ornamental elements. Upon listening to it for the first time played by Glenn Gould and Yehudi Menuhin, I feel that there&#8217;s an interesting contrast between the smoothness of the violin and the pointed, moving accompaniment of the harpsichord. After listening to it several times and studying the score, I noticed several unique features.</p>



<p>One of the key observations I made was that the harpsichord had a repetitive pattern, which allowed the violin to take centre stage. The bass harpsichord usually played a continuous arpeggio starting on the downbeat, while the treble harpsichord had an upward and downward motion with its highest note on the second note of the violin rhythm. The violin melody, in section A, seemed to be a long single melody that lasted 16 bars. Although I could definitely hear that the melody line didn&#8217;t settle until bar 16 and it seemed like Bach avoided a cadence in bars 8 and 12, I was unsure of how he achieved this effect. But my tutor helped clarify that it was a mixture of harmony, not having a perfect cadence, melody/rhythm notes that cross bars, and the use of weaker inversions of chords that gave a feeling of movement instead of a final rest. I hadn&#8217;t thought about how inverting chords could transmit a sense movement and it made much more sense to me after his answer.</p>



<p>Another observation I made was the rhythm of the violin melody and its repetition. This movement of the sonata is a Siciliano which is a musical style from the baroque era, usually in a slow 6/8 time and in a minor key. The violin follows the traditional Siciliana rhythms with a dotted quaver &#8211; semiquaver &#8211; quaver. It&#8217;s interesting to notice that Bach uses this exact rhythm 36 times and some of its variations throughout this movement but without making it feel repetitive. The use of ornamentation is essential here.</p>



<p>Another observation I made was the rhythm of the violin melody and its repetition. This movement of the sonata is a Siciliano, a musical style from the Baroque era, usually in a slow 6/8 time and in a minor key. The violin follows the traditional Siciliana rhythms with a dotted quaver-semiquaver-quaver. It&#8217;s interesting to notice that Bach uses this exact rhythm 36 times and some of its variations throughout this movement without making it feel repetitive. The use of ornamentation is essential here.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="884" height="91" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1151" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image.png 884w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image-300x31.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image-768x79.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image-640x66.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 884px) 100vw, 884px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Siciliano Rhythms</figcaption></figure>



<p>Overall, I find this piece to be deceptively simple yet incredibly evocative and emotionally charged. Reflecting on its various features has helped me gain a deeper understanding of how to approach my assignment with greater insight and understanding.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Caroline Shaw &#038; Sō Percussion &#8211; To the Sky</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-caroline-shaw-so-percussion-to-the-sky/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 13:07:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1112</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I recently became a fan of Caroline Shaw after listening to her Partita for 8 Singer. I have&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Caroline Shaw &amp; Sō Percussion - To the Sky (Live)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/B22fQIHUyvY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I recently became a fan of Caroline Shaw after listening to her Partita for 8 Singer. I have since listened to some of her other songs, including &#8220;To the Sky,&#8221; which features Shaw&#8217;s exceptional vocals and the talented musicianship of the exploratory New York ensemble Sō Percussion. The lyrics for the song are taken from Anne Steele&#8217;s 18th-century hymnal, the Sacred Harp.</p>



<p>The song starts off with a gentle hum and softly rumbling marimba, gradually increasing in intensity and culminating in Shaw&#8217;s powerful vocals. Shaw&#8217;s music often showcases a dynamic range and the versatility of the voice as an instrument.</p>



<p>In addition to Shaw&#8217;s vocals, Sō Percussion&#8217;s expert use of percussion instruments creates a rich and complex soundscape that perfectly complements Shaw&#8217;s voice.</p>



<p>After a gentle start, the song builds to a climax with exuberance and then fades away, leaving me with a sense of awe and wonder.</p>



<p>Overall, &#8220;To the Sky&#8221; is a beautiful and moving piece of music that has left me wanting to hear more from Shaw.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Georg Friedrich Händel – Dixit Dominus</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-georg-friedrich-handel-dixit-dominus/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2022 14:11:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1100</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Because of Project 3.0, I started listening to Händel&#8217;s Dixit Dominus&#8217; first movement and ended up listening to&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Handel: Ode for the Birthday of Queen Anne &amp; Dixit Dominus" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="380" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/2T2GyKe3BFyCa9QgLpMEgx?si=IGbcK_haT-eNXccI9VMzPA&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Because of Project 3.0, I started listening to Händel&#8217;s Dixit Dominus&#8217; first movement and ended up listening to the entire work. </p>



<p>Georg Friedrich Händel was a German-born composer (1685 &#8211; 1759) who worked in Germany, and Italy and settled in London. He was heavily influenced by the middle-German polyphonic choral tradition and the Italian Baroque style. Händel&#8217;s music is considered a pinnacle of the &#8220;high baroque&#8221; style and he is widely regarded as one of the greatest composers of his era.</p>



<p>Dixit Dominus is a psalm setting completed in 1707 and is scored for an SSATB choir and soloists, strings and continuo. </p>



<p>Although I enjoyed the entire piece, I found the first movement to be the most interesting and surprising. As a psalm, I was expecting a contemplative and loving sound. Instead, I found it to be rough and even a bit hostile. This was due to the rhythmic vitality which felt a lot like a warlike snare.</p>



<p>It is not surprising that the piece&#8217;s opening movement evokes a warlike sound, given the psalm&#8217;s theme about God giving the king of Israel the power to defeat his enemies (Clássicos dos Clássicos, 2019).</p>



<p>The ending of Dominus a dextris tuis is another example of the power of the choir, as it resembles a war chant. I imagine this would likely have been striking to an audience in the 1700s, given the religious context in which it was performed.</p>



<p>The choir in this piece reminded me of Caroline Shaw&#8217;s Partita for 8 Voices. I believe that they are similar in their exploration of different vocal timbers and ranges, either together or in counterpoint. Additionally, the staccato rhythm of the voices in both pieces creates an almost drum-like feeling.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Partita for 8 Singers: No. 1. Allemande" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/E98OCHWIv3s?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1670601412288 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Clássicos dos Clássicos (2019) <em>Händel – Dixit Dominus (Disse o Senhor), HWV 232</em>. Available at: https://classicosdosclassicos.mus.br/obras/handel-dixit-dominus-disse-o-senhor-hwv-232/ (Accessed: December 10, 2022).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Franz Liszt &#8211; Les Préludes</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-franz-liszt-les-preludes/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 13:43:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1039</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Les Préludes is a symphonic poem composed by Franz Liszt and premiered in 1854. His symphonic poem is&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Les Préludes (Franz Liszt)  Daniel Barenboim mit Berlin Philharmoniker - Staatsoper Berlin (1998)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jb2bkVQwtBs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Les Préludes is a symphonic poem composed by Franz Liszt and premiered in 1854. His symphonic poem is one of his most famous compositions and is often seen as an example of the genre. This work is based on a poem by Alphonse de Lamartine of the same name that explores ideas of fate and destiny. Liszt uses a variety of musical devices to illustrate Lamartine&#8217;s poem, including changes in tempo and dynamics, harmonic shifts, and orchestral colour.</p>



<p>Liszt&#8217;s use of thematic transformation in Les Préludes is one of the most striking aspects of the work. Thematic transformation is a compositional technique whereby a musical theme is altered or transformed in order to create a distinct idea or mood. In Les Préludes, Liszt uses this technique to great effect, transforming the main theme of destiny into several different musical ideas that represent different aspects of the poem.</p>



<p>Beginning with three notes (C-B-E), the piece is a dreamy introduction. In a thematic transformation, this motif will be repeated throughout the work. Using this single motif, the music moves from a dawn of enchantment to a tumultuous battle to a triumphant ending.</p>



<p>My first experience listening to Liszt&#8217;s Les Préludes was incredibly moving. With Liszt&#8217;s use of thematic transformation, I could really feel the tension that he had created, although sometimes it was challenging to discern where the main theme was. I really like this piece of music.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1669815713034 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><em>Les Préludes | work by Liszt</em> (2013). Available at: https://www.britannica.com/topic/Les-Preludes (Accessed: 30 November 2022).</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Luís de Freitas Branco &#8211; Suite Alentejana No. 1</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-luis-de-freitas-branco-suite-alentejana-no-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 15:11:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1063</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Luís de Freitas Branco was a Portuguese composer, musicologist, and professor of music who played a pre-eminent part&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Suite alentejana No.1: III. Finale: Allegro" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/0XB5x9beMMdC11MLxJh6Ps?si=f3a82eba5a5c40f8&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Luís de Freitas Branco was a Portuguese composer, musicologist, and professor of music who played a pre-eminent part in developing Portuguese music in the first half of the 20th century. He wrote over 150 pieces of music, including orchestral works, chamber music and works for the stage, as well as songs and choral works. Suite Alentejana No. 1 is one of his most famous works and is known for its energetic rhythms, colourful orchestration and vibrant melodies.</p>



<p>The piece is written for a large orchestra with 3 flutes, 2 oboes, English horn, 2 clarinets, bass clarinet, 2 bassoons, 4 trumpets, 3 trombones, tuba, timpani, bass drum, cymbals, triangle, castanets and harp, as well as strings.</p>



<p>Luís de Freitas Branco&#8217;s Suite Alentejana No. 1, written in 1919, is a celebrated work that demonstrates his preference for the Alentejo region of Portugal. Personally, the third and final movement, known as the Fandango, stands out for its vibrant energy and eloquent orchestration. It is written for orchestra with elements of folk music from Alentejo such as a binary-metered rhythm and castanets incorporated into the piece. The form of the piece is tripartite (A-B-A), with an English horn solo leading to a choral section in between two energised sections featuring returning themes. As we close the Fandango brilliantly, the exuberance and vigour of the first section return.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Georg Philipp Telemann &#8211; Sonata in D Major, TWV 44:1</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-georg-philipp-telemann-sonata-in-d-major-twv-441/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 14:36:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1043</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sonata in D Major, TWV 44:1 is a piece of Baroque music composed by the German composer Georg&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Georg Philipp Telemann - Trumpet Sonata in D major, TWV 44:1. Trumpet: Maurice André." width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iUhXRvEPuC4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Sonata in D Major, TWV 44:1 is a piece of Baroque music composed by the German composer Georg Philipp Telemann (1681-1767). It combines elements of concerto and suite genres and is composed for trumpet, strings, and basso continuo.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Three movements make up the piece, each with its own distinctive character. In Sinfonia Spirituoso, the opening trumpet fanfare presents a lively and energetic start. The second movement, Largo, displays two violins in intimate harmony with the basso continuo. With its lively tempo and energetic tone, the closing movement Vivace brings the piece to a triumphant conclusion.</p>



<p>I found it to be a captivating work of Baroque music with an interesting and multifaceted composition. The opening fanfare immediately captivated me with its bold and triumphant sound.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to The Pharcyde &#8211; Runnin</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-the-pharcyde-runnin/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 13:28:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=984</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the last few weeks, I&#8217;ve been reading the book Dilla Time, about the life of James DeWitt&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the last few weeks, I&#8217;ve been reading the book Dilla Time, about the life of James DeWitt Yancey, better known as J Dilla and Jay Dee. He was an American record producer, drummer, rapper, songwriter, and rapper. It is Dilla&#8217;s &#8220;drunk&#8221;, and &#8220;laid back&#8221; time-feel that makes his work unique and difficult to interpret, define, or translate. His production style has inspired some of the world&#8217;s most renowned pop, hip-hop, and jazz musicians &#8212; achieved, in part, because he didn&#8217;t quantize his music (Fitzpatrick, 2011).</p>



<p>While I don&#8217;t listen to a lot of hip-hop, I was intrigued by his stories and how he blew everyone away with his eccentric rhythms, so I decided to check out some of the music he produced or composed (Stadnicki, 2017). My favourite was Running by The Pharcyde, released in 1995.</p>



<p>It begins with a simple maracas sample from James Moody, followed by acoustic guitar from Luiz Bonfá. As I listen to these samples, I realize that the tempo is not always right. I start to understand why people talk about J Dilla when the drums start playing. It seems like the kick drum is rushing (perhaps running?) while the snare is dragging after the hi-hats. This results in strangely relaxed music, with an endless forward motion.</p>



<p>These kinds of not quantized drum sounds are somehow normal nowadays and explored by a lot of musicians, but I can imagine how refreshing it was to listen to such a relaxed and “humanized” beat after listening to so much on-tempo electronic music from the late ’80s and early ’90s.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1667471184588 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Fitzpatrick, R. (2011) <em>J Dilla: The mozart of hip-hop</em>, <em>The Guardian</em>. Guardian News and Media. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/2011/jan/27/j-dilla-suite-ma-dukes (Accessed: November 3, 2022).</p>



<p>Stadnicki, D.A. (2017) “Play like jay: Pedagogies of drum kit performance after J Dilla,” <em>Journal of Popular Music Education</em>, 1(3), pp. 253–280. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1386/jpme.1.3.253_1.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Aaron Copland &#8211; Letter from Home</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-aaron-copland-letter-from-home/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 15:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1049</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[“Letter from Home” is a composition by American composer Aaron Copland, written in 1944 and commissioned as a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Letter from Home" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4BmuwW29smvsvayXpXD0uo?si=338fb8e5c25f456f&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>“Letter from Home” is a composition by American composer Aaron Copland, written in 1944 and commissioned as a patriotic work by Paul Whiteman for his Radio Hall of Fame Orchestra. The piece is a reflection on the experiences of soldiers returning home from war, and the changes that they have undergone during their time away. The piece is written in the style of a letter from a soldier to his family and conveys the bittersweet emotions of coming home after having seen the horrors of war.</p>



<p>The piece begins with a sombre, reflective melody, as the soldier reflects on his experiences and considers the changes that have taken place in his life since departing. The music slowly builds to a more upbeat, hopeful tone, as the soldier finds comfort in the thought of being reunited with his family and friends. The piece ends with a triumphant, joyous melody, as the soldier celebrates the joy of being home. The instrumentation is sparse and haunting, evoking a sense of loneliness and longing.</p>



<p>Ultimately, “Letter from Home” is a powerful and poignant tribute to the soldiers who have sacrificed so much for their country. Through its emotional intensity and evocative musical language, Copland captures the complex emotions of a soldier returning home.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Keith Jarrett &#8211; My Song</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-keith-jarrett-my-song/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 13:48:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1046</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Keith Jarrett is a celebrated American jazz musician and composer. He has been active since the 1960s and&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: My Song" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1fZWZxwDpzMw9qkGv17d4c?si=ba376f2beb304fd8&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Keith Jarrett is a celebrated American jazz musician and composer. He has been active since the 1960s and has released several acclaimed albums, such as My Song, which came out in 1978. His music often features a sublime simplicity and directness that has made it a favorite among jazz enthusiasts.</p>



<p>The title track of Keith Jarrett&#8217;s 1978 album, My Song, is a timeless piece featuring the collaborative efforts of the European Quartet. The melody is introduced by a pensive piano movement that is soon joined by Jan Garabek&#8217;s saxophone and Jon Christensen&#8217;s percussion, which uses shakers and cymbals to create a soft and muted backdrop. Over the years, My Song has become a popular standard among jazz musicians, with Pat Metheny being one of its most notable interpreters.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Jörg Widmann &#8211;  Viola Concerto</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-jorg-widmann-viola-concerto/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 22:45:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Romanticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=974</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It was while researching Berlioz&#8217;s Harold in Italy that I came across an article by French violist Antoine&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It was while researching Berlioz&#8217;s Harold in Italy that I came across an article by French violist Antoine Tamestit. This article stated, in 2015, when he played Harold with John Eliot for the first time, he told German composer Jörg Widmann how delighted he was with the piece. Therefore, Widmann composed a viola concerto filled with narration, journeys and interactions with multiple orchestral instruments.</p>



<p>Based on this description, I decided to watch Tamestit&#8217;s performance with the Frankfurt Radio Symphony conducted by Andrés Orozco-Estrada.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Widmann: Viola Concerto ∙ hr-Sinfonieorchester ∙ Antoine Tamestit ∙ Andrés Orozco-Estrada" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_5WraTt_l_U?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>My overall reaction was one of awe and I still don&#8217;t know if I liked it or not. However, I believe that was the purpose of this concerto. In one interview, Tamestit explains that this piece is intended to disorient the listener (Todes, 2021). While I sometimes understood what the composer was saying, other times I felt disoriented and I wondered if it wasn&#8217;t just too much theatrical for show&#8217;s sake.</p>



<p>In the same interview, Tamestit talks about how the instrumentation is unusual. This concerto, for instance, requires the soloist to scream throughout and requires the pianist to hold a whiskey glass.</p>



<p>I wasn&#8217;t expecting such a theatrical performance with such an emphasis on the viola soloist. But as an homage or follow-up to Berlioz&#8217;s symphony, Widmann seemed to want to keep the viola at the center of this performance.</p>



<p>The viola is the focus of this piece, for me. As it takes the listener through the viola&#8217;s different sounds, blending and clashing with other instruments, and finding its place within the orchestra.</p>



<p>Berlioz&#8217;s symphony and this concerto have many connections, but for me, the biggest one is the instrument&#8217;s representation. In Harold in Italy, the viola embodied Harold, here the instrument symbolized itself. As I realized, Widmann attempted to meta-characterize the viola. And that was a brilliant idea.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1666218709706 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Todes, A. (2021) <em>&#8216;it is in my blood&#8217;: Antoine Tamestit on Jörg Widmann&#8217;s Viola Concerto</em>, <em>London Symphony Orchestra</em>. Available at: https://lso.co.uk/whats-on/alwaysplaying/read/1473-it-is-in-my-blood-antoine-tamestit-on-jorg-widmann-s-viola-concerto.html (Accessed: October 19, 2022).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Omar Thomas &#8211; Come Sunday II. Shout!</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-omar-thomas-come-sunday-ii-shout/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 10:36:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=909</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On the Academic Music Discord server, someone posted a video about Omar Thomas, a composer I had never&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>On the Academic Music Discord server, someone posted a video about Omar Thomas, a composer I had never heard of before.</p>



<p>A composer, arranger and educator, Omar Thomas was born in Brooklyn, N.Y., in 1984. His parents are Guyanese, and he moved to Boston in 2006 to pursue a Master of Music degree at New England Conservatory.</p>



<p>A piece written for a wind ensemble, Piano and Drum Set, Come Sunday celebrates the Hammond organ&#8217;s central role in black worship. The second movement, Shout!, is an energetic celebration of gospel, jazz and blues, which shows influences from Duke Wellington and Charles Mingus as well as traditional church singing.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Thomas: Come Sunday | Baylor University Wind Ensemble | TMEA 2020" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PSr5XurNQF8?start=407&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>In listening to Shout!, I was surprised at how energetic it was after the slow and melodic first movement. There was an instant connection for me to the rhythm of this piece, marked by brass, bass, and drums, with the repetitive woodwinds in a high register adding the necessary tension.</p>



<p>As I listened to this piece, I was reminded of 70s funk horns and woodwinds. That&#8217;s what makes this piece so beautiful. Mixing genres and decades, creating a fresh and joyful time for the listener and for the players.</p>



<p>Since I am unfamiliar with much of the new classical music, I am enjoying this opportunity to listen to contemporary composers. At the same time that I study traditional techniques, I believe this will facilitate me in understanding the paths new composers are taking.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Tan Dun, Eldbjørg Hemsing &#8211; Violin Concerto &#8220;Rhapsody &#038; Fantasia&#8221;: Ia. Rock the Violin in Rhapsody. Hip-Hop</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-tan-dun-eldbjorg-hemsing-violin-concerto-rhapsody-fantasia-ia-rock-the-violin-in-rhapsody-hip-hop/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 11:59:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=889</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In another Spotify discovery, I listened to a piece that I had never heard before. My attention was&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC54eHWKRFlG-NZaNI0EBxGQ"></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Violin Concerto &quot;Rhapsody &amp; Fantasia&quot;: Ia. Rock the Violin in Rhapsody. Hip-Hop" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2Q1w1bAK18GxLVMGJjbH9S?si=46fe411f0dac41ad&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>In another Spotify discovery, I listened to a piece that I had never heard before. My attention was immediately captured when a traditional drum kit entered playing a classic hip-hop pattern in the first 16 seconds.</p>



<p>Rock the Violin in Rhapsody. Hip-Hop is the first movement of the Violin Concerto &#8220;Rhapsody &amp; Fantasy&#8221; by Eldbjørg Hemsing and Tan Dun. Hemsing is one of the best violinists in Norway, while Tan Dun is one of the most renowned conductors and composers that lives in New York but was born in China.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-issuu wp-block-embed-issuu"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div data-url="https://issuu.com/scoresondemand/docs/violin_concerto_rhapsody_fantasia_5/4" style="width: 640px; height: 453px;" class="issuuembed"></div><script type="text/javascript" src="//e.issuu.com/embed.js" async="true"></script>
</div></figure>



<p>Having found a score for this concerto, I discovered that it includes a strong percussion section with five players, in addition to woodwinds, brass, and strings. It&#8217;s easy to hear the rhythm throughout this piece since it&#8217;s very heavy on it.</p>



<p>My favourite aspect of the piece was the constant play between rhythmic, hip-hop ambient and the almost wild solo violin. The play kept the piece alive and prevented it from becoming monotonous, which could happen with a simple hip-hop beat.</p>



<p>As described by Xenia Hanusiak <a href="https://classicalvoiceamerica.org/2018/09/26/dun-links-ancient-modern-worlds-in-new-violin-work/" target="_blank">in her article</a>, the composer calls this Rhapsody and Fantasia &#8220;the perfect result&#8221; of his thirty-five years of living in New York. It is one of the most interesting pieces I have heard in a while due to its combination of street sound rhythm, classical Chinese instruments, and a harsh nordic violin.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Max Bruch &#8211; Concerto for Clarinet &#038; Viola, Op. 88: I. Andante Con Moto</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-max-bruch-concerto-for-clarinet-viola-op-88-i-andante-con-moto/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 11:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=938</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Max Bruch (1838-1920) is a well-known prolific German composer. During his long career, he taught, conducted, and composed.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Max Bruch - Concerto for Clarinet &amp; Viola, Op. 88 (1911)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/m0wYD4MzwUw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Max Bruch (1838-1920) is a well-known prolific German composer. During his long career, he taught, conducted, and composed. In 1911, Bruch composed the Double Concerto in E minor, Op.88. This piece was composed for his son Max Felix Bruch, who was a first-class clarinettist.</p>



<p>A review of Bruch&#8217;s Double Concerto Op.88 premiere, published in Allgemeine Musikzeitung Zeitung No. 40 (1913), called it &#8220;harmless,&#8221; &#8220;weak,&#8221; and &#8220;uninteresting&#8221; (Fifield, 1988).</p>



<p>Initially, I was intrigued by the strange combination of clarinet and viola in this Double Concerto. My impression after listening to this piece is that both instruments can very well mimic human timbres. As a result, the solo instruments have a lyrical and melodic sound. As the two solo instruments weave melodies around each other, the orchestra provides a stable backdrop.</p>



<p>The first movement of this work presents Bruch&#8217;s two solo instruments in a rather dramatic manner. In the beginning, the solo viola is boldly introduced, followed by the clarinet. Throughout the entire movement, it feels as if both instruments are having an intimate conversation.</p>



<p>Upon hearing this movement, I felt as if there was nothing shocking and nothing wrong, at least to my ears. In addition to being a conservative, Bruch was opposed to &#8216;modern madness&#8217; and &#8216;modernists&#8217; like Strauss, Reger, and Debussy (the latter he termed an &#8216;unqualified scribbler&#8217;). As a whole, I enjoyed this piece, especially the interplay between the two solo instruments.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1665658948758 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Fifield, C. (1988) <em>Max Bruch his life and works</em>. London: Gollancz.</p>



<p><em>Viola and clarinet concerto and other viola compositions by Bruch</em> (no date) <em>Viola in Music.com</em>. Available at: http://www.viola-in-music.com/viola-and-clarinet-concerto.html .</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Masses</title>
		<link>./../../../../947-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 14:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Renaissance period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=947</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[During my research, I listened to masses from different periods of history, but my focus was exclusively on&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>During my research, I listened to masses from different periods of history, but my focus was exclusively on the Kyrie.</p>



<p><strong>Machaut: Messe de Nostra Dame: Kyrie (1365)</strong><br>(Guillaume &amp; Royllart, 2016)</p>



<p>This Ordinary of the Mass composed before 1365 is considered the earliest complete setting attributable to any single composer. The Kyrie is written in polyphony for four voices and features lots of melismas. This piece is divided into three sections, each with the same structure: polyphony &#8211; plainchant &#8211; polyphony. As far as the sound quality is concerned, I found it to be very diverse, with each voice having its own distinct characteristics, but working together to create a pleasing whole.</p>



<p><strong>Victoria: Missa O magnum mysterium: Kyrie (1592) <br></strong>(Smith &amp; de, 1997)</p>



<p>O magnum mysterium (published in 1572) became the basis for Victoria&#8217;s 1592 Mass for a four-part choir. Since this short Kyrie is in imitation polyphonic texture, the voices do not appear to have any real distinctive characteristic, but rather blend together to achieve a more common sound.</p>



<p><strong>Bach: Mass in B minor: Kyrie I (1749)<br></strong>(Herreweghe, 2011)</p>



<p>Compared to my previous two masses, this is a big difference. This work is for five voices with instrumental accompaniment, which makes a completely different sound from choral masses without accompaniment. It is evident that Bach is stepping up the masses from church music to concert music, making them suitable for a concert hall. In this polyphonic Kyrie, what I found most interesting is the way, from bar 30, the sound never settles until the last bar. The tension and expectation lasts for about 5 minutes.</p>



<p><strong>Mozart: Great Mass in C  minor K.427: Kyrie (1783)<br></strong>(Bernstein et al., 1991)</p>



<p>After listening to it, I understand why it is considered one of Mozart&#8217;s greatest works. It is a magnificent composition for two soprano soloists, a tenor and a bass, a double chorus and a large orchestra. Similarly to Bach&#8217;s mass, Mozart wanted to make the experience more performance and entertainment-based, instead of contemplative and solemn. For me, the most appealing part of this Kyrie is the soprano solo, particularly when it reaches a low Ab and jumps two octaves higher in the following measure.</p>



<p><strong>Beethoven: Mass in C Major, Op.86:I. Kyrie (1807)<br></strong>(Kampen, K.V. <em>et al.</em>, 2005)</p>



<p>Compared to the previous masses I had listened to, the texture of this Kyrie surprised me. In my opinion, Beethoven decided to compose a homophonic-based mass that heavily relied on the choir. Throughout, there is an intriguing play of dynamics, swaying up and down and conveying different emotions in a short space of time, with some parts with breathtaking soaring voices. A note about Gloria in excelsis Deo, which is one of my favourite versions I&#8217;ve heard.</p>



<p><strong>Bruckner: Mass in E minor: Kyrie (1866)<br></strong>(Parkman, 2019)</p>



<p>It&#8217;s a mass that feels like a travel back in time, stripped of all instrumental accompaniment and focusing primarily on choral. The combination of choir and brass in this Kyrie really caught my attention. This created a very dramatic and mournful sound. But I was most impressed by the use of silences and the absence of sound in some parts, which gave this piece a huge hollowness.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1665744187030 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Guillaume and Royllart, P. (2016) <em>Machaut, G. de: Messe de nostre dame (diabolus in Musica, guerber)</em>, <em>Youtube</em>. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lOVsY1rxJB8.</p>



<p>Smith, S. and de, V.T.L. (1997) <em>Victoria, T.L. de: Vocal music (tenebrae responsories) (ensemble Corund, S. Smith)</em>, <em>Youtube</em>. Naxos Digital Services US Inc. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NGyWrtWgHjA.</p>



<p>Herreweghe, P. (2011) <em>Mass in B minor BWV 232 ; Collegium Vocale Gent ; Philippe Herreweghe</em>, <em>Youtube</em>. Harmonia mundi. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zS2biN257sQ.</p>



<p>Bernstein, L. <em>et al.</em> (1991) <em>Große Messe C-Moll K 427 (417a): Version: Franz Beyer = great mass in C minor = Grande Messe en ut mineur</em>, <em>Youtube</em>. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GUtLXacCT5M.</p>



<p>Kampen, K.V. <em>et al.</em> (2005) <em>Messe C-Dur = Mass in C major = Messe en UT majeur: Op. 86</em>, <em>Spotify</em>. Hänssler Classic. Available at: https://open.spotify.com/track/2k7AQGyLChW5JlcWhvBwLc?si=39803a01a70f4435.</p>



<p>Parkman, S. (2019) <em>Anton Bruckner: Mass in E minor | WDR Rundfunkchor | WDR Sinfonieorchester</em>, <em>Youtube</em>. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YqlcXpPdaBc.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to José Almarcha &#8211; Casa del Gallego</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-jose-almarcha-casa-del-gallego/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 10:47:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=858</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As usual, my Spotify is on shuffle and today I heard some flamenco, which I am not particularly&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Casa del Gallego (Farruca)" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3uXLYVPHGSgEFm5h4hedJB?si=06a81e07e4894526&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>As usual, my Spotify is on shuffle and today I heard some flamenco, which I am not particularly familiar with, but enjoy listening to occasionally. This song caught my attention, so I listened carefully.</p>



<p>Originally from Ciudad Real, José Almarcha is an outstanding guitarist and composer. As a student of flamenco at the Córdoba Conservatory of Music, José studied with flamenco masters including Paco Serrano and Niño de Pura. A number of dancers have been accompanied by him, including Olga Pericet, Marco Flores, and Antonio Canales. His albums have received excellent reviews and he has been hailed as one of Spain&#8217;s most promising flamenco guitarists.</p>



<p>The singer recently released Casa del Gallego, which is a farruca, a dance-centric style of flamenco characterized by sombre virtuosity, aggressive footwork, and dramatic tempo changes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In this song, the melody is introduced by a flamenco guitar riff, but a few seconds into the song, there&#8217;s a surprise: a trombone with a delay effect. Not a typical flamenco sound and a hint to the listener that this probably isn&#8217;t a traditional flamenco but yes, a modern view of the style.</p>



<p>Enters the piano a few seconds later. With the trombone on the bottom, the piano on top with high notes, and the flamenco guitar in the middle, the three instruments make a beautiful sonic sandwich.</p>



<p>A mellow melody is gradually introduced by the trio, along with occasional cymbal sounds.&nbsp;Still, the strumming and tapping of guitars always have a slight tension to them. Suddenly, the tension is released as the full band enters, with a Latin rhythm recognizable as flamenco, accompanied by a shoe-tapping sound, along with another surprise: an electric guitar. There is a clash between traditional and modern sounds in the music now, and I find it very appealing.</p>



<p>As the song continues, tension is built and released with more and more shoe tapping and stomping until the apotheosis.</p>



<p>It was very interesting to see how flamenco is approached in a new way. It was entertaining to watch the piece&#8217;s sudden changes in sound dynamics that are intended to be interpreted by a dancer and add drama to the performance.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 1.0 &#8211; Renaissance madrigals</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-1-0-renaissance-madrigals/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 14:17:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Renaissance period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=846</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Claudio Monteverdi (1567–1643) Monteverdi was an Italian composer, violinist, singer, and priest. He is often considered a revolutionary&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<h3 id="claudio-monteverdi-1567-1643">Claudio Monteverdi (1567–1643)</h3>



<p>Monteverdi was an Italian composer, violinist, singer, and priest. He is often considered a revolutionary who marked the transition from Renaissance to Baroque music.</p>



<p>Until the age of forty, Monteverdi worked primarily on madrigals, composing a total of nine books. In about four years, Monteverdi completed his first book of twenty-one madrigals for five voices. Overall, the first eight madrigals show the massive development from Renaissance polyphonic to baroque monodic styles.</p>



<p>He wrote L&#8217;Orfeo, one of the earliest operas in the history of music, an innovative work that remains a part of today&#8217;s orchestra&#8217;s repertoire. Additionally, he has written sacred music.</p>



<h3 id="orlando-di-lasso-1532-1594">Orlando di Lasso (1532 &#8211; 1594)</h3>



<p>Lasso was a Franco-Flemish composer. With more than two thousand compositions to his credit, he was a prolific and versatile author. This collection includes all genres of his day, secular and sacred, including the mass, secular chanson in several languages, Latin motets, hymns, and madrigals. When he held the position of Kapellmeister at the Munich court, at the end of his life, he cultivated sacred music with a special dedication.</p>



<p>He is considered the chief representative of the mature polyphonic style of the Netherlands school, along with Giovanni Pierluigi da Palestrina. At the end of the 16th century, he was one of the most famous and influential musicians in Europe.</p>



<p>Regarding his madrigals, which he penned while living in Rome, his style was clear and concise, and his tunes were memorable.</p>



<h3 id="comparison-between-orlando-di-lassos-matona-mia-cara-and-claudio-monteverdis-ah-dolente-partita">Comparison between Orlando di Lasso&#8217;s Matona, mia cara and Claudio Monteverdi&#8217;s Ah, Dolente Partita</h3>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Lassus | Matona, mia cara [á 4; The Mirandola Ensemble]" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wl51iST98hA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Ah! Dolente partita   Monteverdi" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-97t3lw2sJA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>The main reason I chose to compare these two madrigals is their contrasting themes. Lasso&#8217;s one is a jovial, lighthearted, and almost mocking monologue between a German soldier and a supposedly Italian woman. Contrary to Monteverdi, his lament is a sombre recognition of death in late life.</p>



<p>From the very beginning, these contrasting themes are evident.&nbsp;Matona, mia cara begins with all four voices in an F Major chord and in a fast tempo. The song develops with a mostly homophonic texture and a very marked rhythm, especially in the &#8220;Don, don, don&#8221; section.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Ah, Dolente partita opens with only two voices in unison, singing a long, high E. The two voices stay in unison until bar 4 when they drift apart. As a result, it sounds very sorrowful and enigmatic. As the other voices enter, they do so timidly and not simultaneously. Only in bar 15 do all five voices sing together. However, just after that, in bar 16, the top two voices become silent. This creates a variety of aural experiences that convey the theme of lamentation.</p>



<p>Monteverdi&#8217;s madrigal has a more polyphonic texture than Lasso&#8217;s. Consequently, Ah, Dolente partita has a richer sound ambience, but Matona, mia cara has a stronger rhythmic mark.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As a final contrast, I would like to mention the melodic shape. In Lasso&#8217;s madrigal, there are some upward and downward lines, with a lot of repetition of the melody, so it could be sung in a group with a dance-like feeling.&nbsp;Monteverdi&#8217;s melody, however, tends to move downward or remain flat, which is most evident towards the end, as if the music is taking small steps toward death.</p>



<p> </p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1663325056128 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Arnold, Denis Midgley. &#8220;Claudio Monteverdi&#8221;. Encyclopedia Britannica, 28 Mar. 2022, https://www.britannica.com/biography/Claudio-Monteverdi. Accessed 16 September 2022.</p>



<p>Britannica, The Editors of Encyclopaedia. &#8220;Orlando di Lasso&#8221;. Encyclopedia Britannica, 10 Jun. 2022, https://www.britannica.com/biography/Orlando-di-Lasso. Accessed 16 September 2022.</p>



<p>MORTENSEN, B., 2009. Recording Reviews &#8211; [Claudio Monteverdi: Madrigals]: &#8220;Flaming Heart&#8221;; &#8220;Fire and Ashes&#8221;. <em>Choral Journal, </em>50(5), pp. 60-61. Accessed 16 September 2022.</p>



<p>fhunrichse, 2008. <em>King&#8217;s Singers &#8211; Madrigal History Tour &#8211; Matona mia cara</em>, YouTube. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TPlb2jKCCQI . Accessed September 16, 2022.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Oscar Peterson &#8211; Hymn To Freedom</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-oscar-peterson-hymn-to-freedom/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 09:44:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=842</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I came across Oscar Peterson through a Mic.com article called&#160;&#8220;Did Jazz Forget About Oscar Petterson?&#8221;. The author points&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I came across Oscar Peterson through a Mic.com article called&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mic.com/culture/oscar-peterson-black-white" target="_blank">&#8220;Did Jazz Forget About Oscar Petterson?&#8221;</a>. The author points out that when you think about jazz names, Petterson&#8217;s is not the first that comes to your mind (Johnson, 2022).</p>



<p>Until today, I was unaware of Oscar Peterson&#8217;s name or work. Therefore, I decided to listen to &#8220;Hymn To Freedom&#8221;, a song featured in the article.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Oscar Peterson - Hymn To Freedom" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tCrrZ1NnCuM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>dgbailey777, 2010.&nbsp;<em>Oscar Peterson &#8211; Hymn To Freedom</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tCrrZ1NnCuM&gt; [Accessed 15 September 2022].</figcaption></figure>



<p>Oscar Peterson was born in Montreal, Canada on August 15, 1925 and grew up in a family where music was required of all five children. At the age of seven, he was able to play trumpet and piano. In his teens, he was already a prodigy when he became the star attraction of Canada&#8217;s renowned big band, the Johnny Holmes Orchestra (Peterson, 2003), and he was just 20 years old when he made his first trio recordings for RCA.</p>



<p>As a result of his musical genius, he was able to play with and alongside many jazz legends of the era, including Ella Fitzgerald, Roy Eldridge, Louis Armstrong, Charlie Parker, and Billie Holiday (Johnson, 2022).</p>



<p>From 1959-1965, he formed and played with the Oscar Peterson trio with Ray Brown on bass and Ed Thigpen on drums, becoming one of jazz history&#8217;s most celebrated groups. Jazz historian Alyn Shipton explains one of their strengths as &#8220;Peterson&#8217;s skill at promoting group interaction marked the beginning of a seismic shift in piano trios.&#8221; (Hansen, 2014).</p>



<p>During the 1960s, there was racial segregation throughout the United States and Canada, and Peterson suffered a lot of racism when he toured with the Oscar Peterson trio. However, the experience of touring all over the world and especially his experiences in the south of the United States and observing the approach Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. took to peaceful protest, led him to write his most influential work, the “Hymn to Freedom” (Small, 2021).</p>



<p>People all over the world quickly embraced &#8220;Hymn To Freedom&#8221; as the anthem of the Civil Rights Movement when it was written in 1962. A timeless and relevant piece, this song has been played at many major events around the globe.</p>



<p>This song&#8217;s main melody captured my attention from the first listen. The song reminded me of a gospel song infused with blues and jazz.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In terms of structure, Peterson plays the melody four times before going into his solo, then returning to the original melody one last time. I believe this is an effective way of structuring a hymn, since the first four times he repeats the melody with almost no variation. As a result, the listener is able to engage with the melodic intention of the song.&nbsp;The piano solo builds upon the previous chord progression, but it is melodically much more unique than those first four repetitions, creating some interest. He concludes the solo with an apotheosis, but then the original melody is played softer, calmer, bringing peace to the listener&#8217;s heart.</p>



<p>My favorite part of this melody is the contrary motion technique, in which both voices go in opposite directions. While I&#8217;m still trying to figure out why I find it so pleasing to hear, I think it&#8217;s because it constantly creates a broader range of sounds. This makes it bigger and more interesting as a way of moving to the next part.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1663234118739 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Johnson, M., 2022. DID JAZZ FORGET ABOUT OSCAR PETERSON?. [online] Mic.Com. Available at:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mic.com/culture/oscar-peterson-black-white">https://www.mic.com/culture/oscar-peterson-black-white</a>&nbsp;[Accessed September 15, 2022].</p>



<p>Hansen, F.A., 2014, The arrangement qualities and musical style of the Oscar Peterson Trio: 1959–1965, Five Towns College [Accessed September 15, 2022].</p>



<p>Peterson, O., 2003, &#8220;A Jazz Odyssey: The Life of Oscar Peterson&#8221;, Jazz Education Journal, vol. 35, no. 4, pp. C2-C4, C7 [Accessed September 15, 2022].</p>



<p>Small, C., 2021. The Black + White Truth about Oscar Peterson and racism in Canada.&nbsp;<em>POV Magazine</em>. Available at: https://povmagazine.com/the-black-white-truth-about-oscar-peterson-and-racism-in-canada/ [Accessed September 15, 2022].&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Gesualdo</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-gesualdo/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 10:52:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Renaissance period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=824</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I must admit that I didn&#8217;t know who Gesualdo was until today, so I had to make some&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I must admit that I didn&#8217;t know who Gesualdo was until today, so I had to make some research about the composer.</p>



<p>A Prince who composed secular madrigals, sacred vocal music, and instrumental music, Carlo Gesualdo da Venosa (c 1566 &#8211; 1613) published six books of madrigals and three books of sacred pieces during his lifetime. He was also notorious for brutally murdering his wife and lover in bed. In addition to this cold-hearted murder, many depraved tales have been told about Gesualdo&#8217;s mental health. Through these stories (whether true or not, it&#8217;s up for debate), we can trace a psychological portrait behind the composer whose work represents the culmination of Renaissance music at the end of the 16th century.</p>



<p>His harmonic language is still considered daring and extravagant today because it incorporates elements of the late Italian madrigals, characterized by sound experimentalism. He used complex chromaticism in a way that was extraordinary for his time. This would not be heard again, or even hinted at until Wagner, Schoenberg and Stravinsky took it to new heights.</p>



<p>This idiosyncratic use of chromaticism was not only an attempt to break the rules, representing his era in which Mannerism was emerging as deliberately disruptive but also had a rather specific objective: word painting.</p>



<p>As an example, when the subject of Amor, pace non chero of his 1st Book of Madrigals calls for his lover, he uses consonance and long notes (Garbuio &amp; Fiorini, 2015).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="676" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/7887a951ab66eeceed472f273e597ee7fb3586bc-1024x676.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-825" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/7887a951ab66eeceed472f273e597ee7fb3586bc-1024x676.jpeg 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/7887a951ab66eeceed472f273e597ee7fb3586bc-300x198.jpeg 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/7887a951ab66eeceed472f273e597ee7fb3586bc-768x507.jpeg 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/7887a951ab66eeceed472f273e597ee7fb3586bc-1536x1014.jpeg 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/7887a951ab66eeceed472f273e597ee7fb3586bc-2048x1352.jpeg 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/7887a951ab66eeceed472f273e597ee7fb3586bc-640x423.jpeg 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/7887a951ab66eeceed472f273e597ee7fb3586bc-960x634.jpeg 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/7887a951ab66eeceed472f273e597ee7fb3586bc-scaled.jpeg 2560w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>But in Mille volte il moro of his 6th Book of Madrigals, the Morte (death) is described with uncontrolled polyphony and highly dissonant intervals (Garbuio &amp; Fiorini, 2015).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="674" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1da1339e64cc90c70e404ab948206bc181d5d580-1024x674.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-827" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1da1339e64cc90c70e404ab948206bc181d5d580-1024x674.jpeg 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1da1339e64cc90c70e404ab948206bc181d5d580-300x198.jpeg 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1da1339e64cc90c70e404ab948206bc181d5d580-768x506.jpeg 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1da1339e64cc90c70e404ab948206bc181d5d580-1536x1011.jpeg 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1da1339e64cc90c70e404ab948206bc181d5d580-2048x1349.jpeg 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1da1339e64cc90c70e404ab948206bc181d5d580-640x421.jpeg 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1da1339e64cc90c70e404ab948206bc181d5d580-960x632.jpeg 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1da1339e64cc90c70e404ab948206bc181d5d580-scaled.jpeg 2560w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>It&#8217;s interesting to see how the technical complexity and themes changed from one book to another during his short life. The polyphonic tradition of the Renaissance dominates the first two books, while harmonic experimentalism dominates the third and fourth books. The last two, however, are characterized by more chromatic and dissonant writing, typically associated with mature composers. Considering the themes, his first two books are more simplistic, whereas his last two books are more dramatic in depicting themes of torture, pain, sadness, and death.</p>



<p>It surprised me to find that although we see Gesualdo as an avant-garde musical genius of his time, some people consider him conservative. </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>&#8220;As conservative as it was possible to be in this time. Monteverdi was the radical, the new. There is a very curious letter from the poet Guarini, in which he says he prefers Gesualdo to the modern style because he is ‘so far from the hardness of Monteverdi.’ For Guarini, Gesualdo is so nice, so easy! Exactly the opposite of what we now think.”</p><cite>(Ross, 2011)</cite></blockquote>



<p>Even though other contemporary composers experimented with new sonorities and pushed further the boundaries of what music could be, I believe Gesualdo was one of the leading composers of the late Renaissance. While developing polyphony, a better sense of structure and rhythmic order, he explored contrasting emotions (like in Dolcissima mia vita) and influenced composers hundreds of years after his death.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1639632443177 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Ross, A., 2011. Gesualdo. <em>Alex Ross: The Rest Is Noise</em>. Available at: https://www.therestisnoise.com/2011/12/gesualdo.html [Accessed September 14, 2022].</p>



<p>Burton-Hill, C., 2014. Gesualdo: Glorious music and grisly murder. <em>BBC Culture</em>. Available at: https://www.bbc.com/culture/article/20130905-a-16th-century-musical-badass [Accessed September 14, 2022].</p>



<p>Garbuio, R.L. &amp; Fiorini, C.F., 2015. &#8220;amor&#8221; e &#8220;morte&#8221; Nos Madrigais de Carlo Gesualdo: Um estudo sobre o desenvolvimento da escrita musical e textual. <em>Per Musi</em>. Available at: https://www.scielo.br/j/pm/a/rfCGr7VrcVTbmsczxX8YTsn/ [Accessed September 14, 2022].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
