<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Coursework &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 14:01:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Exercise 5.5</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-5-5/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 08:55:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1436</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Beethoven’s String Quartet Op. 18, No. 1 is the first of six quartets that were published together in&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="722" height="1024" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001-722x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1437" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001-722x1024.png 722w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001-212x300.png 212w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001-768x1089.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001-1083x1536.png 1083w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001-1444x2048.png 1444w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001-300x425.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001-640x907.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001-960x1361.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0001.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 722px) 100vw, 722px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="562" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0002-1024x562.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1438" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0002-1024x562.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0002-300x165.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0002-768x421.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0002-1536x842.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0002-2048x1123.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0002-640x351.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0002-960x526.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Exercise-5.5-Beethoven_0002.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Beethoven’s String Quartet Op. 18, No. 1 is the first of six quartets that were published together in 1801, known as the Op. 18 quartets. These quartets were written during Beethoven&#8217;s early period, and they represent a transition from the classical style of Haydn and Mozart to Beethoven&#8217;s unique and innovative approach to composition.</p>



<p>This is a composition that greatly impressed me due to its spirited and multifaceted character, full of energy, pathos, and even elements of humour, with abrupt pauses and deceptive endings. The first movement is marked by a playful and vigorous tone, gravitating around the opening motive and employing diverse variations of it throughout the piece. The second movement, by contrast, evokes a more serious and intense atmosphere, that some scholars suggest was inspired by the burial scene in Romeo and Juliet. The third movement, in turn, features a sprightly Scherzo and Trio. Finally, the Allegro finale provides an entertaining and engaging end to the composition, employing silence strategically to evoke a sense of surprise and delight among the audience.</p>



<p>The quartet features a balanced distribution of roles among the instruments. The first violin carries the primary melodic lines, while the other instruments have some supportive role, even though they play monophonically sometime. Indeed, a dynamic interplay exists among the instruments, with the primary melody traversing through all parts.</p>



<p>In my experience, some minor alterations were necessary when arranging a string quartet for solo piano, such as adjusting the harmonies to suit the pianists&#8217; hand limitations. However, the essential character of the quartet can still be captured by a piano, even though it can never catch the dynamic strength of four instruments. I think this is more noticeable in passages with sforzando, like the one in bar 22.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 5.8</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-5-8/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 15:23:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1385</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In Part 5 of this unit, we further explore our comprehension of the Classical Era by examining music&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In Part 5 of this unit, we further explore our comprehension of the Classical Era by examining music on various levels that comprise it. Initially, we obtained a general understanding of the social, political, economic, and cultural circumstances of the era and the influence of significant historical events on this movement. This was a beneficial starting point in comprehending the background and customs of the Classical composers, as well as the innovations they introduced.</p>



<p>Regarding the music itself, the analysis process was usually very similar: listening to the piece following the score, adding annotations to key moments such as themes, sections and modulations, and passages of special textural and sonic interest.</p>



<p>During this particular part, the study of Sonata form held great significance as it allowed me to comprehend how a rigid structure could shape a musical piece or movement. Furthermore, it helped me understand how it offered the composers the flexibility to deviate from the established norms and infuse their own creativity. A prime example of this is Mozart&#8217;s Sonata No.15 in C major for Pianoforte, where he subtly alters the recapitulation by beginning it in the Dominant Key instead of the expected Tonic. Alternatively, some composers such as Bartók, choose to utilize only the fundamental elements of the Sonata form, as demonstrated in the example we analyzed.</p>



<p>Picking on this contrast between Mozart, Haydn and Bartók, I found also helpful to contrast compositions from different eras to identify their unique stylistic features and better appreciate their creative innovations. </p>



<p>Given that the Sonata form embodies the fundamental principles of classicism, emphasizing balance and elegance, it was expected to see that these composers followed these rigid structures. But analysis of the pieces brought to the surface how they crafted remarkable and captivating pieces that respected the structural conventions of the form they employed, while still managing to surprise and delight the listener.</p>



<p>One additional finding after going through different analyses of pieces of this era was that tonal relationships and thematic development were important features of classical works.</p>



<p>Personally, I find the process of &#8220;unpacking&#8221; a composition to be simultaneously fascinating and exhausting. On the one hand, it offers a privileged behind-the-scenes look at the composition, as if one were unravelling the very mind of the composer, as Cook (1987) aptly notes. On the other hand, this process can be time-consuming and arduous, in stark contrast to the simple act of listening to and experiencing a piece. It&#8217;s not uncommon to spend days analyzing a mere 20-minute composition, only to realize that there is still much left to uncover. Nonetheless, this meticulous approach often leads to a newfound appreciation and respect for a work that might have initially appeared less complex than it truly is.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1680275711129 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Cook, N. (1987) <em>A guide to musical analysis.</em> New York: Oxford University Press.</p>



<ul></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 5.4</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-5-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 14:38:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1376</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Steve Reich (born October 3, 1936,&#160;New York, U.S.) is one of the greatest living composers. He is considered&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Steve Reich (born October 3, 1936,&nbsp;New York, U.S.)  is one of the greatest living composers. He is considered one of the greatest contributors to the minimalist music movement with a style based on repetitive and rhythmic patterns. His compositions often feature a limited number of instruments.</p>



<p>In 1988, Steve Reich created &#8220;Different Trains,&#8221; a three-part composition featuring a string quartet and excerpts from audio recordings. This highly personal work draws inspiration from Reich&#8217;s recollections of his Jewish upbringing in the United States and his train voyages across the country. The piece&#8217;s themes are further contextualized by the vastly different connotations associated with train travel during World War II in Europe, where the transportation of Jews took on an entirely different significance.</p>



<p>The pioneering aspect of the composition lies in its integration of prerecorded sounds with a live string quartet. Sourced from a range of records featuring diverse train sounds and spoken-word samples, including those from Holocaust survivors, this unique blend of live performance and recorded sounds lend a layer of profundity and authenticity to the piece. In particular, the first movement stands out for its complete fusion of the strings and recordings, with the latter serving as the motivic ideas that the strings then elaborate upon. This creative approach, innovative for its time, elevates &#8220;Different Trains&#8221; to a remarkable work of art.</p>



<p>Across all three movements, a continuous repetition of sounds and patterns interlock and build upon one another, creating a rich and almost hypnotic soundscape. While this reinforces the rhythmic motion of a train, it also enables the listener to become fully immersed in the 30-minute journey of an industrialized landscape, transitioning into haunting melodies and ultimately concluding on a hopeful note. </p>



<p>While I was unable to discern any conventional chord progressions commonly found in classical string quartets, I observed a pronounced typical rhythmic texture primarily conveyed through the strings. In my opinion, this rhythmic quality injects the composition with a sense of emotion, motion, and intrigue, preventing it from succumbing to monotony and repetitiveness.</p>



<p>In my view, the most fascinating aspect of &#8220;Different Trains&#8221; lies in its harmonious melding of realism and emotion. The inclusion of train whistles and station sounds fosters a vivid and evocative soundscape, while the voices infused throughout the piece infuse a human element that heightens the profound emotional depth already conveyed through the strings.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1680187196987 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (1998b) <em>Steve Reich | Biography, Music, Tehillim, Music for 18 Musicians, Clapping Music, Different Trains, &amp; Facts</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/biography/Steve-Reich.</p>



<p>Schnipper, M. (2017) <em>Listening to Steve Reich’s Holocaust Opus “Different Trains.”</em> Available at: https://pitchfork.com/thepitch/schnips-picks-listening-to-steve-reichs-holocaust-opus-different-trains/.</p>



<p>Wikipedia contributors (2023a) <em>Different Trains</em>. Available at: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Different_Trains.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 5.3</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-5-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 14:57:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1370</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Cook (1987) raises a compelling argument regarding analysing music, which resonated with me in the few analysis I&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Cook (1987) raises a compelling argument regarding analysing music, which resonated with me in the few analysis I made during this course: how intimate you become with the music the more time you spend analysing it as if you&#8217;re unravelling the very mind of the composer. However, Cook also points out that to get that intimacy with the piece and closeness with the composer, one must know what questions to ask during an analysis. And here&#8217;s where analytical methods are important.</p>



<p>Musical analysis can cover a spectrum of considerations such as the social, historical and aesthetic factors and expressive content, as well as more formal analysis concerned to form, melodic, harmonic and rhythmic content.</p>



<p>One of the most recognized formal analyses was created by Heinrich Schenker in the years before the second world war and developed ever since. Cook refers to it as the &#8220;Schenkerian Analysis&#8221; that works very well with tonal music. Schenkerian theory proposes that music is made up of various layers: the ursatz or fundamental structure, which is a two-voice structure that forms the basis for an analytical approach to examine the complexities of a piece; the middle ground which consists of inter-relating the actual foreground of the music with the imaginary voices of the background (Cook, 1987); the foreground or surface level. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="765" height="632" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/image-2.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1373" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/image-2.png 765w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/image-2-300x248.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/image-2-640x529.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 765px) 100vw, 765px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>SOUND PATTERNS: Chapter 31. The 123’s of Schenkerian Analysis</em> (no date). Available at: https://academic.udayton.edu/PhillipMagnuson/soundpatterns/perspec/123graphing.html.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Another field of analysis is the semiotic one, which Jean-Jacques Nattiez is a proponent, does not concern itself with too much the diatonic framework, but rather with the repetition of units and analyzing how they used throughout the piece. </p>



<p>There is also the Set Theory, developed by Milton Babbitt and later Allen Forte. It can be used on any kind of music, including atonal music. Set theory primarily deals with pitch classes, which refer to the &#8220;character&#8221; of a pitch. This analytical approach that allows for the description of all pitch and interval class collections, without relying on the traditional triadic or tonal functions. The result is a reduction in the total number of sets, making the process more manageable and accessible.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1680098828423 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Cook, N. (1987) <em>A guide to musical analysis.</em> New York: Oxford University Press.</p>



<p>Sutcliffe, T. (no date) <em>Music Analysis Introduction</em>. Available at: https://www.harmony.org.uk/book/musical_analysis_introduction.htm.</p>



<p>Whittall, A. (no date) <em>analysis</em>. Available at: https://www-oxfordreference-com.ucreative.idm.oclc.org/view/10.1093/acref/9780199579037.001.0001/acref-9780199579037-e-257.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 5.2</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-5-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 10:06:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A string quartet is generally composed of two violins, a viola and one cello and is typically viewed&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>A string quartet is generally composed of two violins, a viola and one cello and is typically viewed as a genre of music that is like a conversation. In fact, in a letter from 1829, addressed to the composer Carl Friedrich Zelter, Goethe compared the string quartet to &#8220;a stimulating conversation between four intelligent people&#8221; and saw in it &#8220;the most comprehensible of instrumental music genres.&#8221; </p>



<p>The evolution of the string quartet is not entirely clear, although there seems to be an inclination towards the divertimento genre and the Baroque Trio Sonata as possible sources of influence. What is clear is that the string quartet grew in popularity due to its low cost and ease of rehearsal. It was also the ideal size for small home gatherings and allowed for more freedom in composing. In addition to its practicality, the string quartet is also thought to have reflected the aesthetic values of the Enlightenment era: its intimate conversation with equal participation of all voices, as well as its capacity to convey a deep musical thought.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Although other composers such as Holzbauer, Wagenseil, Allegri, and Scarlatti had explored the string quartet, it is Joseph Haydn (1732-1809) who is widely regarded as &#8220;the father of the string quartet.&#8221; While he did not invent the genre, he made the most significant contributions to defining it, composing a total of 68 quartets. Initially, the quartets he wrote were primarily centred on the first violin, with the viola and cello doubling the melody. However, over time, he evolved the texture to be more uniform in terms of the instruments&#8217; importance. Furthermore, he also refined the form, initially starting with five movements, like the divertimento genre, but later settling on four movements, with the first one in sonata form.</p>



<p>Mozart was another influential composer who helped develop the string quartet, notably with the six pieces dedicated to Haydn and the three dedicated to Frederick William II of Prussia. These quartets are regarded as mature works and reflect the style established by Haydn.</p>



<p>Beethoven was influenced by the work of Haydn and Mozart. While his first six quartets, Op.18 (1798–1800), adhered to the established string quartet framework, his three Razumovsky quartets, Opus 59 (1806), are regarded as reflecting his transition towards Romanticism and are widely considered to be among his finest works.</p>



<p>In the 19th century, some composers moved away from classical forms, like Liszt, Wagner, and Richard Strauss, resulting in a decrease in quartet composition. However, Antonín Dvořák wrote 14 quartets. The quartet regained popularity among composers during the Modern era, playing a key role in the works of Debussy, Ravel, Schoenberg, Bartók, and Shostakovich. In the late 20th century the genre still has some composers interested in developing it, such as Karlheinz Stockhausen&#8217;s Helikopter-Quartett composed in 1992-93. Composers such as Riley, Glass, Reich and John Adams produced string quartets in their own style.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1680082470210 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Stowell, R. (2003) <em>The Cambridge Companion to the String Quartet</em>. Cambridge University Press.</p>



<p>Anonymous (2023) <em>Defining the String Quartet: Haydn | Stanford Online</em>. Available at: https://online.stanford.edu/courses/sohs-ymusicstrnqrtet-defining-string-quartet-haydn (Accessed: April 5, 2023).</p>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (1998) <em>Quartet | music</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/art/quartet-music (Accessed: April 5, 2023).</p>



<p>Klorman, E. (2016) <em>String quartets were likened to refined conversation during the 18th and 19th centuries</em>. Available at: https://www.thestrad.com/playing-hub/string-quartets-were-likened-to-refined-conversation-during-the-18th-and-19th-centuries/5161.article (Accessed: April 5, 2023).</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 5.4</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-5-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 11:18:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1357</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The texture of the main theme can be seen as a four-part counterpoint as each instrument has its&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The texture of the main theme can be seen as a four-part counterpoint as each instrument has its own independent line. However, when listening to this section, one perceives a distinct melody on the first violin supported by the accompaniment, especially in the viola and the cello.</p>



<p>In the first variation, the second violin plays the melody while the first violin plays an arpeggiated figure. I&#8217;m not sure if this is considered a two-part counterpoint because there is no distinct melody on the first violin. Nonetheless, the first violin&#8217;s role feels more like an accompaniment. Upon listening to this variation, one can perceive that both instruments are connected, especially in bar 36 when both instruments reach their climax at the same time.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="343" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-11.34.18-1024x343.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1358" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-11.34.18-1024x343.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-11.34.18-300x101.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-11.34.18-768x257.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-11.34.18-1536x515.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-11.34.18-640x214.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-11.34.18-960x322.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-11.34.18.png 1916w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 35-37</figcaption></figure>



<p>The second variation has a richer texture. The cello takes on the primary melody, while the second violin initially moves homophonically with the cello before gradually diverging and converging with the first violin. The first violin features a distinct melody that starts out thin and gradually becomes denser as the variation progresses. Meanwhile, The viola has a simple accompaniment part. This variation can be seen as a three-part counterpoint.</p>



<p>The third variation presents a more intricate texture and a chromatic sound. The viola takes on the primary melody, while the two violins play their own distinct melodies. The cello remains silent for eight bars, but upon entering, it creates an intensely chromatic feeling in bars 69-71, perhaps due to its bass sound serving as the foundation for the chords. This variation appears to have a four-part counterpoint, featuring highly independent lines. However, there are moments where the voices seem to be rhythmically coordinated.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="336" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.21.30-1024x336.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1362" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.21.30-1024x336.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.21.30-300x98.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.21.30-768x252.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.21.30-1536x504.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.21.30-640x210.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.21.30-960x315.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.21.30-1920x632.png 1920w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.21.30.png 1928w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 69-71</figcaption></figure>



<p>The final variation returns to the simplicity of the first variations. The main melody is played by the first violin, and the other voices serve to support it while retaining their unique character. It may not necessarily qualify as a definitive four-part counterpoint. The texture is much more compact compared to the previous variation, and it becomes particularly crisp in bars 91-97, where all instruments play in their upper register.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="370" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.19.42-1024x370.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1361" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.19.42-1024x370.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.19.42-300x108.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.19.42-768x278.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.19.42-1536x555.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.19.42-2048x741.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.19.42-640x231.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.19.42-960x347.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-28-at-12.19.42.png 2428w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 92-95</figcaption></figure>



<p>The main difference between the first and second movements is that in the latter the texture shifts from one variation to the next, but remains constant within each individual variation. In the first movement, the texture continuously changes without a discernible pattern or structure.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 5.3</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-5-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 13:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1354</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I find investigations such as the one conducted on Haydn&#8217;s Emperor to be extremely useful, particularly when seeking&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I find investigations such as the one conducted on Haydn&#8217;s Emperor to be extremely useful, particularly when seeking to bridge the gap between the emotional and rational aspects of classical music. When casually listening to a piece, we can often become consumed by the emotions it evokes, without giving much thought to how they are conveyed. However, investigating the structure and development of a composition, as well as the techniques used by the composer, provides us with a more rational understanding of the music. Through investigation, we can better appreciate the intricate and intentional ways in which the music is made to bring out specific emotional responses and enhance our overall listening experience.</p>



<p>Through this investigation, I gained a deeper understanding of the Sonata form and how it can be developed with different themes. I also gained a new understanding of the techniques used by composers to create a musical journey that navigates from the home key to a distant key and back again. This exploration reminded me that musical forms are not rigid structures, but rather malleable frameworks that composers can use as they see fit, much like Bartók did.</p>



<p>Furthermore, I found the investigative approach to be extremely useful, as it provided me with a structured framework for future analysis. Starting with a broad perspective and progressively digging into specific details:</p>



<ul>
<li>Identify the form</li>



<li>Identify themes and keys</li>



<li>Outline the structure</li>



<li>Establish how the transitions of keys and sections are made</li>



<li>Analyse how themes are built and used throughout the piece</li>
</ul>



<p>One thing that is missing from this analysis is to consider the broader musical landscape at the time of composition, such as the prevailing trends and techniques used by other composers. By understanding the broader musical context, we can better appreciate what makes a piece unique and significant.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 5.2</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-5-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 13:09:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1351</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The piece begins in C major and the first four bars present the themes and are very homogenous&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The piece begins in C major and the first four bars present the themes and are very homogenous in terms of rhythm between the instruments. This and the perfect cadences convey a sense of comfort and stability</p>



<p>The key continues to be C major until bar 13, where the first theme modulates. This brings a confusing mood to the piece, where the centre of tonality seems to be lost. I get the sense that it moves to E, before having the pedal note in D. This pedal tone creates a lot of tension, before establishing the new key.</p>



<p>In the second subject area, the piece moves to the secondary dominant key of G. This feels fresh but still in a bright mood. However, the piece momentarily shifts to G minor at bar 29, creating an edgy and uncertain mood. Overall, this section has a sense of stability but provides unexpected twists and turns, keeping the listener engaged.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 5.1: Bartók’s String Quartet No. 4 (1928)</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-5-1-bartoks-string-quartet-no-4-1928/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 13:27:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1345</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Béla Bartók (1881 &#8211; 1945) was a Hungarian composer, and one of the most influential figures in 20th-century&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Béla Bartók (1881 &#8211; 1945) was a Hungarian composer, and one of the most influential figures in 20th-century music. His pieces are known for their extensive chromaticism and novel rhythms. He is known for collecting and studying authentic Hungarian folk music and incorporating them into his music. He wrote six string quartets which were among his most impressive achievements, being the fourth, the most celebrated.</p>



<p>The String Quartet No.4 has five movements that are written symmetrically. It contains two sets of identical movements with a middle movement which is the central point of the quartet. Here is Bartók explaining it:</p>



<p>&#8220;The work is in five movements; their character corresponds to Classical sonata form. The slow movement is the kernel of the work; the other movements are, as it were, arranged in layers around it. Movement IV is a free variation of II, and I and V have the same thematic material; that is, around the kernel (Movement III), metaphorically speaking, I and V are the outer, II and IV the inner layers.&#8221; (Keller, 2011).</p>



<p>Although Bartók suggests that the nature of the first and final movements corresponds with that of the Classical sonata form, I believe that he merely employed the concept of the sonata form and utilized it liberally as a framework for his composition, without adhering rigorously to its conventions. Distinct motifs are present in the quartet, rather than explicitly articulated themes as found in the sonatas of Beethoven or Haydn. These motific ideas tend to appear for a very short time and disappear quickly. This reminds me of Debussy.</p>



<p>Upon listening to this piece for the first time, I found it much harder to distinguish the sonata sections, in contrast to Haydn&#8217;s quartet, wherein such segments were easily discernible. However, after reading the score and watching Andreyev&#8217;s analysis, I was able to understand the structure of the piece, the division of the sections, and the appearance of each motif.<br></p>



<p>When listening to the entire movement, I found it to be incredibly radical and challenging to follow. This left me confused, especially knowing that Bartók employs several counterpoint techniques that are commonly used in the works of many Western composers, including contrary motion, imitation, inversions, and call-and-response.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="193" height="300" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22-193x300.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1347" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22-193x300.png 193w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22-300x467.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22.png 438w" sizes="(max-width: 193px) 100vw, 193px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Contrary Motion</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="297" height="300" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-297x300.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1346" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-297x300.png 297w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-80x80.png 80w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-300x303.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-640x647.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35.png 702w" sizes="(max-width: 297px) 100vw, 297px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Inversion</figcaption></figure>



<p>Bartók demonstrates an innovative use of the quartet by investigating the sonorities of the three instruments through techniques such as extreme note ranges, varied glissandos, and his unique interpretation of pizzicato, which involves a vigorous plucking motion that produces a sharp snap upon the string&#8217;s impact with the instrument.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1679676452719 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Stevens, H. (2023) <em>Béla Bartók | Hungarian composer</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/biography/Bela-Bartok (Accessed: March 28, 2023).</p>



<p>Keller, J.M. (2011) <em>Chamber Music: A Listener’s Guide</em>. Oxford University Press, USA.</p>



<p>Samuel Andreyev (2017) <em>Béla Bartók’s String Quartet N° 4: Analysis</em>. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pMV7KaxyBIE.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 5.1</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-5-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 14:43:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1328</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="exposition" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1679584588902 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-4 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Exposition</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1796" height="812" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.26.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1337" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.26.png 1796w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.26-300x136.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.26-1024x463.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.26-768x347.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.26-1536x694.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.26-640x289.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.26-960x434.png 960w" sizes="(max-width: 1796px) 100vw, 1796px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 1 and 2</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="410" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.31-1024x410.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1335" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.31-1024x410.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.31-300x120.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.31-768x308.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.31-1536x615.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.31-640x256.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.31-960x384.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.31.png 1768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bar 5</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="649" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.46-1024x649.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1336" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.46-1024x649.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.46-300x190.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.46-768x487.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.46-1536x974.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.46-640x406.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.46-960x609.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-14.57.46.png 1924w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bar 26 and 27</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<h2 id="recapitulation" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1679584599751 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-4 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Recapitulation</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="268" height="300" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.08.15-268x300.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1333" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.08.15-268x300.png 268w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.08.15-300x336.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.08.15-640x717.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.08.15.png 694w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bar 79</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="300" height="271" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.09.01-300x271.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1334" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.09.01-300x271.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.09.01-640x578.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.09.01.png 766w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bar 80</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="296" height="300" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.09.48-296x300.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1332" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.09.48-296x300.png 296w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.09.48-80x80.png 80w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.09.48-300x304.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.09.48.png 608w" sizes="(max-width: 296px) 100vw, 296px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bar 83</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="607" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.11.39-1024x607.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1331" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.11.39-1024x607.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.11.39-300x178.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.11.39-768x455.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.11.39-640x379.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.11.39-960x569.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-23-at-15.11.39.png 1208w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 98 and 99</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 5.0</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-5-0/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Mar 2023 11:48:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1322</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[An illustration of the main sections of the sonata form and how they relate to one another. Stein,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>An illustration of the main sections of the sonata form and how they relate to one another.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="2000" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Multicolor-Professional-Chronological-Timeline-Infographic-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1329" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Multicolor-Professional-Chronological-Timeline-Infographic-1.png 800w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Multicolor-Professional-Chronological-Timeline-Infographic-1-120x300.png 120w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Multicolor-Professional-Chronological-Timeline-Infographic-1-410x1024.png 410w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Multicolor-Professional-Chronological-Timeline-Infographic-1-768x1920.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Multicolor-Professional-Chronological-Timeline-Infographic-1-614x1536.png 614w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Multicolor-Professional-Chronological-Timeline-Infographic-1-300x750.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Multicolor-Professional-Chronological-Timeline-Infographic-1-640x1600.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1679485097236 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Stein, L. (1999) <em>Anthology of Musical Forms &#8211; Structure &amp; Style (Expanded Edition): The Study and Analysis of Musical Forms</em>. Alfred Music.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 5.0</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-5-0/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 14:30:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1317</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[All art evolves in a cultural, social, and political context and music is no exception. The birth of&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>All art evolves in a cultural, social, and political context and music is no exception. The birth of the Classicism in the 18th Century can be traced to the following phenomena: Enlightenment, democratization, humanism, the emergence of the middle class and the development of new musical styles and instruments.</p>



<p>The Enlightenment  (1685 – 1815) was a transformative era in history that rejected traditional ideas of the time and emphasized the importance of reason and logic. It advocated for a rational, scientific approach to life in contrast to superstition and traditionalism. As critical thinking gained traction, it posed a challenge to the established church and organized religion.</p>



<p>During this period, political upheavals and conflicts were prevalent. The American and French Revolutions, the War of the Austrian Succession, and the Seven Years&#8217; War, among others, played a significant role in shaping the ideals of the epoch, highlighting the significance of equal rights. It led to a steep rising in democratization.</p>



<p>Economically, land was no longer the only source of income. With the advent of manufacturing and trading, job opportunities and skills emerged. Individuals were no longer defined solely by their family background, but by their professions. This transformation led to the emergence of the middle class, which in turn put pressure on society to change institutions and improve their standard of living, income, and social mobility.</p>



<p>In terms of intellectual evolution, humanistic ideas regained their prominence and a newfound belief that life on earth is as important as life after death challenged the church&#8217;s traditional stance. Prominent French intellectuals such as Voltaire and Jean-Jacques Rousseau spoke out against outdated concepts of aristocracy, class divisions, and religious and racial prejudices.</p>



<p>During this time, society began to view science and art as complementary rather than opposing forces. There was an increase in the importance of creating harmony and harmony in all aspects of life. The Encyclopaedia of Diderot d’Alembert was a great example of this cross-disciplinary collaboration, as it aimed to gather knowledge from all different areas, including music.</p>



<p>All this led to profound changes in music. </p>



<p>Music was previously only available to the elite, but The Enlightenment changed how music was written and distributed. The music industry became more profitable, and composers were able to earn a living for themselves. Music was democratized, and composers began writing more freely for public concerts pursuing a greater emphasis on the structure of the piece and creating simpler harmonic functions. This led to a departure from the elaborate ornamentation of the Baroque music era.</p>



<p>Musical tastes of the middle-class criteria favoured tuneful, clear and homophonic sounds. The piano, invented in the late Baroque, was capable of greater dynamic sensitivity. Similarly, the violin underwent significant technical changes, resulting in increased range and sound projection. </p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1679409011398 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Lang, P.H. (1967) “The Enlightenment and Music,” <em>Eighteenth-Century Studies</em>, 1(1), p. 93. Available at: https://doi.org/10.2307/3031668.</p>



<p>Taruskin, R. (2009) <em>The Oxford History of Western Music: Music in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries</em>. OUP USA.</p>



<p>Wikipedia contributors (2023a) <em>Humanism</em>. Available at: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humanism (Accessed: March 21, 2023).</p>



<p>Hughes, K. (2014) <em>The middle classes: etiquette and upward mobility</em>. Available at: https://www.bl.uk/romantics-and-victorians/articles/the-middle-classes-etiquette-and-upward-mobility (Accessed: March 21, 2023).</p>



<p>Jaramillo, C. (2023) <em>Art and Music in the Age of Enlightenment</em>. Available at: https://www.theaterseatstore.com/blog/art-music-enlightenment (Accessed: March 21, 2023).</p>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
