<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 22:43:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Beethoven &#8211; Symphony No. 1 in C major, Op. 21</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-beethoven-symphony-no-1-in-c-major-op-21/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 22:11:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1925</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As the lovely and gradual introduction in the first movement gets underway, the anticipation for a strong cadence&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As the lovely and gradual introduction in the first movement gets underway, the anticipation for a strong cadence builds and builds, but it doesn&#8217;t arrive. The music is constantly leaving you on a hook and, just when you think it can&#8217;t get any more energetic, the strings drop into tune and the winds have a moment of stillness. At last, the cadence arrives but the pace never lets up throughout the movement, toying with your expectations throughout. It&#8217;s a back-and-forth of suspense and surprise, the whole way up to a glorious conclusion that couldn&#8217;t leave you in any doubt of the music&#8217;s full force.</p>



<p>The second movement has the feel of classical formality, with a subject and then periods of rest. At first, the emotional restraint in this movement might make it less engaging, but the dramatic volume level gives the music layers of interest that will keep you listening.</p>



<p>Beethoven scores more points with dynamic change and strong contrast in the third movement. These are hallmarks of his style, and you can see why people, like me for example, just really enjoy listening to his music.</p>



<p>The symphony&#8217;s final movement starts dramatically and commands attention immediately. Throughout this movement, it feels like Beethoven is deliberately playing with the listener&#8217;s expectations again, creating moments where the orchestra resembles a choir and leading the listener to anticipate a conclusion, only to defy those expectations. The movement maintains a sense of suspense and anticipation, keeping the listener engaged until the very end.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Clementi &#8211; Sonata Op. 26 No. 2</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-clementi-sonata-op-26-no-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 22:02:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1918</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This was the first Clementi work I listened to, and I found it to have great emotive depth.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This was the first Clementi work I listened to, and I found it to have great emotive depth. It featured intricate harmonies and masterful variation writing, offering a compelling listening experience. The slow movement is particularly poignant, with its evocative expression, providing a glimpse into Clementi&#8217;s musical prowess and his ability to convey powerful emotions.</p>



<p>One of the striking aspects of this piece is the technical usage of the pianoforte. The work progressively presents challenges for the performer, showcasing Clementi&#8217;s understanding of piano technique while exploring imaginative variations. This balance between technical demands and musical depth makes this work intriguing for listeners, allowing them to appreciate the potential of the keyboard.</p>



<p>The unexpected plot twists in the opening movement demonstrate the fusion of technical complexity with expressive musicality. The torrents of notes and sudden, dramatic contrasts make it an impressive movement both in technicality and musicality.</p>



<p>In the final movement, I notice a connection between Clementi&#8217;s writing and that of Beethoven, particularly in the strong dynamic contrasts. However, the rapid arpeggios that set the mood remind me more of a Romantic movement, suggesting that Clementi might have been an influential composer for future generations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Clementi &#8211; Piano Duet in C Major, Op. 6 No. 1</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-clementi-piano-duet-in-c-major-op-6-no-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 23:24:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1921</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This was a truly enjoyable piece to listen to, similar to a vibrant chat between two close friends.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This was a truly enjoyable piece to listen to, similar to a vibrant chat between two close friends. It takes you on a journey through varying moods.</p>



<p>The piece begins with a lively movement, filled with cascading scales and playful tunes. It&#8217;s intriguing how it feels familiar yet different, not a composition from a known composer. The two piano parts intertwine beautifully, creating a delightful blend of friendly rivalry and harmony. The joy in their back-and-forth interactions is palpable, with one piano seemingly predicting the other&#8217;s phrases, building anticipation.</p>



<p>The second movement provides an expectable contrast. The melody becomes more introspective, featuring long, flowing lines that feel like a shared moment of reflection. The tenderness with which the two pianos merge into a single voice creates a sense of closeness and connection.</p>



<p>The final movement reintroduces the energy and excitement. The music surges forward with swift scales and virtuosic passages, a cascade of notes that carries the listener along. There&#8217;s a playful defiance in this movement, a celebration of the sheer joy of creating music.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
