<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 15:16:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Assignment 4</title>
		<link>./../../../../assignment-4-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 14:38:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1288</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Programme notes The beauty of twilight time, between sunset and moonrise, has captivated human beings for centuries. The&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Programme notes</strong></p>



<p>The beauty of twilight time, between sunset and moonrise, has captivated human beings for centuries. The Latins had an expression for this special time of day &#8211; &#8220;lux quae fugit,&#8221; which translates to &#8220;the light that flees.&#8221; This phrase captures the ephemeral and fleeting nature of twilight, which often invokes a mixture of feelings. Some may feel nostalgic for the day that is ending while others may feel peaceful for the night to start. Despite the tumultuous emotions that arise, the eventual arrival of night inevitably brings a sense of calm and tranquillity.</p>



<p><strong>Composition</strong></p>



<p>My composition takes inspiration from Impressionist music, particularly Debussy&#8217;s preludes. The piece is structured into three distinct parts: the relaxing day, the tumultuous feelings of twilight, and the peace of the night.</p>



<p>To achieve an Impressionistic sound, I started by experimenting with various pentatonic scales on the piano, ultimately settling on the arpeggio of the C# minor pentatonic. This scale forms the basis for the first part of the prelude, with modulations to C# Dorian  (bars 5-6) and A Dorian (bars 7-8).</p>



<p>There&#8217;s a brief transition where I actually don&#8217;t know which C major mode I wrote, but I believe it sounds like a D Dorian until it settles in a C Mixolydian.</p>



<p>The middle section of the piece is marked by a play between C Mixolydian and a Whole Tone scale, with a brief detour into the Whole Tone scale based on Eb (bars 18-19). This leads into the &#8220;cascading&#8221; section, where the music moves from the C Mixolydian to the G major modes of A Dorian and B Phrygian, ending in E harmonic minor. This section aims to explore the extremes of the piano, creating a mysterious feeling of going up and down simultaneously.</p>



<p>The final section of the prelude moves from D Major to G Major and ends in C Major, evoking a sense of peace and tranquillity after the tumultuous emotions of twilight.</p>



<p>Throughout the piece, I utilize a pedal tone to build tension and create a sense of stationary motion.</p>



<p>Overall, my goal in this composition was to capture the essence of Impressionist music by exploring unique scales and timbres on the piano while conveying the range of emotions experienced during the transition from day to night.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 4.6</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-4-6/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 12:27:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1283</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Alban Berg (1885-1935), along with Anton Webern (1883–1945), were two of the three composers of the Second Viennese&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Alban Berg (1885-1935), along with Anton Webern (1883–1945), were two of the three composers of the Second Viennese School which Arnold Schoenberg (1874–1951) pioneered. </p>



<p>Alban Berg, an Austrian composer born in Vienna, started his music education with Arnold Schoenberg in 1904. He was active during the remarkable artistic, musical, and literary upsurge in Vienna during the early 20th century, associating with prominent figures such as Gustav Klimt. Berg&#8217;s work is often viewed as more melodious and comprehensible than that of his mentor, Schoenberg. His most renowned compositions encompass a variety of musical forms, including orchestral music, such as Five Orchestral Songs (1912), chamber music, songs, and two pioneering operas, Wozzeck (1925) and Lulu (1937). The Violin Concerto, which Berg composed in 1935, is widely regarded as his masterpiece.</p>



<p>This piece was dedicated to Manon Gropius, the daughter of Alma Mahler and Walter Gropius, who died of polio at the age of eighteen. Berg crafted this piece in two movements, each of which comprised two distinct parts. The first movement adheres to the conventional sonata form, commencing with an Andante section and culminating with an Allegretto segment evocative of dance. This movement is deemed to symbolize life. The second movement primarily revolves around a recurring rhythmic cell (Allegro), which is succeeded by a sombre Adagio portion, portraying death.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="600" height="238" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/bergs_tone_row_600px.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-1286" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/bergs_tone_row_600px.jpeg 600w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/bergs_tone_row_600px-300x119.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></figure>



<p>Berg&#8217;s use of the twelve-tone row in the composition is considerably rooted in conventional harmony. This is due to the fact that the twelve-tone row can be divided into three triad chords, succeeded by notes of the whole tone scale that lead up to G. Alternatively, the tone row can be analyzed as G minor major 7, A minor major 7, followed by the notes of the whole tone scale.</p>



<p>Upon listening to the piece and studying the score, it appears that Berg&#8217;s selection of the tone row effectively established tonality into an essentially atonal framework. I believe that this decision contributed to the composers&#8217; capacity to pay tribute to Manon Gropius.</p>



<p>Ultimately, despite the rigorously technical structure, the composition evokes strong emotional sentiments and conveys profound expressivity.</p>



<p>Anton Webern, a notable composer and conductor, was also born in Vienna. In 1904 he started receiving composition lessons from Arnold Schoenberg. Webern is considered as one of the foremost proponents of the twelve-tone technique and is renowned for pushing it to its limits. Despite producing some orchestral works, his work primarily comprises vocal and instrumental chamber music, with only a single symphonic composition.</p>



<p>His compositional style is distinguished by its succinctness, brevity, and intensity. The composer undertook an exploration of innovative dimensions of musical expression, particularly atonality, while simultaneously exhibiting meticulous attention to detail, and at times, an exacting rigidity in his musical compositions. He was very fond of utilizing classical forms as a foundational framework upon which to construct his twelve-tone music. I believe that his compositional style is particularly evident in Symphony, Op.21.</p>



<p>In contrast to Berg&#8217;s concerto, Webern&#8217;s Symphony highlights a more radical utilization of the twelve-tone methodology. The use of canons in the first movement and the theme and variations in the second movement are a more methodical use for the twelve-tone. Despite the presence of classical forms in this composition, its analysis presents considerable challenges to me. The melody line, shaped by the canons and their inversions, rapidly transitions between different instruments, reflecting a distinctive style of Webern&#8217;s compositional style.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="721" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-10.52.13-1024x721.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1289" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-10.52.13-1024x721.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-10.52.13-300x211.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-10.52.13-768x541.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-10.52.13-1536x1081.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-10.52.13-2048x1442.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-10.52.13-640x451.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-10.52.13-960x676.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-10.52.13.png 2338w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Mario Yesyes (2022) <em>Webern symphony op. 21: 4-part double canon with colours and tone-rows analysed</em>. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8PDcD3PoYA4.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Webern&#8217;s implementation of the twelve-tone row methodology is characterized by a pronounced mathematical orientation, contrasting with Berg&#8217;s harmonic approach. The composer utilized a symmetrical row structure that may be divided into two parts, with the second part representing a retrograde of the first. Moreover, it is noteworthy that the interval between the first and twelfth, second and eleventh, and so forth, is always a tritone. This row exemplifies Webern&#8217;s preference for the utilization of half-steps in his compositions.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="155" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-12.00.59-1024x155.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1290" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-12.00.59-1024x155.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-12.00.59-300x45.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-12.00.59-768x116.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-12.00.59-640x97.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-12.00.59-960x145.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-10-at-12.00.59.png 1320w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>After listening to it several times, I feel that the composition is distinguished by its minimalistic character and sparse texture. Despite the limited instrumentation, the piece is remarkable for its extraordinary intensity. The attention to detail is evident in the nuanced interplay of instruments, where each contributes to a great variety of colour and texture, creating a dense and complex web of sounds that together form a cohesive whole.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1678451216989 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Reich, W. (2023) <em>Alban Berg | Austrian composer</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/biography/Alban-Berg (Accessed: March 10, 2023).</p>



<p><em>British Library</em> (no date b). Available at: https://www.bl.uk/people/alban-berg (Accessed: March 10, 2023).</p>



<p>Gresham, M. (2020) <em>Review: Beethoven set the tone for ASO concert, with landmark works by Berg and Shostakovich | EarRelevant</em>. Available at: https://www.earrelevant.net/2020/01/review-aso-beethoven-berg-shostakovich/ (Accessed: March 10, 2023).</p>



<p><em>British Library</em> (no date). Available at: https://www.bl.uk/people/anton-webern (Accessed: March 10, 2023).</p>



<p>Service, T. (2017) <em>Symphony guide: Webern’s op 21</em>. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/tomserviceblog/2013/dec/17/symphony-guide-webern-op-21 (Accessed: March 10, 2023).</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Devonté Hynes &#8211; The Long Ride II</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-devonte-hynes-the-long-ride-ii/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 14:39:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I decided to listen to Devonté Hynes&#8217; music after reading a review in the Guardian of his concert&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Devonté Hynes: The Long Ride II; Inheritance with Adam Tendler" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_PcxLhJrkGI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I decided to listen to Devonté Hynes&#8217; music after reading a review in the Guardian of his concert with the London Symphony Orchestra. I didn&#8217;t know his work, so it was interesting to dig a bit into his work. </p>



<p>Devonté Hynes&#8217; Long Ride II is a two-piano rendition that was written for HBO&#8217;s Series “We Are Who We Are.” Hynes is primarily known for his R&amp;B and indie music, but he has recently been exploring classical music, which I find an interesting move. </p>



<p>The Long Ride II features a repetitive arpeggio and chords in one of the pianos, while the other builds upon the background, almost as if it is improvising. It has an impressionist feeling of improvisation, and perhaps in the live version, the pianist is really improvising.</p>



<p>The piece is based on an F major chord, and there doesn&#8217;t seem to be a defined structure. Instead, there is an increase in texture that keeps growing until almost the finale where one of the pianos plays alone, which is like a return to the beginning.</p>



<p>Although Devonté Hynes&#8217; Long Ride II is an intriguing piece of music that showcases Hynes&#8217; exploration of classical music, its repetitive nature doesn&#8217;t appeals to me. Nonetheless, it was worth listening to it.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 4.5: Stravinsky and Neoclassicism</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-4-5-stravinsky-and-neoclassicism/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 15:36:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1277</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Despite being perceived as holding irreconcilable positions by their contemporaries, it is now widely understood that the apparent&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Despite being perceived as holding irreconcilable positions by their contemporaries, it is now widely understood that the apparent conflict between Schoenberg and Stravinsky was largely manufactured by political propagandists. Contemporary views acknowledge that both artists shared similar aims and objectives.</p>



<p>During the interwar period, the Romantic era approached a state of near-collapse, as evidenced by the prevalence of monumental symphonic works and autobiographical tone poems. This led to a conscious rejection of the whole apparatus of late Romantic music and a call for a simpler, more objective music. They felt the need to go back in time, a nostalgia, for inspiration and perhaps a homage to previous composers such as Mozart, Bach or Beethoven, in order to bring some clarity and order to music. </p>



<p>Various artists had differing perspectives on the interpretation of &#8220;order&#8221;. Notably, serialists, particularly Schoenberg, regarded the notion of order as a strict construct, almost akin to the concept of law. In fact, Josef Matthias Hauer presented his &#8220;law of the twelve tones&#8221; in 1919.</p>



<p>In contrast, there were a group of artists who believed that this order should be less strict and more based on musical forms and stylistic features from previous eras, such as the Classical Period. This led to Neoclassicism.</p>



<p>Neoclassicism involved a rejection of the lush harmonies and exaggerated emotionalism of late Romanticism, as well as a rejection of modernism&#8217;s atonal and experimental tendencies. Instead, neoclassical composers sought to create clear, concise, and intellectually rigorous works using classical forms and structures such as the sonata, concerto, and symphony.</p>



<p>Although Prokofiev&#8217;s Classical Symphony (1918) may seem to be the first neoclassical work, the start of the movement is generally attributed to Igor Stravisnky&#8217;s Pulcinella (1919), a ballet using themes by Giovanni Battista Pergolesi and other baroque composers. Stravinsky continued to explore neoclassical ideas in works such as the &#8220;Octet for Wind Instruments&#8221; (1923), the &#8220;Concerto for Piano and Wind Instruments&#8221; (1924), and the &#8220;Symphony of Psalms&#8221; (1930). In these works, Stravinsky used classical forms and structures but also incorporated elements of modernism, such as dissonant harmonies and polyrhythms.</p>



<p>One of the most important Neoclassical artists was Paul Hindemith who systematically developed a new contrapuntal style, described as a 20th-century version of Bach.</p>



<p>Some other important composers that have written in neoclassical style are Satie, Bartók, Milhaud, de Falla or Tailleferre. </p>



<p>Given the considerable experimentation and creative exploration present in various musical styles in the early twentieth century, it is understandable why some regarded neoclassicism as a musical step backwards, a regression through past musical history. But as serialism, it is clear now that neoclassicism has become recognized as an important movement that synthesized new and old musical ideas and created a unique aesthetic that continues to inspire contemporary composers.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1677598302408 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Lessem, Alan (1982). Schoenberg, Stravinsky, and Neo-Classicism: The Issues Reexamined. The Musical Quarterly, 68(4), 527–542. Available at: http://www.jstor.org/stable/742156 (Accessed: February 28, 2023).</p>



<p>Apel, W. (1969) Harvard Dictionary of Music, 2nd Revised and Enlarged Edition. Second Revised&amp;enlarged. Belknap Press: An Imprint of Harvard University Press.</p>



<p>Walsh, S. (no date) <em>Stravinsky and Neoclassicism</em>. Available at: https://www.bl.uk/20th-century-music/articles/stravinsky-and-neoclassicism (Accessed: February 28, 2023).</p>



<p>Wikipedia contributors (2023) <em>Neoclassicism (music)</em>. Available at: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neoclassicism_(music) (Accessed: February 28, 2023).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Gamelan</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-gamelan/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 12:57:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1256</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[After reading about Debussy&#8217;s fascination with Javanese gamelan music and its influence on his compositions, I became intrigued&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>After reading about Debussy&#8217;s fascination with Javanese gamelan music and its influence on his compositions, I became intrigued and decided to listen to it myself.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Sound Tracker - Gamelan (Indonesia)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UEWCCSuHsuQ?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Balinese Gamelan - Sekar Jupun" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0RKM2xj0qKc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Angklung Pupuan" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Dwc9voKOgyw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Gamelan music, originating from Java in Indonesia, features an ensemble of tuned metal instruments, including gongs and percussion instruments. This type of music is also found throughout Southeast Asia. The sound of gamelan music is characterized by an interplay of metallic sounds defined by one of two scales: slendro, which divides the octave into five equal intervals, and pelog, which divides it into seven.</p>



<p>Balinese music is structured like a tree, with different instruments symbolizing the trunk, branches, and flowers. The core melody, or pokok, is played by one group of instruments in one octave. Another group stresses this melody at regular intervals, while a third expands it into a full melody with a range of two to three octaves. A fourth group doubles and paraphrases it an octave higher, while a fifth group plays an ornamental figuration. Gongs punctuate and structure the music, while the drums provide rhythmic support.</p>



<p>Upon listening to gamelan music, one is struck by the clear and metallic sounds, which evoke the stirring of a thousand bells. The interplay of the sounds is delicate, and confused, and possesses a sensuous charm. The overall effect is one of mystery, which can be quite overpowering.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1679316807717 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Channing, A. (2020) <em>Balinese gamelan: a complete guide to a unique world of sound</em>. Available at: https://www.songlines.co.uk/features/balinese-gamelan-a-complete-guide-to-a-unique-world-of-sound (Accessed: February 28, 2023).</p>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 4.4</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-4-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 15:43:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1268</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The impact of Claude Debussy&#8217;s musical vocabulary on the evolution of jazz has been profound (Pamies, 2021), influencing&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The impact of Claude Debussy&#8217;s musical vocabulary on the evolution of jazz has been profound (Pamies, 2021), influencing a number of composers such as Duke Ellington, one of the founding fathers of jazz. (Ross, 2018).</p>



<p>To fully appreciate the compositional styles of Claude Debussy and Miles Davis, it is important to understand the underlying motivations that led to their musical breakthroughs. Both artists sought to distance themselves from the current artistic movements of their time, with Debussy aiming to break away from the influence of Germanic Romanticism and Davis seeking to move beyond the heavy tonality and fast harmonic rhythms of bebop jazz. In other words, both composers sought to break free from the constraints of their respective musical traditions and push the boundaries of what was possible in terms of harmonic and melodic freedom.</p>



<p>To achieve their respective goals, Debussy adopted an Impressionist style of music, while Davis found inspiration in modal jazz.</p>



<p>The 1959 release of Miles Davis&#8217; album, &#8220;Kind of Blue,&#8221; marked a pivotal moment in the history of jazz, especially the inaugural track of the album, &#8220;So What,&#8221; which is famous for being one of the first modal jazz songs.</p>



<p>Waters (2005) argues that there exist four salient techniques that typify modal jazz, namely the utilization of extended pedal points, suppression of standard harmonic progressions, slow harmonic rhythm, and association of a seven-note scalar collection with each harmony. The presence of these characteristics in the music of Debussy is a compelling evidence of his influence on jazz.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="524" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-14.19.21-1024x524.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1270" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-14.19.21-1024x524.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-14.19.21-300x153.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-14.19.21-768x393.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-14.19.21-1536x786.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-14.19.21-2048x1048.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-14.19.21-640x327.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-14.19.21-960x491.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-14.19.21.png 2960w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Example of a Pedal Point in &#8220;Les sons et le parfums tournent dans l&#8217;air du soir&#8221;</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="650" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-15.00.09-1024x650.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1271" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-15.00.09-1024x650.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-15.00.09-300x190.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-15.00.09-768x487.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-15.00.09-1536x974.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-15.00.09-2048x1299.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-15.00.09-640x406.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-15.00.09-960x609.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-24-at-15.00.09.png 2576w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Example of slow harmonic rhythm in &#8220;Reflets dans l’eau&#8221;</figcaption></figure>



<p>Besides the direct reference in the introduction to Debussy&#8217;s Voiles, both styles share a preoccupation with harmony and colour, and they tend to focus on creating a mood or atmosphere rather than following a rigid melodic or harmonic structure. Debussy’s use of whole-tone and pentatonic scales and unconventional chord progressions echo the modal jazz style that Davis developed in “So What.”</p>



<p>Regarding dissonance, one of Debussy&#8217;s biggest influences in this track in particular and in Jazz, in general, is the idea of “free dissonance”. The thinking that the 7th or 9th of a chord can exist as a sonority on its own without the need for resolution into a consonance. </p>



<p>Additionally, &#8220;So What&#8221; reflects another significant feature of Debussy&#8217;s style: improvisational feeling. Focusing on the use of a single mode or scale over extended periods and placing equal harmonic weight on all notes associated with a particular chord, resulted in a heightened sense of liberation in both melodic and harmonic exploration, ultimately fostering a greater degree of creative freedom for improvisation and experimentation.This approach influenced the genre and ultimately led to the development of Free Jazz.</p>



<p>Overall, it can be argued that Debussy&#8217;s influence on Miles Davis and Bill Evans can be summed up as promoting harmonic and melodic freedom, with a focus on color, imagination, and sound.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1677160755404 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Pamies, S. (2021) “Deconstructing Modal Jazz Piano Techniques: The Relation between Debussy’s Piano Works and the Innovations of Post-Bop Pianists,” Jazz Education in Research and Practice, 2(1), p. 76. Available at: https://doi.org/10.2979/jazzeducrese.2.1.06.</p>



<p>Ross, A. (2018) <em>The Velvet Revolution of Claude Debussy</em>. Available at: https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2018/10/29/the-velvet-revolution-of-claude-debussy (Accessed: February 23, 2023).</p>



<p>Waters, K. (2005) “Modes, Scales, Functional Harmony, and Nonfunctional Harmony in the Compositions of Herbie Hancock,” Journal of Music Theory, 49(2), pp. 333–357. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1215/00222909-011.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Haydn &#8211; String Quartet in E-flat, Op. 33, No. 2</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-haydn-string-quartet-in-e-flat-op-33-no-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 12:10:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1300</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In 1781, Franz Joseph Haydn composed his Op. 33 String Quartets, which he dedicated to the Grand Duke&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In 1781, Franz Joseph Haydn composed his Op. 33 String Quartets, which he dedicated to the Grand Duke Paul of Russia. Consequently, these quartets are frequently referred to as the &#8220;Russian&#8221; quartets. The second quartet in E-flat, commonly known as the &#8220;Joke&#8221; quartet, is the most celebrated of the set. The nickname &#8220;Joke&#8221; is believed to have originated from the final movement, which incorporates a series of playful musical jokes, such as a mock conclusion and an unexpected outburst of powerful chords, which leave the listener with a feeling of joyful surprise.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="716" height="1024" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-716x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1302" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-716x1024.png 716w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-210x300.png 210w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-300x429.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40-640x915.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.09.40.png 747w" sizes="(max-width: 716px) 100vw, 716px" /></figure>



<p>Comprising four movements, the piece follows a a non-traditional structure. The first movement is composed in Sonata form, while the second, instead of being a Minuet and Trio, is a Scherzo and Trio. The third and fourth movements are both arranged as a Rondo.</p>



<p>The quartet opens with a delightful theme that is subsequently fragmented, manipulated, and reassembled in various ways. Personally, I found this movement to be lighthearted and fascinating, particularly as Haydn deftly plays with the theme, departing from and returning to it, as demonstrated in the following example.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="713" height="517" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.43.45.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1303" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.43.45.png 713w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.43.45-300x218.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.43.45-640x464.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 713px) 100vw, 713px" /></figure>



<p>The second movement caught my attention with the violin slides present in the Trio section. The movement has a dance-like quality to it, with the second violin intermittently interacting with the first violin. At the same time, the viola and cello provide a steady foundation for the piece.</p>



<p>The third movement presents a stark contrast, opening with the lower strings and at a slower tempo in a Largo style. I found the movement to be somewhat dramatic, particularly with the powerful forte chords played by all strings. An illustration of this effect is evident in the following example towards the end of the movement.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="453" height="295" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.57.43.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1307" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.57.43.png 453w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-20-at-11.57.43-300x195.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 453px) 100vw, 453px" /></figure>



<p>The Rondo in the fourth movement shows a catchy, memorable theme that is both danceable and owns a humorous character. The coda segment of the movement is surprising, as the expected recurrence of the theme is subject to hesitant pauses, creating a sense of suspense and uncertainty for the listener. The final pause builds a sense of anticipation, ultimately ending with a soft whisper that leaves the listener with an unresolved sense of closure.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 4.3</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-4-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 13:48:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1264</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#8220;Voiles,&#8221; meaning &#8220;sails&#8221; or &#8220;veils,&#8221; gave me the impression of a connection to the wind. As I listened&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>&#8220;Voiles,&#8221; meaning &#8220;sails&#8221; or &#8220;veils,&#8221; gave me the impression of a connection to the wind. As I listened to it, the gentle, ethereal quality of the music immediately brought to mind the iconic Plastic Bag scene from the film &#8220;American Beauty.&#8221;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="AMERICAN BEAUTY ~ Plastic Bag Scene [HD]" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Qssvnjj5Moo?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>After re-watching the scene, I believe the composer, Thomas Newman, was inspired by Debussy&#8217;s &#8220;Voiles&#8221;. There are similarities between the two pieces: both feature motifs that move in parallel chords, with an unresolved melodicism and a persistent pedal point running throughout.</p>



<p>While &#8220;Voiles&#8221; evokes a sense of wind, it also carries a certain air of mystery, which can be attributed to the concept of veils. The pervasive use of the whole-tone scale throughout the piece may contribute to this enigmatic quality, adding to the overall impression of ambiguity and uncertainty.</p>



<p>In the opening of the prelude, Debussy builds a small melodic motif around a whole-tone scale harmonized by intervals of a 3rd and 4th, with the pedal note B-flat providing a sense of grounding that will persist throughout almost every bar of the piece. In a way, it seems as though the piece doesn&#8217;t really go anywhere &#8211; it lacks a clear direction or purpose, much like a veil (or a plastic bag) caught in the wind. It simply floats and drifts, carried along by the shifting currents of the melody.</p>



<p>Debussy repeats and develops the initial motif throughout the piece until he eventually suspends the pedal and introduces a new melodic element &#8211; a minor pentatonic scale in E-flat &#8211; as a response and a closing of the development. This section feels like a release from the constraint of the previous material and is perhaps the most exciting part of the piece. However, it doesn&#8217;t last long, and soon the melody returns to its drifting, aimless quality, leaving the listener with a sense of unresolved tension and mystery.</p>



<p>The main whole-tone section returns after just a few bars, and with it comes the sensation of floating, only now with some runs that add a bit of movement to the melody. There&#8217;s a sense that the piece is building towards a climax, with a cadence perhaps just around the corner &#8211; but it never arrives. The floating feeling persists all the way to the end, leaving the listener with a sense of lingering uncertainty and an unfulfilled sense of resolution.</p>



<p>Especially in the first few pages of the score, I can sense a clear counterpoint between the voices, such as the use of contrary motion in this example, as well as a sense of distinct rhythms between them.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="412" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-17-at-13.32.17-1024x412.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1265" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-17-at-13.32.17-1024x412.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-17-at-13.32.17-300x121.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-17-at-13.32.17-768x309.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-17-at-13.32.17-1536x619.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-17-at-13.32.17-640x258.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-17-at-13.32.17-960x387.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-17-at-13.32.17.png 1574w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 4.2</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-4-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 16:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1254</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The history of the modes goes back to ancient Greece when they used different scale systems to divide&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The history of the modes goes back to ancient Greece when they used different scale systems to divide the octave and named them after territories of Greece and around. The Christian church, around 750 AD, developed seven different scale patterns called Gregorian chant, and gave them the names of the Greek modes, without worrying about their similarities. By 1700, most music used only two of the seven modes, which became known as the major and minor keys. In modern music, modes are less commonly used than major or minor keys, but they can also be found in folk, jazz, classical, and pop music (Powell, 2011).</p>



<p>The seven Greek modes are:</p>



<ol>
<li>Ionian (also known as the major scale)</li>



<li>Dorian</li>



<li>Phrygian</li>



<li>Lydian</li>



<li>Mixolydian</li>



<li>Aeolian (also known as the natural minor scale)</li>



<li>Locrian</li>
</ol>



<p>Each mode consists of a set pattern of tones and semitones derived from the W-W-H-W-W-W-H pattern from the major scale as we can see from the example below.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="803" height="1024" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-15-at-12.26.57-803x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1259" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-15-at-12.26.57-803x1024.png 803w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-15-at-12.26.57-235x300.png 235w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-15-at-12.26.57-768x980.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-15-at-12.26.57-300x383.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-15-at-12.26.57-640x817.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-15-at-12.26.57-960x1225.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-15-at-12.26.57.png 1124w" sizes="(max-width: 803px) 100vw, 803px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The seven European heptatonic diatonic &#8220;church&#8221; modes (Tagg,2014)</figcaption></figure>



<p>The most interesting aspect to me is understanding why should a composer use such modes. The straight answer is to give the composer more emotional options than the standard major and minor dichotomy. With modes, is as if the composer is able to introduce, even briefly, a new colour or flavour to convey a specific mood or emotion.</p>



<p>I found Tagg&#8217;s (2014) explanation of which traits each mode has, very helpful.</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Ionian</strong>: is the most common mode in western music and its intervals are the most comfortable to the regular western listener. Music in Ionian mode tends to be happy and bright with examples such as national anthems (God Save The Queen, The Star-Spangled Banner), Happy Birthday or Jingle Bells.</li>



<li><strong>Dorian</strong>: after the Ionian and Aeolian, this is the most common mode mostly because of its similarity with the natural minor (except for the raised sixth in Dorian). Its distinctiveness comes from the combination of minor 3rd and 7th and major 6th. In order to sound Dorian, one must use the 1st, 3rd, 5th and 6th which lends the music a melancholic yet optimistic sound.</li>



<li><strong>Phrygian: </strong>this is the only mode that has a minor 2nd and a perfect 5th and it&#8217;s commonly used in Flamenco. Being a minor mode, it has a darker feel than the Aeolian because of the minor 2nd and has been used by the heavy metal genre to convey a mysterious and &#8220;doom&#8221; feeling, such as in Wherever I May Roam by Metallica.</li>



<li><strong>Lydian:</strong> this mode is just like Ionian but it has a raised 4th which lends the scale an airy, floating and happier sound than Ionian. Film composers tend to adopt this mode for cheerful tunes, John WIlliams one of its main adepts using it in themes such as ET and Back to the Future.</li>



<li><strong>Mixolodyan:</strong> similar to Ionian but with a flattened 7th is characteristic for having a lack of leading tone, which makes it sound smoother than a major scale. It is commonly used in traditional songs from England and Ireland, as well as tunes from Northeastern Brazil, such as Forró. It is also used in rock guitar solos since the flattened 7th exists in the 7th, 9th, 11th, and 13th chords.</li>



<li><strong>Aeolian:</strong> is the same as a natural minor scale and its characteristic sound comes from the positioning of its two semitones &#8211; between the 2nd and 3rd, and the 5th and 6th. The repetition of these intervals is perceived as conveying grief, pain or misery. It can be heard in Chopin&#8217;s Marche Funebre as well as Nirvana&#8217;s Smells Like Teen Spirit.</li>



<li><strong>Locrian: </strong>is the least used mode because of its lack of a perfect fifth and a presence of a tritone between the 1st and 5th. It is extremely dissonant and unstable with an extreme tension that lends it a dark mood. It&#8217;s hard to find examples of songs using this mode, but Björk&#8217;s Army Of Me is one of the few examples that keep appearing.</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1676478509840 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Powell, J. (2011) <em>How Music Works: The Science and Psychology of Beautiful Sounds, from Beethoven to the Beatles and Beyond</em>. Reprint. Little, Brown Spark.</p>



<p>Tagg, P. (2014) <em>Everyday Tonality II</em>. The Mass Media Scholars Press, Inc.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 4.1</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-4-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 16:10:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1249</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Claude Debussy&#8217;s &#8220;Prélude à l&#8217;après-midi d&#8217;un faune&#8221; is a musical composition that is based on the poem &#8220;L’après-midi&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Claude Debussy&#8217;s &#8220;Prélude à l&#8217;après-midi d&#8217;un faune&#8221; is a musical composition that is based on the poem &#8220;L’après-midi d’un faune&#8221; Stéphane Mallarmé. The poem tells the story of a faun, a mythical creature who is half-man and half-goat, as he wakes up from a nap in the forest and is overwhelmed by lustful desires towards nymphs. </p>



<p>This bucolic poem represented a historic milestone of literary symbolism. It places emphasis on the stimuli surrounding the action, rather than the action itself. This creates a reality that is diffuse, with a stronger focus on perception than representation. Is the faun dreaming? Or is all that real? The reader never knows. What is true is that the poem is full of ambiguity and musicality, taking advantage of the French language and its nuances: colour, vowels, and diphthongs. Mallarmé followed the French belief of that time: &#8220;how you say something is as important as what you say: style (timbre) is as important as substance (pitch and rhythm)&#8221; (Greenberg, 2013).</p>



<p>Debussy&#8217;s &#8220;Prélude à l&#8217;après-midi d&#8217;un faune,&#8221; composed between 1892 and 1894, is a musical reflection of the elusive ambiguity present in Mallarmé&#8217;s poem. The fluid rhythms and tonal uncertainties of Debussy&#8217;s composition effectively capture the hazy, indistinct quality of Mallarmé&#8217;s writing.</p>



<p>I believe it cannot be considered a symphonic poem, as it does not adhere to a narrative or a formal structure based on the exposition-development-recapitulation sequence. Instead, it flows freely, mimicking the emotions of its titular character. This free-form approach was a wise decision, as it keeps the listener engaged and constantly surprised. With each listening, one is never quite certain where the music is headed, making for a captivating and unpredictable musical experience.</p>



<p>Starting from the famous opening flute melody, which has an emphasis on the tritone (the ambiguous interval), followed by the horns and soft harp glissandos, set a dreamy and soft awaking tone that resembles the opening of the poem.</p>



<p>One of the most intriguing parts for me starts in bar 17, where the oboe and clarinet produce a sensual and exotic sound. They are then joined by the full orchestra before the clarinet is left to play alone. To me, it feels like the sound of the wind, a whisper, or a call. The repetition of the orchestra adds depth and enhances the overall effect, making this part truly captivating.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="832" height="1024" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-10-at-14.57.15-832x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1250" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-10-at-14.57.15-832x1024.png 832w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-10-at-14.57.15-244x300.png 244w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-10-at-14.57.15-768x945.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-10-at-14.57.15-1249x1536.png 1249w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-10-at-14.57.15-300x369.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-10-at-14.57.15-640x787.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-10-at-14.57.15-960x1181.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-10-at-14.57.15.png 1338w" sizes="(max-width: 832px) 100vw, 832px" /></figure>



<p>Debussy, in my opinion, uses all the sounds and timbres at his disposal to convey the emotions he perceives in Mallarmé&#8217;s poem. He does not follow a specific structure or formal harmonic progression or even tries to follow the story of the poem. Instead, he uses the music as a means to an end, rather than an end in itself, being effective in evoking senses beyond the earthly and capable of creating a fantastical and almost hypnotic musical experience. </p>



<p>This approach aligns with the principles of impressionist painters and symbolist poets who were more concerned with evoking emotions through their work, rather than simply creating a realistic representation. This shift in perspective paved the way for the development of modern art as we know it today.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1676045068403 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Greenberg, R. (2013) <em>How to Listen to and Understand Great Music, 3rd Edition</em>. The Great Courses.</p>



<p><em>Prelude to the Afternoon of a Faun (Claude Debussy)</em> (no date). Available at: https://www.laphil.com/musicdb/pieces/577/prelude-to-the-afternoon-of-a-faun.</p>



<p>Schwarm, B. (2013) <em>Prelude to the Afternoon of a Faun | work by Debussy</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/topic/Prelude-to-the-Afternoon-of-a-Faun.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Igor Stravinsky &#8211; Symphonies of Wind Instruments</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-igor-stravinsky-symphonies-of-wind-instruments/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 15:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1242</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[During my research on Debussy, I discovered that he and Stravinsky were close friends. Following Debussy&#8217;s death, Stravinsky&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="IGOR STRAVINSKY Symphonies of Wind Instruments (1947 version)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VyKTujyLie4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>During my research on Debussy, I discovered that he and Stravinsky were close friends. Following Debussy&#8217;s death, Stravinsky paid tribute by composing a serene chorale, which was later incorporated into the &#8220;Symphonies of Wind Instruments&#8221; in 1920. In 1945, Stravinsky revised the work, publishing it in 1947, and made alterations including the removal of the alto flute and alto clarinet, as well as reworking the musical score.</p>



<p>After listening to it the first time, I absolutely loved this piece. I keep finding Stravinsky&#8217;s work amazing and it&#8217;s one of the composers I most like to listen to, but at the same time is the one I find most difficult to analyze. In the next paragraphs I&#8217;ll try to understand what made me like this piece.</p>



<p>The first hint comes from the title. The &#8220;Symphonies of Wind Instruments&#8221; is a musical work with a title that alludes to the original definition of symphony (as opposed to the musical form) as a harmonious blending of instruments. That&#8217;s one of the characteristics of this piece that stroke me right away. The interplay between the different wind instruments, particularly in terms of the contrasting chromatic tones between the woodwinds and brass, is particularly striking. Stravinsky&#8217;s manipulation of the instruments, such as in bar 3 where he plays a Bb in the trumpet and a B in the clarinets, creates a unique sonic landscape that highlights the tonal differences between the instruments.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="774" height="900" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1243" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41.png 774w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41-258x300.png 258w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41-768x893.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41-300x349.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.33.41-640x744.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 774px) 100vw, 774px" /></figure>



<p>The formal structure of the piece proves to be elusive and challenging to categorize. It frequently alternates between tempos, including 144, 108, and 72 beats per minute, which are related by a ratio of 2:3:4. The fluctuating time signature only adds to the impression of multiple distinct musical ideas being woven together in the composition.</p>



<p>From the beginning, Stravinsky introduces contrasting thematic materials, switching between joyful flutes, mournful full chords, and the chorale theme, which symbolizes Debussy&#8217;s death or funeral. Throughout the piece, there is no clear narrative or progression. The musical ideas seem to shift abruptly, giving the impression of a series of disconnected fragments.</p>



<p>The chorale theme, which recurs throughout the piece, serves as a unifying thread and provides the piece with a sense of direction. It becomes the focus of the conclusion, which is joyful and uplifting, spreading a sense of peace and resolution.</p>



<p> </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="111" height="1024" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2023-02-09-at-13.59.52-111x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1244"/></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point 4.0 &#8211; Impressionism and Symbolism</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-4-0-impressionism-and-symbolism/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 14:57:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Moving into the Twentieth Century]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1235</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The late 19th and early 20th centuries saw a significant transformation in society as a result of rapid&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The late 19th and early 20th centuries saw a significant transformation in society as a result of rapid advancements in science and technology. The invention of new forms of communication led to a change in perceptions of time, space and distance. All these frenetic changes paved the way for new ideas, new perceptions and a new ability to process art that led artists to completely break with the old ways of doing art and start thinking about how they can be relevant in a constant-changing world.</p>



<p>Beyond the hyper expressivity and the “abortive gesture” &#8211; doing the “wrong” thing for the “right” expressive reason &#8211; there were technological advances in materials such as recordings or new canvas that allowed artists to explore their expressions outside.</p>



<p>It was in this context that two styles emerged: impressionism and symbolism.</p>



<p>The Impressionist movement in art sought to capture the reality of the modern world, taking inspiration from the realism of Gustave Courbet. The movement was characterized by its emphasis on capturing the fleeting and ephemeral aspects of light and colour in outdoor environments, diverging from the established tradition of creating posed and historical compositions in a studio setting.</p>



<p>The term &#8220;Impressionism&#8221; as a label for the movement gained widespread recognition following the criticism by Louis Leroy of Claude Monet&#8217;s &#8220;Impression, Sunrise&#8221; (Musée Marmottan Monet, Paris) in 1874, which he disparagingly referred to as a mere &#8220;impression&#8221;.</p>



<p>The chief exponents of Impressionism were Paris-based and include Claude Monet, Pierre-Auguste Renoir, and Edgar Degas in visual arts and Claude Debussy and Maurice Ravel in music.</p>



<p>In contrast, the Symbolist movement was characterized by the use of symbols and imagery to express deeper, abstract concepts and emotions. The movement was influenced by the ideas of Charles Baudelaire and other Symbolist poets, who sought to evoke a deeper meaning beyond the literal representation of objects or scenes in their works.</p>



<p>Prominent Symbolists, such as Paul Gauguin, James Whistler, Gustave Moreau, and Odilon Redon, utilized this approach to explore themes such as spirituality, the unconscious, and the imagination.</p>



<p>But in the end, both Impressionists and Symbolists shared a motivation to represent the ephemeral and emotional elements of experience, in order to facilitate the expression of the artist&#8217;s feelings. These movements disrupted conventional modes of artistic expression and established avenues for subsequent art movements, be it through visual arts, poetry, or music.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1675868304930 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Tate (s.d.) Impressionism. At: https://www.tate.org.uk/art/art-terms/i/impressionism (Accessed on 08 February 2023)</p>



<p>Encyclopaedia Britannica (2013) ‘Symbolism’ [online] At: https://www.britannica.com/art/Symbolism-literary-and-artistic-movement (Accessed on 08 February 2023)</p>



<p>Greenberg, R. and Courses, T.G. (2013) <em>How to Listen to and Understand Great Music, 3rd Edition</em>. The Great Courses.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
