<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 16:31:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Debussy &#8211; The Snow is Dancing</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-debussy-the-snow-is-dancing/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 16:09:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Sound Developments]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=274</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I first listened to this piece I was struck by how well it evokes the image of falling snow. The piece starts with a 16h note ostinato in the high part of the piano....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When I first listened to this piece I was struck by how well it evokes the image of falling snow. The piece starts with a 16h note ostinato in the high part of the piano. These notes made me think of snowflakes drifting down from the sky.</p>



<p>The piece has an interesting sound that comes from how Debussy uses the piano. At the beginning, there&#8217;s a bouncing effect that creates a light texture. Most of the time, the music is light and airy, with lots of quick notes in the high range of the piano. In the middle section, though, the notes are spread out more, using both the high and low parts of the piano. This change makes the music feel deeper and more intriguing.</p>



<p>The constant flow of fast notes makes it feel like the snow is always moving. At the same time, the overall feel of the piece doesn&#8217;t change much, which is kind of like how a snowfall can seem both always moving and always the same.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Focus &#8211; Hocus Pocus</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-focus-hocus-pocus/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 21:52:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Sound Developments]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=272</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I first heard &#8220;Hocus Pocus&#8221; by Focus, I was really surprised and excited. The song is unlike anything I&#8217;ve heard before. It mixes rock music with some really unconventional vocal sounds. The song starts...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When I first heard &#8220;Hocus Pocus&#8221; by Focus, I was really surprised and excited. The song is unlike anything I&#8217;ve heard before. It mixes rock music with some really unconventional vocal sounds.</p>



<p>The song starts with regular rock instruments &#8211; electric guitar, bass, and drums. But then it gets interesting. An organ and a high-pitched singing that sounds like yodeling or tirolesque. It&#8217;s a strange mix, but it works.</p>



<p>The song doesn&#8217;t follow a normal structure. It begins with the band playing fast and loud. Then suddenly, just the singing and organ come in. The rest of the song switches back and forth between the main riff and the solo parts.</p>



<p>I like how Focus tried something new with rock music almost 50 years ago. It&#8217;s refreshing to hear how they mix hard rock with innovative singing, at least for prog-rock. It&#8217;s not what I was expecting, and that&#8217;s what makes it exciting.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Fred Onovwerosuoke &#8211; Twenty-Four Studies in African Rhythms</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-fred-onovwerosuoke-twenty-four-studies-in-african-rhythms/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 20:22:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Sound Developments]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=269</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I listened to this whole piece a few days ago, and my initial reaction to this piece was one of fascination and intrigue. The rhythmic prominence and what I recognized as African musical elements immediately...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I listened to this whole piece a few days ago, and my initial reaction to this piece was one of fascination and intrigue. The rhythmic prominence and what I recognized as African musical elements immediately stood out to me.</p>



<p>This work is scored for solo piano, but the piano is used in an interesting way to emulate percussive instruments. The rapid, syncopated rhythms and the use of the piano&#8217;s full range to create a rhythmic sense. What I liked most was the contrast between the staccato playing and legato melodies, as for example in Study V &#8211; Jali or Study XI &#8211; Aye Dance 3.</p>



<p>I must admit it has been a source of inspiration. It has encouraged me to explore new ways of incorporating rhythmic elements into my own compositions, and to consider how I can use the piano in more unconventional and percussive ways to create a unique sound world.</p>



<p>The nuances and subtleties within the rhythmic patterns have become more apparent with each subsequent listening. I find myself noticing new ways in which the rhythms interact and overlap, contributing to the work&#8217;s constantly evolving and engaging nature.</p>



<p>Through my research, I&#8217;ve learned that Onovwerosuoke is a Ghanaian-American composer who has dedicated much of his work to exploring the different African cultures through music. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
