<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Coursework &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 22:42:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Exercise The Classical opera</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-the-classical-opera/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2024 23:15:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1905</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Marriage of Figaro is a comic opera composed by Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, with an Italian libretto written&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="programme" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1707952589748 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Programme</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The Marriage of Figaro is a comic opera composed by Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, with an Italian libretto written by Lorenzo Da Ponte. It premiered in 1786 at the Burgtheater in Vienna. Based on the play La folle journée, ou le Mariage de Figaro by Pierre Beaumarchais, the opera tells the story of the clever servant Figaro, who is preparing to marry the vivacious Susanna. Their wedding day gets off to a rocky start, however, as their employer Count Almaviva tries to exercise his feudal right to bed the bride before the groom. The plot revolves around a single day filled with twists and turns, as various characters hatch plans to fool one another.</p>



<p>The opera is structured in four acts. Act I establishes the basic plot &#8211; Count Almaviva wants to seduce Figaro&#8217;s bride-to-be, Susanna and has abolished the medieval right of a lord to sleep with a servant girl on her wedding night to make his intentions seem more honourable. Figaro, the count&#8217;s servant, plots to outwit his master&#8217;s plans. In Act II, the Countess laments her husband&#8217;s infidelity while plotting with Susanna to publicly expose the Count&#8217;s plans to embarrass him. In Act III, complications arise with the adolescent page Cherubino, who has a crush on the Countess. There are disguises and much confusion before Susanna and the Countess expose the Count&#8217;s intentions. Finally, in Act IV all is resolved after much scheming, including multiple plans to dress up Cherubino as a girl. The Count begs for forgiveness, the Countess forgives him, and the opera ends with rejoicing over the two marriages – Figaro and Susanna, and the reunited Count and Countess Almaviva.</p>



<p>The Marriage of Figaro shows Mozart&#8217;s genius through brilliant ensemble writing and memorable melodies that capture the emotions of the drama. The overture introduces no less than 9 musical themes or theme fragments that set the mood for this opera. From the famed &#8220;Non più andrai&#8221; where Figaro teasingly says farewell to Cherubino&#8217;s carefree days, to the Countess&#8217;s hauntingly melancholy &#8220;Dove sono i bei momenti,&#8221; the opera overflows with musical riches. The finale of Act IV concludes the opera with one of Mozart&#8217;s most joyful and technically dazzling ensemble finales as all celebrate the happy outcome.</p>



<p>The Marriage of Figaro was an instant hit at its premiere and it has remained as one of the most popular operas for over 200 years. Its characters are recognizable archetypes depicting master-servant class tensions, marital infidelity and forgiveness, outwitting authority, and the confusion of young love. Musically and dramatically, the opera represents the height of the opera buffa (comic opera) genre with Mozart&#8217;s sublime music animating Da Ponte&#8217;s hilarious situations and characters. Performed frequently worldwide, The Marriage of Figaro continues to fascinate modern audiences.<br></p>



<h2 id="personal-review" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1707951249497 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Personal Review:</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>I just saw Mozart&#8217;s &#8220;The Marriage of Figaro&#8221; production by the RCM Opera Orchestra on YouTube. They delivered a delightful evening filled with humour, beautiful music, and impressive performances. While not a seasoned opera critic, I was captivated by the production, particularly the interplay between the skilled musicians and the engaging cast.</p>



<p>While largely traditional, the staging beautifully evoked the opulence of 18th-century Vienna. The classic sets and costumes felt timeless, allowing the focus to remain on the characters and their comedic antics. Sir Thomas Allen&#8217;s direction navigated the opera&#8217;s twists and turns, keeping the pace lively and the humour fresh.</p>



<p>The standout performances were truly captivating. Adam Maxey&#8217;s Figaro was a charming and endearing presence, his voice effortlessly conveying both wit and warmth. Julieth Lozano&#8217;s Susanna was a force of nature, her powerful and passionate vocals embodied the character&#8217;s intelligence and determination. The rest of the cast also impressed, with each singer delivering their roles with commitment and vocal skill.</p>



<p>However, the true highlight of the performance was the RCM Opera Orchestra. With the conductor Michael Rosewell, the musicians delivered a flawless performance. Their playing was tight, nuanced, and full of emotion, perfectly capturing the wide range of moods in Mozart&#8217;s score. From the brilliant Overture to the dramatic climaxes, the orchestra provided a solid foundation for the singers and truly elevated the overall experience.</p>



<p>While the individual performances were strong, the most memorable aspect of the production was the seamless collaboration between the orchestra and the cast. The final scene, where the music and characters come together in a joyful celebration of love and forgiveness, was truly magical.</p>



<p>While I might not be an expert, I felt that the RCM Opera Orchestra&#8217;s &#8220;The Marriage of Figaro&#8221; was thoroughly entertaining.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.google.com/search?region=wt-wt&amp;q=Mozart%27s+The+Marriage+of+Figaro+RCM+Opera+Orchestra+performance+review&amp;tbm=nws" target="_blank"></a></p>



<p><br><br><br></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point &#8211; Music Publishing in the 18th century</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-music-publishing-in-the-18th-century/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 22:18:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1901</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the early 18th century, music publishing centered around major cities like London, Amsterdam, and Paris. Publishers like&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the early 18th century, music publishing centered around major cities like London, Amsterdam, and Paris. Publishers like John Walsh in London helped popularize Italian instrumental music and songs from London&#8217;s theater scene. Engraving allowed more music to be published and distributed across Europe. Meanwhile, the Ballard family held a monopoly on music printing in France, restricting publishing there.</p>



<p>Around 1750, Johann Gottlob Immanuel Breitkopf in Leipzig started experimenting with different printing methods to make sheet music more widely available. He used a combination of movable type, engraving, and manuscript copies . His editions were cheaper than engraved music, allowing him to distribute music more widely and create new markets. Breitkopf helped popularize the German sentimental song genre. Other German publishers like Hartknoch, Rellstab, and Schwickert adopted his techniques.</p>



<p>The onset of the 18th century witnessed a significant shift in music publishing, particularly with the commercial use of engraving. This method allowed for faster production and distribution of music, a stark contrast to the heavy movable type and manuscript copying that had been predominately used. Although manuscript copies and letterpress printing of music continued throughout the century, the development of engraving led to a more extensive and competitive music publication market.</p>



<p>London&#8217;s music publishing scene thrived around 1700, closely followed by Paris between 1740 and 1760, Vienna just before 1780, and Leipzig around 1800. Each city, in its prime, contributed to the cumulative growth of available published music, fostering a competitive environment that spurred public interest in music. This period intertwined with the rising of the middle class, whose demand for printed music became insatiable. Amateur music-making at home became a widespread phenomenon, breaking the monopoly of professional concerts and bringing music into the intimate circles of family and friends. This change democratized music, making it accessible to a wider audience beyond the aristocracy and religious institutions that had previously dominated musical patronage.</p>



<p>The engraving method, which began in London and Amsterdam, facilitated the international distribution of copies through Northern and Western Europe, propelling the music of Italian masters and others to unprecedented popularity. The success and efficiency of engraving caught on quickly, with publishers in major cities adopting the technique and contributing to its refinement. This led to an increased production of instrumental music and operatic scores, bringing a wider variety of music to the public.</p>



<p>In London, the music publishing industry saw significant growth under figures like John Walsh, who became the principal publisher of Handel’s music. Through such publishers, a more organized and expansive distribution system emerged, bringing music to more people than ever before. In parallel, similar developments occurred in Paris and Vienna, each adapting the engraving method to their unique cultural contexts and musical tastes, thus enriching the diversity of music available in the public domain.</p>



<p>The influence of music publishing in this era extended far beyond the mere accessibility of music. It catalyzed a shift in musical tastes, with public concerts becoming more popular and the amateur musician trend fostering a new consumer base for publishers. This period marked a crucial point in the history of music, where the production and consumption of music witnessed revolutionary changes, setting the stage for the dynamic developments in music publishing that would continue into the 19th century and beyond.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1707775994458 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Boorman, S., Selfridge-Field, E. and Krummel, D.W. (2014) ‘Printing and publishing of music’, in <em>Grove Music Online</em>,<em> Oxford Music Online</em> [Online], Oxford, Oxford University Press. Available at http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com.libezproxy.open.ac.uk/subscriber/article/grove/music/40101pg2.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise The Mannheim School</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-the-mannheim-school/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2024 22:38:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1898</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I listened to the first movement of Mozart&#8217;s Flute Concerto in G, following along with the score as&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I listened to the first movement of Mozart&#8217;s Flute Concerto in G, following along with the score as best I could. I was able to follow the score fairly well during the opening orchestral sections and especially during the flute solo passages. However, there were times when the complex interplay between instruments made it tricky to follow every line simultaneously on the score. Still, I found that following the score enhanced my enjoyment of the music rather than detracting from it.</p>



<p>Seeing the notes on the page almost acted as a sort of spoiler, allowing me a sneak peek at whether the melody would go high or low next. Yet this glimpse into the music&#8217;s future only piqued my interest and engagement. I enjoyed anticipating how a phrase would develop or how the flute soloist would embellish the next repetition of the theme. It allowed me to listen more actively and attentively rather than just letting the music wash over me.</p>



<p>In studying the score, a few trademarks of the Mannheim School jumped out at me. First, the homophonic texture was apparent, with a clear melody in the flute over accompaniment harmony in the strings. Second, the harmonies tended to change slowly and smoothly during melodic passages. Finally, the virtuosic flute writing conformed to the Mannheim practice of featuring wind soloists. The flute gets several chances to shine both in lyrical passages and brisk, technical displays.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point &#8211; Period and Modern Ensemble</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-period-and-modern-ensemble/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 22:03:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1895</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When listening to period and modern ensemble recordings of the same classical works, there are some differences in&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When listening to period and modern ensemble recordings of the same classical works, there are some differences in instrumental tone quality, balance, and emotional impact. For example, I compared recordings of Beethoven&#8217;s 5th by the Orchestra of the 18th Century (period instruments) and the West-Eastern Divan Orchestra (modern instruments).</p>



<p>I must confess that I didn&#8217;t find a striking difference between both recordings. Maybe the contrast in earlier periods such as the Baroque might be more noticeable. In these recordings, the most striking contrast is in the tone of the winds and brass. On period instruments like natural horns, the sound is more raw, hollow, and buzzy compared to the refined, rounded tone of modern instruments. The period string section also tends to have a leaner, more transparent ensemble sound.</p>



<p>Emotionally, the period performances often feel lighter, fleeter, and less weighty. Dramatic moments have more nervous tension than rich, stormy anguish. Of course, much depends on the performers&#8217; interpretive choices; period recordings can still convey profound feelings. But the very sound of the instruments naturally lends itself to a different aesthetic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point &#8211; Other Classical Composers</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-other-classical-composers/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 21:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1889</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Classical era was dominated by three figures in Western music: Haydn (1732-1809), Mozart (1756-1791), and Beethoven (1770-1827).&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Classical era was dominated by three figures in Western music: Haydn (1732-1809), Mozart (1756-1791), and Beethoven (1770-1827). However, many lesser-known composers also made significant contributions that shaped the musical landscape leading to Romanticism. Composers like Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach (1714-1788), Luigi Boccherini (1743-1805), Johann Nepomuk Hummel (1778-1837), Muzio Clementi (1752-1832), Christoph Willibald Gluck (1714-1787), Antonín Rejcha (1770-1836), Johann Christian Bach (1735-1782), and Leopold Kozeluch (1747-1818) were influential in developing the gallant style and early classical forms of the symphony, sonata, string quartet and concerto.</p>



<p>Studying their works side-by-side with the great masters reveals similarities that suggest stylistic influences flow both ways. For instance, Mozart&#8217;s early symphonies bear resemblance to those of Johann Christian Bach, whom Mozart deeply admired. Clementi&#8217;s virtuosic piano works were likely a challenge for Beethoven to stretch his technical limits on the instrument. </p>



<p>Johann Christian Bach (1735–1782), the youngest son of J.S. Bach, was an important figure in London&#8217;s music scene and had a profound influence on the young Mozart when the latter visited London in the 1760s. </p>



<p>As the youngest son of the great J.S. Bach, I expected his music to be similar &#8211; intricate counterpoint, dense textures, almost mathematical complexity. But J.C. Bach&#8217;s style is completely different &#8211; light, tuneful, and crystal clear in its expression.</p>



<p>When I listen to J.C. Bach’s keyboard concertos and sonatas, I imagine aristocrats in powdered wigs and pastel suits, sipping tea and nodding along to the music. The melodic lines are so pleasant and catchy, with memorable themes that get lodged in my head. Underneath lies a simple accompaniment that allows the melody to shine.</p>



<p>Refined yet accessible, skillfully crafted but not flashy, his &#8220;Galant&#8221; style hints at the Classical period ahead under composers like Mozart and Haydn. No wonder the young Mozart was profoundly moved meeting J.C. Bach &#8211; the seeds of his melodic genius can be heard in the elder composer&#8217;s long, singing lines and transparent textures. J.C. Bach&#8217;s music floats by lightly, a pleasing precursor to high Classical elegance. (Sadie, 2006).</p>



<p>Among others we might consider is Muzio Clementi (1752–1832), a contemporary of the great masters who was both a noted composer and a famous pianist. Clementi and Mozart even faced off in a piano competition judged by Emperor Joseph II, which reportedly ended in a tie. This event, and Clementi&#8217;s virtuosic style, is thought to have influenced Mozart&#8217;s piano compositions to some extent (Georges De St.-Foix and Martens, 1923).</p>



<p>When I listen to the piano sonatas and other keyboard works of Muzio Clementi, I&#8217;m struck by their nimble, sparkling quality. The fast passages cascade up and down the keyboard with a lightness and clarity that sounds almost modern to my ears.  But there is also passion, especially in the Piano Duet in C Major, Op. 6 No. 1 or his Sonata Op. 26 No. 2 in F sharp minor. Here Clementi unleashes torrents of notes and sudden, dramatic contrasts that sound like Beethoven and it looks like it anticipated the Romantic period.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1707431895826 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Sadie, S. (2006) <em>Mozart: The Early Years 1756-1781, pp. 88-89</em>. Oxford University Press.</p>



<p>Georges De St.-Foix and Martens, F.H. (1923) &#8216;Muzio Clementi (1752-1832),&#8217; <em>The Musical Quarterly</em>, 9(3), pp. 350–382. https://www.jstor.org/stable/738494.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Johann-Christian-Bach#:~:text=In%201772%20he%20was%20invited,from%20and%20greatly%20respected%20Bach." target="_blank"></a></p>



<p><a href="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Johann-Christian-Bach#:~:text=In%201772%20he%20was%20invited,from%20and%20greatly%20respected%20Bach." target="_blank"></a></p>



<p><a href="https://www.quora.com/Who-had-more-influence-on-classical-music-Beethoven-or-Mozart-Did-any-other-composers-have-similar-impact-as-them" target="_blank"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Enjoying Classical music</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-enjoying-classical-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 21:45:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1884</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;ve just heard Haydn&#8217;s Symphony No. 104 for the first time and I believe I can transmit my&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I&#8217;ve just heard Haydn&#8217;s Symphony No. 104 for the first time and I believe I can transmit my understanding of it to you in simple terms since I don&#8217;t think you need to know any musical terms to enjoy it.</p>



<p>The first thing to know is that since it&#8217;s a classical symphony, you might expect it to have 4 movements or parts. This is true of this symphony, called London. Although it has a name that sets it in a location, I think of this symphony as a ball, with several characters presented along the four parts.</p>



<p>First Movement (Adagio — Allegro)</p>



<p>The first part, or the &#8216;introduction,&#8217; greets you with a bold announcement, as if you&#8217;re entering the ball. There&#8217;s the announcement &#8220;The ball is starting!&#8221; Everyone seems shy at first, there&#8217;s not much action happening. The announcements keep coming and everyone walks in gracefully, but then the energy suddenly picks up and the dancers burst into movement. The strings act like a chatty, energetic and playful crowd, while the horns are like the grand host, full of bold and regal proclamations.</p>



<p>Second Movement (Andante)</p>



<p>The second part, often considered the &#8216;slow movement,&#8217; takes on a more reflective tone. Now, we stroll into a peaceful garden, a bit outside of the ball. This part feels like a leisurely walk, with a melody that seems to sing a heartfelt song, gracefully passed between the strings and winds. Sometimes we&#8217;re reminded that there&#8217;s a ball happening, but the characters here continue a chat filled with emotion, depth and sometimes melancholy.</p>



<p>Third Movement (Menuetto: Allegro — Trio)</p>



<p>The third movement is like the party games, more rhythmic. We&#8217;re back inside the ball for the real start of the party &#8211; everyone is dancing. It&#8217;s playful and lively but at one point, it dances into a lighter, more delicate section called the Trio &#8211; imagine taking a detour into a smaller group of dancers. It&#8217;s a musical break for refreshment and socializing before the climax of the dance.</p>



<p>Fourth Movement (Finale: Spiritoso)</p>



<p>Finally, the celebration reaches its peak with an energetic and spirited finale. This is the big finish, with all instruments joining a lively and joyful dance, celebrating the end of a wonderful day packed with adventures. Listen for the fast violin notes that seem to be extremely excited, while the rest of the orchestra adds depth and grandeur. It is a vibrant, joyful dance bringing satisfying closure to this sonic ball.</p>



<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symphony_No._104_(Haydn)" target="_blank"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
