<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Coursework &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 20:46:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Research Point: Antonio Vivaldi</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-antonio-vivaldi/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 22:33:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1935</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Antonio Vivaldi, born in Venice in 1678, was a virtuoso violinist and composer, known for his innovative and&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Antonio Vivaldi, born in Venice in 1678, was a virtuoso violinist and composer, known for his innovative and descriptive music. His father, a part-time professional violinist and flamboyant hairdresser, taught him the violin and instilled in him a love for the instrument. Vivaldi&#8217;s flaming ginger locks earned him the nickname &#8220;Red Priest&#8221; when he entered the clergy, but his asthma made it difficult for him to recite Mass, leading him to abandon his religious duties and become a violin teacher.</p>



<p>It was in 1712 that he wrote Violin Concerto in A minor, Op. 3 No. 6, the sixth concerto in his 12 concerto collection &#8211; L&#8217;Estro Armonico. Overall it sounded too virtuosic for the solo violin, especially the first and third movements. </p>



<p>The three movements offer a delightful journey through contrasting tempos and moods. The first movement is vibrant and energetic, with intricate melodies that challenge the violinist&#8217;s technical skills. In contrast, the Largo movement introduces a serene and contemplative atmosphere, allowing for expressive phrasing and emotional depth. The final movement brings a lively and spirited conclusion, showcasing a rhythmic drive and dynamic contrasts.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Itzhak Perlman-Violin Concerto in A minor,RV 356 Op 3 No 6" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eTPiZup0QmM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Vivaldi&#8217;s career took a significant turn when he became the music director of a Venetian orphanage in 1716, where he was tasked with writing two concertos a month for the all-girls orchestra. In 1718, he took a second job as Chapel Master for the governor of Mantua, where he found inspiration in the beautiful North Italian countryside. This led to the creation of his most famous work, The Four Seasons, which he dedicated to the orphan girls back home.</p>



<p>The Four Seasons is not a single piece, but a set of four separate violin concertos, each with three movements, that are part of a larger collection of 12 violin concertos titled &#8220;The Contest between Harmony and Invention.&#8221; Each concerto is written for solo violin, accompanied by violins, viola, and basso continuo, and corresponds to a specific season: Spring, Summer, Autumn, and Winter.</p>



<p>Vivaldi&#8217;s Four Seasons is considered one of the earliest examples of program music, as it is accompanied by a series of sonnets that describe the scenes and emotions of each season. Vivaldi printed the text of the sonnets in the music and even inserted descriptive words next to particular notes, guiding performers on how to interpret the piece.</p>



<p>Throughout he creates diverse settings with his music, translating the vivid sights and sensations of each season into an amazing sonic narrative. Despite the short instrumentation, his composition creates powerful and diverse settings for listeners to discover. The first concerto, Spring, opens with an infectiously happy theme, followed by a chorus of singing birds, a gentle breeze, and a thunderstorm. The second concerto, Summer, begins with the oppressive heat of the sun, a singing turtle dove, a goldfinch, and a violent storm. The third concerto, Autumn, celebrates the bountiful harvest with a village dance, a drunken display of virtuosity, and a hunting scene. The final concerto, Winter, depicts the harsh cold, an icy wind, the chattering of teeth, and a cosy fire.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Vivaldi: The Four Seasons (Orquesta Reino de Aragón)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4rgSzQwe5DQ?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Around the 1730s, Vivaldi&#8217;s later years were lived with financial struggles and a waning interest in his musical endeavours, as the shifting musical landscape of the Enlightenment era posed challenges to his traditional Baroque style. The decline in demand for his operatic works and the ban on opera performances following the death of Emperor Charles VI contributed to Vivaldi&#8217;s financial hardships and dwindling popularity in Vienna. Despite his erstwhile celebrity and wealth, Vivaldi&#8217;s final years were marred by poverty, culminating in his passing in 1741.</p>



<p>Despite his celebrity and riches in his lifetime, he died in poverty, and his extraordinary music slowly disappeared. The rediscovery of his music began in Italy when Alberto Gentilly, a lecturer in musical history at the University of Turin, made an unexpected and important musical discovery in 1927. He was sent to value a collection of music that was for sale at the Collegio San Marco in the small town of San Martino Natale. Gentilly found 14 volumes of music by Vivaldi, which contained 140 instrumental works, 29 cantatas, 12 operas, and an oratorio. It was an amazing find, but there was more excitement to come. Gentilly realized that half of the collection was missing, and he had a brainwave that it might be part of a split inheritance. He tracked down the rest of the collection and persuaded the reluctant aristocratic owner to sell it. Vivaldi, who had been regarded by experts as a minor figure of the Baroque era, was about to become a major star.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1710542014969 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Knapp, R.L., Porter, W.V. and Talbot, M. (no date) <em>Antonio Vivaldi | Biography, Compositions, &amp; Facts</em>. https://www.britannica.com/biography/Antonio-Vivaldi.</p>



<p>Prego, C. (2023) &#8216;How did this musical genius go from superstar to has-been to icon?,&#8217; <em>Premium</em>, 20 July. https://www.nationalgeographic.com/premium/article/antonio-vivaldi-composer-four-seasons.</p>



<p>Cartwright, M. and La Cave, F.M. (2023) &#8216;Antonio Vivaldi,&#8217; <em>World History Encyclopedia</em> [Preprint]. https://www.worldhistory.org/Antonio_Vivaldi/.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Renaissance composers</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-renaissance-composers/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 21:50:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1945</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tomás Luis de Victoria was born around 1548 in Avila, Spain, and passed away in 1611 in Madrid.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Tomás Luis de Victoria was born around 1548 in Avila, Spain, and passed away in 1611 in Madrid. He is considered one of the greatest composers of the 16th century, alongside Palestrina and Orlando di Lasso. His career spanned both Spain and Italy, and he was known for his almost exclusively sacred and polyphonic vocal music, set to Latin texts.</p>



<p>Victoria was sent by King Philip II of Spain in 1565 to prepare for holy orders at the German College in Rome. He may have studied with Palestrina around this time, and certainly, he was influenced by the Italian style. He held various positions, including chapelmaster and instructor of plainsong. In 1575, Victoria was appointed Maestro di Capella at S. Apollinare.</p>



<p>Notably, Victoria devoted himself entirely to composing sacred music, unlike many of his peers who also composed secular works. His works include 21 masses and 44 motets. He also wrote psalm settings, hymns, several Magnificats, four offices for the dead, and music for Holy Week services. His last work was the Requiem Officium Defunctorum (1605) in memory of the empress Maria.</p>



<p>Victoria’s music is known for its depth of purpose, which I found very present in O Magnum Mysterium. He fused the contrapuntal technique of Palestrina with an intense dramatic feeling that is uniquely personal and deeply Spanish.</p>



<p>As for comments by his contemporaries, specific records are scarce. However, his influence on later Spanish composers was incalculable. His pupils included Manuel de Falla, Isaac Albéniz, and Enrique Granados. His editions of early Spanish music laid the foundations of Spanish musicology.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1710366592777 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (1998e) <em>Tomás Luis de Victoria | Renaissance polyphony, sacred music, motets</em>. https://www.britannica.com/biography/Tomas-Luis-de-Victoria.</p>



<p><em>Composer of the week: Tomas Luis de Victoria</em> (no date). https://www.bbc.com/mediacentre/proginfo/2022/25/composer-of-the-week-tomas-luis-de-victoria.</p>



<p>Punzi, L.P. (2021) <em>The Art of Tomás Luis de Victoria</em>. https://earlymusicseattle.org/the-art-of-tomas-luis-de-victoria/.</p>



<p>Abbott, G. (2021) <em>Tomás Luis de Victoria</em>. https://www.grahamsmusic.net/post/tom%C3%A1s-luis-de-victoria.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point: Humanism</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-humanism/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 20:52:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1943</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Humanism is a philosophical stance that emphasizes the value and agency of human beings. Specifically, humanism affirms that&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Humanism is a philosophical stance that emphasizes the value and agency of human beings. Specifically, humanism affirms that human beings have the right and responsibility to give meaning and shape to their own lives, rather than have meaning imposed externally by a higher power. Humanism focuses on human values, capacities, and worth. It places importance on human dignity and rationality.</p>



<p>Humanism originated during the Renaissance in 14th-century Italy as a cultural movement promoting classical learning and values.</p>



<p>Some key principles of humanism include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Emphasis on critical thinking and evidence over dogma</li>



<li>The belief that truth is discovered by human endeavour rather than revealed by a higher power</li>



<li>Commitment to the use of reason and science as ways of understanding the natural world and our place within it</li>
</ul>



<p>The humanist focus on human dignity, potential, and values translated into music that highlighted the skills and creativity of individual composers and performers. Complex polyphonic styles and instrumental music developed to showcase composer and performer virtuosity.</p>



<p>Humanist themes praised human emotions, experiences, intellect, and achievements became common musical subject matter. Vocal music with texts exploring love, loss, joy, carpe diem etc reflected humanist ideals.</p>



<p>Humanism&#8217;s emphasis on earthly life led to the growing popularity of secular music styles like madrigals and dance music. The use of vernacular languages instead of Latin also became more common, reflecting humanist values.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point: Dissonance in Music</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-dissonance-in-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 21:59:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1941</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In my research on the history of dissonance, I discovered an insightful video by Alan Belkin that shed&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In my research on the history of dissonance, I discovered an insightful video by Alan Belkin that shed light on the evolution and usage of dissonance in music. Belkin makes a compelling point about the shift from vocal music to instrumental music and how this transition impacted the use of dissonance. Dissonance is more challenging to employ in vocal music, as singers must accurately hit the notes, especially when dealing with large intervals. In contrast, instruments can easily play virtually any interval.</p>



<p>Throughout music history, composers have used dissonance in various ways to achieve different effects. In the Baroque Era, composers like Bach utilised dissonance to build tension, which would then resolve to consonance. Bach employed suspension, creating dissonance that the ear accepts because it anticipates the resolution. This added drama and interest to the music.</p>



<p>During the Classical Era, composers like Mozart used dissonance sparingly to heighten emotion at strategic moments. Quick resolutions maintained overall harmonic stability. Mozart would occasionally insert dissonant notes into otherwise consonant themes, creating a playful dissonance.</p>



<p>In the Romantic Era, composers exploited dissonance more freely to convey intense emotions. Pieces often lingered in dissonance before resolving, using clashing intervals and chords to evoke strong feelings.</p>



<p>The 20th century saw composers like Arnold Schoenberg introduce the concept of the &#8220;emancipation of dissonance,&#8221; aiming to treat dissonant intervals and chords as equals with consonant ones. Additionally, microtonal music was created on top of dissonant sounds, generating micro-dissonances that could be subtle or very harsh.</p>



<p>In styles like jazz, dissonant seventh chords became fundamental building blocks of the harmonic language. For example, Gershwin&#8217;s harmonic language is infused with tangy flavors and impish energy through the use of juicy seventh chords.</p>



<p>Belkin argues that the true emancipation of dissonance lies not in using it constantly, but rather employing it strategically to create expressive effects. The perceived tension of dissonance depends on several factors, including the intervals between notes and the register (pitch) of the notes. The closer the notes are and the smaller the intervals between them, the more dissonance there is. However, there is a limit to how intense dissonance can become. A skilled composer will use dissonance purposefully to create expressive effects, rather than incorporating it merely for its own sake.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1710280582838 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Alan Belkin (2019) <em>Analysis for Composers #14 &#8211; on dissonance</em>. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TLLuZEGPns8.</p>



<p>Tommasini, A. (2014) &#8216;Musical dissonance, from Schumann to Sondheim,&#8217; <em>The New York Times</em>, 30 May. https://www.nytimes.com/2014/06/01/arts/music/musical-dissonance-from-schumann-to-sondheim.html.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point: Impact of printing on the dissemination of music</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-impact-of-printing-on-the-dissemination-of-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 21:58:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1939</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[During the early Middle Ages (800-1450), the Catholic Church held significant power over many cultural aspects, including music.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>During the early Middle Ages (800-1450), the Catholic Church held significant power over many cultural aspects, including music. As the clergy and a select few were the only individuals capable of reading and writing, the Church was responsible for creating most music notation. These notations were meticulously crafted in highly decorative manuscripts known as illuminated manuscripts, which were carefully copied by scribes, often monks, onto parchment or vellum.</p>



<p>The process of handwriting and copying music was incredibly time-consuming and resource-intensive, with each manuscript requiring substantial effort to complete. This laborious process limited the number of copies of each piece of music, making the widespread distribution of music challenging. Additionally, the human factor introduced the possibility of errors, with each copy potentially containing inaccuracies rather than being a faithful reproduction of the original.</p>



<p>By the late 15th century, a new technique emerged for printing music, known as woodblock printing. In 1450, Johann Gutenberg&#8217;s invention of the printing press revolutionized the music world. With the advent of printing, the time and resources required to reproduce a sheet of music decreased significantly, leading to a rapid increase in the dissemination of musical scores across Europe. The fidelity of printing not only reduced the errors caused by human copying but also helped standardize musical notation.</p>



<p>One of the most significant impacts of the printing press was the reduction in the cost of reproducing music sheets. As scores became more accessible to musicians and the public, ideas and artistic movements spread more quickly, encouraging the development of new musical styles.</p>



<p>Although Gutenberg&#8217;s invention was a major breakthrough, other technological advancements also played a crucial role in disseminating music. Audio recording allowed for musical preservation and freed music from being locally confined. With recording technology, music performed in one part of the world could be experienced in another, providing a similar listening experience. Simultaneously, the widespread adoption of radio technology enabled music to be broadcast into homes, stimulating interest in various genres.</p>



<p>Ultimately, the internet has been a significant contributor to the widespread dissemination of music. In the present day, music is more accessible than ever, as digitized tracks can be instantly accessed globally, providing creators with platforms to share their work with a broad audience.</p>



<p>In conclusion, since Gutenberg&#8217;s invention, the dissemination of music has been closely tied to technological advancements. These developments have reduced the time and resources required to create and distribute music, making it more accessible to people around the world than ever before.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Musical patronage</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-musical-patronage/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 20:50:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1937</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Musical patronage has been a long-standing tradition in the world of arts, with its roots tracing back to&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Musical patronage has been a long-standing tradition in the world of arts, with its roots tracing back to ancient civilizations. It is a system where individuals or organizations provide financial support to musicians, enabling them to create and perform their work. This relationship between patrons and artists is complex and multifaceted, offering numerous advantages and some potential drawbacks.</p>



<p>One of the most apparent benefits of musical patronage is the financial support it provides to artists. Patrons offer direct financial backing, which allows musicians to focus on their creative work without the burden of financial worries. This financial stability can lead to a higher quality of work, as artists can devote their time and energy to honoring their craft rather than worrying about survival.</p>



<p>Musical patronage also extends its benefits to the wider community. Patrons who are familiar with the local music scene can support projects that benefit the community at large. This could involve funding music education programs, sponsoring community concerts, or supporting local music festivals. These initiatives not only enrich the cultural life of the community but also foster a sense of belonging and unity among its members.</p>



<p>Another significant advantage of musical patronage is its role in cultural preservation. Throughout history, patronage has been instrumental in preserving countless masterpieces and cultural heritage. Today, patrons continue this tradition by funding projects that preserve and promote historical and traditional music. This ensures that these musical traditions are not lost to time but are instead passed down to future generations.</p>



<p>However, musical patronage is not without its potential drawbacks. One of the main concerns is the dependency on patrons. Artists may become overly reliant on their patrons, which could compromise their artistic integrity. This could lead to a situation where artists are creating work to please their patrons rather than following their own creative vision. It is crucial that arts remain free from constraints other than those of the creators themselves.</p>



<p>Another potential issue is the concentration of wealth and power in the hands of a few patrons. This can perpetuate social hierarchies and favor artists with connections or privilege. It can also lead to a lack of meritocracy, where qualifications become secondary to loyalty. This could result in unqualified individuals occupying important positions in the music industry.</p>



<p>In my view, a healthy balance is the ideal solution. The market works well for popular styles of music, where artists can earn a living through sales and performances. However, I believe that there should always be some form of patronage to support music that may not be commercially viable but is culturally or artistically significant. For instance, state funding can support foundations dedicated to preserving national music heritage and education. Private and corporate patrons also play a crucial role in promoting new artists, especially those from lower-income backgrounds who may not have the connections or resources to showcase their work.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point &#8211; Early Instruments</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-early-instruments/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 21:52:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 Ars Nova, Renaissance and Baroque Music]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1929</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Shawm The shawm is an ancient double-reed wind instrument, introduced to Europe during the Crusades, that is&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="the-shawm" class="wp-block-heading">The Shawm</h2>



<p>The shawm is an ancient double-reed wind instrument, introduced to Europe during the Crusades, that is considered a predecessor to the modern oboe. Its sound is produced by blowing through a reed, causing it to vibrate. Shawms were played by medieval and Renaissance musicians and used in dance and ceremonial music.</p>



<h2 id="the-viol" class="wp-block-heading">The Viol</h2>



<p>The viol is a bowed, string instrument that was popular during the 16th to 18th centuries. Its sound is produced by drawing a bow across its strings. It shares similarities in tuning and construction with the Renaissance lute. The viol is an ancestor of the modern violin family. It was played by chamber musicians and used in ensemble music.</p>



<h2 id="the-crumhorn" class="wp-block-heading">The Crumhorn</h2>



<p>The crumhorn is a Renaissance-era double reed woodwind that produces sound through a vibrating reed. Its cylindrical body curves upward at one end. The crumhorn is an early form of double reed instruments like the modern oboe or bassoon. It was played by court and street musicians during the Renaissance and used for dance music.</p>



<h2 id="the-sackbut" class="wp-block-heading">The Sackbut</h2>



<p>The sackbut is an early form of slide trombone, played from the Renaissance through the Baroque eras. Its telescopic slide mechanism alters tube length to change pitches. Sound emanates from buzzing lips against a cupped mouthpiece. The sackbut was played by Renaissance and Baroque instrumental ensembles and used in a variety of secular and sacred musical contexts.</p>



<h2 id="the-dulcian" class="wp-block-heading">The Dulcian</h2>



<p>The dulcian is a double reed ancestor of the bassoon that was popular 1550-1700. Like other double reeds, its sound comes from vibrating reeds. Dulcians were played by Renaissance and early Baroque instrumental consorts and used in chamber and orchestral settings.</p>



<h2 id="the-clavichord" class="wp-block-heading">The Clavichord</h2>



<p>The clavichord is a stringed keyboard instrument that produces sound by striking its brass or iron strings with small metal blades called tangents. It was mainly used in the Late Middle Ages through the Classical era. The clavichord is a forerunner of the piano and other keyboard instruments. It was played primarily by amateur musicians to accompany songs or for personal enjoyment.</p>



<h2 id="the-lute" class="wp-block-heading">The Lute</h2>



<p>The lute is a plucked string instrument and important precursor to the guitar. Its strings are plucked by the performer and its hollow body amplifies the sound. Lutes were extremely popular Renaissance instruments played by amateur and professional musicians. They were utilized in song accompaniment, chamber music, and solo performance.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
