<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 22:27:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Caroline Shaw &#8211; and the swallow</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-caroline-shaw-and-the-swallow/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 22:23:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Composing for Choirs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=379</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I was pleasently surprise by listeinng to this piece. The way Shaw uses silence is particularly interesting &#8211; instead of just being empty space, these quiet moments build excitement and add meaning to the music....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I was pleasently surprise by listeinng to this piece. The way Shaw uses silence is particularly interesting &#8211; instead of just being empty space, these quiet moments build excitement and add meaning to the music.</p>



<p>The piece starts simply. From there, it grows more complex as the voices weave together in interesting ways. Sometimes all the voices are homophonic, and other times they move into polyphonic lines. The overall sound ranges from a full chorus singing together to just whispers, showing how versatile a choir can be.</p>



<p>I believe she does something interesting with the words in this piece. Sometimes she lets us hear them clearly so we understand their meaning. Other times, she breaks them apart into pure sounds, like using the voice as an instrument. This creates an interesting back-and-forth between understanding the words and just experiencing the sounds.</p>



<p>Even though it&#8217;s a recent piece (2017), it reminds me of chant music. One can hear this connection in several ways:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>The slow, thoughtful pace</li>



<li>The melismas</li>



<li>How the group recites text together</li>



<li>The peaceful, meditative feeling it creates</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Bach &#8211; Harpsichord concerto in F minor BWV 1056</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-bach-harpsichord-concerto-in-f-minor-bwv-1056/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 20:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=205</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What stood out most to me was the dynamic relationship between the harpsichord and the string orchestra. The way Bach manipulates this relationship throughout the piece creates a constantly evolving sound that kept me interested...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>What stood out most to me was the dynamic relationship between the harpsichord and the string orchestra. The way Bach manipulates this relationship throughout the piece creates a constantly evolving sound that kept me interested from beginning to end. I found myself particularly drawn to the moments of contrast: when the strings would suddenly align rhythmically with the harpsichord, or when they would stop completely, leaving the harpsichord in the spotlight, or even when the strings played sustained notes.</p>



<p>The emotional range of the piece was also captivating. While I felt there was a dramatic tone in the work, I appreciated the moments of lightness. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Beethoven &#8211; String quartet Op 18 No 1 in F major: Allegro con brio</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-beethoven-string-quartet-op-18-no-1-in-f-major-allegro-con-brio/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 20:29:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=202</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Allegro con brio stood out for its energy and dynamism. Throughout the quartet, Beethoven uses and reuses the musical material, creating a sense of cohesion and development across the movement. One of the most...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Allegro con brio stood out for its energy and dynamism. Throughout the quartet, Beethoven uses and reuses the musical material, creating a sense of cohesion and development across the movement.</p>



<p>One of the most interesting aspects of the piece was how he playful manipulates the listener&#8217;s expectations. The moments where the music seemed to approach a conclusion, only to continue in unexpected ways, kept me engaged and often surprised throughout the performance.</p>



<p>What I found most fascinating was Beethoven&#8217;s approach to thematic development. His ability to create a sense of familiarity by reusing and transforming musical material throughout the piece. This reminded me of how in modern music, the chorus often brings back familiar themes that feel comforting and satisfying. Beethoven seemed to anticipate this idea, exploring how good it feels to hear something recognisable.</p>



<p>The varied use of texture and dynamics also stood out to me. At times, the texture was very thin, with just the high notes of a solo violin, creating a delicate, almost fragile sound. Other times, the texture became rich and full as all four instruments played together, producing a powerful and dense sound. The dynamics were constantly shifting, adding to the drama and excitement of the piece.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Eugene Bozza &#8211; Ballade for Trombone and Piano</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-eugene-bozza-ballade-for-trombone-and-piano/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 21:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=200</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to this piece, composed in 1944, was a pleasant surprise that showcased the expressive capabilities of the trombone and the potential for an interesting musical dialogue between both instruments. The way the two instruments...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to this piece, composed in 1944, was a pleasant surprise that showcased the expressive capabilities of the trombone and the potential for an interesting musical dialogue between both instruments.</p>



<p>The way the two instruments conversed musically, changing character together, created a sense of unity and purpose in the performance. This interplay added depth to the piece and kept me interested throughout the 8 minutes.</p>



<p>The diversity of styles employed by Bozza was what felt most interesting to me. The progression from a ballad through impressionistic and jazzy sections to a humorous conclusion showcased not only Bozza&#8217;s intention but also the trombone&#8217;s versatility. This stylistic journey made the piece feel like a mini-tour of 20th-century musical idioms.</p>



<p>While the strong presence of the trombone added to the piece&#8217;s dynamic nature, I did find that it occasionally dominated the piano. This dominance sometimes made it challenging to fully appreciate the piano&#8217;s contribution to the musical dialogue. However, this could be an intentional choice by Bozza to highlight the trombone&#8217;s capabilities.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Toshiko Akiyoshi &#8211; The Village</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-toshiko-akiyoshi-the-village/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 21:22:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=198</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I first listened to &#8220;The Village&#8221;, I was immediately surprised and captivated. From what I read about Akiyoshi before listening to this piece, I had expected a classic big-band jazz piece. But what I...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@icedrum1"></a>When I first listened to &#8220;The Village&#8221;, I was immediately surprised and captivated. From what I read about Akiyoshi before listening to this piece, I had expected a classic big-band jazz piece. But what I found was a fusion of big band jazz with Afro-Cuban and African influences.</p>



<p>Right from the beginning, the piece caught my attention with a rhythm that more closely resembled Afro-Cuban patterns than traditional jazz. This rhythmic foundation, established by the congas and supported by a repetitive bass piano pattern, created an exotic and somewhat hypnotic mood that I found very appealing.</p>



<p>Throughout the piece, I noticed how different instruments were given opportunities to shine. The congas, in particular, played a prominent role in shaping the piece&#8217;s unique character. I found the interplay between the traditional big band instruments and the Afro-Cuban percussion created a fascinating texture that kept me engaged throughout the extended duration of the piece.</p>



<p>I must admit that my background in jazz is limited, so I may have missed some nuances. However, I was able to identify some classic big band elements, such as the strident sound of the horns and the energetic rhythms that reminded me of what I know about 1920s jazz. Interestingly, despite knowing that Akiyoshi is Japanese, I couldn&#8217;t detect any obvious Japanese influences in the piece. </p>



<p>While I found the middle section, featuring more traditional big band elements, less interesting than the opening, it still offered exciting moments, particularly in the trombone features. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Florence Beatrice Price &#8211; Dances in the Canebrakes</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-florence-beatrice-price-dances-in-the-canebrakes/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 21:07:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Timbre and Texture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=207</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As someone unfamiliar with Price&#8217;s work, I was immediately struck by the piece&#8217;s vibrant energy and its exciting rhythms in the piano. The ragtime influences in the first movement, &#8220;Nimble Feet,&#8221; were immediately apparent and...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As someone unfamiliar with Price&#8217;s work, I was immediately struck by the piece&#8217;s vibrant energy and its exciting rhythms in the piano.</p>



<p>The ragtime influences in the first movement, &#8220;Nimble Feet,&#8221; were immediately apparent and enjoyable, evoking the spirit of Scott Joplin&#8217;s compositions. However, it was the second movement, &#8220;Tropical Noon,&#8221; that really captured my attention. The slower tempo and the incorporation of tango rhythms created a more introspective mood that I found particularly engaging.</p>



<p>From a learning perspective, I found &#8220;Dances in the Canebrakes&#8221; to be extremely relevant to my current studies. The use of octaves in the melody brought a playful and contrasting tone. Similarly, the light texture at the beginning of the &#8220;Silk Hat&#8221; section was a great constrast with the other movements.</p>



<p>This listening experience has sparked my curiosity to explore more works by African American composers. Learning that Price was the first African American woman to have her music performed by a major symphony orchestra lended a greater significance to this piece. In particular, this experience led me to discover Fred Onovwerosuoke and his &#8220;Studies in African Rhythm,&#8221; which I plan to listen to closely in the future.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Jon Batiste &#8211; What a Wonderful World</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-jon-batiste-what-a-wonderful-world/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 16:57:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=167</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jon Batiste&#8217;s cover of &#8220;What a Wonderful World&#8221; is a reinterpretation of the classic song, offering a contemplative and sombre take that contrasts with Louis Armstrong&#8217;s iconic original version. The instrumentation is minimal, featuring only...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Jon Batiste&#8217;s cover of &#8220;What a Wonderful World&#8221; is a reinterpretation of the classic song, offering a contemplative and sombre take that contrasts with Louis Armstrong&#8217;s iconic original version.</p>



<p>The instrumentation is minimal, featuring only Batiste&#8217;s piano and voice. This sparse arrangement allows for a deep focus on the emotional delivery of the lyrics and the smoothness of the piano. The use of higher notes and a pentatonic scale on the piano adds an interesting texture to the piece, creating a sense of levitation and hope.</p>



<p>The tempo is slower than the original, at around 90 bpm compared to Armstrong&#8217;s 110 bpm. This slower pace contributes to a more reflective mood, allowing for a long and thoughtful articulation of the lyrics. The overall atmosphere feels melancholic and introspective, which contrasts with the uplifting tone of Armstrong&#8217;s interpretation.</p>



<p>One of the most surprising elements is the intense repetition of the E note, which contributes to the feeling of sadness and sorrow that marks the song. This repetitiveness creates a sense of tension and emotional depth that sets it apart from the original.</p>



<p>Batiste&#8217;s version differs significantly from Armstrong&#8217;s in several key aspects. In terms of duration, Batiste&#8217;s interpretation is nearly twice as long at 4 minutes, compared to Armstrong&#8217;s 2 minutes. The emotional tone also diverges considerably; while Armstrong&#8217;s delivery feels warm and optimistic, Batiste&#8217;s interpretation is more introspective and melancholic. The arrangement varies greatly as well, with the original featuring a full orchestra creating a light, moving harmony, whereas Batiste&#8217;s piano-only arrangement feels more static and profound. Rhythmically, Armstrong&#8217;s version has a danceable quality, while Batiste&#8217;s is more atmospheric and free-flowing. Lastly, the vocal presence differs; Armstrong&#8217;s voice is prominent throughout the song, while Batiste allows more space for instrumental passages, creating a different balance between voice and accompaniment.</p>



<p>Batiste&#8217;s reinterpretation of &#8220;What a Wonderful World&#8221; demonstrates artistic courage. Taking one of the most beloved and well-known songs of the 20th century and reimagining it in a more introspective and sombre style, shows that music is not a static artefact, but a dynamic, living entity that can evolve and adapt, continually revealing new facets of meaning and emotion.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
