<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Part 4 The Classical style &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 22:44:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Assignment 4</title>
		<link>./../../../../assignment-4-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 21:50:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1909</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For this assignment, I listened to the recording of Prokofiev’s ‘Classical’ Symphony by the Frankfurt Radio Symphony conducted&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For this assignment, I listened to the recording of Prokofiev’s ‘Classical’ Symphony by the Frankfurt Radio Symphony conducted by Alondra de la Parra (2020) and the recording of Pulcinella (1920) by Stravinsky played by the Orchestre Philharmonique de Radio France conducted by Barbara Hannigan (2021).</p>



<p>From a historical perspective, the premiere of &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; in 1920 and the &#8220;Classical Symphony&#8221; in 1918 allows one to situate both works squarely in the aftermath of World War I. This was a period of cultural change that moved against the Romantic era, marked by emotional expressivity and complex harmonic language. After the apocalyptic experience of World War I, people started to favour practicality and realism in art and philosophy, instead of abstract and metaphysical concepts (Taruskin, 2010). In music, as Burkholder et al. (2014:798) state, this led to a move away from intense emotions, irrationality, yearning, individualism, and nationalism, towards a return to the values of an earlier, seemingly more civilised era, such as the Classical style.</p>



<p>When addressing the apparent paradox of twentieth-century composers employing eighteenth-century Classical idioms, it is helpful to leverage the concept of &#8220;Neoclassicism.&#8221; This term, as Burkholder et al. (2014:798) explains, denotes a deliberate evocation of the principles and forms associated with the music of pre-Romantic music, including Baroque. Neoclassicism in music emphasised simplicity, polished textures, and refined melodies, emphasising instrumental over vocal, standardising orchestras and forms like sonata and rondo. Both Stravinsky and Prokofiev can be found within this neoclassical framework, yet they applied these influences in uniquely individual ways.</p>



<p>The exploration of Igor Stravinsky’s &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; unveils an interesting journey through musical experimentation mixed with homage to the musical past. Composed between 1919 and 1920, and premiered as a ballet in May 1920, &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; emerged during a period when Stravinsky began to divert from his earlier Russian nationalist style, characterised by works like &#8220;The Rite of Spring,&#8221; to what would later be labelled as his neoclassical phase. In &#8220;Pulcinella,&#8221; Stravinsky recasts the music attributed to 18th-century composer Giovanni Battista Pergolesi and his contemporaries with a contemporary touch, embodying the initial states of neoclassicism in the early 20th century (Leitão, n.d.).</p>



<p>Although it is considered a hallmark in Stravinsky’s production, as a turning point in the composer’s style, there is no consensus about whether &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; truly fits the neoclassical label. Unlike typical neoclassical compositions, where the borrowed material is often reworked to fit a more modern style, Stravinsky keeps much of the original material in &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; unchanged. For Cross (2003:110), his additions seem more like an elegant enhancement or gloss on the existing material instead of a complete re-composition.</p>



<p>I respectfully diverge from Cross’ perspective. While I acknowledge that Stravinsky reproduces certain movements largely in their original form (such as the Overture, Serenata and Gavotta), I argue that he engages in substantial recomposition in other sections (e.g. Allegro assai and Vivo). It is imperative to go into specific examples to illustrate this further.</p>



<p>Listening to the overture, it is clear that there’s a classical sound to it. The memorable theme being played immediately at the beginning is a Gallant trait and a repetition with a slight change, resembling, for example, Mozart’s Eine Kleine Nachtmusik, K. 525. This theme undergoes variations throughout the piece, showcasing the classical hallmark of Ritornello, a musical device extensively utilised during the Baroque and classical periods.</p>



<p>The Sinfonia&#8217;s melody-dominated homophony and the contrapuntal exchange between bassoon and oboe work reinforce the Baroque feel (bars 7-9).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="165" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-1024x165.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1910" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-1024x165.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-300x48.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-768x123.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-1536x247.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-2048x329.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-640x103.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39-960x154.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.20.39.png 2452w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 6-9 of Overture: Allegro moderato </figcaption></figure>



<p>The classical feeling is further reinforced by the presence of traditional voice leading and the utilisation of perfect cadences. Ratner (1956) argues that in the Gallant style, full cadences are much more frequent and can be employed not only at the end but also within the composition. This is evident, for example, in the straightforward D major perfect cadence (bar 15).</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="674" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-1024x674.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1911" style="width:340px;height:auto" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-1024x674.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-300x198.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-768x506.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-640x421.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33-960x632.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.23.33.png 1312w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bara 15-17 of Overture: Allegro moderato</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Despite these classical hallmarks, subtle hints of modernity begin to emerge, such as the strategic use of dynamics to create a dramatic interpretation.</p>



<p>Stravinsky employs a similar compositional approach in the Serenade movement, adhering substantially to the original classical style of the piece while subtly integrating select modernist elements. The melody retains the lyrical, cantabile quality and thin homophonic accompaniment texture characteristic of the original composition. However, Stravinsky introduces hints of 20th-century harmonic practices such as the dissonant harmonisation supporting the sustained vocal note (bar 17-18).</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="847" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-1024x847.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1912" style="width:501px;height:auto" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-1024x847.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-300x248.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-768x635.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-1536x1271.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-640x530.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08-960x794.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.26.08.png 1622w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 17-19 of Serenata: Larghetto: &#8220;Mentre l&#8217;erbetta&#8221;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>This manipulation of the traditional harmonic language can often be subtle, cushioned within the familiar cadences of the classical style, as we’ve seen before. Yet at times, it can be unsettling, particularly when he introduces dissonant vertical sonorities, resembling The Rite of Spring, that challenge the listener’s expectations steeped in the conventions of tonal music. A notable instance is the Allegro assai, where a dissonant C minor 6th is repeated 21 times at the beginning and 33 times at the end, each time at Fortississimo. This kind of dissonant intensity diverges from the norms of the 18th century, where dissonances were promptly resolved.</p>



<p>The choice of instrumentation in the Vivo movement, specifically the pairing of contrabass and trombone, allows for striking timbral effects and contrasts that are far from a classical choice of instrumentation.</p>



<p>Furthermore, the choice of only wind instruments in the Gavotte is a deviation from the traditional classical orchestration, further explored by Stravinsky with the melodic line frequently alternating between the oboe and flute, with the lower register instruments also periodically assuming the melody. This is a clear deviation from typical Baroque era roles of clear melody versus accompaniment.</p>



<p>Looking at the suite as a whole, Stravinsky&#8217;s innovations emerge gradually. At first, the work resembles a straightforward orchestration of an 18th-century piece. As it continues, hints of Stravinsky&#8217;s style periodically appear, becoming increasingly obvious. The transformation culminates in the jazzy ending that foreshadows the sound Copland would later develop.</p>



<p>This oscillation between conformity and defiance of classical norms encapsulates the dual nature of &#8220;Pulcinella&#8221; that could be seen explored by Prokofiev two years before.</p>



<p></p>



<p>Prokofiev tried a different approach for what would later be understood as his first (if not the first ever) Neoclassical work. In his Symphony No. 1 in D major, Op. 25, commonly referred to as the &#8220;Classical&#8221; Symphony, instead of reworking pre-existing material from the classical era, he created a composition with original material but “in the style of Haydn” &#8211; Prokofiev, as cited in Robinson (1987: 130).</p>



<p>In this symphony, which premiered in 1918, Prokofiev consciously adopted classical forms for each movement of the symphony, such as the sonata form for the first movement, a slow lyrical second movement, a gavotte replacing the conventional minuet and trio for the third, and a lively Sonata for the finale. In each of these movements, Prokofiev maintained the hallmark of Classical music: brief, restrained, symmetrical, transparent and scored for a small Haydnesque ensemble (Robinson, 1987:185). The light and elegant texture created by the modest orchestration of two flutes, two oboes, two clarinets, two bassoons, two horns, two trumpets, timpani and strings employs a classical ambient to the overall sound.</p>



<p>On top of the classical four-movement structure as we’ve seen before, harmonically, the use of D major in the first, third, and fourth movements, with the second set in the dominant key, A major, reflects the Classical practice of tonal organisation.</p>



<p>The melodies are brought forward and are discernible. The thematic and melodic elements are employed economically, reminiscent of classical composition, transitioning across instrumentation to create timbral contrast. One clear example can be found in the second theme of the first movement, presented in bars 19-20, and explored in the subsequent measures.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="428" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-1024x428.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1913" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-1024x428.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-300x126.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-768x321.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-1536x643.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-2048x857.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-640x268.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39-960x402.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.35.39.png 2218w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 16-20 of First Movement &#8211; Allegro</figcaption></figure>



<p>Within the third movement&#8217;s Gavotte, a brief interplay of counterpoint arises. The middle segment maintains a homophonic texture dominated by a distinct melody; however, with the entrance of a counter melody in the solo oboe (bar 21), a two-part counterpoint emerges, reflecting an influence of the Baroque era.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="763" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-1024x763.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1914" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-1024x763.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-300x223.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-768x572.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-1536x1144.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-2048x1526.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-640x477.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11-960x715.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.38.11.png 2062w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 19-23 of Third Movement &#8211; Gavotte</figcaption></figure>



<p>In addition to form and melody, Prokofiev incorporates specific techniques linked to Haydn and Mozart. The sudden bursts in the opening bars of the first movement recall the famed Mannheim Rocket figures that Haydn adopted. The extra silent bar at the end of the exposition is a grand pause, another Mannheim trait meant to stress the sonata form&#8217;s architecture.</p>



<p>However, Prokofiev also differs from the Classical style. There are many unexpected key changes and distant modulations. For example, in the first movement he surprisingly, and almost provocatively, shifts from D major to C major.</p>



<p>Additionally, Prokofiev adds complex, syncopated rhythms beyond the Classical norm. Specifically in the development section in the first movement, the orchestra falls out of rhythmic alignment, introducing highly modern syncopations.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="531" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-1024x531.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1915" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-1024x531.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-300x156.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-768x398.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-1536x796.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-2048x1062.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-640x332.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37-960x498.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-03-01-at-22.55.37.png 2434w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bars 131-135 of First Movement &#8211; Allegro</figcaption></figure>



<p>Finally, Prokofiev’s playful mixing of themes, witty contrasts and overall humour align more with the modernist inclination toward irony and satire than with the earnestness of the Classical symphonic tradition. His provocative modulations, such as initiating the recapitulation of the first movement in an unrelated C major, can be seen as a playful critique or jest at the conventions of classical music. This approach underscores his unique style, which often challenges and reinterprets traditional norms.</p>



<p>While both composers adopted a neoclassical approach in their respective pieces, it&#8217;s fascinating to listen to how each infused their compositions with distinct personal traits. Stravinsky, for instance, introduced his characteristic abrupt dynamics, unsettling repetitions and pushing the boundaries of instrumentation. On the other hand, Prokofiev employed his signature modulations and unexpected key changes. Here lies the beauty of neoclassicism. Its ability to evoke a sense of familiarity yet is full of novel elements waiting to be explored.</p>



<p><em>Word Count: 1578</em></p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="reflective-account" class="wp-block-heading">Reflective Account</h2>



<p><br>Engaging with this unit on the classical era of music history helped me develop several new skills. Most notably, I gained a much deeper understanding of the musical concept of neoclassicism. While I was familiar with the term in the context of visual arts, studying its application to music in assignment 4 gave me new insight. Realizing how cyclical arts tend to be was also an interesting takeaway. Artists often look back in time for inspiration, not usually to the immediate past but rather to more distant eras. I see this happening currently as more musicians use musical ideas, samples, and lexicon from the 80s and 90s, similar to how composers in the 1920s neoclassical period were inspired by the 18th-century classical period.</p>



<p>This assignment also allowed me to solidify my personal preferences within the genre. The dramatic shifts, unsettling sounds, and instrumental experimentation present in Stravinsky&#8217;s work deeply resonate with me. What truly impresses me is his ability to infuse classical forms with his unique style, influencing music for years to come. Stravinsky&#8217;s work embodies the spirit of innovation within a traditional framework, making him a composer I&#8217;m particularly drawn to.</p>



<p>However, this journey wasn&#8217;t without its challenges. My enthusiasm for research sometimes overshadowed the pure act of listening. Getting bogged down in historical details and technical aspects occasionally prevented me from simply experiencing the music on an emotional level. Moving forward, I plan to strike a balance between intellectual exploration and pure listening pleasure.</p>



<p>The exercise I found most valuable in developing my skills was explaining the essence of Haydn’s Symphony No. 104 in simple, clear terms. Distilling complex musical ideas and history concisely takes practice and I believe this strengthened my ability. On the other hand, comparing period orchestras to modern ones was disappointing, as I did not perceive the contrast I expected in their sounds. Perhaps I would select a different piece to better highlight their differences.</p>



<p>Listening to lesser-known composers beyond the trio of Mozart, Beethoven and Haydn brought welcome new perspectives. I was particularly intrigued by Muzio Clementi and hope to explore more of his and other contemporaneous composers’ work in the future. If I were to undertake a similar exercise again, I would set aside more time to go more deeply into the biographical details and compositional outputs of more minor classical-period figures, especially women. Their contributions to the development of the era’s predominant musical style deserve more attention than I could give them here.</p>



<p>Overall, I found this an exciting first step in more fully studying Western classical music. The discoveries I made have motivated me to continue learning more about music history across different eras. Understanding context opens up a greater appreciation of the compositions themselves, so I am eager to keep developing a richer framework through which to enjoy the fruits of musical geniuses past and present.<br><br><em>Word Count: 480</em></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1709330599039 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Taruskin, R. (2010). Chapter 4 Extinguishing the “Petty ‘I’ ” (Transcendentalism, I). In Oxford University Press, Music in the Early Twentieth Century. New York, USA. Retrieved 19 Feb. 2024, from https://www.oxfordwesternmusic.com/view/Volume4/actrade-9780195384840-div1-004009.xml</p>



<p>Burkholder, J.P., Grout, D.J. and Palisca, C.V. (2014) A history of Western music. W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</p>



<p>Leitão, R.C. (n.d.) Pulcinella de Stravinsky &#8211; Metropolitana. https://www.metropolitana.pt/musicalia/pulcinella-de-stravinsky/ (Accessed: February 19, 2024).</p>



<p>Cross, J. (2003) <em>The Cambridge Companion to Stravinsky</em>, <em>Cambridge University Press eBooks</em>. https://doi.org/10.1017/ccol9780521663304.</p>



<p>Robinson, H. (1987) <em>Sergei Prokofiev: A Biography</em>. Northeastern University Press.</p>



<p>Ratner, L.G. (1956) <em>Eighteenth-Century Theories of Musical Period Structure</em>, The Musical Quarterly, XLII(4), pp. 439–454. https://doi.org/10.1093/mq/xlii.4.439.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise The Classical opera</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-the-classical-opera/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2024 23:15:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1905</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Marriage of Figaro is a comic opera composed by Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, with an Italian libretto written&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="programme" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1707952589748 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Programme</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The Marriage of Figaro is a comic opera composed by Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, with an Italian libretto written by Lorenzo Da Ponte. It premiered in 1786 at the Burgtheater in Vienna. Based on the play La folle journée, ou le Mariage de Figaro by Pierre Beaumarchais, the opera tells the story of the clever servant Figaro, who is preparing to marry the vivacious Susanna. Their wedding day gets off to a rocky start, however, as their employer Count Almaviva tries to exercise his feudal right to bed the bride before the groom. The plot revolves around a single day filled with twists and turns, as various characters hatch plans to fool one another.</p>



<p>The opera is structured in four acts. Act I establishes the basic plot &#8211; Count Almaviva wants to seduce Figaro&#8217;s bride-to-be, Susanna and has abolished the medieval right of a lord to sleep with a servant girl on her wedding night to make his intentions seem more honourable. Figaro, the count&#8217;s servant, plots to outwit his master&#8217;s plans. In Act II, the Countess laments her husband&#8217;s infidelity while plotting with Susanna to publicly expose the Count&#8217;s plans to embarrass him. In Act III, complications arise with the adolescent page Cherubino, who has a crush on the Countess. There are disguises and much confusion before Susanna and the Countess expose the Count&#8217;s intentions. Finally, in Act IV all is resolved after much scheming, including multiple plans to dress up Cherubino as a girl. The Count begs for forgiveness, the Countess forgives him, and the opera ends with rejoicing over the two marriages – Figaro and Susanna, and the reunited Count and Countess Almaviva.</p>



<p>The Marriage of Figaro shows Mozart&#8217;s genius through brilliant ensemble writing and memorable melodies that capture the emotions of the drama. The overture introduces no less than 9 musical themes or theme fragments that set the mood for this opera. From the famed &#8220;Non più andrai&#8221; where Figaro teasingly says farewell to Cherubino&#8217;s carefree days, to the Countess&#8217;s hauntingly melancholy &#8220;Dove sono i bei momenti,&#8221; the opera overflows with musical riches. The finale of Act IV concludes the opera with one of Mozart&#8217;s most joyful and technically dazzling ensemble finales as all celebrate the happy outcome.</p>



<p>The Marriage of Figaro was an instant hit at its premiere and it has remained as one of the most popular operas for over 200 years. Its characters are recognizable archetypes depicting master-servant class tensions, marital infidelity and forgiveness, outwitting authority, and the confusion of young love. Musically and dramatically, the opera represents the height of the opera buffa (comic opera) genre with Mozart&#8217;s sublime music animating Da Ponte&#8217;s hilarious situations and characters. Performed frequently worldwide, The Marriage of Figaro continues to fascinate modern audiences.<br></p>



<h2 id="personal-review" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1707951249497 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Personal Review:</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>I just saw Mozart&#8217;s &#8220;The Marriage of Figaro&#8221; production by the RCM Opera Orchestra on YouTube. They delivered a delightful evening filled with humour, beautiful music, and impressive performances. While not a seasoned opera critic, I was captivated by the production, particularly the interplay between the skilled musicians and the engaging cast.</p>



<p>While largely traditional, the staging beautifully evoked the opulence of 18th-century Vienna. The classic sets and costumes felt timeless, allowing the focus to remain on the characters and their comedic antics. Sir Thomas Allen&#8217;s direction navigated the opera&#8217;s twists and turns, keeping the pace lively and the humour fresh.</p>



<p>The standout performances were truly captivating. Adam Maxey&#8217;s Figaro was a charming and endearing presence, his voice effortlessly conveying both wit and warmth. Julieth Lozano&#8217;s Susanna was a force of nature, her powerful and passionate vocals embodied the character&#8217;s intelligence and determination. The rest of the cast also impressed, with each singer delivering their roles with commitment and vocal skill.</p>



<p>However, the true highlight of the performance was the RCM Opera Orchestra. With the conductor Michael Rosewell, the musicians delivered a flawless performance. Their playing was tight, nuanced, and full of emotion, perfectly capturing the wide range of moods in Mozart&#8217;s score. From the brilliant Overture to the dramatic climaxes, the orchestra provided a solid foundation for the singers and truly elevated the overall experience.</p>



<p>While the individual performances were strong, the most memorable aspect of the production was the seamless collaboration between the orchestra and the cast. The final scene, where the music and characters come together in a joyful celebration of love and forgiveness, was truly magical.</p>



<p>While I might not be an expert, I felt that the RCM Opera Orchestra&#8217;s &#8220;The Marriage of Figaro&#8221; was thoroughly entertaining.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.google.com/search?region=wt-wt&amp;q=Mozart%27s+The+Marriage+of+Figaro+RCM+Opera+Orchestra+performance+review&amp;tbm=nws" target="_blank"></a></p>



<p><br><br><br></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point &#8211; Music Publishing in the 18th century</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-music-publishing-in-the-18th-century/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 22:18:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1901</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the early 18th century, music publishing centered around major cities like London, Amsterdam, and Paris. Publishers like&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the early 18th century, music publishing centered around major cities like London, Amsterdam, and Paris. Publishers like John Walsh in London helped popularize Italian instrumental music and songs from London&#8217;s theater scene. Engraving allowed more music to be published and distributed across Europe. Meanwhile, the Ballard family held a monopoly on music printing in France, restricting publishing there.</p>



<p>Around 1750, Johann Gottlob Immanuel Breitkopf in Leipzig started experimenting with different printing methods to make sheet music more widely available. He used a combination of movable type, engraving, and manuscript copies . His editions were cheaper than engraved music, allowing him to distribute music more widely and create new markets. Breitkopf helped popularize the German sentimental song genre. Other German publishers like Hartknoch, Rellstab, and Schwickert adopted his techniques.</p>



<p>The onset of the 18th century witnessed a significant shift in music publishing, particularly with the commercial use of engraving. This method allowed for faster production and distribution of music, a stark contrast to the heavy movable type and manuscript copying that had been predominately used. Although manuscript copies and letterpress printing of music continued throughout the century, the development of engraving led to a more extensive and competitive music publication market.</p>



<p>London&#8217;s music publishing scene thrived around 1700, closely followed by Paris between 1740 and 1760, Vienna just before 1780, and Leipzig around 1800. Each city, in its prime, contributed to the cumulative growth of available published music, fostering a competitive environment that spurred public interest in music. This period intertwined with the rising of the middle class, whose demand for printed music became insatiable. Amateur music-making at home became a widespread phenomenon, breaking the monopoly of professional concerts and bringing music into the intimate circles of family and friends. This change democratized music, making it accessible to a wider audience beyond the aristocracy and religious institutions that had previously dominated musical patronage.</p>



<p>The engraving method, which began in London and Amsterdam, facilitated the international distribution of copies through Northern and Western Europe, propelling the music of Italian masters and others to unprecedented popularity. The success and efficiency of engraving caught on quickly, with publishers in major cities adopting the technique and contributing to its refinement. This led to an increased production of instrumental music and operatic scores, bringing a wider variety of music to the public.</p>



<p>In London, the music publishing industry saw significant growth under figures like John Walsh, who became the principal publisher of Handel’s music. Through such publishers, a more organized and expansive distribution system emerged, bringing music to more people than ever before. In parallel, similar developments occurred in Paris and Vienna, each adapting the engraving method to their unique cultural contexts and musical tastes, thus enriching the diversity of music available in the public domain.</p>



<p>The influence of music publishing in this era extended far beyond the mere accessibility of music. It catalyzed a shift in musical tastes, with public concerts becoming more popular and the amateur musician trend fostering a new consumer base for publishers. This period marked a crucial point in the history of music, where the production and consumption of music witnessed revolutionary changes, setting the stage for the dynamic developments in music publishing that would continue into the 19th century and beyond.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1707775994458 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Boorman, S., Selfridge-Field, E. and Krummel, D.W. (2014) ‘Printing and publishing of music’, in <em>Grove Music Online</em>,<em> Oxford Music Online</em> [Online], Oxford, Oxford University Press. Available at http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com.libezproxy.open.ac.uk/subscriber/article/grove/music/40101pg2.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Beethoven &#8211; Symphony No. 1 in C major, Op. 21</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-beethoven-symphony-no-1-in-c-major-op-21/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 22:11:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1925</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As the lovely and gradual introduction in the first movement gets underway, the anticipation for a strong cadence&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As the lovely and gradual introduction in the first movement gets underway, the anticipation for a strong cadence builds and builds, but it doesn&#8217;t arrive. The music is constantly leaving you on a hook and, just when you think it can&#8217;t get any more energetic, the strings drop into tune and the winds have a moment of stillness. At last, the cadence arrives but the pace never lets up throughout the movement, toying with your expectations throughout. It&#8217;s a back-and-forth of suspense and surprise, the whole way up to a glorious conclusion that couldn&#8217;t leave you in any doubt of the music&#8217;s full force.</p>



<p>The second movement has the feel of classical formality, with a subject and then periods of rest. At first, the emotional restraint in this movement might make it less engaging, but the dramatic volume level gives the music layers of interest that will keep you listening.</p>



<p>Beethoven scores more points with dynamic change and strong contrast in the third movement. These are hallmarks of his style, and you can see why people, like me for example, just really enjoy listening to his music.</p>



<p>The symphony&#8217;s final movement starts dramatically and commands attention immediately. Throughout this movement, it feels like Beethoven is deliberately playing with the listener&#8217;s expectations again, creating moments where the orchestra resembles a choir and leading the listener to anticipate a conclusion, only to defy those expectations. The movement maintains a sense of suspense and anticipation, keeping the listener engaged until the very end.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise The Mannheim School</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-the-mannheim-school/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2024 22:38:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1898</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I listened to the first movement of Mozart&#8217;s Flute Concerto in G, following along with the score as&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I listened to the first movement of Mozart&#8217;s Flute Concerto in G, following along with the score as best I could. I was able to follow the score fairly well during the opening orchestral sections and especially during the flute solo passages. However, there were times when the complex interplay between instruments made it tricky to follow every line simultaneously on the score. Still, I found that following the score enhanced my enjoyment of the music rather than detracting from it.</p>



<p>Seeing the notes on the page almost acted as a sort of spoiler, allowing me a sneak peek at whether the melody would go high or low next. Yet this glimpse into the music&#8217;s future only piqued my interest and engagement. I enjoyed anticipating how a phrase would develop or how the flute soloist would embellish the next repetition of the theme. It allowed me to listen more actively and attentively rather than just letting the music wash over me.</p>



<p>In studying the score, a few trademarks of the Mannheim School jumped out at me. First, the homophonic texture was apparent, with a clear melody in the flute over accompaniment harmony in the strings. Second, the harmonies tended to change slowly and smoothly during melodic passages. Finally, the virtuosic flute writing conformed to the Mannheim practice of featuring wind soloists. The flute gets several chances to shine both in lyrical passages and brisk, technical displays.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point &#8211; Period and Modern Ensemble</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-period-and-modern-ensemble/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 22:03:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1895</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When listening to period and modern ensemble recordings of the same classical works, there are some differences in&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When listening to period and modern ensemble recordings of the same classical works, there are some differences in instrumental tone quality, balance, and emotional impact. For example, I compared recordings of Beethoven&#8217;s 5th by the Orchestra of the 18th Century (period instruments) and the West-Eastern Divan Orchestra (modern instruments).</p>



<p>I must confess that I didn&#8217;t find a striking difference between both recordings. Maybe the contrast in earlier periods such as the Baroque might be more noticeable. In these recordings, the most striking contrast is in the tone of the winds and brass. On period instruments like natural horns, the sound is more raw, hollow, and buzzy compared to the refined, rounded tone of modern instruments. The period string section also tends to have a leaner, more transparent ensemble sound.</p>



<p>Emotionally, the period performances often feel lighter, fleeter, and less weighty. Dramatic moments have more nervous tension than rich, stormy anguish. Of course, much depends on the performers&#8217; interpretive choices; period recordings can still convey profound feelings. But the very sound of the instruments naturally lends itself to a different aesthetic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research point &#8211; Other Classical Composers</title>
		<link>./../../../../research-point-other-classical-composers/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 21:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1889</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Classical era was dominated by three figures in Western music: Haydn (1732-1809), Mozart (1756-1791), and Beethoven (1770-1827).&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Classical era was dominated by three figures in Western music: Haydn (1732-1809), Mozart (1756-1791), and Beethoven (1770-1827). However, many lesser-known composers also made significant contributions that shaped the musical landscape leading to Romanticism. Composers like Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach (1714-1788), Luigi Boccherini (1743-1805), Johann Nepomuk Hummel (1778-1837), Muzio Clementi (1752-1832), Christoph Willibald Gluck (1714-1787), Antonín Rejcha (1770-1836), Johann Christian Bach (1735-1782), and Leopold Kozeluch (1747-1818) were influential in developing the gallant style and early classical forms of the symphony, sonata, string quartet and concerto.</p>



<p>Studying their works side-by-side with the great masters reveals similarities that suggest stylistic influences flow both ways. For instance, Mozart&#8217;s early symphonies bear resemblance to those of Johann Christian Bach, whom Mozart deeply admired. Clementi&#8217;s virtuosic piano works were likely a challenge for Beethoven to stretch his technical limits on the instrument. </p>



<p>Johann Christian Bach (1735–1782), the youngest son of J.S. Bach, was an important figure in London&#8217;s music scene and had a profound influence on the young Mozart when the latter visited London in the 1760s. </p>



<p>As the youngest son of the great J.S. Bach, I expected his music to be similar &#8211; intricate counterpoint, dense textures, almost mathematical complexity. But J.C. Bach&#8217;s style is completely different &#8211; light, tuneful, and crystal clear in its expression.</p>



<p>When I listen to J.C. Bach’s keyboard concertos and sonatas, I imagine aristocrats in powdered wigs and pastel suits, sipping tea and nodding along to the music. The melodic lines are so pleasant and catchy, with memorable themes that get lodged in my head. Underneath lies a simple accompaniment that allows the melody to shine.</p>



<p>Refined yet accessible, skillfully crafted but not flashy, his &#8220;Galant&#8221; style hints at the Classical period ahead under composers like Mozart and Haydn. No wonder the young Mozart was profoundly moved meeting J.C. Bach &#8211; the seeds of his melodic genius can be heard in the elder composer&#8217;s long, singing lines and transparent textures. J.C. Bach&#8217;s music floats by lightly, a pleasing precursor to high Classical elegance. (Sadie, 2006).</p>



<p>Among others we might consider is Muzio Clementi (1752–1832), a contemporary of the great masters who was both a noted composer and a famous pianist. Clementi and Mozart even faced off in a piano competition judged by Emperor Joseph II, which reportedly ended in a tie. This event, and Clementi&#8217;s virtuosic style, is thought to have influenced Mozart&#8217;s piano compositions to some extent (Georges De St.-Foix and Martens, 1923).</p>



<p>When I listen to the piano sonatas and other keyboard works of Muzio Clementi, I&#8217;m struck by their nimble, sparkling quality. The fast passages cascade up and down the keyboard with a lightness and clarity that sounds almost modern to my ears.  But there is also passion, especially in the Piano Duet in C Major, Op. 6 No. 1 or his Sonata Op. 26 No. 2 in F sharp minor. Here Clementi unleashes torrents of notes and sudden, dramatic contrasts that sound like Beethoven and it looks like it anticipated the Romantic period.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1707431895826 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Sadie, S. (2006) <em>Mozart: The Early Years 1756-1781, pp. 88-89</em>. Oxford University Press.</p>



<p>Georges De St.-Foix and Martens, F.H. (1923) &#8216;Muzio Clementi (1752-1832),&#8217; <em>The Musical Quarterly</em>, 9(3), pp. 350–382. https://www.jstor.org/stable/738494.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Johann-Christian-Bach#:~:text=In%201772%20he%20was%20invited,from%20and%20greatly%20respected%20Bach." target="_blank"></a></p>



<p><a href="https://www.britannica.com/biography/Johann-Christian-Bach#:~:text=In%201772%20he%20was%20invited,from%20and%20greatly%20respected%20Bach." target="_blank"></a></p>



<p><a href="https://www.quora.com/Who-had-more-influence-on-classical-music-Beethoven-or-Mozart-Did-any-other-composers-have-similar-impact-as-them" target="_blank"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Clementi &#8211; Sonata Op. 26 No. 2</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-clementi-sonata-op-26-no-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2024 22:02:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1918</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This was the first Clementi work I listened to, and I found it to have great emotive depth.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This was the first Clementi work I listened to, and I found it to have great emotive depth. It featured intricate harmonies and masterful variation writing, offering a compelling listening experience. The slow movement is particularly poignant, with its evocative expression, providing a glimpse into Clementi&#8217;s musical prowess and his ability to convey powerful emotions.</p>



<p>One of the striking aspects of this piece is the technical usage of the pianoforte. The work progressively presents challenges for the performer, showcasing Clementi&#8217;s understanding of piano technique while exploring imaginative variations. This balance between technical demands and musical depth makes this work intriguing for listeners, allowing them to appreciate the potential of the keyboard.</p>



<p>The unexpected plot twists in the opening movement demonstrate the fusion of technical complexity with expressive musicality. The torrents of notes and sudden, dramatic contrasts make it an impressive movement both in technicality and musicality.</p>



<p>In the final movement, I notice a connection between Clementi&#8217;s writing and that of Beethoven, particularly in the strong dynamic contrasts. However, the rapid arpeggios that set the mood remind me more of a Romantic movement, suggesting that Clementi might have been an influential composer for future generations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Clementi &#8211; Piano Duet in C Major, Op. 6 No. 1</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-clementi-piano-duet-in-c-major-op-6-no-1/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 23:24:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1921</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This was a truly enjoyable piece to listen to, similar to a vibrant chat between two close friends.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This was a truly enjoyable piece to listen to, similar to a vibrant chat between two close friends. It takes you on a journey through varying moods.</p>



<p>The piece begins with a lively movement, filled with cascading scales and playful tunes. It&#8217;s intriguing how it feels familiar yet different, not a composition from a known composer. The two piano parts intertwine beautifully, creating a delightful blend of friendly rivalry and harmony. The joy in their back-and-forth interactions is palpable, with one piano seemingly predicting the other&#8217;s phrases, building anticipation.</p>



<p>The second movement provides an expectable contrast. The melody becomes more introspective, featuring long, flowing lines that feel like a shared moment of reflection. The tenderness with which the two pianos merge into a single voice creates a sense of closeness and connection.</p>



<p>The final movement reintroduces the energy and excitement. The music surges forward with swift scales and virtuosic passages, a cascade of notes that carries the listener along. There&#8217;s a playful defiance in this movement, a celebration of the sheer joy of creating music.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise Enjoying Classical music</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-enjoying-classical-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 21:45:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 The Classical style]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=1884</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;ve just heard Haydn&#8217;s Symphony No. 104 for the first time and I believe I can transmit my&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I&#8217;ve just heard Haydn&#8217;s Symphony No. 104 for the first time and I believe I can transmit my understanding of it to you in simple terms since I don&#8217;t think you need to know any musical terms to enjoy it.</p>



<p>The first thing to know is that since it&#8217;s a classical symphony, you might expect it to have 4 movements or parts. This is true of this symphony, called London. Although it has a name that sets it in a location, I think of this symphony as a ball, with several characters presented along the four parts.</p>



<p>First Movement (Adagio — Allegro)</p>



<p>The first part, or the &#8216;introduction,&#8217; greets you with a bold announcement, as if you&#8217;re entering the ball. There&#8217;s the announcement &#8220;The ball is starting!&#8221; Everyone seems shy at first, there&#8217;s not much action happening. The announcements keep coming and everyone walks in gracefully, but then the energy suddenly picks up and the dancers burst into movement. The strings act like a chatty, energetic and playful crowd, while the horns are like the grand host, full of bold and regal proclamations.</p>



<p>Second Movement (Andante)</p>



<p>The second part, often considered the &#8216;slow movement,&#8217; takes on a more reflective tone. Now, we stroll into a peaceful garden, a bit outside of the ball. This part feels like a leisurely walk, with a melody that seems to sing a heartfelt song, gracefully passed between the strings and winds. Sometimes we&#8217;re reminded that there&#8217;s a ball happening, but the characters here continue a chat filled with emotion, depth and sometimes melancholy.</p>



<p>Third Movement (Menuetto: Allegro — Trio)</p>



<p>The third movement is like the party games, more rhythmic. We&#8217;re back inside the ball for the real start of the party &#8211; everyone is dancing. It&#8217;s playful and lively but at one point, it dances into a lighter, more delicate section called the Trio &#8211; imagine taking a detour into a smaller group of dancers. It&#8217;s a musical break for refreshment and socializing before the climax of the dance.</p>



<p>Fourth Movement (Finale: Spiritoso)</p>



<p>Finally, the celebration reaches its peak with an energetic and spirited finale. This is the big finish, with all instruments joining a lively and joyful dance, celebrating the end of a wonderful day packed with adventures. Listen for the fast violin notes that seem to be extremely excited, while the rest of the orchestra adds depth and grandeur. It is a vibrant, joyful dance bringing satisfying closure to this sonic ball.</p>



<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symphony_No._104_(Haydn)" target="_blank"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
