<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 23:02:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Rosalía, Carminho – Memória</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-rosalia-carminho-memoria/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 22:19:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Designing Your Project]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=629</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The global success of Rosalía’s new album, Lux, made it impossible for me to ignore, so I finally sat down to listen. In my view, the record is a triumph because it is a conceptual...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The global success of Rosalía’s new album, Lux, made it impossible for me to ignore, so I finally sat down to listen. In my view, the record is a triumph because it is a conceptual work where a mainstream artist takes the liberty to create something entirely different from the formatted pop we hear today. Among the tracks, <em>Memória</em> stood out most. Partly because I am Portuguese and I adore Carminho, but also because of how it bridges two worlds.</p>



<p>To me, <em>Memória</em> captures a deep sense of saudade through its inherent sadness. The dramatic contrast between the quiet instruments and the intense, longing delivery of the lyrics creates a mood of profound introspection. It feels like a bridge between the past and the present, where the minimalist production allows the emotional weight of the Fado tradition to shine without being over-produced. I found the experience deeply moving, as it proves that mainstream music can still be surprising.</p>



<p>I adore how the minimalist texture, featuring a delicate interplay between harp and piano, replaces the traditional Portuguese guitar, pushing the sound toward an ethereal, dreamlike atmosphere rather than a standard folk style.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Joseph Turrin &#8211; Lullaby for Vaska</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-joseph-turrin-lullaby-for-vaska/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 22:55:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Designing Your Project]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=644</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This piece combines chamber orchestra, narrator, and voice in a way that clearly separates their roles. The orchestra provides the main emotional and structural foundation, using long, sustained lines and gentle dynamics that reflect the...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This piece combines chamber orchestra, narrator, and voice in a way that clearly separates their roles. The orchestra provides the main emotional and structural foundation, using long, sustained lines and gentle dynamics that reflect the idea of a lullaby. These musical features create a calm and continuous background rather than strong contrasts or dramatic development.</p>



<p>The narrator delivers the text in a clear and direct manner, which allows the meaning of the words to remain understandable. The solo voice adds another layer, using simple melodic material that blends with the orchestral texture instead of standing out too strongly.</p>



<p>This work moved me, particularly the contrast between the innocence of a &#8220;lullaby&#8221; and the brutal reality of the siege. The dramatic contrast between the narrator&#8217;s steady voice and the soaring, mournful soprano at the end felt like a deep experience, reflecting both deep despair and a glimmer of hope. It reinforces my belief that including a narrator can transform a musical performance into a personal, cinematic journey.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Dana Wilson – Mirror for String Quartet and Narration</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-dana-wilson-mirror-for-string-quartet-and-narration/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 22:45:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Designing Your Project]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=642</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to this was a different experience from most string quartet music I know. What interested me most was how the spoken text and the music exist together without competing. The narration does not tell...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to this was a different experience from most string quartet music I know. What interested me most was how the spoken text and the music exist together without competing. The narration does not tell a story in a dramatic way. Instead, it feels like quiet thoughts placed inside the music. This made me listen more carefully to both elements.</p>



<p>I found that the music creates a space for reflection rather than strong emotions. The rhythmic patterns and repeated ideas reminded me of everyday movement and energy, especially in modern life. At the same time, the spoken words felt personal and honest. Because the text is spoken, not sung, I could understand it easily, and it felt more direct and human.</p>



<p>I also liked that the piece changes depending on where it is performed and who writes the text. This made me think about music as something connected to people and place. Overall, the piece made me reflect on how music can support thinking and listening, rather than leading the listener too strongly. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Herbert Howells &#8211; A Spotless Rose</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-herbert-howells-a-spotless-rose/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 18:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: What is Collaboration?]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=622</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Impression I was completely unfamiliar with this piece before this listening, so I had no expectations. Listening to the recording by The Sixteen, I was immediately surprised by the complexity of the melody. It felt...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Impression I was completely unfamiliar with this piece before this listening, so I had no expectations. Listening to the recording by The Sixteen, I was immediately surprised by the complexity of the melody. It felt distinctively different from the straightforward, folk-like structure of traditional carols.</p>



<p>The defining characteristic of this piece is the extensive use of melisma. It uses these flowing, intricate lines to create a fluid sense of motion. I noticed that the meter (time signature) feels very flexible, avoiding a rigid beat. This rhythmic freedom, combined with the rolling melismas, created a sensation that I interpreted as gentle waves. It feels as though the music is physically rocking the listener.</p>



<p>The music flows organically from start to finish. The final cadence was breathtaking to me; it settles into a peaceful resolution that feels ethereal. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Gustav Holst &#8211; In the Bleak Midwinter</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-gustav-holst-in-the-bleak-midwinter/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: What is Collaboration?]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=620</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I listened to the Royal Choral Society&#8217;s performance of this piece. It is such a beautiful example a choral sound. It&#8217;s very polite, restrained, but deeply emotional. I have been discovering that Holst has a...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I listened to the Royal Choral Society&#8217;s performance of this piece. It is such a beautiful example a choral sound. It&#8217;s very polite, restrained, but deeply emotional. I have been discovering that Holst has a specific way of writing melodies that feels very human and grounded.</p>



<p>The melody is the most striking element. The melody moves mostly in stepwise. The melody starts by ascending gently, reaching a hopeful peak (perhaps symbolizing heaven), but ultimately descends back down to the tonic note, finding a resting place (symbolizing earth). This creates a sense of resignation and humility. The harmony is diatonic and simple, avoiding complex chromatic chords, which matches the poem&#8217;s theme of poverty and simplicity.</p>



<p>The slow tempo establishes a somber but peaceful mood. It perfectly captures the image of a &#8220;bleak&#8221; winter landscape. It felt very intimate to me, despite being sung by a large choir.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to John Williams &#8211; Somewhere in My Memory</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-john-williams-somewhere-in-my-memory/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 17:18:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: What is Collaboration?]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Since Home Alone is the movie of my childhood, which I have watched dozens of times, John Williams’ &#8220;Somewhere in My Memory&#8221; is a piece I have listened to unconsciously for more than twenty years....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Since Home Alone is the movie of my childhood, which I have watched dozens of times, John Williams’ &#8220;Somewhere in My Memory&#8221; is a piece I have listened to unconsciously for more than twenty years. However, analysing it now with a music student’s ear, I realised that while the melody is simple, the arrangement is what generates that instant feeling of nostalgia.</p>



<p>The orchestration is central to the atmosphere. The texture begins lightly, using the celesta and glockenspiel which provide a bright, thin timbre. This is supported by a juvenile choir, whose vocal quality adds an element of innocence and purity that adult voices could not achieve. Beneath this, the string section provides a &#8220;velvet foundation,&#8221; playing legato lines that warm the overall sound.</p>



<p> In a compositional view, the chord progression uses downward motion. I have been noticing that this descending bass line is a hallmark of Christmas songs, perhaps because it mimics a sigh or a settling down, creating a sense of comfort. </p>



<p>What stood out to me most was the dynamic structure. The piece does not stay static; it features a significant crescendo. It starts with a very thin melodic line, but as the piece progresses, the texture thickens until the full orchestra joins the choir. This expansion from intimacy to grandiosity makes the listening experience deeply emotional. It captures a cinematic feeling of the holidays. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to The Kills &#8211; The Last Goodbye</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-the-kills-the-last-goodbye/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 13:16:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=608</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have been interested in piano music recently, focusing on how a single instrument can carry such depth. Though The Last Goodbye has a simple arrangement, the power of it immediately impressed me. The piece...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I have been interested in piano music recently, focusing on how a single instrument can carry such depth. Though <em>The Last Goodbye</em> has a simple arrangement, the power of it immediately impressed me. The piece opens directly with the piano accompaniment, setting a 3/4 tempo that establishes the ballad character.</p>



<p>The instrumentation here is simple: piano and voice. What stood out to me most was the timbre of the singe&#8217;s voice. It has this slightly rough, lower register quality, almost a whisper at times, which keeps the music from becoming too lyrical. When the vocal enters, it is conversational, resting above the piano. The overall texture is thin, giving the song an intimate sound. </p>



<p>While the musical setting, the slow, waltz-like rhythm, creates melancholy, her voice introduces a paradoxical sense of peace. It is not a crying-out sadness; rather, it is a calm, reflective resignation. I felt like I was listening to someone quietly accept an inevitable loss. This contrast, where the sadness of the music is met with a relaxed tone, makes the piece memorable. This simplicity makes the emotion feel real.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Joy Crookes &#8211; Skin</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-joy-crookes-skin/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 13:09:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=606</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When I first hear &#8220;Skin,&#8221; I am struck by its immediate, almost cinematic quality, which is rooted in its instrumental texture. The introduction is marked by a deliberate and stately piano line, establishing a gentle...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When I first hear &#8220;Skin,&#8221; I am struck by its immediate, almost cinematic quality, which is rooted in its instrumental texture. The introduction is marked by a deliberate and stately piano line, establishing a gentle but firm rhythmic pulse in a ballad tempo. This immediately gives the piece a meditative, perhaps melancholic, quality.</p>



<p>The instrumentation and texture are what really make this piece captivating for me. It is a soul-jazz ballad, but it is elevated by the use of orchestral elements. As the first verse begins, Crookes&#8217; voice, with a smoky, rich timbre, is front and center. Underneath the vocal melody, the texture is sparse, dominated by a simple piano. However, it is the entrance of the string section that acts as the primary structural marker. The strings bring a warm lush, rising counter-melody, adding a grandiosity that contrasts beautifully with the intimacy of the piano.</p>



<p>The overall emotional interpretation I take from the piece is one of tender, yet strong, reassurance. The music speaks of resilience and self-acceptance. It is not a song of dramatic conflict, but rather a reflective thought. It makes me wonder about the specific person Crookes was thinking of, and how much a simple, beautiful melody can carry the weight of life&#8217;s biggest struggles.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
