<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 18:34:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Herbert Howells &#8211; A Spotless Rose</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-herbert-howells-a-spotless-rose/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 18:32:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: What is Collaboration?]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=622</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Impression I was completely unfamiliar with this piece before this listening, so I had no expectations. Listening to the recording by The Sixteen, I was immediately surprised by the complexity of the melody. It felt...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Impression I was completely unfamiliar with this piece before this listening, so I had no expectations. Listening to the recording by The Sixteen, I was immediately surprised by the complexity of the melody. It felt distinctively different from the straightforward, folk-like structure of traditional carols.</p>



<p>The defining characteristic of this piece is the extensive use of melisma. It uses these flowing, intricate lines to create a fluid sense of motion. I noticed that the meter (time signature) feels very flexible, avoiding a rigid beat. This rhythmic freedom, combined with the rolling melismas, created a sensation that I interpreted as gentle waves. It feels as though the music is physically rocking the listener.</p>



<p>The music flows organically from start to finish. The final cadence was breathtaking to me; it settles into a peaceful resolution that feels ethereal. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to St. George&#8217;s Chapel Choir &#8211; Carol of the Bells</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-st-georges-chapel-choir-carol-of-the-bells/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 17:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: What is Collaboration?]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=618</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Although Christmas carols have been present through all my life, I realised that I rarely listen to them with a critical ear. Usually, they are just background atmosphere for the holiday season. Listening to this...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Although Christmas carols have been present through all my life, I realised that I rarely listen to them with a critical ear. Usually, they are just background atmosphere for the holiday season. Listening to this specific recording by St. George&#8217;s Chapel Choir forced me to stop and observe why I have always enjoyed this piece, moving beyond simple nostalgia to a deeper musical understanding.</p>



<p>Structurally, the piece is built on contrast and accumulation. I liked the relationship between the different voice parts: while the harmonic progression in the bass line is often downward/descending, the melody in the upper registers continues to rise. This contrary motion creates a high level of musical tension.</p>



<p>The dynamic range is what creates the drama. The song transforms from a quiet, almost secretive opening into a massive wall of sound. There is a rapid and intense crescendo that builds until the choir reaches a climax. At this peak, it feels as if the music explodes into a mesh of voices. This sudden shift evokes a sense of breathless excitement, like a flurry of snow or ringing bells.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Gustav Holst &#8211; In the Bleak Midwinter</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-gustav-holst-in-the-bleak-midwinter/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: What is Collaboration?]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=620</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I listened to the Royal Choral Society&#8217;s performance of this piece. It is such a beautiful example a choral sound. It&#8217;s very polite, restrained, but deeply emotional. I have been discovering that Holst has a...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I listened to the Royal Choral Society&#8217;s performance of this piece. It is such a beautiful example a choral sound. It&#8217;s very polite, restrained, but deeply emotional. I have been discovering that Holst has a specific way of writing melodies that feels very human and grounded.</p>



<p>The melody is the most striking element. The melody moves mostly in stepwise. The melody starts by ascending gently, reaching a hopeful peak (perhaps symbolizing heaven), but ultimately descends back down to the tonic note, finding a resting place (symbolizing earth). This creates a sense of resignation and humility. The harmony is diatonic and simple, avoiding complex chromatic chords, which matches the poem&#8217;s theme of poverty and simplicity.</p>



<p>The slow tempo establishes a somber but peaceful mood. It perfectly captures the image of a &#8220;bleak&#8221; winter landscape. It felt very intimate to me, despite being sung by a large choir.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to John Williams &#8211; Somewhere in My Memory</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-john-williams-somewhere-in-my-memory/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 17:18:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: What is Collaboration?]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=616</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Since Home Alone is the movie of my childhood, which I have watched dozens of times, John Williams’ &#8220;Somewhere in My Memory&#8221; is a piece I have listened to unconsciously for more than twenty years....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Since Home Alone is the movie of my childhood, which I have watched dozens of times, John Williams’ &#8220;Somewhere in My Memory&#8221; is a piece I have listened to unconsciously for more than twenty years. However, analysing it now with a music student’s ear, I realised that while the melody is simple, the arrangement is what generates that instant feeling of nostalgia.</p>



<p>The orchestration is central to the atmosphere. The texture begins lightly, using the celesta and glockenspiel which provide a bright, thin timbre. This is supported by a juvenile choir, whose vocal quality adds an element of innocence and purity that adult voices could not achieve. Beneath this, the string section provides a &#8220;velvet foundation,&#8221; playing legato lines that warm the overall sound.</p>



<p> In a compositional view, the chord progression uses downward motion. I have been noticing that this descending bass line is a hallmark of Christmas songs, perhaps because it mimics a sigh or a settling down, creating a sense of comfort. </p>



<p>What stood out to me most was the dynamic structure. The piece does not stay static; it features a significant crescendo. It starts with a very thin melodic line, but as the piece progresses, the texture thickens until the full orchestra joins the choir. This expansion from intimacy to grandiosity makes the listening experience deeply emotional. It captures a cinematic feeling of the holidays. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
