<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 10:08:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.5</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Project 1: Tutorial</title>
		<link>./../../../project-1-tutorial/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 16:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=151</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reflection Ending this Project 1, I find myself in a unique position. With a background in journalism, many of the research skills covered in this Project were familiar to me. However, this does not mean...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Reflection</h2>



<p>Ending this Project 1, I find myself in a unique position. With a background in journalism, many of the research skills covered in this Project were familiar to me. However, this does not mean revisiting these isn&#8217;t worth refreshing my mind. Journalism has sparked my insterest inthe importance of careful research, but I find that academic writing demands even more rigour in ensuring the information&#8217;s credibility.</p>



<p>I must confess that sometimes I rely on easily accessible sources like Wikipedia for research. Additionally, I tend to seek out information that supports my existing arguments, neglecting to consider contraditory sources. These habits can lead to incomplete or biased research. In my previous level, I have learned to use academic databases more effectively and to cross-reference information from multiple sources to ensure its accuracy.</p>



<p>As a creative writer by profession, I&#8217;m used to taking certain liberties with facts for narrative effect. However, this served as a reminder that there is a clear difference between creative and academic use of sources. It&#8217;s important to always ground my academic work in verifiable facts and reputable sources.</p>



<p>Perhaps the most significant takeaway from this project is the renewed commitment to analytical thinking and factual precision in my academic writing. As it happened in my first level, I sometimes find myself going into a more prosaic style, using evocative language that may not always be academically appropriate. This project has reinforced the reminder to keep a clear distinction between my creative and academic writing. In creative writing, embellishing details can turn my writing more interesting, but in academic writing, these practices can undermine the credibility of my work. In the future, I aim to use straightforward language, avoid unnecessary flourishes, and ensure that every argument is backed by solid evidence.</p>



<p>This project has also inspired me to look into the topic of &#8216;fake news&#8217; in various fields more deeply. Understanding how misinformation spreads and affects public perception is something I find extremely interesting, not just in music history but in all areas of study. For instance, examining case studies of misinformation in different fields can provide valuable insights into how false or poor information is constructed and disseminated. This knowledge can help me critically evaluate sources and improve my research practices.</p>



<p>As I proceed with my chosen pathways, I will carry this refreshed commitment to academic writing. I look forward to applying these skills to my studies, confident that the balance between my creative background and this academic approach will make my learning experience better and contribute to more interesting academic work. This balance allows me to bring a unique perspective to my academic writing, combining the creativity of storytelling with the rigour of academic research.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Statement of Intent</h2>



<p>As I continue my music degree, I have decided to pursue the Composition and Orchestration pathways. This choice aligns with my long-term career goals and personal interests, as well as my professional background and future aspirations.</p>



<p>For over 15 years, I have worked in the advertising industry as a copywriter. During this time, I developed a deep appreciation for the music of the ads we created. The use of music to create an atmosphere and convey emotions always fascinated me. This passion led me to pursue a music degree, with the aim of sustaining my creative process and acquiring the technical skills necessary to compose music professionally.</p>



<p>My recent career shift to the learning and development industry was intentional. I have always been drawn to education and the idea of nurturing the next generation. This move reflects my long-term goal of teaching music, in addition to composing. </p>



<p>The Composition pathway is my primary focus because it directly aligns with my career aspirations. I believe that composing music for ads, films, and video games requires a solid foundation in music theory, creativity, and technical skills. Through this pathway, I aim to develop a deep understanding of music theory. This will enable me to create compositions that are not only original but also harmonically and melodically rich. Learning different compositional techniques and styles, will allow me to expand my creative toolkit.</p>



<p>The Orchestration pathway complements the Composition pathway by providing me with the skills to arrange music for different ensembles and instruments. Learning how to effectively write for different instruments will allow me to create more dynamic and interesting compositions. Orchestration also adds depth and complexity to music. I hope to gain the understanding to be able to add rich textures and layers to my compositions.</p>



<p>Ultimately, my goal is to become a well-rounded composer and arranger, capable of creating music for various media formats. In the distant future, I also aspire to teach music, sharing my knowledge and passion with aspiring musicians.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 10: Critical Listening</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-10-critical-listening/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 15:33:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=164</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Sparks, a band formed by brothers Ron and Russell Mael, have captivated audiences for over 50 years with their unique blend of simplicity, relatability, and innovation. Their extensive discography, consisting of around 30 albums,...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Sparks, a band formed by brothers Ron and Russell Mael, have captivated audiences for over 50 years with their unique blend of simplicity, relatability, and innovation. Their extensive discography, consisting of around 30 albums, reflects their ability to consistently produce engaging music that remains relevant across decades. This essay explores the elements that make The Sparks&#8217; music appealing, the insights gained from their interpretations, and the distinctive features present across their recordings.</p>



<p>Formed in 1966 in Los Angeles, California. Throughout the 1970s, Sparks became known for their theatrical live performances and innovative use of synthesizers. In the 1990s and 2000s, they continued to experiment with their sound, producing concept albums like &#8220;Lil&#8217; Beethoven&#8221; (2002), which combined orchestral arrangements with repetitive lyrics and minimalist compositions. </p>



<p>One of the most striking aspects of The Sparks&#8217; music is its simplicity. Their songs often give the impression of being created by two brothers playing in their bedroom, where the primary focus is on the joy of making music. &#8220;My Baby’s Taking Me Home,&#8221; for example, is characterised by repetition that emphasize fun and engagement over complexity. This simplicity doesn&#8217;t seem a limitation but a choice that makes their music accessible and enjoyable.</p>



<p>Their writing is usually about mundane, everyday subjects. Their lyrics often go into topics that are universally relatable, such as the use of smartphones, the frustration of &#8220;batteries not included,&#8221; or simple subjects like pineapples and visits to the Louvre. This approach grounds their music in real-life experiences. By addressing ordinary themes with humor and wit, they create a sense of familiarity and comfort in their music.</p>



<p>Their sound has often been ahead of its time, incorporating elements that would later become popular in other musical eras. In their 1970s albums, they used synthesizers long before they became a trend of 1980s pop music. Their use of electric guitars and vocal styles has seem to influend various artists like The Killers and Franz Ferdinand.</p>



<p>As stated previously, the key aspect of The Sparks&#8217; music is the evident fun and enjoyment in their creative process. Despite this light approach to music, their work is deeply innovative and respected within the music industry. Collaborations with artists like Max Richter and Franz Ferdinand demonstrate their versatility and the respect they are held by their peers. Even with more than 50 years of work, they continue to engage and inspire listeners, proving that they are much more than just two &#8220;kids&#8221; making random music. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Task 3: History and Curation</title>
		<link>./../../../research-task-3-history-and-curation/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 14:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=161</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Canon Historical Musicology Historiography Historicism Periodization Reflection Reflecting on the books I have read about history in general and music particularly, I can see that most texts cover major eras and key caracthers. In music...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Canon</h4>



<ul>
<li>Canon refers to a body of musical works and composers regarded as highly valuable and exemplary.</li>



<li>Romanticism in the 19th century significantly shaped the canon, emphasising composers like Haydn, Mozart, and Beethoven.</li>



<li><strong>Scholarly Canon:</strong> Driven by musicological and historiographical activities.</li>



<li><strong>Pedagogical Canon:</strong> Influences music teaching and has a longstanding tradition.</li>



<li><strong>Performance Canon:</strong> Influences concert programming and recordings, thus shaping public perception.</li>



<li>The inclusion of works in the canon bestows them with authority and cultural power, often marginalising non-canonical music.</li>



<li>Modern perspectives criticise the canon for its exclusivity and offer counter-canonical strategies focusing on marginalised music.</li>



<li>In popular music, canonical pressures still exist, highlighting classics like the Beatles and Bob Dylan.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Historical Musicology</h4>



<ul>
<li>Historical musicology was formalised by Guido Adler in 1885, focusing on Western concert music&#8217;s history, notation, performance practice, and instrument history.</li>



<li>Adler&#8217;s division included systematic musicology (ethnomusicology, aesthetics, music theory) alongside historical musicology.</li>



<li>The field has evolved to incorporate interdisciplinary perspectives, addressing critical and interpretative aspects of music history.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Historiography</h4>



<ul>
<li>Historiography is the discipline of writing history, including music history.</li>



<li>The writing of music history began significantly in the 18th century, influenced by Enlightenment ideals.</li>



<li>The linear and progressive models of historiography often exclude alternative perspectives.</li>



<li>Canonical histories, like Grout’s <em>A History of Western Music</em>, focus on great composers and works, potentially marginalising other music.</li>



<li>Recent historiographies incorporate diverse genres, including popular and non-Western music, reflecting modern inclusivity.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Historicism</h4>



<ul>
<li>Historicism views historical subjects as products of their social, political, and cultural contexts, valuing past and present equally.</li>



<li>It contrasts Enlightenment views of history as linear human progress, promoting cultural relativism.</li>



<li>Historicism led to the study of music within its specific historical contexts, influencing methodologies like the new historicism of the late 20th century.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Periodization</h4>



<ul>
<li>Periodization is the division of music history into distinct periods (e.g., Baroque, Classical, Romantic) for analytical purposes.</li>



<li>Periodization can imply a linear progression that overlooks the fluidity and overlap of musical developments.</li>



<li>Critical perspectives question traditional periodization models, proposing alternatives like the &#8220;long 18th century&#8221; or &#8220;short 20th century.&#8221;</li>



<li>Periodization helps manage and interpret historical and stylistic groupings but may also reinforce canonical biases.</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Reflection</h4>



<p>Reflecting on the books I have read about history in general and music particularly, I can see that most texts cover major eras and key caracthers. In music history, however, there is often less emphasis on less-known composers, women in music, and non-Western traditions. Contemporary and popular music genres may also be underrepresented.</p>



<p>Let&#8217;s not forget that truly unbiased writing doesn&#8217;t exist. Even computer-generated texts are influenced by biases, so it is normal that all human writing reflects the perspectives of its authors. This is why I believe it is crucial to read a variety of sources, even when studying something as seemingly factual as music history. A text written by a Western author might show a different approach compared to one written by an Indian or African writer, for example.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Task 2: Il Pastor Fido</title>
		<link>./../../../research-task-2-il-pastor-fido/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 10:00:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=159</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Initially, I was surprised to learn that &#8220;Il Pastor Fido&#8221;, long attributed to Vivaldi, was composed by Nicolas Chedeville, a relatively unknown French court musician. The story behind this misattribution is particularly intriguing. Chedeville, as...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Initially, I was surprised to learn that &#8220;Il Pastor Fido&#8221;, long attributed to Vivaldi, was composed by Nicolas Chedeville, a relatively unknown French court musician. The story behind this misattribution is particularly intriguing. Chedeville, as a musette player, created these pieces to expand the repertoire for his instrument. In doing so, he borrowed from Vivaldi&#8217;s works, even directly transcribing parts of a Vivaldi concerto. This blending of original composition with borrowed material makes me wonder&#8230; wasn&#8217;t this an early form of sampling?</p>



<p>This case also makes me reflect on the impact of such discoveries on our appreciation of music. Anderson describes the pieces as &#8220;extraordinarily dull,&#8221; which makes me wonder: would he have used the same language if he still believed them to be Vivaldi&#8217;s work? How much does our perception of a piece&#8217;s quality depend on its attributed composer?</p>



<p>But undoubetly, the role of the French musicologist, Philippe Lescat, was a great example of how important the musicolagy scrutiny and historical research is in ensuring the accuracy of musical attributions.</p>



<p>Moreover, this incident has made me more aware of other instances of musicological &#8216;fake news&#8217;. Mozart&#8217;s Symphony No. 37, long thought to be by Mozart, it was later discovered to be mostly the work of Michael Haydn, with only the introduction by Mozart.</p>



<p>In conclusion, this exploration of &#8220;Il Pastor Fido&#8221; has reinforced for me the vital role of musicology in shaping our understanding of musical heritage. It highlights the importance of approaching historical claims with a critical eye and remaining open to new discoveries.</p>



<p></p>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading">References</h1>



<p><em>Vivaldi/Chédeville il pastor Fido</em> (no date). https://www.gramophone.co.uk/review/vivaldich%C3%A9deville-il-pastor-fido.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 6: Real or Fake?</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-6-real-or-fake/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 09:49:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=156</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Baroque composers who wrote concertos include Vivaldi, Handel, and Bach. This statement is accurate. Vivaldi, George Handel, and Bach were prominent Baroque composers as stated in Britannica&#8217;s website. One of the earliest pieces to use...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Baroque composers who wrote concertos include Vivaldi, Handel, and Bach.</strong></p>



<p>This statement is accurate. Vivaldi, George Handel, and Bach were prominent Baroque composers as stated in <a href="https://www.britannica.com/art/Baroque-music" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.britannica.com/art/Baroque-music">Britannica&#8217;s website</a>. </p>



<p><strong>One of the earliest pieces to use piccolo was Beethoven’s 5th Symphony in 1808.</strong></p>



<p>This statement is true. Beethoven&#8217;s 5th Symphony, first performed in 1808, includes a piccolo in the fourth movement. There may be earlier uses of the piccolo in other compositions, but Beethoven&#8217;s use is among the earliest notable ones in a symphony. <a href="https://philharmonia.co.uk/resources/instruments/piccolo/" data-type="link" data-id="https://philharmonia.co.uk/resources/instruments/piccolo/">Source</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Microtones sound bad or out of tune.</strong></p>



<p>To some Western listeners, microtones might sound unusual or &#8220;out of tune&#8221; because they are not commonly used in Western music traditions. But this is not accurante. This is subjective and culturally biased.</p>



<p><strong>Mahler’s colossal Eighth Symphony [is] literally a Symphony of A Thousand.</strong></p>



<p>This statement is generally correct. Mahler&#8217;s Eighth Symphony requires a large orchestra, multiple choirs, and soloists, typically involving around 1,000 performers. However, the exact number of performers can vary, and it is not always literally 1,000. </p>



<p><strong>There are no mistakes in music composition.</strong></p>



<p>This depends on the perspective. It can be false from an artistic perspective, where any creation can be seen as a valid form of expression. But from a technical standpoint, there can be mistakes in music composition.</p>



<p><strong>Syrinx was the first significant piece for solo flute after the Sonata in A minor by CPE Bach over 150 years before (1747).</strong></p>



<p>This sentence was taken from wikipedia but there are no factual sources that comprove that. There may have been other solo flute pieces composed between these times that were significant in their own right, though perhaps less well-known today.</p>



<p><strong>Improvisation in the performing arts is a very spontaneous performance without specific or scripted preparation.</strong></p>



<p>This statement is true for many forms of improvisation, where performers create and adapt in the moment without a predefined script. But even in improvisation, performers often practice and prepare extensively.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 4: Identifying the Main Points</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-4-identifying-the-main-points/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 09:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=146</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ul>
<li><strong>Music vs. Musicology</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Music is a practical activity with a long history.</li>



<li>Musicology is the study and reflection on music, with a relatively shorter history.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Definition of Musicology</strong>
<ul>
<li>Broadly defined as the thinking about and study of music</li>



<li>Stands outside the creative process to provide perspective on:
<ul>
<li>The creative process itself</li>



<li>The end product (musical work)</li>



<li>Social and cultural contexts</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Historical Development of Musicology</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Early figures like Forkel and Fétis proposed early forms of musicology.</li>



<li>Guido Adler (1885) formalised musicology, separating it into historical and systematic dimensions.</li>



<li>The historical dimension involves organizing music history into epochs and regions.</li>



<li>The systematic dimension focuses on internal properties like harmony and tonality.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Expansion of Scope</strong>
<ul>
<li>Traditional focus on Western classical music</li>



<li>Now includes ethnomusicology, jazz, and popular music studies</li>



<li>Reflects a more inclusive &#8220;whole musical field&#8221; approach</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Historical Narrative of Musicology</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Traces origins back to ancient Greece (Plato and Aristotle) and through medieval, Renaissance, and Enlightenment periods.</li>



<li>The Enlightenment and 19th-century Romanticism influenced musicology with a focus on historicism and aesthetics.</li>



<li>Modernism in the 20th century brought systematic study and musicology as a discipline.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Contemporary Musicology</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Joseph Kerman&#8217;s work in the 1980s marked a significant shift.</li>



<li>Kerman critiqued formalism and positivism in musicology, advocating for a more humane criticism.</li>



<li>The field has become more critical, interdisciplinary, and focused on interpretation rather than mere facts.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Current State of Musicology</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Embraces a broad range of music and critical models.</li>



<li>Reflects ongoing changes and expansions in the field.</li>



<li>Provides a stimulating and motivational context for current and future research.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 3: Primary and Secondary Sources</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-3-primary-and-secondary-sources/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 21:18:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=144</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ul>
<li><strong>Audio recording of a piece of baroque music</strong>: Since the first audio recording of music was in the 19th century, any recording of baroque music would be a secondary source.</li>



<li><strong>The first edition of a score</strong>: This is a direct representation of the composer&#8217;s work and it can be considered a primary source.</li>



<li><strong>A recorded interview with a composer</strong>: The composer is discussing their own work, so it&#8217;s a primary source.</li>



<li><strong>A book about Beethoven by an early 20th-century author</strong>: This is an analysis and interpretation of Beethoven&#8217;s life and music, so it&#8217;s a secondary source.</li>



<li><strong>A book about the history of music</strong>: This can be debatable, but for me it is a secondary source, since it is an analysis and interpretation by an author not directly implied in the history of such music.</li>



<li><strong>An article about performance practice</strong>: This analyses how music is performed, so it&#8217;s a secondary source.</li>



<li><strong>A portrait of Haydn</strong>: Ot doesn&#8217;t directly provide information about his music and so I considered it a secondary source.</li>



<li><strong>Mozart&#8217;s letters to his father</strong>: Primary sources, since these are first-hand accounts from the composer himself.</li>



<li><strong>An Urtext edition</strong>: It is secondary source, since it is an attempt to recreate the composer&#8217;s original score.</li>
</ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 2: Types of Sources</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-2-types-of-sources/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 10:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=142</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<ul>
<li>Books (including textbooks, monographs, and edited volumes)</li>



<li>Academic journals</li>



<li>Websites</li>



<li>Newspapers and magazines</li>



<li>Audio recordings (podcasts, interviews, lectures)</li>



<li>Video recordings (documentaries, lectures, interviews)</li>



<li>Archival materials (letters, diaries, manuscripts)</li>



<li>Papers and presentations from academic conferences</li>



<li>Dissertations and theses</li>



<li>Encyclopedias and reference works</li>



<li>Patents</li>



<li>Social media posts and discussions</li>



<li>Blog posts and online articles</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 1: Choosing Your Pathways</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-1-choosing-your-pathways/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 21:59:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=132</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have some experience in composing original pieces but no experience on arranging existing works. Therefore, I recognise that there&#8217;s still much to learn in both areas. Composition has always been a passion of mine,...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I have some experience in composing original pieces but no experience on arranging existing works. Therefore, I recognise that there&#8217;s still much to learn in both areas. Composition has always been a passion of mine, allowing me to express my creative ideas through music. Orchestration, while less familiar, fascinates me with its potential to explore sonorities and colours of existing compositions.</p>



<p>Strengths in composition include my ability to generate musical ideas and my understanding of basic harmonic structures. Areas for improvement include developing a more sophisticated approach to form and expanding my rhythmic vocabulary. In orchestration, I&#8217;m eager to deepen my knowledge of instruments and their capabilities, as well as learn how to effectively combine them to create varied textures and timbres.</p>



<p>My ambitions align well with these pathways. I aspire to create music that is not only personally expressive but also technically proficient and sonically rich. By focusing on composition, I&#8217;ll be able to refine my musical language and develop a distinctive creative voice. The orchestration pathway will complement this by enabling me to realize my compositions more fully, understanding how to distribute musical material effectively across different instruments and ensembles.</p>



<p>The synergy between these two pathways is particularly exciting. As I learn more about orchestration, I anticipate that this knowledge will inform my compositional choices, leading to more idiomatic writing for various instruments. Conversely, as I develop my compositional skills, I&#8217;ll have a deeper pool of musical ideas to work with when creating arrangements and orchestrations.</p>



<p>I&#8217;m confident that Composition would be the ideal first choice for me. Orchestration &amp; Arrangement emerges as the most fitting second choice, allowing me to develop a comprehensive skillset that encompasses both composing and effectively presenting my musical ideas.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Jon Batiste &#8211; What a Wonderful World</title>
		<link>./../../../listening-to-jon-batiste-what-a-wonderful-world/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 16:57:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=167</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jon Batiste&#8217;s cover of &#8220;What a Wonderful World&#8221; is a reinterpretation of the classic song, offering a contemplative and sombre take that contrasts with Louis Armstrong&#8217;s iconic original version. The instrumentation is minimal, featuring only...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Jon Batiste&#8217;s cover of &#8220;What a Wonderful World&#8221; is a reinterpretation of the classic song, offering a contemplative and sombre take that contrasts with Louis Armstrong&#8217;s iconic original version.</p>



<p>The instrumentation is minimal, featuring only Batiste&#8217;s piano and voice. This sparse arrangement allows for a deep focus on the emotional delivery of the lyrics and the smoothness of the piano. The use of higher notes and a pentatonic scale on the piano adds an interesting texture to the piece, creating a sense of levitation and hope.</p>



<p>The tempo is slower than the original, at around 90 bpm compared to Armstrong&#8217;s 110 bpm. This slower pace contributes to a more reflective mood, allowing for a long and thoughtful articulation of the lyrics. The overall atmosphere feels melancholic and introspective, which contrasts with the uplifting tone of Armstrong&#8217;s interpretation.</p>



<p>One of the most surprising elements is the intense repetition of the E note, which contributes to the feeling of sadness and sorrow that marks the song. This repetitiveness creates a sense of tension and emotional depth that sets it apart from the original.</p>



<p>Batiste&#8217;s version differs significantly from Armstrong&#8217;s in several key aspects. In terms of duration, Batiste&#8217;s interpretation is nearly twice as long at 4 minutes, compared to Armstrong&#8217;s 2 minutes. The emotional tone also diverges considerably; while Armstrong&#8217;s delivery feels warm and optimistic, Batiste&#8217;s interpretation is more introspective and melancholic. The arrangement varies greatly as well, with the original featuring a full orchestra creating a light, moving harmony, whereas Batiste&#8217;s piano-only arrangement feels more static and profound. Rhythmically, Armstrong&#8217;s version has a danceable quality, while Batiste&#8217;s is more atmospheric and free-flowing. Lastly, the vocal presence differs; Armstrong&#8217;s voice is prominent throughout the song, while Batiste allows more space for instrumental passages, creating a different balance between voice and accompaniment.</p>



<p>Batiste&#8217;s reinterpretation of &#8220;What a Wonderful World&#8221; demonstrates artistic courage. Taking one of the most beloved and well-known songs of the 20th century and reimagining it in a more introspective and sombre style, shows that music is not a static artefact, but a dynamic, living entity that can evolve and adapt, continually revealing new facets of meaning and emotion.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
