<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 14:34:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Research Point 3.2</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-3-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 11:55:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1214</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Vivaldi Recomposed, composed by the British composer Max Richter and performed by the Konzerthaus Kammerorchester Berlin, is a&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Recomposed By Max Richter: Vivaldi, The Four Seasons" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="352" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/5yuG2LEkf7QA9ZGIXldCmy?si=GZo_r9qyQ02_EbXHkFWNOw&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Vivaldi Recomposed, composed by the British composer Max Richter and performed by the Konzerthaus Kammerorchester Berlin, is a reinterpretation of Antonio Vivaldi&#8217;s iconic Four Seasons. Richter, known for his unique blend of classical and contemporary music, masterfully weaves themes and ideas from the original composition and adds his modern touch to create a fresh and exciting listening experience.</p>



<p>When I first heard about Vivaldi Recomposed, I couldn&#8217;t help but wonder why a composer would take on such a bold and daring task. After all, the Four Seasons is considered a masterpiece, so why would anyone want to tamper with it? But Richter&#8217;s response to this question was simple and illuminating: &#8220;It&#8217;s just everywhere. In a way, we stop being able to hear it.&#8221; (Service, 2017). And with that, it all made sense. The Four Seasons has become so ubiquitous that it has become background noise. I prefer to look at this work as a wake-up call or a provocation to think about something you take for granted.</p>



<p>After listening to it more than once, a few elements caught my attention. First and foremost, Richter&#8217;s work is not an arrangement of the original piece, but an entirely reimagined interpretation based on Vivaldi&#8217;s core. This became clear to me when my 5-year-old daughter began whistling like a bird when I listened to the Spring movement. Richter effectively conveyed the birds singing as Vivaldi intended, but in a creative and innovative way.</p>



<p>Another aspect that caught my attention was the simplicity and repetition of the movements. I don&#8217;t see it as superior or inferior to Vivaldi&#8217;s original, but a reflection of modern aesthetics valuing repetition over baroque flamboyance, and Richter&#8217;s style emphasizing prolonged notes played over repetitive themes (e.g. Infra 8).</p>



<p>Additionally, the use of synthesizers in the piece was particularly interesting to me, as they were used not to over-modernize the soundscape, but rather as a hint of modernity that amplified the range of sounds and added depth to the strings.</p>



<p>I can rephrase the initial &#8220;Why?&#8221; to &#8220;Should?&#8221; I believe the answer is yes, composers like Richter should continue creating recomposed works, <a href="./../../../../../listening-to-boris-blacher-variations-on-a-theme-of-paganini/index.html" data-type="post" data-id="135" target="_blank">as I previously observed</a>.</p>



<p>I believe music is a living and organic force, not a static one. The reason for this is that musical instruments evolved, tuning evolved, and players evolved. Therefore, the way we hear these compositions today doesn&#8217;t sound the way they did when previous composers such as Vivaldi composed them. By reimagining these works, we not only pay tribute to the greats of the past but also ensure that music lives on for generations to come.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1675079696142 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Tom Service (2017) <em>Max Richter spring-cleans Vivaldi’s The Four Seasons</em>. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/2012/oct/21/max-richter-vivaldi-four-seasons.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Bach: Brandenburg Concerto No. 5 in D Major</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-bach-brandenburg-concerto-no-5-in-d-major/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 15:19:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1207</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reading &#8220;How to Listen to Great Music&#8221; by Robert Greenberg has been an invaluable resource in learning how&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Reading &#8220;How to Listen to Great Music&#8221; by Robert Greenberg has been an invaluable resource in learning how to listen to and analyze music. The author suggests listening to Bach&#8217;s Brandenburg Concerto No. 5 as a way to gain a deeper understanding of Baroque concertos, with a particular emphasis on the ritornello. The concerto, which is composed for flute, solo violin, harpsichord, and strings, presents several interesting features upon listening and studying the score.</p>



<p>Right from the start of the concerto, I noticed the ritornello theme, which was highlighted by Greenberg, and how it reappears in fragments throughout the movement before being repeated in the end after the harpsichord solo.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="547" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-1024x547.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1209" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-1024x547.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-300x160.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-768x410.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-640x342.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29-960x513.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.05.29.png 1292w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Ritornello Theme</figcaption></figure>



<p>As Greenberg explains in his book, the function of the ritornello theme is to create a sense of logical inevitability, providing a feeling of returning home and familiarity, even if only for a brief moment. This helps the listener relax and not be overwhelmed by constant new sounds.</p>



<p>It works similarly to a chorus in modern-day popular music. but it typically appears at the beginning and end of the movement, while choruses in contemporary music typically appear in the middle and end of songs. I am curious as to why composers have shifted the placement of this familiar theme from the beginning to the middle of their compositions.</p>



<p>This movement also stands out for its unique use of the harpsichord as a solo instrument. While it was often used as a continuo instrument in the past, Bach elevated its role to that of a true solo instrument, giving it equal importance alongside the flute and violin. According to Greenberg, this concerto marks a significant moment in music history as the harpsichord&#8217;s solo capabilities were truly showcased for the first time. </p>



<p>The second movement of the concerto is an affettuoso, characterized by its melodic singing between the flute and violin. As I listened, I noticed two features that I had previously encountered in Bach&#8217;s violin sonata &#8211; the use of long, melodic lines that persistently avoid resolving to a steady cadence (as exemplified by the flute&#8217;s quick movement to C), and the repetition of a rhythmic pattern (in this case, quaver-quaver-dotted semiquaver-demisemiquaver) throughout the entire movement.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.20.07.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1210" width="445" height="304" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.20.07.png 738w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.20.07-300x205.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-27-at-14.20.07-640x437.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 445px) 100vw, 445px" /></figure>



<p>The third movement starts with the exposition of a fugal theme by the violin, which is then repeated by the flute. However, as the movement progresses, the violin and flute often play in unison, rather than in counterpoint as is typical in a true fugue. Despite this, there is a significant use of polyphonic texture throughout the movement.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Bach: Sonata No. 4 for violin and harpsichord in C Minor, BMV 1017: 1. Siciliano</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-bach-sonata-no-4-for-violin-and-harpsichord-in-c-minor-bmv-1017-1-siciliano/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 16:22:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1145</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This sonata looks like a good example of Baroque music, characterized by its long melodic lines and ornamental&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Glenn Gould &amp; Yehudi Menuhin - Bach, Sonata No. 4 in C minor (OFFICIAL)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Boii0EA6hWo?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This sonata looks like a good example of Baroque music, characterized by its long melodic lines and ornamental elements. Upon listening to it for the first time played by Glenn Gould and Yehudi Menuhin, I feel that there&#8217;s an interesting contrast between the smoothness of the violin and the pointed, moving accompaniment of the harpsichord. After listening to it several times and studying the score, I noticed several unique features.</p>



<p>One of the key observations I made was that the harpsichord had a repetitive pattern, which allowed the violin to take centre stage. The bass harpsichord usually played a continuous arpeggio starting on the downbeat, while the treble harpsichord had an upward and downward motion with its highest note on the second note of the violin rhythm. The violin melody, in section A, seemed to be a long single melody that lasted 16 bars. Although I could definitely hear that the melody line didn&#8217;t settle until bar 16 and it seemed like Bach avoided a cadence in bars 8 and 12, I was unsure of how he achieved this effect. But my tutor helped clarify that it was a mixture of harmony, not having a perfect cadence, melody/rhythm notes that cross bars, and the use of weaker inversions of chords that gave a feeling of movement instead of a final rest. I hadn&#8217;t thought about how inverting chords could transmit a sense movement and it made much more sense to me after his answer.</p>



<p>Another observation I made was the rhythm of the violin melody and its repetition. This movement of the sonata is a Siciliano which is a musical style from the baroque era, usually in a slow 6/8 time and in a minor key. The violin follows the traditional Siciliana rhythms with a dotted quaver &#8211; semiquaver &#8211; quaver. It&#8217;s interesting to notice that Bach uses this exact rhythm 36 times and some of its variations throughout this movement but without making it feel repetitive. The use of ornamentation is essential here.</p>



<p>Another observation I made was the rhythm of the violin melody and its repetition. This movement of the sonata is a Siciliano, a musical style from the Baroque era, usually in a slow 6/8 time and in a minor key. The violin follows the traditional Siciliana rhythms with a dotted quaver-semiquaver-quaver. It&#8217;s interesting to notice that Bach uses this exact rhythm 36 times and some of its variations throughout this movement without making it feel repetitive. The use of ornamentation is essential here.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="884" height="91" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1151" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image.png 884w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image-300x31.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image-768x79.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image-640x66.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 884px) 100vw, 884px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Siciliano Rhythms</figcaption></figure>



<p>Overall, I find this piece to be deceptively simple yet incredibly evocative and emotionally charged. Reflecting on its various features has helped me gain a deeper understanding of how to approach my assignment with greater insight and understanding.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to SZA &#8211; Kill Bill</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-sza-kill-bill/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 13:41:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1221</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Although I appreciate pop music, I&#8217;m usually turned away from songs that are too popular on the charts.&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Kill Bill" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1Qrg8KqiBpW07V7PNxwwwL?si=0505b2005f2b4d8b&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Although I appreciate pop music, I&#8217;m usually turned away from songs that are too popular on the charts. But, when I stumbled upon SZA&#8217;s &#8220;Kill Bill&#8221; on the radio without knowing what it was, I was extremely surprised. The song really caught my attention. My impression was that the song never settled down, a feeling (a very good feeling) I also had when <a href="./../../../../../listening-to-beach-boys-god-only-knows/index.html" data-type="post" data-id="531" target="_blank">listening to God Only Knows</a>.</p>



<p>The aspect that impressed me the most was the chorus vocal melody. It was straightforward yet stunning and flowed smoothly. Upon transcribing it, I discovered the song was in Ab Major, but the vocal melody only utilized the Ab once on the last note of the 4th beat, which was a rather weak one. There was also an A flat, a chromatic note just a half-step from the tonic, leading to a sense of uncertainty and incompletion.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="74" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1024x74.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1222" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1024x74.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-300x22.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-768x55.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1536x111.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-2048x148.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-640x46.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-960x69.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26.png 2578w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The chord progression also caught my attention. Throughout the song, it used the same progression: Bbm-Eb-Ab-F or ii-V-I-VI. This again contributed to a sense of instability as it started on ii and placed the I on the third bar, which is a weaker position for establishing the key. The final chord was a modulation to a chromatic chord of F Major, which was my favourite part of the chorus. It was playful, and daring, and complemented the lyrics perfectly (e.g. &#8220;Rather be in jail than alone&#8221;).</p>



<p>But right from the beginning, the song starts off sounding vague. There&#8217;s a distinct out-of-tune waver that is completely undefined. From that point, the song could head in any direction. Then, the drum beat enters and as with any typical pop song, you anticipate listening to a four-beat loop until the vocals begin. But the vocals come in on the fourth beat, like an anacrusis, unexpectedly.</p>



<p>Ultimately, I don&#8217;t think &#8220;Kill Bill&#8221; will be regarded as a masterpiece like &#8220;God Only Knows,&#8221; but in today&#8217;s landscape of overwhelming similar-sounding pop music, I found the song to be invigorating. I hope it serves as inspiration for other artists to create pop music that departs from standard harmonic and melodic structures.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Schubert: String Quintet in C Major</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-schubert-string-quintet-in-c-major/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2022 15:31:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1229</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lately, I&#8217;ve been enjoying it more and more the cello. Actually, I think I&#8217;m particularly drawn to low-pitched&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Schubert: String Quintet In C Major D.956, Op. Posth. 163" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="352" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/0tRo5sjdmtVi80mM5Ds2vR?si=1jo0RyGnTia2r_Ftt7vlpg&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Lately, I&#8217;ve been enjoying it more and more the cello. Actually, I think  I&#8217;m particularly drawn to low-pitched instruments like the acoustic bass, bassoon, and cello. When I learned that Schubert wrote a piece for a string quintet with a second cello instead of the usual second viola, I was curious to listen to it.</p>



<p>Listening to it was an emotional journey. The piece seemed to effortlessly shift from one mood to another. For instance, in the first movement (10:03-13:05), it transitioned from a beautiful melodic line to an intense, almost violent cello and back to the melodic line and again back to an angry mood. All this in just 3 minutes.</p>



<p>Sometimes the piece reminded me of Beethoven. For example, at the beginning of the third movement (00:00-04:03), where there is such a strength that it almost looks like an entire orchestra is playing. I think sometimes I could hear a brass instrument within the strings, and it&#8217;s amazing how Schubert was able to create such magic.</p>



<p>I think the decision to use two cellos gave the piece a full orchestral sound, especially during moments with a darker mood, such as the first movement.</p>



<p>Overall, I thoroughly enjoyed this piece and it has sparked my interest in exploring Schubert&#8217;s other works.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Caroline Shaw &#038; Sō Percussion &#8211; To the Sky</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-caroline-shaw-so-percussion-to-the-sky/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 13:07:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1112</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I recently became a fan of Caroline Shaw after listening to her Partita for 8 Singer. I have&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Caroline Shaw &amp; Sō Percussion - To the Sky (Live)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/B22fQIHUyvY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I recently became a fan of Caroline Shaw after listening to her Partita for 8 Singer. I have since listened to some of her other songs, including &#8220;To the Sky,&#8221; which features Shaw&#8217;s exceptional vocals and the talented musicianship of the exploratory New York ensemble Sō Percussion. The lyrics for the song are taken from Anne Steele&#8217;s 18th-century hymnal, the Sacred Harp.</p>



<p>The song starts off with a gentle hum and softly rumbling marimba, gradually increasing in intensity and culminating in Shaw&#8217;s powerful vocals. Shaw&#8217;s music often showcases a dynamic range and the versatility of the voice as an instrument.</p>



<p>In addition to Shaw&#8217;s vocals, Sō Percussion&#8217;s expert use of percussion instruments creates a rich and complex soundscape that perfectly complements Shaw&#8217;s voice.</p>



<p>After a gentle start, the song builds to a climax with exuberance and then fades away, leaving me with a sense of awe and wonder.</p>



<p>Overall, &#8220;To the Sky&#8221; is a beautiful and moving piece of music that has left me wanting to hear more from Shaw.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Georg Friedrich Händel – Dixit Dominus</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-georg-friedrich-handel-dixit-dominus/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2022 14:11:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Baroque Period]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1100</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Because of Project 3.0, I started listening to Händel&#8217;s Dixit Dominus&#8217; first movement and ended up listening to&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Spotify Embed: Handel: Ode for the Birthday of Queen Anne &amp; Dixit Dominus" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="380" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/2T2GyKe3BFyCa9QgLpMEgx?si=IGbcK_haT-eNXccI9VMzPA&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Because of Project 3.0, I started listening to Händel&#8217;s Dixit Dominus&#8217; first movement and ended up listening to the entire work. </p>



<p>Georg Friedrich Händel was a German-born composer (1685 &#8211; 1759) who worked in Germany, and Italy and settled in London. He was heavily influenced by the middle-German polyphonic choral tradition and the Italian Baroque style. Händel&#8217;s music is considered a pinnacle of the &#8220;high baroque&#8221; style and he is widely regarded as one of the greatest composers of his era.</p>



<p>Dixit Dominus is a psalm setting completed in 1707 and is scored for an SSATB choir and soloists, strings and continuo. </p>



<p>Although I enjoyed the entire piece, I found the first movement to be the most interesting and surprising. As a psalm, I was expecting a contemplative and loving sound. Instead, I found it to be rough and even a bit hostile. This was due to the rhythmic vitality which felt a lot like a warlike snare.</p>



<p>It is not surprising that the piece&#8217;s opening movement evokes a warlike sound, given the psalm&#8217;s theme about God giving the king of Israel the power to defeat his enemies (Clássicos dos Clássicos, 2019).</p>



<p>The ending of Dominus a dextris tuis is another example of the power of the choir, as it resembles a war chant. I imagine this would likely have been striking to an audience in the 1700s, given the religious context in which it was performed.</p>



<p>The choir in this piece reminded me of Caroline Shaw&#8217;s Partita for 8 Voices. I believe that they are similar in their exploration of different vocal timbers and ranges, either together or in counterpoint. Additionally, the staccato rhythm of the voices in both pieces creates an almost drum-like feeling.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Partita for 8 Singers: No. 1. Allemande" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/E98OCHWIv3s?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1670601412288 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Clássicos dos Clássicos (2019) <em>Händel – Dixit Dominus (Disse o Senhor), HWV 232</em>. Available at: https://classicosdosclassicos.mus.br/obras/handel-dixit-dominus-disse-o-senhor-hwv-232/ (Accessed: December 10, 2022).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
