<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Project 3: Designing Your Project &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 23:02:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Rosalía, Carminho – Memória</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-rosalia-carminho-memoria/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 22:19:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Designing Your Project]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=629</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The global success of Rosalía’s new album, Lux, made it impossible for me to ignore, so I finally sat down to listen. In my view, the record is a triumph because it is a conceptual...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The global success of Rosalía’s new album, Lux, made it impossible for me to ignore, so I finally sat down to listen. In my view, the record is a triumph because it is a conceptual work where a mainstream artist takes the liberty to create something entirely different from the formatted pop we hear today. Among the tracks, <em>Memória</em> stood out most. Partly because I am Portuguese and I adore Carminho, but also because of how it bridges two worlds.</p>



<p>To me, <em>Memória</em> captures a deep sense of saudade through its inherent sadness. The dramatic contrast between the quiet instruments and the intense, longing delivery of the lyrics creates a mood of profound introspection. It feels like a bridge between the past and the present, where the minimalist production allows the emotional weight of the Fado tradition to shine without being over-produced. I found the experience deeply moving, as it proves that mainstream music can still be surprising.</p>



<p>I adore how the minimalist texture, featuring a delicate interplay between harp and piano, replaces the traditional Portuguese guitar, pushing the sound toward an ethereal, dreamlike atmosphere rather than a standard folk style.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Joseph Turrin &#8211; Lullaby for Vaska</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-joseph-turrin-lullaby-for-vaska/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 22:55:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Designing Your Project]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=644</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This piece combines chamber orchestra, narrator, and voice in a way that clearly separates their roles. The orchestra provides the main emotional and structural foundation, using long, sustained lines and gentle dynamics that reflect the...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This piece combines chamber orchestra, narrator, and voice in a way that clearly separates their roles. The orchestra provides the main emotional and structural foundation, using long, sustained lines and gentle dynamics that reflect the idea of a lullaby. These musical features create a calm and continuous background rather than strong contrasts or dramatic development.</p>



<p>The narrator delivers the text in a clear and direct manner, which allows the meaning of the words to remain understandable. The solo voice adds another layer, using simple melodic material that blends with the orchestral texture instead of standing out too strongly.</p>



<p>This work moved me, particularly the contrast between the innocence of a &#8220;lullaby&#8221; and the brutal reality of the siege. The dramatic contrast between the narrator&#8217;s steady voice and the soaring, mournful soprano at the end felt like a deep experience, reflecting both deep despair and a glimmer of hope. It reinforces my belief that including a narrator can transform a musical performance into a personal, cinematic journey.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Dana Wilson – Mirror for String Quartet and Narration</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-dana-wilson-mirror-for-string-quartet-and-narration/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 22:45:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Designing Your Project]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=642</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Listening to this was a different experience from most string quartet music I know. What interested me most was how the spoken text and the music exist together without competing. The narration does not tell...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Listening to this was a different experience from most string quartet music I know. What interested me most was how the spoken text and the music exist together without competing. The narration does not tell a story in a dramatic way. Instead, it feels like quiet thoughts placed inside the music. This made me listen more carefully to both elements.</p>



<p>I found that the music creates a space for reflection rather than strong emotions. The rhythmic patterns and repeated ideas reminded me of everyday movement and energy, especially in modern life. At the same time, the spoken words felt personal and honest. Because the text is spoken, not sung, I could understand it easily, and it felt more direct and human.</p>



<p>I also liked that the piece changes depending on where it is performed and who writes the text. This made me think about music as something connected to people and place. Overall, the piece made me reflect on how music can support thinking and listening, rather than leading the listener too strongly. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 3: Risk Assessments and Ethics</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-3-risk-assessments-and-ethics/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 23:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Designing Your Project]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=626</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Working with Children This is the extreme risk and rightly so. I&#8217;ve never composed for children before, and whilst Elena and John will supervise everything, I&#8217;m acutely aware I could inadvertently cause harm. The case...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><h2 class="text-text-100 mt-3 -mb-1 text-[1.125rem] font-bold" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); letter-spacing: normal; white-space: normal;">Working with Children</h2><p class="font-claude-response-body break-words whitespace-normal leading-[1.7]" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); white-space: normal;">This is the extreme risk and rightly so. I&#8217;ve never composed for children before, and whilst Elena and John will supervise everything, I&#8217;m acutely aware I could inadvertently cause harm. The case study about the film students getting arrested whilst filming gang violence really struck me. Good intentions aren&#8217;t enough if you don&#8217;t think through practical implications.</p><p class="font-claude-response-body break-words whitespace-normal leading-[1.7]" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); white-space: normal;"></p><h2 class="text-text-100 mt-3 -mb-1 text-[1.125rem] font-bold" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); letter-spacing: normal; white-space: normal;">Making Them Feel Rubbish About Themselves</h2><p class="font-claude-response-body break-words whitespace-normal leading-[1.7]" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); white-space: normal;">This worry feels almost embarrassing to write down, but it&#8217;s real: what if I write music that&#8217;s too hard and students feel inadequate? I don&#8217;t want to make these children feel small. Q<span style="background-color: rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.2);">uite possible some students will struggle, and the emotional impact could be significant.</span></p><p class="font-claude-response-body break-words whitespace-normal leading-[1.7]" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); white-space: normal;"></p><p class="font-claude-response-body break-words whitespace-normal leading-[1.7]" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); white-space: normal;"></p><h2 class="text-text-100 mt-3 -mb-1 text-[1.125rem] font-bold" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); letter-spacing: normal; white-space: normal;"><span style="font-size: 1.75rem; background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);">What If We Just Fail?</span></h2><p class="font-claude-response-body break-words whitespace-normal leading-[1.7]" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); white-space: normal;">The collaboration might break down. We might disagree. Students might lose interest. The timeline might prove impossible. And that&#8217;s okay, as long as I document it honestly.<span style="background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);"> </span>I still feel anxious though. What if Elena and John get frustrated with my inexperience? What if students are disappointed? I need to be really honest throughout. Not pretending I know what I&#8217;m doing when I don&#8217;t, asking for help early, and being willing to stop if it&#8217;s not working.</p><h2 class="text-text-100 mt-3 -mb-1 text-[1.125rem] font-bold" style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0); color: rgb(0, 0, 0); letter-spacing: normal; white-space: normal;"></h2></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 1: Expectations</title>
		<link>./../../../../exercise-1-expectations/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 22:30:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 3: Designing Your Project]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=624</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Shared Expectations What we all agree on: What we all need: Communication: Decision-Making: Roles and Responsibilities: Boundaries and Limitations:]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Shared Expectations</h3>



<p><strong>What we all agree on:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>The process is more important than the final product</li>



<li>We value honest communication and feedback throughout</li>



<li>We want students to be actively involved in the co-creation process</li>



<li>We recognise this is experimental and requires flexibility from everyone</li>



<li>We want to create something that connects students to Portuguese history and CAISL&#8217;s heritage</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>What we all need:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Regular communication and check-ins</li>



<li>Flexibility and understanding of each other&#8217;s constraints</li>



<li>Honesty about what is/isn&#8217;t working</li>



<li>Willingness to revise and adapt as the project develops</li>



<li>Time to adequately prepare students once the composition is ready</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Communication:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Regular meetings (approximately monthly) to discuss progress and challenges</li>



<li>Email updates between meetings as needed</li>



<li>Open door policy &#8211; anyone can raise concerns or questions at any time</li>



<li>Pedro to share drafts and ideas early and often for feedback</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Decision-Making:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Compositional decisions led by Pedro with input from Elena and John</li>



<li>Pedagogical decisions (what&#8217;s appropriate for students) led by Elena and John</li>



<li>Major decisions about project direction made collaboratively</li>



<li>If disagreements arise, we discuss openly and seek compromise</li>



<li>If collaboration breaks down, we document the process and reasons honestly</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Roles and Responsibilities:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Pedro: Lead composer, draft musical ideas, revise based on feedback, document process</li>



<li>Elena: Provide string expertise, facilitate orchestra access, lead string rehearsals, provide piano support</li>



<li>John: Provide vocal expertise, facilitate choir access, lead vocal rehearsals, coordinate with drama if needed</li>



<li>All: Attend collaborative sessions with students, provide honest feedback, communicate openly</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Boundaries and Limitations:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Pedro has never composed for such young players. Learning curve expected</li>



<li>5th graders have significant technical limitations. Music must be very simple</li>



<li>Timeline is tight. All collaborators have other commitments</li>



<li>Exploratory rotation schedule affects which students are available when</li>



<li>School calendar is busy. Rehearsal time may be limited</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
