<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Part 4 Exploring counterpoint &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 11:39:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Revision of Assignment 4 after tutor feedback</title>
		<link>./../../../../revision-of-assignment-4-after-tutor-feedback/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 14:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=764</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My reviewed score can be viewed here. In my revision, I developed the C and A&#8217; sections since&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>My reviewed score can be viewed <a href="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Assignment-4-Revision-Full-Score.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Assignment-4-Revision-Full-Score.pdf" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>



<p>In my revision, I developed the C and A&#8217; sections since the tutor pointed out that they were the most characteristic passages. In my composition, I explored and developed the uncommon harmonies and the contrapuntal section.</p>



<p>My tutor pointed out that both instruments had a number of challenging passages. As for the bassoon, these passages aren&#8217;t impossible to play and their musical sonority justifies them. The vibraphone, however, had some difficult passages, particularly fast chords of three notes. I changed most of the three-note chords to two-note chords without losing the sonority I intended.</p>



<p>As for the notation, I rearranged the order of the instruments, because the bassoon should be above the vibraphone. Additionally, I deleted the bracket in the vibraphone, changed the font for tempo, and adjusted the layout so that the gaps between the instruments are consistent.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reflections on Assignment 4</title>
		<link>./../../../../reflections-on-assignment-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 13:09:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://shocking-purpose.localsite.io/?p=590</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[For part 4 of this unit, I had the opportunity to explore how a counterpoint composition can be&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For part 4 of this unit, I had the opportunity to explore how a counterpoint composition can be developed with the main subject as the focal point. Bach&#8217;s fugues proved to be of great importance here.</p>



<p>I also explored tuned percussion instruments for the first time. I found them varied and versatile. I will certainly explore composition with the timpani and the glockenspiel.</p>



<p>As a result of listening to Ragtime, I also developed a better understanding of rhythm and syncopation in some compositions.</p>



<h3 id="about-assignment-4" class="wp-block-heading">About Assignment 4</h3>



<p>So far, this assignment has been the most challenging. The assignment was difficult for me for a number of reasons, but I suspect it was the challenge of writing something different that I placed on myself.</p>



<p>In general, I am not pleased with the composition. It has some parts that I like, especially the motif and some rhythmic details in section C, but as a whole, it doesn&#8217;t appeal to me as much as some of my other compositions.</p>



<p>Despite being aware that a university is a place where people take chances, I will attempt to create something I&#8217;m more familiar with in the next assignment to increase my self-confidence.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 4</title>
		<link>./../../../../assignment-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 10:07:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://shocking-purpose.localsite.io/?p=582</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In assignment 4, I had to compose an imitative counterpoint for around 3 minutes using woodwinds and tuned&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In assignment 4, I had to compose an imitative counterpoint for around 3 minutes using woodwinds and tuned percussion.</p>



<p>You can find the final score <a href="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-43-Full-Score.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-43-Full-Score.pdf" target="_blank">here</a> and listen to it below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-4.mp3"></audio></figure>



<h2 id="the-idea-theme" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108541003 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Idea / Theme</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Having felt that my previous assignments were a bit on the safe side, I decided to incorporate the element of surprise into this assignment. It was important for me to try things I hadn&#8217;t done before. I wanted to go to places that made me uncomfortable and use my ingenuity to see if I could surprise myself.</p>



<p>Regarding the theme, along with the idea of surprise, this piece will be about a party, for instance, a wedding, where a dance will be performed by two voices. Then something goes wrong between these two voices, maybe an argument or an altercation that completely changes the mood. Ultimately, both parties reach an agreement and get back to dancing.</p>



<h2 id="the-structure" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108659753 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Structure</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The idea largely determines the structure. This turns the structure into an A-B-C-A-B. I envision this piece beginning with an intro (A section) that will be in the same key, but rhythmically different from the B section. When we move from the B section to the C section, there will be a change in key, time signature, tempo, and dynamics to create a full contrast. After this section, we return to the intro and then the B section.</p>



<p>The A section will be in a minor key, the B section in a major key, and the C section in a minor key. In this piece, I will start in the key of E minor, then move to its relative major key of G major. In the C section, I will use the key of B minor, which is a fifth from the key of E minor, because I want to create some contrast without sounding too abrupt.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-regular cnvs-block-core-table-1628498574118"><table><thead><tr><th>Theme</th><th>Section &amp; Triad</th><th>Duration / Tempo</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>The instruments present themselves and get in the mood for the party</td><td>A &#8211; E minor</td><td>~20 seconds at 75 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They party and dance together with one instrument initiating the dance and the other following</td><td>B &#8211; G major</td><td>~50 seconds at 95 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>Tension builds up and there&#8217;s a fight</td><td>C &#8211; B minor</td><td>~40 seconds at 80 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They come into agreement and return to get themselves in the mood for part</td><td>A&#8217; &#8211; E minor</td><td>~20 seconds at 75 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They slowly return to the dance and party until the end</td><td>B&#8217; &#8211; G major</td><td>~50 seconds at 95 bpm </td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 id="the-motifs" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108877461 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Motifs</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>As I was playing around with the piano, I came up with a motif (in red) that started short and developed into a bigger subject.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="252" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-1024x252.png" alt="" class="wp-image-595" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-1024x252.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-300x74.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-768x189.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-1536x378.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-2048x504.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-640x157.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432-960x236.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-432.png 2172w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h2 id="the-instruments" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110169912 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Instruments</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Having reviewed a recent video from Philharmonia, I decided to choose the vibraphone because of the sustained sound it produces.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Instruments: Percussion" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-lJctvybAJ8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Philharmonia Orchestra (London, UK), 2013. Instruments: Percussion. Available at:&lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-lJctvybAJ8&gt; [Accessed 15 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>I decided to go with the bassoon for the woodwind instrument again because I am finding it to be much more versatile than I had anticipated.</p>



<p>The combination of these instruments seemed unusual to me, and I was not wrong. Youtube and Spotify returned few results, but I found this performance of a piece by Alexandre Ouzounoff that encouraged me to continue experimenting with these two instruments.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Alexandre Ouzounoff: Cependant, la lune se lève pour basson et vibraphone (2013)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vo1Fgqq8-Kw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>University of Michigan Bassoon Studio, 2015.&nbsp;Alexandre Ouzounoff: Cependant, la lune se lève pour basson et vibraphone (2013). Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vo1Fgqq8-Kw&gt; [Accessed 15 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<h2 id="the-composition" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110414281 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The composition</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><strong>Section A</strong> Bars 1-6</p>



<p>As an introduction to the piece, I composed a short section with both instruments presenting themselves in different moods: the bassoon is strong and sustained, and the vibraphone is fast and harmonious.</p>



<p>I was inspired by Stravinsky&#8217;s bassoon solo in Rite Of Spring to start the piece on a high sustained note.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Stravinsky&#039;s Rite Of Spring Bassoon solo by Gustavo Nunez" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Xfg9IIXhcPk?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Nick B., 2007.&nbsp;<em>Stravinsky&#8217;s Rite Of Spring Bassoon solo by Gustavo Nunez</em>. Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xfg9IIXhcPk&gt; [Accessed 15 November 2021].<br></figcaption></figure>



<p>This introduction ends abruptly to convey the main idea of a piece with surprise elements.</p>



<p><strong>Section B</strong> Bars 7-26</p>



<p>Here, the time signature changes and the bassoon plays the main subject, copied by the vibraphone. With the bassoon playing a countersubject in E in bar 13, the vibraphone is now free to play the main subject in G, which now is a major third.</p>



<p>In bar 20, the bassoon returns to the main theme but starts in C, which is a major 4th of G. The vibraphone continues to fill the room with ascending and descending notes.</p>



<p>Both instruments start ascending melodies in bar 23, which leads to a climax and the end of this section.</p>



<p><strong>Section C</strong> Bars 27-40</p>



<p>The section begins with a low dynamic and just the vibraphone playing. Although the key changes to B minor, I wanted to create another level of surprise and ambiguity, so I played an F major chord on the high notes, while the low notes created dissonance.</p>



<p>This section motif is then played by the bassoon, accompanied by a steady rhythm played by the vibraphone. Sometimes the vibraphone completes a triad, such as the A major in bar 28, but sometimes it just plays dissonant tones.</p>



<p>In the absence of harmony between the instruments, the tension rises with minor triads and the tempo increases.</p>



<p>At Bar 36, both instruments play staccato, and the tempo is the fastest in the entire piece. The vibraphone continues with its ascending and descending melody, while the bassoon is more steady in its notes.</p>



<p>At the end, in bar 40, they are both tired of the previous part and rest in minim notes before concluding with a B major triad.</p>



<p><strong>Section A&#8217;</strong> Bars 41-43</p>



<p>The section starts with a chord in G major, marking a key change, and proceeds into a version of the intro.</p>



<p><strong>Section B</strong>&#8216; Bars 44-67</p>



<p>In this section, a bassoon augmented subject is played while the vibraphone plays the motif, followed by a counterpoint.</p>



<p>In bar 56, the bassoon plays an inversion of the subject while the vibraphone plays parts of the motif and triads.</p>



<p>In bar 62, the bassoon plays the main motif, which is quickly repeated by the vibraphone in increasing tones until they both end in a G.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Assignment-4.mp3" length="3017582" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Bach&#8217;s Fugues</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-bachs-fugues/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 02:58:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=541</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 8 in D-Sharp Minor, BWV 853 I felt this fugue was&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h4 id="the-well-tempered-clavier-book-1-fugue-no-8-in-d-sharp-minor-bwv-853" class="wp-block-heading"><meta charset="utf-8">The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 8 in D-Sharp Minor, BWV 853</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 8 in D-Sharp Minor, BWV 853" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZG8LVgUzSc0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Gould, G., 2015.&nbsp;<em>The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 8 in D-Sharp Minor, BWV 853</em>. Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZG8LVgUzSc0&gt; [Accessed 12 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>I felt this fugue was really lovely, especially because I enjoyed the theme and Bach used it frequently throughout this composition. In fact, I thought this fugue was quite theme-centric, with the theme inverted, augmented, and rhythmically varied. It’s also worth noting that this fugue goes from a straightforward exposition to a three-voiced narrative.</p>



<p>To be clear, some sources indicate that this fugue is in Eb minor; nevertheless, the prelude is in Eb minor, but the fugue is in D# minor in most scores I discovered. Although I don’t believe it matters, I’ll keep mentioning that this fugue is in D# minor.</p>



<p>This fugue begins with the first voice exposition of the theme, while the second voice (in red) imitate it. Right away, the lowest voice repeats it a second time. Bach repeats this three-bar theme four times in the first 14 bars, which shows how important this theme is to him.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="614" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-1024x614.png" alt="" class="wp-image-544" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-1024x614.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-300x180.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-768x461.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-1536x921.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-640x384.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1-960x576.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.15.14-1.png 1884w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>In order to emphasize the theme-centric nature of the fugue, the theme is repeated five times from bar 19 to bar 29, before there is an inversion (in blue). I was interested to see if the inversion is an exact mirror of the theme. I got my answer right away: no. The very first note, D#, goes to an A#, the perfect fifth. However, the inversion goes down a perfect fourth. Following these first notes, everything is mirrored.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="573" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-1024x573.png" alt="" class="wp-image-545" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-1024x573.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-300x168.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-768x430.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-1536x859.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-640x358.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32-960x537.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-12.28.32.png 1888w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Afterwards, the lower voice plays an augmentation of the theme (in green) at double speed. In my opinion, this is where the piece begins to climax and become more complex.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="396" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-1024x396.png" alt="" class="wp-image-546" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-1024x396.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-300x116.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-768x297.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-1536x593.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-640x247.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14-960x371.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-25-at-14.56.14.png 1934w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>It is difficult for me to follow and analyze without assistance from here. I noticed that the theme is imitated and reversed as well as amplified and augmented throughout the entire piece, making it a complex and engaging ending.</p>



<h4 id="the-well-tempered-clavier-book-i-fugue-no-14-in-f-sharp-minor-bwv-859" class="wp-block-heading">The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book I: Fugue <meta charset="utf-8">No. 14 in F-sharp minor, BWV 859</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 14 in F-Sharp Minor, BWV 859" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uzeucBPHi00?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Gould, G., 2015.&nbsp;<em>The Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1: Fugue No. 14 in F-Sharp Minor, BWV 859</em>. Available at: &lt;https://youtu.be/uzeucBPHi00&gt; [Accessed 12 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>I found this fugue to be slow, sorrowful, but at the same time, I found it to sometimes be beautifully harmonious. Contrary to other fugues I have heard, I believe this could be played in a church, with the long notes resonating in the long walls. Alternatively, a choral group could perform it.</p>



<p>The theme (in red) and countertheme (in brown) are presented in the first six bars of this fugue, which is interesting. The theme’s long notes are precisely counterbalanced by the countertheme’s quavers, allowing both to be heard clearly. When the third voice is added in the lower bass, it sounds really lovely to me. This produces a really fascinating and recognizable sound that binds all of the voices together.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1008" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-1024x1008.png" alt="" class="wp-image-548" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-1024x1008.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-300x295.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-768x756.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-80x80.png 80w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-640x630.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03-960x945.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.25.03.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>I was curious as to how Bach composed the theme and counter-theme to work together so beautifully, so I decided to investigate further. One thing I observed is that both melodies, especially the countertheme, move in a step-by-step manner, only leaping in the finish. This, I believe, allows the intervals to move from fifths to thirds, as seen at the start of bar 5. In addition, the opposing motion in the first two bars, when one of the melodies rises (in red) and the other falls (in blue), generates a lovely contrast and tension, which is released in the last two bars, when both move in the same direction.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="678" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-1024x678.png" alt="" class="wp-image-549" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-1024x678.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-300x199.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-768x508.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-640x424.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43-960x635.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-10.41.43.png 1496w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>When I previously stated that I considered this piece to be quite harmonic at moments, I was making reference to bars 13 and 14. All melodies, I suppose, have the same function here: to set the stage for the return of the theme and countertheme, but this time in a more powerful form. The theme is mostly played by the two upper voices with the thirds. This brings the piece to a close with a mini-climax.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1001" height="1024" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-1001x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-550" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-1001x1024.png 1001w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-293x300.png 293w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-768x786.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-1501x1536.png 1501w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-300x307.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-640x655.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10-960x982.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.17.10.png 1604w" sizes="(max-width: 1001px) 100vw, 1001px" /></figure>



<p>Something new appears later, at the conclusion of bar 20. The motif has been inverted (in blue). This inversion is accompanied by lower voice quavers that sound like the countertheme. I believe this is employed to have a familiar sound with this new inversion theme.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="724" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-1024x724.png" alt="" class="wp-image-551" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-1024x724.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-300x212.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-768x543.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-1536x1087.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-640x453.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16-960x679.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.29.16.png 1668w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>One last thing I’d like to mention is something I don’t recall hearing in previous fugues. When two voices play similar melodies while the other two wait their time to play identical tunes. As with prior examples, most of this is done using the third interval. All of this builds up to the final theme and countertheme section.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="355" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-1024x355.png" alt="" class="wp-image-552" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-1024x355.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-300x104.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-768x267.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-1536x533.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-2048x711.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-640x222.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33-960x333.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-26-at-11.41.33.png 2328w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Stravinsky &#8211; Rite Of Spring</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-stravinsky-rite-of-spring/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 11:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=714</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Bassoons are turning into one of my favourite instruments because of their sound and versatility of being able&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Bassoons are turning into one of my favourite instruments because of their sound and versatility of being able to be both a rhythmic and melodic instrument. As I was researching about it, I came across the introduction to Stravinsky&#8217;s Rite Of Spring, where the bassoon plays an extremely unusual high note and a beautiful melody. As a result of this unusual sound, I was drawn to listen to the whole piece more closely.</p>



<p>Rite Of Spring was commissioned by Serge Diaghilev, the noted impresario of the Ballets Russes who had also produced The Firebird (1910) and Petrushka (1911) and it was not a huge hit on opening night (Schwarm, n.d.).</p>



<p>In 1913, the Rite Of Spring was received by the audience at the premiere at the Théâtre des Champs-Elysées in Paris with shouts and yells. There was so much noise that the dancers were unable to hear the orchestra. It was a total disaster (Stravinsky&#8217;s The Rite of Spring: Keeping Score | PBS, 2022). However, later became known as one of the most influential pieces of music of the 20th century.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Igor Stravinsky - The Rite of Spring (1913)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rP42C-4zL3w?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Cmaj7, 2018. <em>Igor Stravinsky &#8211; The Rite of Spring (1913)</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://youtu.be/rP42C-4zL3w> [Accessed 11 November 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>This piece was influenced by Russian culture and folk-inspired forms and melodies, but its chaotic percussive momentum challenged its audience. Stravinsky, for example, borrowed the bassoon introduction from a Lithuanian folk song titled &#8220;Tu, manu seserėlė&#8221;. But he added multiple instruments and heightened this melody with dissonant melodies, recurrent changes in meter and rhythmic syncopations.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Oh My Sister (Tu Mano Seserėle)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YDz4HCqTRPs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>I can imagine the audience at the premiere of the Rite Of Spring being stunned by the orchestra&#8217;s clash of sounds. After listening to it for the first time, I got shocked when The Augurs of Spring, Dances of the Young Girls began. This work had so much power, violence, and changing rhythms that I was not prepared for it.</p>



<p>This piece relies heavily on rhythm as it leads almost all the parts. Even though the orchestral size of The Rite Of Spring is enormous, sometimes the rhythm is not played by percussion instruments but by other instruments, especially strings. In the Sacrificial Dance as well as The Dance of Young Girls, the orchestra&#8217;s percussive nature can be heard.</p>



<p>The rhythm sometimes evokes an African/Oceanic sound, as at the start of the Ritual of Abduction. Don&#8217;t forget that this piece was written at the height of African and Oceanian colonization. During the colonial period, there was a cultural clash that caused some artists to create art that didn&#8217;t resonate with previous creations. In a previous post, I discussed the importance of polyphony in Polynesia, which had a large French population. I wonder how much this influenced Stravinsky in the Rite Of Spring.</p>



<p>Creatively speaking, the piece possesses a lot of originality. Stravinsky layers a variety of melodies and rhythms on top of each other, creating what some would call noise. Yet ultimately, I believe this is a sonorous experience that requires dozens of listens to understand how each instrument fits into the music.</p>



<p>As I listened to the entire piece, I found it to be more enjoyable than I initially expected. What I enjoyed more than the rhythmic asymmetries, the dissonances, and the layers of ostinatos played simultaneously was the surprise element. Stravinsky played with the listener&#8217;s expectations and never let the music settle in a safe place, even though there are repetitions (especially underlying chords). After the listener becomes comfortable with a sonority, there is a twist, just like a plot twist in a narrative, and everything is new again.</p>



<p>As a result of this unexpected element, I understand why the audience at the premiere was shocked and furious. Apparently, it was the surprise, and I believe it was a loud one, that drove people crazy, even leading to the conductor, Pierre Monteux, admitting that &#8220;everything available was tossed in our direction&#8221; (Jones, n.d.). But this led me to raise a question.</p>



<p>Since when has music not shocked people? Almost since I was born, I recall tv shows, movies, and exhibitions that shocked the public. Music, however, does not seem to have shocked audiences as much. Does this mean that music is becoming less experimental? Is it because the audience is just accustomed to ignoring things they don&#8217;t like? Perhaps the &#8220;Next&#8221; button on the music player is to blame. Nowadays, listeners are not &#8220;obligated&#8221; to sit in a theatre for 90 minutes to hear a piece they&#8217;ve never heard before. What will be the next musical rage?</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1641311964550 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Schwarm, B., n.d.&nbsp;<em>The Rite of Spring | History, Composer, &amp; Facts</em>. [online] Encyclopedia Britannica. Available at: &lt;https://www.britannica.com/topic/The-Rite-of-Spring&gt; [Accessed 11 November 2021].</p>



<p>Pbs.org. n.d.&nbsp;<em>Stravinsky&#8217;s The Rite of Spring: Keeping Score | PBS</em>. [online] Available at: &lt;https://www.pbs.org/keepingscore/stravinsky-rite-of-spring.html&gt; [Accessed 11 November 2021].</p>



<p>Jones, E., n.d.&nbsp;<em>Stravinsky’s The Rite of Spring | Music 101</em>. [online] Courses.lumenlearning.com. Available at: &lt;https://courses.lumenlearning.com/suny-musicapp-medieval-modern/chapter/stravinskys-the-rite-of-spring/&gt; [Accessed 11 November 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project 12: Two-Part Invention</title>
		<link>./../../../../project-12-two-part-invention/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 07:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=610</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the first exercise for a two-part experience, I aimed to compose something similar to what I heard&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the first exercise for a two-part experience, I aimed to compose something similar to what I heard from Bach and a more &#8220;traditional&#8221; invention. After reading about invention, I gathered some process rules that allow writing an invention.</p>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled"><li>Write a motif in one voice</li><li>The second voice repeats the motif in another octave</li><li>The first voice imitates the motif on the dominant</li><li>The second voice imitates the motif it played before but this time on the dominant</li><li>Then use parts or the whole motif in augmented, diminuted or inversed version while the other voice plays counterpoint</li><li>End in the tonic</li></ul>



<p>Although I know these are not strict rules, I tried to apply the process here to help me compose faster and with fewer elements. I must say I liked this process. I started with a motif that is played in both voices on the tonic and on the dominant. I then passed to both voices playing a diminuted version of the motif and ending with the oboe playing an inversion while the bassoon plays an augmented motif. </p>



<p>You can download the Sibelius file <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1pPstCcpc3z2l_4XrVz9I3iQzVwV7HI0L/view?usp=sharing" data-type="URL" data-id="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1pPstCcpc3z2l_4XrVz9I3iQzVwV7HI0L/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="722" height="1024" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1-722x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-784" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1-722x1024.png 722w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1-212x300.png 212w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1-768x1089.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1-1083x1536.png 1083w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1-1445x2048.png 1445w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1-300x425.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1-640x907.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1-960x1361.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/project-12-1.png 2222w" sizes="(max-width: 722px) 100vw, 722px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p>In my second exercise, I tried to apply a more rhythmic invention while using the marimba. As in the first exercise, I created a motif that is repeated and imitated by both voices. I didn&#8217;t feel the need to augment the motif since I got the sense that I would lose the rhythm of it, so I used a diminuted version of the motif in the marimba while the flute plays an inversion.</p>



<p>You can download the Sibelius file <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1pPstCcpc3z2l_4XrVz9I3iQzVwV7HI0L/view?usp=sharing" data-type="URL" data-id="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1pPstCcpc3z2l_4XrVz9I3iQzVwV7HI0L/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="928" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-12-2-1024x928.png" alt="" class="wp-image-788" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-12-2-1024x928.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-12-2-300x272.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-12-2-768x696.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-12-2-1536x1392.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-12-2-2048x1856.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-12-2-640x580.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-12-2-960x870.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Project-12-2.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Scott Joplin &#8211; Maple Leaf Rag</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-scott-joplin-maple-leaf-rag/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 13:04:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=561</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Scott Joplin was a remarkable composer who was able to combine African musical influences with classical music from&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="key-takeaways" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1636018788468 wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Key takeaways </span>
	</span>
</h2>



<ul type="rich" class="wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio is-style-cnvs-list-styled-positive"><li>Scott Joplin was a remarkable composer who was able to combine African musical influences with classical music from Europe.</li><li>Syncopation adds variety and forward movement to music, making it feel faster even when the tempos aren&#8217;t.</li><li>The I-V progression is useful for conveying comfort and familiarity.</li></ul>



<p>When researching for black composers I came across Scott Joplin, whom, I must admit, I didn&#8217;t know much of his work. Although I had heard some ragtime music before, I was far from knowing what exactly makes a ragtime song and how important it was to modern popular music.</p>



<h4 id="joplins-history" class="wp-block-heading">Joplin&#8217;s History</h4>



<p>Scott Joplin was born in northeastern Texas in 1867 or 1868, one of the first generation of African Americans born after slavery was abolished. His father used to be a slave, but his mother was born free. Both of Scott&#8217;s parents were performers, and he and his siblings grew up surrounded by music, primarily African traditional music performed by slaves.</p>



<p>Scott&#8217;s mother recognized his interest in music and was able to find him a free music teacher in exchange for housework. Julius Weiss, a German immigrant who, according to other students, was a follower of the European musical heritage with a special fondness for opera, was his teacher. Scott Joplin&#8217;s music owed a great deal to this. A descendant of an African slaver was not supposed to get a formal education, much less musical education. However, it was because of Weiss that he was able to understand piano technique, music theory, and, most crucially, European musical knowledge such as opera (Berlin, nd.).</p>



<h4 id="the-role-of-joplin-in-rag-music" class="wp-block-heading">The role of Joplin in Rag music</h4>



<p>There is no doubt that Scott Joplin&#8217;s music took on the fresh feel it had because of the convergence of African and European music. He combined the syncopation of Afro-American folk music with the harmonization and marching tempos of 19th-century European romanticism to form the ultimate combination (Jasen &amp; Tichenor, 1989). As a result, this led him to ragtime.</p>



<p>According to Grove Music Online, ragtime is &#8220;a style of popular music that flourished from the mid-1890s to 1918. Its main identifying trait is its ragged—i.e., syncopated—rhythm&#8221; (Berlin, 2013).</p>



<p>Joplin was known for his rags, particularly Maple Leaf Rag. Although it was not the first rag to be published, it was one of the most influential compositions in establishing ragtime as the first African-American music style to be widely adopted, earning him the title of King of Ragtime.</p>



<p>The Maple Leaf Rag and many other Joplin&#8217;s rags are considered Classic Rags. By &#8220;classic&#8221; we consider that the rag has a structure that &#8220;has three or four sections, each featuring a different 16-measure musical theme, or melody. In turn, these equal sections are divided into four lines of four measures each. Once a theme is played through, it is generally repeated immediately; in certain cases, it reappears later in the piece.&#8221; (The Library of Congress, Classic Rag).</p>



<p>Maple Leaf Rag is a good example of a Classic Rag since it not only follows the usual AABBACCDD pattern, is in duple meter, and has significant syncopation in the melody, but it is also very well thought out. To perform this composition successfully, you&#8217;ll need a developed pianistic talent.</p>



<p>Scott&#8217;s publisher, John Stark, believed his publications were as good as best classical music, and he promoted his view in elaborate ads. &#8220;Why are the Stark Music Co&#8217;s Rags called Classic? This is the reason: They are intellectual musical thoughts grounded in the emotional principle of humanity.&#8221; <meta charset="utf-8"> (The Library of Congress, Classic Rag).</p>



<h4 id="my-listening-of-maple-leaf-rag" class="wp-block-heading">My listening of Maple Leaf Rag</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Scott Joplin: Maple Leaf Rag" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bCxLAr_bwpA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Ronchi, D., 2017. Scott Joplin: Maple Leaf Rag. <em>Youtube</em>. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bCxLAr_bwpA [Accessed November 4, 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>This composition drew my attention since Joplin defines the rhythm, speed, and atmosphere of the music from the first bar. He doesn&#8217;t build up any anticipation, and there aren&#8217;t many opportunities for both hands to rest. After playing this rag, I can image a pianist becoming really fatigued.</p>



<p>However, I believe that the absence of build-up, along with the melody&#8217;s powerful syncopation, results in a danceable and incredibly catchy music. At the same time, for individuals who are used to classical music and marches, the continuous simple bass progression (which is usually an I-V progression) provides a very familiar and comforting feel.</p>



<p>Philosophically, I believe the contrast between the syncopated melody and the structured bass reflects Joplin&#8217;s position in the artistic culture of the period. On the one hand, having been raised in an African musical background, he came from a culture where syncopated percussion beats are very prominent and where rhythm is vital to making people dance and interact with music. On the other hand, he was given formal classical training that allowed him to learn how the best European classical composers composed their works. The Maple Leaf Rag and others demonstrate that he learned from both cultures and passed them on to the composition.</p>



<p>You can clearly hear the syncopation and the I-V progression in Maple Leaf Rag&#8217;s first bars in the A section, where the bass line plays a steady rhythm, while the melody plays a syncopated rhythm. The syncopation is prominent in the song throughout.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="252" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled6-1024x252.png" alt="" class="wp-image-562" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled6-1024x252.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled6-300x74.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled6-768x189.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled6-1536x378.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled6-2048x504.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled6-640x158.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled6-960x236.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled6.png 2087w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Another key point to note is that, like previous classical composers, Joplin knew how to generate tension and release it. My past hearing of folk African music led me to believe that it was heavily reliant on repetition rather than dramatic moments. In bars 7-9, you can sense the tension building up.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="289" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled10-1024x289.png" alt="" class="wp-image-568" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled10-1024x289.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled10-300x85.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled10-768x217.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled10-1536x433.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled10-2048x578.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled10-640x181.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled10-960x271.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled10.png 2251w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>In the B section, Joplin inserts chromatism to give the music a fresh perspective and, in my opinion, to instill the composition with some of his musical understanding.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="291" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled9-1024x291.png" alt="" class="wp-image-567" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled9-1024x291.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled9-300x85.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled9-768x218.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled9-1536x436.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled9-2048x582.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled9-640x182.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled9-960x273.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled9.png 2087w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The modulation from Ab Major to Db Major at the beginning of the C section and back to Ab at the beginning of the D section, especially the last one, is done quite smoothly. Although the modulation to the subdominant is a common ragtime modulation, I feel Joplin handled it in a fluid manner to once again demonstrate his abilities.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="308" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled8-1-1024x308.png" alt="" class="wp-image-566" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled8-1-1024x308.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled8-1-300x90.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled8-1-768x231.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled8-1-1536x462.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled8-1-2048x616.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled8-1-640x192.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled8-1-960x289.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled8-1.png 2072w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Another aspect of this music that I found intriguing is the triumphal finale, which has a counter motion between the voices and a large chord that eventually allows the pianist to rest after demonstrating his abilities.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="291" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled7-1024x291.png" alt="" class="wp-image-564" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled7-1024x291.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled7-300x85.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled7-768x218.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled7-1536x436.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled7-2048x582.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled7-640x182.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled7-960x273.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/11/untitled7.png 2087w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Upon hearing Scott Joplin and reading about him, I concluded that he always fought for recognition. Despite the fact that Rags were not considered high-quality music, he had a formal musical education. I believe that confrontation is what caused his pieces to be considered so well-written, timeless, and a template for other styles that grew from it, including jazz.</p>



<p>After having studied both Joseph Bologne and Scott Joplin I find their similarities and differences very insightful. Both came from one musical background and were later exposed to another. But it did not impact them in the same way. The novelty and merge of cultures I was expecting, was more evident in Joplin&#8217;s music. My point is not that one is better or more relevant than the other. The two composers were inspirations and essential to composers who came after them. But when you think of music as an evolving landscape of different artistic viewpoints, I believe Joplin played a significant role in showing composers that you could mix them all and create beautiful pieces of music.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1636012819747 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Berlin, E.A., Scott Joplin: Brief Biographical Sketch. Edward A. Berlin. Available at: https://www.edwardaberlin.com/scott_joplin__brief_biographical_sketch___33423.htm [Accessed November 3, 2021].</p>



<p>Jasen, D.A. &amp; Tichenor, T.J., 1989. Rags and Ragtime: A musical history, New York: Dover.</p>



<p>Berlin, E.A., 2013. Ragtime. Grove Music Online. Available at: https://www-oxfordmusiconline-com.ucreative.idm.oclc.org/grovemusic/view/10.1093/gmo/9781561592630.001.0001/omo-9781561592630-e-1002252241. [Accessed November 3, 2021].</p>



<p>The Library of Congress, Classic Rag. The Library of Congress. Available at: https://www.loc.gov/item/ihas.200035813/ [Accessed November 4, 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Joseph Bologne, Chevalier de Saint-Georges &#8211; Violin Concerto No. 9 in G Major, Op. 8</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-joseph-bologne-chevalier-de-saint-georges-violin-concerto-no-9-in-g-major-op-8/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 04:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There are black composers who don&#8217;t get the attention they deserve, and Joseph Bologne is one of them&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="key-takeaways" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1632458688251 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Key takeaways </span>
	</span>
</h2>



<ul class="is-style-cnvs-list-styled-positive"><li>There are black composers who don&#8217;t get the attention they deserve, and Joseph Bologne is one of them</li><li><span style="font-size: var(--cnvs-list-styled-font-size); color: var(--cs-color-primary); font-family: var(--cs-font-base-family), sans-serif; font-style: var(--cs-font-base-style); font-weight: var(--cs-font-base-weight); letter-spacing: var(--cs-font-base-letter-spacing);">I couldn&#8217;t fiind an African inspired sound in his works, maybe because of his European education</span></li><li><span style="font-size: var(--cnvs-list-styled-font-size); color: var(--cs-color-primary); font-family: var(--cs-font-base-family), sans-serif; font-style: var(--cs-font-base-style); font-weight: var(--cs-font-base-weight); letter-spacing: var(--cs-font-base-letter-spacing);">I find descending notes pleasing, once again </span></li></ul>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Violin Concerto Op.8 No.2 in G Major by Joseph Bologne Le Chevalier de Saint-Georges:Classical Music" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eiLPZCUaHEA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>Badass Joseph Saint-Georges, 2020. <em>Violin Concerto Op.8 No.2 in G Major by Joseph Bologne Le Chevalier de Saint-Georges:Classical Music</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eiLPZCUaHEA> [Accessed 27 October 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>One thought occurred to me while I was searching for music to listen to. What is the reason for the scarcity of well-known African classical composers? I couldn&#8217;t think of one, and a quick Google search reveals that the first dozen names that come up are all white men. I recognize that my lack of knowledge stems primarily from my western culture, so I set out to find black composers, which I am glad I did.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="179" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-1024x179.png" alt="" class="wp-image-556" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-1024x179.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-300x52.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-768x134.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-1536x268.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-2048x357.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-640x112.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27-960x167.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-27-at-11.27.27.png 3028w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>One of the articles I read was from classicfm.com entitled <a href="https://www.classicfm.com/discover-music/black-composers-who-made-classical-music-history/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.classicfm.com/discover-music/black-composers-who-made-classical-music-history/" target="_blank">&#8220;9 Black composers who changed the course of classical music history&#8221;.</a> The first featured composer is Joseph Bologne, Chevalier de Saint-Georges.</p>



<p>Joseph Bologne was born to a wealthy plantation owner and his Senegalese slave mistress in Basse-Terre, Guadaloupe, in 1745. He received the best education his father could afford during the family&#8217;s move to France and grew into an exceptionally gifted student. He had professional training, as evidenced by his extensive work list, which includes a number of comedic operas, symphonies and concertos, as well as chamber works (Banat, 2001).</p>



<p>Despite his pejorative nickname of The Black Mozart (also known as The Other Mozart), I find myself wondering if it shouldn&#8217;t be the other way around. Joseph Bologne is regarded as one of the greatest composers of the 18th century, according to Marlon Daniel. He was known to frequent salons as a guest of the French nobility, including those of queen Marie Antoinette, who was an accomplished singer herself. He influenced Franz Joseph Haydn, François-Joseph Gossec, Carl Stamitz, and, most notably, Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, making him a leader rather than a follower of trends in the musical evolution of his century (Daniel, 2021).</p>



<p>His work was innovative since his earlier compositions, according to a New York Times article. &#8220;The six-string quartets of his Opus 1 were among the first in that genre to be written in France. His three sonatas for keyboard and violin (Op. 1a) feature those instruments as equals, breaking away from the Baroque tradition of basso continuo, which was still very much in vogue&#8221; (Balter, 2020).</p>



<p>Despite how innovative Bologne&#8217;s work may have sounded after listening to his violin concertos, my mind constantly tells me that he sounds a lot like some of his contemporaries. This, I believe, is a case of knowledge bias.</p>



<p>His Violin Concerto No. 9 in G Major, Op. 8 is one of my favourite works. I was struck by the three movements&#8217; energy and rhythm, as well as the motifs he created. I couldn&#8217;t find a free score for this piece, but they can easily compete with other well-known motifs, in my humble and naive opinion. Why hasn&#8217;t his music been used in an advertisement commercial?</p>



<p>The second movement, Largo, is one of my favourites. Despite the fact that it is a slower movement, I consider it to be a continuation of the first movement&#8217;s accentuated rhythm. The syncopation provides a solid sound of descending notes in the first minute, which I find pleasing. In fact, I find this movement to be quite contemporary. While listening to him, I noticed parallels with Nicolas Britell&#8217;s, in my opinion, amazing Succession Tv Show soundtrack, particularly the Adagio in C Minor I show below.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Spotify Embed: Adagio in C Minor" width="100%" height="80" style="[object Object]" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2hdBC9gUzlb0mpzDFOWv8n?si=ec602f74e4074406&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>In the end, I was thrilled about this discovery. I&#8217;m not qualified to say whether Joseph Bologne was a better composer than Mozart, but after hearing some of his works, I believe he deserves at least more credit.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1635310066343 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Banat, G., 2001. Saint-Georges [Saint-George], Joseph Bologne, Chevalier de.. [online] Oxford University Press. Available at: <a href="https://www-oxfordmusiconline-com.ucreative.idm.oclc.org/grovemusic/view/10.1093/gmo/9781561592630.001.0001/omo-9781561592630-e-0000024316">https://www-oxfordmusiconline-com.ucreative.idm.oclc.org/grovemusic/view/10.1093/gmo/9781561592630.001.0001/omo-9781561592630-e-0000024316</a> [Accessed 27 October 2021].</p>



<p>Daniel, M., 2021. THE MUSIC OF JOSEPH BOLOGNE CHEVALIER DE SAINT-GEORGES. [ebook] Tafelmusik. Available at: <a href="https://www.tafelmusik.org/downloads/Tafelmedia/joseph-bologne-digital-booklet.pdf">https://www.tafelmusik.org/downloads/Tafelmedia/joseph-bologne-digital-booklet.pdf</a> [Accessed 27 October 2021].</p>



<p>Balter, M., 2020. His Name Is Joseph Boulogne, Not ‘Black Mozart’. [online] Nytimes.com. Available at: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/22/arts/music/black-mozart-joseph-boulogne.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/22/arts/music/black-mozart-joseph-boulogne.html</a> [Accessed 27 October 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Beach Boys &#8211; God Only Knows</title>
		<link>./../../../../listening-to-beach-boys-god-only-knows/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 08:07:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=531</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Despite not being a huge fan of the Beach Boys, I&#8217;ve always enjoyed this song, mostly because it&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Despite not being a huge fan of the Beach Boys, I&#8217;ve always enjoyed this song, mostly because it doesn&#8217;t seem like a typical love song. But I&#8217;ve never given any thought to how this song&#8217;s melody and harmony were created.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote has-background has-white-background-color is-style-solid-color"><blockquote class="has-text-color has-black-color"><p>“I love God Only Knows and its bow to the baroque that goes all the way back to 1740 and J. S. Bach. It represents the whole tradition of liturgical music that I feel is a spiritual part of Brian’s music.&#8221; &#8211; Jimmy Webb<br></p><cite>Sullivan, 2013</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>I chose to explore this piece after reading this quote when researching Bach&#8217;s fugues.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="The Beach Boys: God Only Knows (Live At Unicef Concert - 1967)" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YTpzKDhdjms?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>God Only Knows is regarded as one of The Beach Boys&#8217; best songs and is adored by many musicians, including Paul McCartney who admitted this is one of his favourite songs. (Paul McCartney Comments, n.d.) Brian Wilson and Tony Asher wrote it for the Pet Sounds album with the goal of moving The Beach Boys away from a mainstream boyband sound and musically challenging the Beatles (Whatley, 2021). Paul McCartney later admitted that God Only Knows and the Pet Sounds inspired Sgt. Pepper&#8217;s Lonely Hearts Club Band. So this creative battle was won by all of us.</p>



<p>I believe the song&#8217;s theme is about the end of a relationship and the doubts that follow it. The hesitation in the opening lyrics &#8220;I may not always love you&#8221; distinguishes this song from other love songs. Throughout the lyrics and music, there is a sense of ambiguity, with a really weak tonal centre (Scott, 2019). As David Bennett&#8217;s video shows, the music modulates multiple times, and there are many reversed chords, so the sound never feels stable.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="4 Inventive Key Changes in Pop Music" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oQ81Sz38Acw?start=552&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption>David Bennett Piano, 2018.&nbsp;<em>4 Inventive Key Changes in Pop Music</em>.  Available at: &lt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oQ81Sz38Acw&amp;t=552s&gt; [Accessed 22 October 2021].</figcaption></figure>



<p>I read various analyses of this song, and while I think the music harmony is beautifully composed, I&#8217;m going to concentrate on melody and counterpoint because these concepts are covered in this section of the course.</p>



<p>The opposing motion between the vocal melody and the bass is the first fascinating melodic design I recognized. As I explained below, there&#8217;s a lively conversation going on between the two voices, with one going down and the other going up, and vice &#8211; versa. Even when they appear to be heading in the same direction, as in bar 3 of this example, they quickly diverge in bar 4. I believe this was written with the goal of drawing attention to the ambiguity and leaving the listener in the dark about what to expect.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="837" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled5-1-1024x837.png" alt="" class="wp-image-535" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled5-1-1024x837.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled5-1-300x245.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled5-1-768x628.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled5-1-1536x1256.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled5-1-2048x1675.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled5-1-640x523.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled5-1-960x785.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled5-1.png 2229w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Another section that sparked my curiosity was the bridge or brake, in which the keyboards and flute play a short instrumental passage that repeats the preceding opposite motion, but in a much more pronounced manner.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="175" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled3-1024x175.png" alt="" class="wp-image-533" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled3-1024x175.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled3-300x51.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled3-768x131.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled3-1536x262.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled3-2048x350.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled3-640x109.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled3-960x164.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled3.png 2190w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>This bridge introduces a three-voice counterpoint that I&#8217;ve always found fascinating. I did my best to transcribe as accurately as I could, so it&#8217;s not perfect, but it allowed me to understand how the three voices work together to form triads, and how they mostly move in thirds and sixth intervals.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="684" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled4-1024x684.png" alt="" class="wp-image-536" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled4-1024x684.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled4-300x201.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled4-768x513.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled4-1536x1027.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled4-2048x1369.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled4-640x428.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled4-960x642.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/untitled4.png 2078w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The music comes to a close with a round that I discussed in a previous entry.</p>



<p>Overall, I believe I enjoy this song more now that I am fully aware of the incredible labour that went into the melody and the blending of all voices. I see some parallels with Bach&#8217;s work, but I think I need to learn more about Bach&#8217;s music to really see how they might be related.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634889216649 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Sullivan, Steve. Encyclopedia of Great Popular Song Recordings, Scarecrow Press, 2013. ProQuest Ebook Central, http://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/ucreative-ebooks/detail.action?docID=1466981.</p>



<p>albumlinernotes. n.d. Paul McCartney Comments. [online] Available at: <a href="http://albumlinernotes.com/Paul_McCartney_Comments.html">http://albumlinernotes.com/Paul_McCartney_Comments.html</a> [Accessed 22 October 2021].</p>



<p>Whatley, J., 2021.&nbsp;<em>The Story Behind The Song: ‘God Only Knows’ by The Beach Boys, Brian Wilson’s ultimate love song</em>. [online] Far Out Magazine. Available at: https://faroutmagazine.co.uk/beach-boys-brian-wilson-god-only-knows-the-story-behind-the-song/ [Accessed 22 October 2021].</p>



<p>Scott, S., 2019.&nbsp;<em>The luxuriant mysteries of “God Only Knows” (Year of the Month) | The-Solute</em>. [online] The-solute.com. Available at: https://www.the-solute.com/the-luxuriant-mysteries-of-god-only-knows-year-of-the-month/ [Accessed 22 October 2021].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project 11 &#8211; Inventing free counterpoint</title>
		<link>./../../../../project-11-inventing-free-counterpoint/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 10:27:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 4 Exploring counterpoint]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../index.html?p=519</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[During this project, I had to practice composing counterpoints for two instruments. There were two parts to the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>During this project, I had to practice composing counterpoints for two instruments. There were two parts to the brief. With exercises 1 and 2, one of the instruments is already provided in the briefing, and the challenge is to compose a counterpoint for it. The task in exercises 3 and 4 is to compose two tunes with contrasting characters.</p>



<p>The workbook states that any tuning percussion instrument and woodwind instrument may be used. In order to get more familiar with tuned percussion, I decided to use them in all exercises.</p>



<p>You can download all Sibelius files <a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1RwWNerEX1QPvJzQT24C15wWg5U_f1dK6?usp=sharing" data-type="URL" data-id="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1RwWNerEX1QPvJzQT24C15wWg5U_f1dK6?usp=sharing" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" id="exercise-1">Exercise 1</h4>



<p>With this exercise, the top melody was provided and I was asked to compose the bottom melody. As I looked at the written melody for the first time, I noticed that it had long notes, mirims, and crochets, so I decided to use mostly quavers and semiquavers to have a nice rhythmic contrast. I also took advantage of the opportunity to contrast the dynamics, sometimes having the vibraphone play higher than the flute.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="329" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-1024x329.png" alt="" class="wp-image-521" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-1024x329.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-300x96.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-768x246.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-1536x493.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-2048x657.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-640x205.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1-960x308.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-1.png 2163w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" id="exercise-2">Exercise 2</h4>



<p>Here, the bottom part was given, and I composed the top melody. With the first three bars of my melody, I worked with the staccato from the flute by adding semiquavers, resulting in an interaction between the two instruments. In the next three bars, I made the marimba melody follow the descending flute melody, but with fast notes to emphasize the different melodies. The marimba contrasts with the flute in the last three bars by going up while the flute continues to go down.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="577" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-1024x577.png" alt="" class="wp-image-522" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-1024x577.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-300x169.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-768x433.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-1536x866.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-2048x1154.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-640x361.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2-960x541.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-2.png 2166w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" id="exercise-3">Exercise 3</h4>



<p>In the third exercise, I followed the workbook&#8217;s suggestion and started one melody later than the other, so the listener could more easily pick out the different voices. I developed a little theme that begins with the flute, then the tubular bells accompany it. Following this repetition, however, both melodies drift away. With a wave-shaped melody, the flute is more unstable, with a descending melody in bar 3 and an ascending melody until bar 5. In the meantime, the tubular bells are more stable, using almost always the same rhythm except for bar 7 when they take the opportunity of the calmer flute to express themselves.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="662" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-1024x662.png" alt="" class="wp-image-523" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-1024x662.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-300x194.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-768x497.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-1536x994.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-2048x1325.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-640x414.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3-960x621.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-3.png 2223w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" id="exercise-4">Exercise 4</h4>



<p>Similarly to the previous exercise, I tried to start one melody after another, while the instruments followed a similar theme. I could see how this theme could be used in different ways if it were a longer composition. Thus, for example, the xylophone plays two notes on the first part of the theme while the bassoon plays staccato over the same notes. However, after this repetition, the melodies go the opposite way. Generally, they move oppositely, except in the last bar when both move down and up to the final F.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="681" src="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-1024x681.png" alt="" class="wp-image-524" srcset="./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-1024x681.png 1024w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-300x199.png 300w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-768x511.png 768w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-1536x1021.png 1536w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-2048x1361.png 2048w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-640x425.png 640w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4-960x638.png 960w, ./../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Project-11-4.png 2222w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
