<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignments &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 11:30:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Revision of Assignment 3 after tutor feedback</title>
		<link>./../../../../../revision-of-assignment-3-after-tutor-feedback/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 10:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Round, descants, polyphony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=759</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My reviewed score can be accessed here. Although the tutor&#8217;s feedback was positive, he pointed out several issues,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>My reviewed score can be accessed <a href="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Assignment-3-Revision-Full-Score.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Assignment-3-Revision-Full-Score.pdf" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>



<p>Although the tutor&#8217;s feedback was positive, he pointed out several issues, the biggest of which was the heavyweight of the B and C sections, compared to the lightness and elegance of the A section. The suggestion was that I offer some of the lightness of the beginning in the next sections, so there would be a balance between all sections.</p>



<p>Despite my attempts to incorporate some of the qualities of the opening into the C section, I was not able to do it because every time I tried to change it, I felt that I was losing my sense of what this piece was.&nbsp;</p>



<p>However, most of the changes were made in section B. Particularly the creation of a two-part counterpoint between the oboe and bassoon.&nbsp;</p>



<p>I changed the key signature in the B section from C# to Db because, as the tutor pointed out, five flats are easier to read than seven sharps.</p>



<p>Because there were times when staccatos and repeated notes were under slurs, I reviewed them all. My tutor pointed out that this wasn&#8217;t modern standard notation.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As the tutor pointed out, the oboe and bassoon did not have any rests and the flute had very few rests. Throughout the piece, I added a few rests for all three instruments, without sacrificing the overall sonority I wanted. Other than the flute, which has a long rest in the middle section, I couldn&#8217;t find space for long rests on the other instruments.</p>



<p>It hadn&#8217;t occurred to me that the two first pages were denser than the rest, so I spread them out.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reflections on Assignment 3</title>
		<link>./../../../../../reflections-on-assignment-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 12:50:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Round, descants, polyphony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=510</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Moving from monophonic to polyphonic music, in my opinion, was a significant step forward in terms of both&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Moving from monophonic to polyphonic music, in my opinion, was a significant step forward in terms of both complexity and creativity.</p>



<p>I had the opportunity to write for three instruments in this assignment, which proved to be more difficult than I anticipated, especially considering I had to write separate melodies for each of them. I can now better appreciate how great composers like Bach were able to compose in masterful harmony when they used 4 or more voices.</p>



<p>My hearing and analysis of rounds, descants, and, especially, polyphony, I believe, aided me in better understanding how voices might be written in harmony but with differing melodies.</p>



<h3 id="about-assignment-3">About Assignment 3</h3>



<p>As I previously stated, I found this task to be far more challenging than the prior two. Considering three instruments, each with their distinct melodies and &#8220;personalities,&#8221; brought a level of difficulty I hadn&#8217;t anticipated. However, I believe that this additional complexity will be advantageous in the long run as assignment tasks become longer and include more instruments.</p>



<p>In terms of notation, I made an effort to avoid some of the faults I made in earlier assignments, such as rhythmic spelling, correct beaming, and phrasing.</p>



<p>My ability to construct a two-minute composition and transpose the concepts I had in my head to a score surprised me. I wanted to compose a piece that put polyphony to work for the music rather than the other way around. The repeated theme and various small melodies throughout the music, I believe, made this polyphonic composition both familiar and fresh at the same time.</p>



<p>Being self-critical, I think this piece contains too many elements. As a result, I feel that I could turn this into a 4-minute musical piece that develops some of the ideas I wanted to include.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 3</title>
		<link>./../../../../../assignment-3/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Composing Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 3 Round, descants, polyphony]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=467</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[My third task was to compose a work for three woodwind instruments in a mostly polyphonic approach. This&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>My third task was to compose a work for three woodwind instruments in a mostly polyphonic approach. This composition should last about two minutes and follow a predetermined structure (seen below), in which one begins with a triad, moves to another, and concludes with another.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img width="1024" height="358" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-1024x358.png" alt="" class="wp-image-473" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-1024x358.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-300x105.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-768x268.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-640x224.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47-960x336.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Screenshot-2021-10-04-at-14.36.47.png 1190w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>You can find the final score <a href="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V2-Full-Score.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V2-Full-Score.pdf" target="_blank">here</a> and listen to it below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V2.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p><meta charset="utf-8">I had few questions after seeing example 45. Should the first triad last several bars? (If that&#8217;s the case, I&#8217;ll have to use different chords in the meanwhile, or it&#8217;ll sound stuck). Or is the example intended to be regarded as a chord progression that should be used throughout the piece?</p>



<p>My tutor assisted me with these questions by directing me to consider these triads as harmonic centres for the music.</p>



<p>With this in mind, I decided to use three triads, each representing a different essence of the music, resulting in a piece of music with three parts.</p>



<h2 id="the-idea-theme" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108541003 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Idea / Theme</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>After reflecting on my polyphonic studies, I came up with the idea for this composition. I listened to polyphonic music in three different styles: Renaissance, Baroque, and African/Polynesian polyphony. Because the assignment&#8217;s predetermined structure required three triads, I challenged myself to write a piece of music in three parts, each inspired by a different style of polyphonic music.</p>



<p>About the theme, this piece will be about a love triangle involving three instruments. After meeting and dancing in an African<meta charset="utf-8">/Polynesian section, they progressed to the baroque section, where they fell in love, then finalized the dance with a passionate and harmonious section (Renaissance), showcasing their love for one another.</p>



<h2 id="the-structure" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108659753 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Structure</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The structure was mostly determined upon the development of the idea. This would be a straightforward story in which A leads to B, which leads to C. I wanted the music to begin rhythmically as if the instruments were dancing together and each had its own individuality. Then, in a more melodic section, the instruments repeat the motif as though they discover something in common and fall in love. Ending in harmony and love, each instrument repeats the same motif but then each plays its own melodic line while respecting the harmony of the others.</p>



<p>I decided to produce a piece in the key of C# major after studying pentatonic scales. The other triads and keys were chosen based on the least amount of note change between them.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-regular cnvs-block-core-table-1628498574118"><table><thead><tr><th>Theme</th><th>Section &amp; Triad</th><th>Duration / Tempo</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>The instruments meet and dance together, each with its own personality</td><td>A &#8211; B major</td><td><meta charset="utf-8">~30 seconds at 110 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They fall in love, repeating the same motif</td><td>B &#8211; C# major</td><td><meta charset="utf-8">~30 seconds at 70 bpm </td></tr><tr><td>They live happily ever after, each with their own motif but harmonically</td><td>C &#8211; Ab major</td><td>~60 seconds at 70 bpm</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 id="the-motifs" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634108877461 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Motifs</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>As I had done with prior projects and assignments, I began playing around with the piano, hoping to find a theme that sounded good to me and would serve as a catapult for this composition. After a time, I came upon a motif that I really loved and decided to go a little deeper into it.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="75" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-1024x75.png" alt="" class="wp-image-480" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-1024x75.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-300x22.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-768x57.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-1536x113.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-2048x151.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-640x47.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5-960x71.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-5.png 2171w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Because the song is divided into three distinct sections, I thought it would be fascinating if the same motif appeared in each section, but was played differently and by different instruments. This way, something would connect all three pieces.</p>



<p>This motif is performed subtly in semiquavers in the A section by the oboe.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="238" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-1024x238.png" alt="" class="wp-image-476" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-1024x238.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-300x70.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-768x178.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-1536x356.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-2048x475.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-640x149.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1-960x223.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-1.png 2172w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The B section is played more explicitly and with quavers by the flute.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="100" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-1024x100.png" alt="" class="wp-image-478" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-1024x100.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-300x29.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-768x75.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-1536x151.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-2048x201.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-640x63.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3-960x94.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-3.png 2171w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The motif is performed by the bassoon nearly in the background with crochets in the C section.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="64" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-1024x64.png" alt="" class="wp-image-479" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-1024x64.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-300x19.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-768x48.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-1536x96.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-2048x127.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-640x40.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4-960x60.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-4.png 2171w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>This division was quite helpful in enabling me to start writing each section quicker.</p>



<h2 id="the-instruments" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110169912 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The Instruments</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Flute, oboe, and bassoon were my natural choices for a woodwind trio. I chose these three instruments because I believe they complement each other in terms of timbre while remaining distinct enough for the listener to hear each one&#8217;s melody.</p>



<p>I listened to three pieces to gain a sense of how a trio of woodwinds works together and how other composers used these instruments.</p>



<p>One of the first instances I found of the three I selected to work with was Antonio Vivaldi&#8217;s Concerto for Flute, Oboe, and Bassoon in G Minor, RV 103. This composition didn&#8217;t particularly appeal to me, but it did teach me how much prominence the flute can have at times, as well as how the oboe and flute can sound good together without clashing, with the flute in a high register and the oboe in a middle and low register.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Antonio Vivaldi - Concerto for Flute, Oboe, and Bassoon in G Minor, RV 103" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cMptoH6bo-I?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>The Trio for Flute, Oboe, and Bassoon, Op. 86 by Röntgen was an excellent illustration of what I was attempting. Each instrument&#8217;s identity is respected alongside the melody, yet they also repeat each other. This adds a lot of depth to the music.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Röntgen - Trio for Flute, Oboe and Bassoon, Op. 86" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/9ke2oCFJatM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Pastorale for Wind Trio, Op. 147 by Darius Milhaud omits the flute but includes the clarinet. I was especially inspired by how wonderfully polyphony worked beginning in bar 24.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Darius Milhaud - Pastorale for Wind Trio, Op. 147 (1935) [Score-Video]" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TMctPXaihD8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<h2 id="the-composition" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1634110414281 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>The composition</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p><meta charset="utf-8"><strong>Section A</strong> Bars 1-9</p>



<p>I intended to portray more rhythmic and fast-paced music in this section. As a result, I employed semiquavers in all three instruments and staccato most of the time.</p>



<p>This section is in the key of B major, although it begins with a D#m triad. The B major triad is present in the second beat of the first bar to create the home triad.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="376" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-1024x376.png" alt="" class="wp-image-481" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-1024x376.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-300x110.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-768x282.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-1536x564.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-2048x752.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-640x235.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23-960x352.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V23.png 2218w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The oboe and flute begin by playing nearly the identical melody with a 3rd, 5th, or 6th interval, but at bar 4 the flute begins to move from a quick staccato to a slower legato. Meanwhile, the bassoon plays a more danceable melody.</p>



<p>This section has the most triad changes, with the majority being B major, D# minor, F# major and G# minor.</p>



<p>This section ends with a VI &#8211; I, reintroducing the home triad and leading to the next triad.</p>



<p><strong>Section B</strong> Bars 10-20</p>



<p>The music here shifts to a more elaborate yet slower paced approach. The speed is reduced to 70 quaver beats per minute, and the notes are predominantly quavers. In bar 11, the flute plainly states that the key signature has changed to C# major.</p>



<p>The home triad, like the first section, is played right at the start to express the feeling of the new home triad. This time, I stuck with the home triad for a little longer than in&nbsp;the first section, with inversions of the triad lasting two bars and the primary motif repeated by the three instruments.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="360" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-1024x360.png" alt="" class="wp-image-483" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-1024x360.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-300x106.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-768x270.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-1536x540.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-2048x720.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-640x225.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6-960x338.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-6.png 2218w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>In contrast to the preceding section, this one contains a clearly defined chord progression: I &#8211; IV &#8211; iii &#8211; V.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="771" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-1024x771.png" alt="" class="wp-image-484" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-1024x771.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-300x226.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-768x578.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-1536x1156.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-2048x1541.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-640x482.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7-960x722.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V22-7.png 2222w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>It ends with an I &#8211; IV, which leads to the next triad, that is expected to be the V: G# major.</p>



<p><strong>Section C</strong> Bars 21-40</p>



<p>Despite the fact that the tempo remains constant, I wanted the music to feel slower and more harmonized. As a result, I utilized a lot of crochets, minims, and semibreves.</p>



<p>This section is in the key of Ab major. I wanted it to be in G# major scale, but I learned that G# major isn&#8217;t commonly used because it&#8217;s too complex for practical use, and that Ab major is a better option.</p>



<p>In contrast to the other sections, I do not explicitly tell the listener of the key change. Though I begin with the Ab major triad, it isn&#8217;t until the third beat of the second bar of this section (bar 22) that I reach an Ab major triad.</p>



<p>In the final part of this section I wanted to express pure polyphony, with each instrument adding their own melody one at a time, culminating with all three instruments playing distinct melodies until they rise to end in Ab major triad.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Assignment-3-V2.mp3" length="2567231" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
