<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignments &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 13:50:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Exercise &#8211; Exploring contemporary classical composition &#8211; Revision after tutor&#8217;s feedback</title>
		<link>./../../../../../exercise-exploring-contemporary-classical-composition-revision-after-tutors-feedback/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 20:29:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=2008</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To improve my essay, the tutor pointed out that I should try and eliminate unqualified, unsupported, positive descriptors&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="tutors-feedback" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1713212956369 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-4 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Tutor&#8217;s feedback</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>To improve my essay, the tutor pointed out that I should try and eliminate unqualified, unsupported, positive descriptors from my essay writing. Also, I should support some of my personal opinions with analysis and evidence. Therefore I made some changes to reflect this feedback.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="essay" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1713212983666 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>Essay</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Magnus Lindberg (1958, Helsinki) burst onto the global contemporary music scene in the early 80s, blending different styles, from total serialism to rock. He joined Sibelius Academy at 15, studying under Paavo Heininen, who fuelled his interest in European trends. He co-founded Korvat auki (1977) and later founded Toimii Ensemble (1980) which became the birthplace of his compositional experiments.</p>



<p>The essay aims to examine the evolution of Lindberg’s compositional style over two decades, during which, according to Mellor (2016), Lindberg transitioned from a modernist to a &#8220;mellow composer,&#8221; creating orchestral pieces that incorporate hints of Romanticism. </p>



<p>After his studies, he travelled to Paris and Berlin, where he discovered punk rock and specifically the German metal band Einstürzende Neubauten. This exposure changed his musical style, turning him into an &#8220;angry modernist,&#8221; (Mellor, 2016). This could be perceived in <em>Kraft</em> (1985), written for orchestra, electronics, and junkyard percussion. I understood why it is considered such a powerful piece when I heard it. It astonishes the listener with its aggressive changes in dynamics. As Service (2013) notes in his article, I also drew a parallel between Stravinsky&#8217;s Rite of Spring and Lindberg&#8217;s Kraft. However, Lindberg pushed the boundaries of instrumentation and aggression even further using unconventional percussion instruments. </p>



<p>In 1994, he composed <em>Aura</em>, a symphony in four movements for a large orchestra. As I listened to each part, I noticed that it sounded closer to <em>Rite of Spring</em> rather than moving further away in terms of rhythmic exploration and instrumentation innovation. I even recognised a hint of the famous <em>Rite of Spring</em> rhythm around the ninth minute of the first movement in the recording by the Finnish Radio Symphony Orchestra. On the whole, there is a sense of clarity, balance, and harmony that contrasts with <em>Kraft</em>. If I had to guess how Lindberg&#8217;s use of instrumentation would evolve ten years after <em>Kraft</em>, I would have imagined a greater emphasis on electronic elements rather than acoustic ones. This surprise increased my admiration for <em>Aura</em>.</p>



<p>In 2002, he composed the <em>Clarinet Concerto</em>, which garnered positive reviews from the critics I read. It is his most popular piece on Spotify. And I can see why. Compared to the previous two compositions, this piece felt more approachable, melodious, and well-structured. The instrumentation has a more traditional quality. It felt like a refined version of <em>Aura</em>. According to Clemments (2005), this single-movement work is sprinkled with allusions to other composers. Although I may not possess the musical knowledge to identify them, I was able to recognise the reference to Gershwin&#8217;s <em>Rhapsody in Blue</em>. That was my favourite part of this piece.</p>



<p>Overall, I was delighted to meet Magnus Lindberg. One thing that stood out in the compositions I listened to was his ability to combine tension/release. His music slowly builds up suspense, and then it bursts forth with pure force. However, the main takeaway from this research is how it demonstrates that artists can evolve and freely change their sound without being tied to a specific style. It reminded me of an interview with the Spanish musician Rosalía where she says that she couldn&#8217;t do two similar albums because she desires to showcase her diverse emotions across different moments in time. It&#8217;s a great definition of artistic evolution.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1688248461088 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Clements, A. (2005) “Lindberg: Clarinet Concerto; Gran Duo; Chorale, Kriikku/Finnish Radio SO/ Oramo,” <em>The Guardian</em>, 9 September. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/2005/sep/09/classicalmusicandopera.shopping3 (Accessed: July 1, 2023).</p>



<p>Howell, T. (2014) “Magnus Lindberg: Narratives of Time and Space,” <em>Contemporary Music Review</em> [Preprint]. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1080/07494467.2014.977025.</p>



<p>Mellor, A, (2016). &#8220;Magnus Lindberg: the influential Finnish composer&#8217;s creative output continues to resist easy categorization.&#8221; <em>Gramophone</em>, vol. 93, no. 1131, pp. 72+. <em>Gale General OneFile</em>, link.gale.com/apps/doc/A444655727/ITOF?u=ucca&amp;sid=bookmark-ITOF&amp;xid=0b404893. (Accessed: July 1, 2023).</p>



<p>Richey, J. (1999). &#8220;Review of&nbsp;<em>Compositeurs d’aujourd’hui: Magnus Lindberg</em>, by M. Lindberg&#8221; <em>Computer Music Journal</em>, vol. 23, no. 3, pp. 111–12. <em>JSTOR</em>, http://www.jstor.org/stable/3681247 (Accessed: July 1, 2023).</p>



<p>Tom Service (2013) “A guide to Magnus Lindberg’s music,” <em>The Guardian</em>, 16 April. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/music/musicblog/2013/apr/16/contemporary-music-guide-magnus-lindberg (Accessed: July 1, 2023).</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assignment 1 &#8211; Reflective account</title>
		<link>./../../../../../1624-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 21:54:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1624</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This course unit was quite challenging, especially since I decided to take on a full-time job alongside my&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This course unit was quite challenging, especially since I decided to take on a full-time job alongside my studies. Balancing a full-time job, being a parent, and studying part-time has been quite demanding. As a result, my reflection centres around my perception that I wasn&#8217;t able to go as deeply into the subjects as I would have liked.</p>



<p>I found the first two projects to be incredibly valuable. They kickstarted my reflection on various aspects of music, such as its nature, what constitutes good music, and the differences between popular and classical music. This led me to question many of my preconceived notions.</p>



<p>One thing that pleasantly surprised me in this unit was the diverse range of music I was exposed to. From movie soundtracks to Indian music and contemporary styles I hadn&#8217;t encountered before, it expanded my musical horizons. Since my musical background was one of my main challenges, this exposure was truly beneficial. In hindsight, I think it would have been great to take this course as my first.</p>



<p>But, looking back, I wish I had spent more time on each subject. For example, I had a strong affinity for holy minimalist composers, and I would have loved to explore them further. On the other hand, microtonality and spectralism were not as enjoyable for me. I believe that with more time and study, I might have come to understand and appreciate what these composers are trying to convey.</p>



<p>The projects that focused on the Batman soundtrack and researching Magnus Lindberg were the ones I dedicated the most time to. Perhaps that&#8217;s why I found them particularly rewarding. Both projects allowed me to exercise a skill I had developed in the Stylistic Techniques course: writing about music. In both cases, I aimed to bring my own perspective to the table, going beyond regurgitating information readily available online. I hope I succeeded in conveying my own viewpoint while grounding it in factual information.</p>



<p>When I consider the overall content of the unit, I realize that some projects, such as those on orchestral instruments and music notation, had already been covered in other courses. If this had been my first course, those projects would have been perfect. However, since I had already delved into those topics before, I chose to skip them and dedicate more time to other projects.</p>



<p>Ultimately, I see progression in my studies, particularly in the broadening of my &#8220;musical baggage&#8221;. As for my writing skills, I have discovered that I find reflective texts much easier to write than &#8220;listening&#8221; ones. The most important lesson I have learned thus far is the need to improve my listening skills. I want to write about my experiences with music in a way that is clear, accurate, and captures everything that makes the music special to me.</p>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
