<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignments &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 22:38:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Assignment 1 &#8211; Reflective account</title>
		<link>./../../../../../1624-2/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 21:54:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 1 Music Today]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1624</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This course unit was quite challenging, especially since I decided to take on a full-time job alongside my&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This course unit was quite challenging, especially since I decided to take on a full-time job alongside my studies. Balancing a full-time job, being a parent, and studying part-time has been quite demanding. As a result, my reflection centres around my perception that I wasn&#8217;t able to go as deeply into the subjects as I would have liked.</p>



<p>I found the first two projects to be incredibly valuable. They kickstarted my reflection on various aspects of music, such as its nature, what constitutes good music, and the differences between popular and classical music. This led me to question many of my preconceived notions.</p>



<p>One thing that pleasantly surprised me in this unit was the diverse range of music I was exposed to. From movie soundtracks to Indian music and contemporary styles I hadn&#8217;t encountered before, it expanded my musical horizons. Since my musical background was one of my main challenges, this exposure was truly beneficial. In hindsight, I think it would have been great to take this course as my first.</p>



<p>But, looking back, I wish I had spent more time on each subject. For example, I had a strong affinity for holy minimalist composers, and I would have loved to explore them further. On the other hand, microtonality and spectralism were not as enjoyable for me. I believe that with more time and study, I might have come to understand and appreciate what these composers are trying to convey.</p>



<p>The projects that focused on the Batman soundtrack and researching Magnus Lindberg were the ones I dedicated the most time to. Perhaps that&#8217;s why I found them particularly rewarding. Both projects allowed me to exercise a skill I had developed in the Stylistic Techniques course: writing about music. In both cases, I aimed to bring my own perspective to the table, going beyond regurgitating information readily available online. I hope I succeeded in conveying my own viewpoint while grounding it in factual information.</p>



<p>When I consider the overall content of the unit, I realize that some projects, such as those on orchestral instruments and music notation, had already been covered in other courses. If this had been my first course, those projects would have been perfect. However, since I had already delved into those topics before, I chose to skip them and dedicate more time to other projects.</p>



<p>Ultimately, I see progression in my studies, particularly in the broadening of my &#8220;musical baggage&#8221;. As for my writing skills, I have discovered that I find reflective texts much easier to write than &#8220;listening&#8221; ones. The most important lesson I have learned thus far is the need to improve my listening skills. I want to write about my experiences with music in a way that is clear, accurate, and captures everything that makes the music special to me.</p>



<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
