<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 21:46:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Sabrina Carpenter &#8211; Please Please Please</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-sabrina-carpenter-please-please-please/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 22:15:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Introduction to Orchestration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=416</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Even though this isn&#8217;t the type of music I usually listen to, I found myself really enjoying it. The song feels like a modern take on an older style, kind of like taking a vintage...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Even though this isn&#8217;t the type of music I usually listen to, I found myself really enjoying it. The song feels like a modern take on an older style, kind of like taking a vintage outfit and giving it a fresh, trendy update.<br></p>



<p>The song is packed with classic 80s sounds: synthesisers, distinctive drums, a soft electric guitar, and a bouncy bass line.</p>



<p>Carpenter&#8217;s voice stands out immediately &#8211; she sings in a very high pitch that instantly brings to mind Dolly Parton. The interplay between Carpenter&#8217;s high, strident vocal timbre and the lush synth background, contrasted against the robust bass and drum elements, creates a sonically engaging experience.</p>



<p>What makes this song really interesting is its harmonic suprises. The chromatic chords, F# Major and C# Major, show a level of musical complexity not often heard in mainstream pop. A particularly notable moment is the modulation to C Major, which adds an unexpected and refreshing harmonic twist.<br></p>



<p>Dynamicly, the song follows a typical pop music pattern &#8211; it starts soft and builds up during the chorus, maintaining a consistent energy throughout.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"></h2>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Tom Waits &#8211; Tango Till They&#8217;re Sore</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-tom-waits-tango-till-theyre-sore/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2024 10:50:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Introduction to Orchestration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=421</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As a listener not typically drawn to Tom Waits&#8217; music but I found that this music feels like an improvisational moment &#8211; as if the recording were made spontaneously in an old bar. The performance...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As a listener not typically drawn to Tom Waits&#8217; music but I found that this music feels like an improvisational moment &#8211; as if the recording were made spontaneously in an old bar. The performance feels very authentic and not overproduced.</p>



<p>The instrumentation is immediately interesting, centered around an old, out-of-tune piano that serves as the foundational element of the piece. This imperfect piano is complemented by a bass, trumpet.</p>



<p>Harmonically, the piece follows a relatively traditional i-iv-V-i progression, providing a familiar structural backbone. However, they introduce intrigue through the vocal melody, which occasionally explores higher vocal registers. This subtle musical tension adds depth to the seemingly straightforward harmonic structure.</p>



<p>The most compelling aspect of the performance lies in its dynamic and timbral qualities. Waits&#8217; vocal delivery is dramatically dynamic, shifting between different intensities and characters. These variations convey the persona of an unstable, potentially drunk performer, bringing a theatrical quality to the music. The timbre is equally surprising &#8211; the sharp, out-of-tune piano finds a perfect companion in Waits&#8217; rough, sometimes off-key voice. This is contrasted by the more straightforward bass and the melodic trumpet.<br><br></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Dmitri Shostakovich &#8211; Festive Overture op. 96</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-dmitri-shostakovich-festive-overture-op-96/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 22:43:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=419</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I really enjoyed this piece. It feels like a musical parade &#8211; marching, bold, and definitely festive. The extended final cadence is my favourite part. It&#8217;s almost like Shostakovich is having a bit of fun,...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I really enjoyed this piece. It feels like a musical parade &#8211; marching, bold, and definitely festive. The extended final cadence is my favourite part. It&#8217;s almost like Shostakovich is having a bit of fun, stretching out the celebration just a little longer than you&#8217;d expect.</p>



<p>Right from the start, the music grabs the attention with a bold brass fanfare that sounds almost like a military celebration. The sound shifts constantly, with different instrument groups taking turns. At times, the delicate woodwinds cut through the heavy brass, creating interesting moments of contrast. When all the instruments play together, the sound becomes powerful and full.</p>



<p>In terms of timber the brass section maintains a strong, penetrating quality, while the woodwinds provide high, punctuating tones. The strings show versatility, moving from delicate passages when paired with woodwinds to powerful reinforcement when joining the full orchestral texture.</p>



<p>This piece doesn&#8217;t have a single, easy-to-follow melody. Instead, it&#8217;s filled with musical fragments &#8211; quick runs in the strings, bursts of sound from the brass, and rhythmic patterns that keep you listening. The harmony is pretty straightforward, but Shostakovich throws in a surprise at the end with an extended final section that almost feels like a musical joke, stretching out the ending for nearly two minutes.</p>



<p>The dynamic range of the piece is loud, with most sections performed above forte. This consistent high-energy approach reinforces the work&#8217;s festivity, with rare moments of piano dynamics.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
