<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Uncategorized &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 21:11:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Exercise Considering chance and serial music</title>
		<link>./../../../exercise-considering-chance-and-serial-music/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 21:11:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[From Present to Past]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 2 Twentieth-century Music]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=1679</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sonatas and interludes for Prepared Piano &#8211; This piece has a strong focus on rhythm. The prepared piano,&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Sonatas and interludes for Prepared Piano &#8211; This piece has a strong focus on rhythm. The prepared piano, with objects placed on and between strings, creates an unconventional timbre. Yet within this unique soundworld, Cage constructs an organized and cohesive musical work. I heard some resemblance to Javanese Gamelan music and some parts reminded me of the Rite of Spring.</p>



<p>Imaginary Landscape No. 4 &#8211; Cage&#8217;s first piece of chance music. By tuning radios to different frequencies, chance collages of sounds, speech and music emerge. The juxtaposition of these fragments is unpredictable but often intriguing. It&#8217;s music created by randomness rather than conscious design. Though it abandons traditional musical elements, it has a sense of playfulness and spontaneity that I find amusing.</p>



<p>Roaratorio, an Irish circus on Finnegans Wake &#8211; I found it really hard to enjoy this long composition. Combines field recordings, spoken word, and segments of Irish traditional music into a sound collage. The complex overlays create textures and rhythms. </p>



<p>Regarding serial and chance music, both approaches challenge conventional tonality and require an open mind from the listener. Cage demonstrates that music can emerge from unconventional sound sources, chance procedures and found objects. He accomplished to expand the conceptions of music, art and listening.</p>



<p>The serialist pieces have a very ordered, logical structure that comes through clearly in the listening. The rigid rules of serialism &#8211; avoiding repetition, and ordered rotations through the 12 tones &#8211; result in cerebral, mathematical music.</p>



<p>In contrast, Cage&#8217;s chance music lacks that calculated complexity. The randomness and unpredictability create a more chaotic, spontaneous feel. While the serialist process is evident to the listener, Cage&#8217;s process is opaque. We cannot directly hear compositional systems, but I find this obscure and surprising thought interesting.</p>



<p>I  still believe that my definition of music is still valid in this discussion. While the composer organizes sounds and applies musical techniques, the real art happens in the listener&#8217;s mind. As Cage showed, music can emerge from non-traditional sounds when the listener lends them meaning. My definition recognizes how the listener&#8217;s role gives life and validity to music. Without the listener&#8217;s act of listening, there is no music.</p>



<p>Cage&#8217;s chance pieces may not convey traditional emotional arcs, but they can evoke moods like dissatisfaction, serendipity, and even humour. Serialist works induce intellectual stimulation more than direct emotion. But even in this case, a listener need not comprehend the serial process to be affected by the music&#8217;s dramatic quality.</p>



<p>So while the compositional approach shapes aesthetic effect, I believe music can deliver emotional impact being it systematically composed or leaving it to chance. The listener&#8217;s subjective experience remains central to lending music it meaning.</p>



<p>While the compositional approach undoubtedly shapes the aesthetic effect, I believe music retains the power to deliver emotional impact whether coming from a serialist complexity or Cage&#8217;s randomness. Ultimately, the listener&#8217;s subjective experience remains central to lending music its meaning.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
