<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Coursework &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 22:13:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Exercise 3: Transcription for Solo Strings</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../exercise-3-transcription-for-solo-strings/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 22:13:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Introduction to Orchestration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=402</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Lilium (Elfen Lied) for Cello Homeward Bound for Violin]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Lilium (Elfen Lied) for Cello</strong></h1>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="2116" height="2951" src="./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-1-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-405" srcset="./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-1-1.png 2116w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-1-1-215x300.png 215w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-1-1-734x1024.png 734w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-1-1-768x1071.png 768w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-1-1-1101x1536.png 1101w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-1-1-1469x2048.png 1469w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-1-1-700x976.png 700w" sizes="(max-width: 2116px) 100vw, 2116px" /></figure>



<p></p>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Homeward Bound for Violin</strong></h1>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" width="2113" height="2956" src="./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-2-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-406" srcset="./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-2-1.png 2113w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-2-1-214x300.png 214w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-2-1-732x1024.png 732w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-2-1-768x1074.png 768w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-2-1-1098x1536.png 1098w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-2-1-1464x2048.png 1464w, ./../../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2024/12/Exercise-3-Transcription-for-Solo-Strings-2-1-700x979.png 700w" sizes="(max-width: 2113px) 100vw, 2113px" /></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 2: Aroura</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../exercise-2-aroura/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2024 22:32:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Introduction to Orchestration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=400</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Extended Techniques: Xenakis uses extended string techniques to create dramatic contrasts and rich, layered sounds. For example, chaotic glissandi produce a swirling sound, while sul ponticello adds a sharp, metallic tone. There&#8217;s a sense that...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Extended Techniques:</h3>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Glissandi</strong>:
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Both chaotic and coordinated glissandi structures. Chaotic glissandi produce a gritty effect, while coordinated movements suggest structured progression, such as ascending or descending lines​.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Sul Ponticello</strong>:
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Creates a harsher, more metallic sound. This technique contributes to the noisy texture characteristic of certain sections.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Harmonics</strong>:
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Creates ethereal and high-pitched sounds​.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Tremolo</strong>:
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Creates textural density and timbral variation.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Pizzicato</strong>:
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Adds rhythmic and tonal variation​.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li><strong>Col Legno</strong>:
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Creates a percussive effect.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>



<p></p>



<p>Xenakis uses extended string techniques to create dramatic contrasts and rich, layered sounds. For example, chaotic glissandi produce a swirling sound, while sul ponticello adds a sharp, metallic tone. There&#8217;s a sense that he blends these techniques to guide the piece from order to chaos and back.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Task 1: Pictures at an Exhibition</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../research-task-1-pictures-at-an-exhibition/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 22:19:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Introduction to Orchestration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the piano version, Mussorgsky uses abrupt dynamic contrasts to convey the grotesque, lurching character of the gnome. This contrasts and rapid chromatic lines create tension. Ravel’s orchestration addresses this by expanding the instrumentation and...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the piano version, Mussorgsky uses abrupt dynamic contrasts to convey the grotesque, lurching character of the gnome. This contrasts and rapid chromatic lines create tension. Ravel’s orchestration addresses this by expanding the instrumentation and using the full range of the orchestra to heighten the drama and grotesque qualities of the gnome’s depiction.</p>



<p>He assigns the initial stumbly melody to the woodwinds, particularly the bassoon and clarinet, whose dark, reedy tones amplify the grotesque mood. But the softer melody is assigned to the flute and oboe. The strings, playing the glissando phrases, mimic the gnome’s jerky, irregular movements, while the brass and low percussion provide a lot of weight. This layering of timbres, impossible to achieve with a solo piano, creates a vivid and immersive soundscape.</p>



<p>Another transformation lies in doubling and layering lines across multiple instruments. Ravel distributes these lines among the orchestra, creating a dialogue between instruments that adds different textures and complexity. The addition of bass instruments like the tuba and contrabassoon gives the piece a more grounded, ominous foundation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exercise 1: Getting a Sense of the Possibilities</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../exercise-1-getting-a-sense-of-the-possibilities/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 22:35:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orchestration Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 2: Introduction to Orchestration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=388</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Claude Vivier &#8211; Lonely Child Overall there&#8217;s haunting sound. The soprano blends with the clarinet, horns, and strings, while the Japanese brass Rin remains constant, adding a bell-like resonance. Percussion instruments like the gong and...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Claude Vivier &#8211; Lonely Child </h2>



<p>Overall there&#8217;s haunting sound. The soprano blends with the clarinet, horns, and strings, while the Japanese brass Rin remains constant, adding a bell-like resonance. Percussion instruments like the gong and bass drum deliver sudden, shocking moments that increase the tension.</p>



<p>The texture shifts dramatically, with sudden transitions from sparse sounds to dense orchestration, sometimes followed by silence that provides a brief sense of relief. The soprano’s melody is doubled by the strings, horns and clarinet, while dissonant harmonies maintain tension without resolution. Techniques like glissandos and harmonics in the strings add an unstable quality to the sound.</p>



<p>Dynamic changes are sharp and surprising, often highlighted by percussion. The soprano uses tremolo and rolled Rs, adding to the unsettling atmosphere. The use of tubular chimes and woods creates a church-like tone, enhancing the dark, cohesive timbre that defines the piece.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Arvo Pärt &#8211; Cantus in Memoriam Benjamin Britten</h2>



<p>The texture begins sparsely, with the bell and strings introducing the music, and gradually grows into a dense, layered sound as all the strings join. The strings play continuously until the end, with no silences or breaks.</p>



<p>The melody, mostly played by the violins, passes to the lower strings at the end, creating the impression of a sorrowful cry. It starts with a forceful high notes but eventually descends, evoking a sense of loss. The sharp violins lend this crying effect.</p>



<p>The dynamics build steadily throughout the piece, starting with a soft pianissimo and reaching an intense fortissimo at the climax.</p>



<p>Articulation is simple, with the use of marcato and down-bow strokes to add weight to the notes. The overall timbre is dark and hypnotic, driven by the low-register drone of the bass strings. High notes in the melody briefly break through the heaviness. The resonating bell adds a church-like quality, amplifying the solemn and reflective atmosphere.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Maurice Ravel &#8211; Piano Concerto in G major, Second Movement</h2>



<p>In terms of instrumentation, the piano maintains a continuous presence, while the woodwinds engage in varied combinations to share the melody. The strings primarily provide gentle support.</p>



<p>The texture begins with the piano alone, creating a soft and warm sound. As the orchestra joins, the texture becomes slightly denser but remains light and transparent. The melody starts on the piano and is passed to different woodwind combinations. The harmonies are mostly consonant, adding to the serene and lyrical character of the music.</p>



<p>Dynamics remain subtle throughout, staying close to a piano level with minimal dramatic shifts. Articulation is simple, with a few marcato and occasional tremolo. The piano’s warm and lovely timbre dominates the solo passages, becoming more passionate when the strings add support and the woodwinds carry the melody. As the music becomes slightly more dissonant, the bassoon emerges, deepening the timbre and lending it a darker, more introspective quality.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
