<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 22:38:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Rob Orbison &#8211; Working For The Man</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-rob-orbison-working-for-the-man/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 22:21:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Composing for Choirs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=381</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This song opens with something unexpected &#8211; a brief acappella introduction where the chorus sings &#8220;uh&#8217;s&#8221; intercalated by Orbison&#8217;s vocals. This opening creates an interesting contrast with what follows, although the chorus keeps the &#8220;uh&#8217;s&#8221;...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This song opens with something unexpected &#8211; a brief acappella introduction where the chorus sings &#8220;uh&#8217;s&#8221; intercalated by Orbison&#8217;s vocals. This opening creates an interesting contrast with what follows, although the chorus keeps the &#8220;uh&#8217;s&#8221; throughout the song.</p>



<p>The song&#8217;s most noticeable feature is its strong, steady beat. It uses a rockabilly shuffle rhythm that keeps pushing forward without letting up. This driving rhythm does more than just keep time &#8211; it actually helps tell the story of the song by matching the feeling of working non-stop, just like the lyrics describe.</p>



<p>I enjoyed particularly the rhythm section that keeps a steady beat while guitars add short, decorative fills between the vocal lines. The song uses simple chord changes that were common in early rock and roll. While these chord progressions aren&#8217;t complicated, they work perfectly for this song. They provide a solid foundation that lets listeners focus on the rhythm and Orbison&#8217;s voice.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Thundercat &#8211; Them Changes</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-thundercat-them-changes/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 22:33:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Composing for Choirs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=384</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The first thing that caught my ear was the powerful bass line. Unlike most songs where the bass stays in the background, here it&#8217;s front and centre, thanks to some cool effects that make it...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The first thing that caught my ear was the powerful bass line. Unlike most songs where the bass stays in the background, here it&#8217;s front and centre, thanks to some cool effects that make it sound bigger and more interesting. The way the bass is used here completely changes how the song feels – it&#8217;s not just keeping the rhythm but actually leading the melody.</p>



<p>Overall the song has a sad, moody feeling that matches perfectly with the song&#8217;s theme about heartbreak. When the bridge (middle section) comes in, the chords take some surprising turns that keep things interesting and unexpected.</p>



<p>Another thing I liked was how the song sounds both old and new at the same time. It has the warm, rich sound you might hear in funk records from the 1970s, but it&#8217;s mixed in a modern way that makes everything clear and punchy. The drums hit hard like in hip-hop tracks, while still fitting naturally with the other instruments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Caroline Shaw &#8211; and the swallow</title>
		<link>./../../../../../../listening-to-caroline-shaw-and-the-swallow/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 22:23:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Composition Pathway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.1: Developing Specialisms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 5: Composing for Choirs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../../index.html?p=379</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I was pleasently surprise by listeinng to this piece. The way Shaw uses silence is particularly interesting &#8211; instead of just being empty space, these quiet moments build excitement and add meaning to the music....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I was pleasently surprise by listeinng to this piece. The way Shaw uses silence is particularly interesting &#8211; instead of just being empty space, these quiet moments build excitement and add meaning to the music.</p>



<p>The piece starts simply. From there, it grows more complex as the voices weave together in interesting ways. Sometimes all the voices are homophonic, and other times they move into polyphonic lines. The overall sound ranges from a full chorus singing together to just whispers, showing how versatile a choir can be.</p>



<p>I believe she does something interesting with the words in this piece. Sometimes she lets us hear them clearly so we understand their meaning. Other times, she breaks them apart into pure sounds, like using the voice as an instrument. This creates an interesting back-and-forth between understanding the words and just experiencing the sounds.</p>



<p>Even though it&#8217;s a recent piece (2017), it reminds me of chant music. One can hear this connection in several ways:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>The slow, thoughtful pace</li>



<li>The melismas</li>



<li>How the group recites text together</li>



<li>The peaceful, meditative feeling it creates</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
