<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Assignment &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 20:28:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Assignment 1: Reflection</title>
		<link>./../../../../../assignment-1-reflection/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 20:28:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Assignment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Music 2.2: Experimental Encounters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Project 1: Introduction to Collaboration]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=604</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[At this point in the course, I find myself in a state of exciting tension. At the same time, I&#8217;m drawn to and apprehensive about the possibilities of collaborative creative practice. This duality reminds me...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>At this point in the course, I find myself in a state of exciting tension. At the same time, I&#8217;m drawn to and apprehensive about the possibilities of collaborative creative practice. This duality reminds me of my past experiences in a band. While I was excited about creating music with others, that feeling was often undermined by the energy drain that comes with my introverted nature. I&#8217;m not antisocial at all, but being around people drains my energy reserves quickly, which created a challenging dynamic during those musical collaborations.</p>



<p>Looking back, my response to this energy limitation might have been counterproductive. In an attempt to make the most of our limited time together, I would arrive with pre-formed ideas, essentially bypassing the open creative process that makes collaboration valuable. </p>



<p>From the exercises, what excited me most now was the example of Dubois and her work with the French Space Agency. Her ability to take collaboration to an entirely new level, creating work that has not only an artistic impact but also a personal transformation, represents the kind of ambitious creative partnership I aspire to explore.</p>



<p>This connects to my growing interest in exploring collaborations beyond the music field entirely. While my initial instinct was to work with other musicians, the readings and discussions with my tutor have opened my thinking to partnerships with people from completely different disciplines.</p>



<p>One of the most compelling opportunities I see is the potential for collaboration to address what I recognise as my greatest creative weakness: my tendency to generate many ideas without following through to completion. I have countless starting points that never develop into finished work. Collaboration could provide not only the external accountability of deadlines but also the peer pressure to think more deeply about these initial sparks.</p>



<p>However, this opportunity is shadowed by a fear: having to compromise my vision and accept others&#8217; ideas that don&#8217;t align with my creative instincts. I know myself well enough to recognise that I typically avoid conflict, which could lead to acceptance of directions that don&#8217;t follow my vision. This creates a paradox: I need collaboration to push my ideas forward, but I worry that the collaborative process itself might dilute what makes those ideas interesting to me. But despite my concerns, I am genuinely open to listening and trying completely different approaches. This openness could be my greatest asset in collaborative relationships.</p>



<p>My ambition is to find collaborative partnerships that function more like the Dubois model, where different forms of expertise genuinely enhance each other&#8217;s work rather than requiring compromise. The risk, of course, is that such partnerships are rare and require not only compatible working styles but also aligned levels of commitment and vision. There&#8217;s also the risk that my energy management challenges could limit the depth of collaboration I&#8217;m capable of sustaining.</p>



<p>Moving forward, I see collaboration as finding ways to expand my creativity through a partnership that honours both my introverted nature and my curiosity about what becomes possible with collaboration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
