<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 14:42:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Research Point 5.4</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-5-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 14:38:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1376</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Steve Reich (born October 3, 1936,&#160;New York, U.S.) is one of the greatest living composers. He is considered&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Steve Reich (born October 3, 1936,&nbsp;New York, U.S.)  is one of the greatest living composers. He is considered one of the greatest contributors to the minimalist music movement with a style based on repetitive and rhythmic patterns. His compositions often feature a limited number of instruments.</p>



<p>In 1988, Steve Reich created &#8220;Different Trains,&#8221; a three-part composition featuring a string quartet and excerpts from audio recordings. This highly personal work draws inspiration from Reich&#8217;s recollections of his Jewish upbringing in the United States and his train voyages across the country. The piece&#8217;s themes are further contextualized by the vastly different connotations associated with train travel during World War II in Europe, where the transportation of Jews took on an entirely different significance.</p>



<p>The pioneering aspect of the composition lies in its integration of prerecorded sounds with a live string quartet. Sourced from a range of records featuring diverse train sounds and spoken-word samples, including those from Holocaust survivors, this unique blend of live performance and recorded sounds lend a layer of profundity and authenticity to the piece. In particular, the first movement stands out for its complete fusion of the strings and recordings, with the latter serving as the motivic ideas that the strings then elaborate upon. This creative approach, innovative for its time, elevates &#8220;Different Trains&#8221; to a remarkable work of art.</p>



<p>Across all three movements, a continuous repetition of sounds and patterns interlock and build upon one another, creating a rich and almost hypnotic soundscape. While this reinforces the rhythmic motion of a train, it also enables the listener to become fully immersed in the 30-minute journey of an industrialized landscape, transitioning into haunting melodies and ultimately concluding on a hopeful note. </p>



<p>While I was unable to discern any conventional chord progressions commonly found in classical string quartets, I observed a pronounced typical rhythmic texture primarily conveyed through the strings. In my opinion, this rhythmic quality injects the composition with a sense of emotion, motion, and intrigue, preventing it from succumbing to monotony and repetitiveness.</p>



<p>In my view, the most fascinating aspect of &#8220;Different Trains&#8221; lies in its harmonious melding of realism and emotion. The inclusion of train whistles and station sounds fosters a vivid and evocative soundscape, while the voices infused throughout the piece infuse a human element that heightens the profound emotional depth already conveyed through the strings.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1680187196987 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (1998b) <em>Steve Reich | Biography, Music, Tehillim, Music for 18 Musicians, Clapping Music, Different Trains, &amp; Facts</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/biography/Steve-Reich.</p>



<p>Schnipper, M. (2017) <em>Listening to Steve Reich’s Holocaust Opus “Different Trains.”</em> Available at: https://pitchfork.com/thepitch/schnips-picks-listening-to-steve-reichs-holocaust-opus-different-trains/.</p>



<p>Wikipedia contributors (2023a) <em>Different Trains</em>. Available at: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Different_Trains.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 5.1: Bartók’s String Quartet No. 4 (1928)</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-5-1-bartoks-string-quartet-no-4-1928/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 13:27:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1345</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Béla Bartók (1881 &#8211; 1945) was a Hungarian composer, and one of the most influential figures in 20th-century&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Béla Bartók (1881 &#8211; 1945) was a Hungarian composer, and one of the most influential figures in 20th-century music. His pieces are known for their extensive chromaticism and novel rhythms. He is known for collecting and studying authentic Hungarian folk music and incorporating them into his music. He wrote six string quartets which were among his most impressive achievements, being the fourth, the most celebrated.</p>



<p>The String Quartet No.4 has five movements that are written symmetrically. It contains two sets of identical movements with a middle movement which is the central point of the quartet. Here is Bartók explaining it:</p>



<p>&#8220;The work is in five movements; their character corresponds to Classical sonata form. The slow movement is the kernel of the work; the other movements are, as it were, arranged in layers around it. Movement IV is a free variation of II, and I and V have the same thematic material; that is, around the kernel (Movement III), metaphorically speaking, I and V are the outer, II and IV the inner layers.&#8221; (Keller, 2011).</p>



<p>Although Bartók suggests that the nature of the first and final movements corresponds with that of the Classical sonata form, I believe that he merely employed the concept of the sonata form and utilized it liberally as a framework for his composition, without adhering rigorously to its conventions. Distinct motifs are present in the quartet, rather than explicitly articulated themes as found in the sonatas of Beethoven or Haydn. These motific ideas tend to appear for a very short time and disappear quickly. This reminds me of Debussy.</p>



<p>Upon listening to this piece for the first time, I found it much harder to distinguish the sonata sections, in contrast to Haydn&#8217;s quartet, wherein such segments were easily discernible. However, after reading the score and watching Andreyev&#8217;s analysis, I was able to understand the structure of the piece, the division of the sections, and the appearance of each motif.<br></p>



<p>When listening to the entire movement, I found it to be incredibly radical and challenging to follow. This left me confused, especially knowing that Bartók employs several counterpoint techniques that are commonly used in the works of many Western composers, including contrary motion, imitation, inversions, and call-and-response.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="193" height="300" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22-193x300.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1347" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22-193x300.png 193w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22-300x467.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22.png 438w" sizes="(max-width: 193px) 100vw, 193px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Contrary Motion</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="297" height="300" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-297x300.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1346" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-297x300.png 297w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-80x80.png 80w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-300x303.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-640x647.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35.png 702w" sizes="(max-width: 297px) 100vw, 297px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Inversion</figcaption></figure>



<p>Bartók demonstrates an innovative use of the quartet by investigating the sonorities of the three instruments through techniques such as extreme note ranges, varied glissandos, and his unique interpretation of pizzicato, which involves a vigorous plucking motion that produces a sharp snap upon the string&#8217;s impact with the instrument.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1679676452719 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Stevens, H. (2023) <em>Béla Bartók | Hungarian composer</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/biography/Bela-Bartok (Accessed: March 28, 2023).</p>



<p>Keller, J.M. (2011) <em>Chamber Music: A Listener’s Guide</em>. Oxford University Press, USA.</p>



<p>Samuel Andreyev (2017) <em>Béla Bartók’s String Quartet N° 4: Analysis</em>. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pMV7KaxyBIE.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
