<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Listening Log &#8211; Pedro Vintém</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../../../index.html</link>
	<description>Learning Log</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 13:51:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Listening to Cecilia Todd &#8211; Acidito</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-cecilia-todd-acidito/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 11:34:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1457</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Upon watching an Instagram Reel by David Asher Brown on Venezuelan merengue and its unique 5/8 rhythm, I&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Upon watching an Instagram Reel by David Asher Brown on Venezuelan merengue and its unique 5/8 rhythm, I decided to explore one of the genre&#8217;s most renowned compositions, Acidito. The song was composed by Adelis Fréitez and has been popularized by several singers and bands. </p>



<p>Cecilia Todd Vallenilla is a well-known Venezuelan musician, recognized for her performances of traditional Venezuelan folk music. She is especially skilled in playing the cuatro, which she uses to accompany herself in performances both within Venezuela and abroad.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Cecilia Todd - Acidito - Encuentro en el Estudio - Temporada 7" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/o20jefoabvE?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Upon close listening, it became clear that the 5/8 rhythm of Venezuelan merengue, as described by David Asher Brown, feels natural without any apparent sense of strain. The natural quality of this rhythmic structure may be attributed to the tempo at which it is played.</p>



<p>After looking at the bass score, I realized that it consists of a two-quaver and one-crotchet rhythm. This raises the question of where the accent falls, whether it is on the first or the fifth beat. Based on the position of the break and the melodic leap, it appears that the accent may be on the fifth beat, although I may not be entirely right.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="166" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/image-1024x166.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1458" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/image-1024x166.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/image-300x49.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/image-768x125.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/image-1536x250.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/image-2048x333.png 2048w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/image-640x104.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/image-960x156.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/image.png 2216w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>This video from Berklee College of Music presents a straightforward explanation of the rhythm.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Venezuelan Merengue - Alexis Soto and Carlos Capacho (Berklee Artist Notes)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ICAviMybq94?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Heitor Villa-Lobos &#8211; 12 Études for Guitar</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-heitor-villa-lobos-12-etudes-for-guitar/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 11:13:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1453</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Although not typically drawn to classical guitar compositions, I discovered the Brazilian composer Heitor Villa-Lobos&#8217; (1887-1957) 12 Études&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Although not typically drawn to classical guitar compositions, I discovered the Brazilian composer Heitor Villa-Lobos&#8217; (1887-1957) 12 Études for Guitar and decided to listen to it.</p>



<p>Heitor Villa-Lobos is widely regarded as one of the foremost composers of Latin American music in the 20th century. His work is notable for its unique synthesis of Western classical music and traditional Brazilian folk songs and rhythms. Among his many notable works are the Etudes, composed in 1928 and dedicated to the renowned guitarist Andres Segovia. Alongside their didactic function, these pieces are often featured in live performances due to their musical richness and technical demands.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Heitor Villa-lobos - 12 Études for Guitar (Score video)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JP8R7JBu_UM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>A few of the études caught my attention.</p>



<p>Study No. 1, employs the technique of right-hand arpeggio. The formula is fixed, interrupted only in measures 23-24. The Study can be divided into three sections: the first section goes until measure 11, which is characterized by stability in the harmony. The second section runs from measure 12 to measure 22, where the arpeggios move down the scale by step, with a pedal E bass note. The third section covers measures 23 to 33, where the range of the notes is expanded. The study was symmetrically constructed with sections of 11 measures. The beauty of this piece lies in the cyclical repetition of each bar, which effectively generates a sense of tension and release.</p>



<p>Study No. 4 is centred on the continuous repetition of chords in the right hand while extensively exploring the harmonic capabilities of the guitar. I hear in these chords elements that anticipate the emergence of Brazilian popular music and bossa nova in the years following its composition.</p>



<p>Study No. 10 is characterized by a range of idiomatic resources and technical challenges, including the use of open strings as pedal notes and ornamental techniques for accompanying open strings. The first 20 bars of the piece are constructed around a fixed position of the left hand, which ascends chromatically, creating a sense of mounting tension. I believe this section showcases Villa-Lobos&#8217; skilful use of harmonic and melodic devices to create a dynamic and engaging piece of music.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Beatles &#8211; Here, There and Everywhere</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-beatles-here-there-and-everywhere/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 20:35:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1427</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Beatles&#8217; &#8220;Here, There and Everywhere&#8221; is a lyrical and melodic love song, and according to Paul McCartney&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Beatles&#8217; &#8220;Here, There and Everywhere&#8221; is a lyrical and melodic love song, and according to Paul McCartney in the McCartney 1, 2, 3 documentary, it is his favourite melody he composed. Despite its compelling melody, it is strange, for me, that it&#8217;s not as well-known as other Beatles love songs such as &#8220;Something&#8221; or &#8220;And I Love Her.&#8221; Nevertheless, the explicit lyrics leave no room for doubt that the singer wants the lover to be present at all times and everywhere, which makes the theme of the song relatable and impactful.</p>



<p>The structure of the song is intriguing because there is ambiguity about which parts serve as the verse or chorus. There is no melodic and harmonic division that lets the listener distinguish which one serves as chorus or verse. Instead, it is easier to structure the song as Introduction &#8211; A &#8211; B &#8211; A &#8211; B &#8211; A.</p>



<p>Looking closer at the harmony, it is remarkable that the song has two modulations, which is uncommon in pop music, especially considering the song&#8217;s brief 2:24 minute runtime. The song is in the key of G major, and the first modulation happens in the A section, where the music shifts to the relative minor, E, with an F#m7 chord followed by a B major chord, and then moves to E minor chord shifting back to the key of G major.</p>



<p>The other modulation occurs in the B section, where the song modulates to Bb major. This is a relatively dramatic shift, but it is attenuated with preparation at the end of the A section, where the melody sings a Bb note before moving to the B section.</p>



<p>The melody is what I like the most about this music, especially the leap that first appears at bar 5. Upon closer inspection, this leap is similar to SZA&#8217;s &#8220;Kill Bill&#8221; melody (I wrote about it here), which employs an upward preparation followed by a descent with a longer duration. This is a good melodic technique that contributes to the song&#8217;s appeal.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="141" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-04-30-at-21.20.48-1024x141.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1431" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-04-30-at-21.20.48-1024x141.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-04-30-at-21.20.48-300x41.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-04-30-at-21.20.48-768x106.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-04-30-at-21.20.48-1536x212.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-04-30-at-21.20.48-640x88.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-04-30-at-21.20.48-960x132.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-04-30-at-21.20.48.png 1698w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Here, There, Everywhere melody line</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="120" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1-1024x120.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1433" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1-1024x120.png 1024w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1-300x35.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1-768x90.png 768w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1-1536x180.png 1536w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1-640x75.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1-960x113.png 960w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Screenshot-2023-01-30-at-12.30.26-1.png 1587w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Kill Bill melody line</figcaption></figure>



<p>The vocal harmonies in the song are simple and effective. According to the producer George Martin, &#8220;the boys&#8221; hummed basic triads behind the melody, resulting in moving block harmonies.</p>



<p>The song&#8217;s arrangement never seems to settle, similar to the Beach Boys&#8217; &#8220;God Only Knows,&#8221; which was, in fact, an inspiration for McCartney when he wrote, &#8220;Here, There and Everywhere.&#8221;</p>



<p>In conclusion, &#8220;Here, There and Everywhere&#8221;, for me, is a great example of a love song that demonstrates mastery of melody and harmony, but also simplicity. It is an excellent example of pop music that uses modulation effectively.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 5.4</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-5-4/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 14:38:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1376</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Steve Reich (born October 3, 1936,&#160;New York, U.S.) is one of the greatest living composers. He is considered&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Steve Reich (born October 3, 1936,&nbsp;New York, U.S.)  is one of the greatest living composers. He is considered one of the greatest contributors to the minimalist music movement with a style based on repetitive and rhythmic patterns. His compositions often feature a limited number of instruments.</p>



<p>In 1988, Steve Reich created &#8220;Different Trains,&#8221; a three-part composition featuring a string quartet and excerpts from audio recordings. This highly personal work draws inspiration from Reich&#8217;s recollections of his Jewish upbringing in the United States and his train voyages across the country. The piece&#8217;s themes are further contextualized by the vastly different connotations associated with train travel during World War II in Europe, where the transportation of Jews took on an entirely different significance.</p>



<p>The pioneering aspect of the composition lies in its integration of prerecorded sounds with a live string quartet. Sourced from a range of records featuring diverse train sounds and spoken-word samples, including those from Holocaust survivors, this unique blend of live performance and recorded sounds lend a layer of profundity and authenticity to the piece. In particular, the first movement stands out for its complete fusion of the strings and recordings, with the latter serving as the motivic ideas that the strings then elaborate upon. This creative approach, innovative for its time, elevates &#8220;Different Trains&#8221; to a remarkable work of art.</p>



<p>Across all three movements, a continuous repetition of sounds and patterns interlock and build upon one another, creating a rich and almost hypnotic soundscape. While this reinforces the rhythmic motion of a train, it also enables the listener to become fully immersed in the 30-minute journey of an industrialized landscape, transitioning into haunting melodies and ultimately concluding on a hopeful note. </p>



<p>While I was unable to discern any conventional chord progressions commonly found in classical string quartets, I observed a pronounced typical rhythmic texture primarily conveyed through the strings. In my opinion, this rhythmic quality injects the composition with a sense of emotion, motion, and intrigue, preventing it from succumbing to monotony and repetitiveness.</p>



<p>In my view, the most fascinating aspect of &#8220;Different Trains&#8221; lies in its harmonious melding of realism and emotion. The inclusion of train whistles and station sounds fosters a vivid and evocative soundscape, while the voices infused throughout the piece infuse a human element that heightens the profound emotional depth already conveyed through the strings.</p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1680187196987 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>The Editors of Encyclopaedia Britannica (1998b) <em>Steve Reich | Biography, Music, Tehillim, Music for 18 Musicians, Clapping Music, Different Trains, &amp; Facts</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/biography/Steve-Reich.</p>



<p>Schnipper, M. (2017) <em>Listening to Steve Reich’s Holocaust Opus “Different Trains.”</em> Available at: https://pitchfork.com/thepitch/schnips-picks-listening-to-steve-reichs-holocaust-opus-different-trains/.</p>



<p>Wikipedia contributors (2023a) <em>Different Trains</em>. Available at: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Different_Trains.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Listening to Mozart &#8211; String Quartet No. 19 &#8220;Dissonance&#8221;</title>
		<link>./../../../../../listening-to-mozart-string-quartet-no-19-dissonance/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 14:27:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1450</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This String Quartet got my attention right at the beginning. The opening is a slow and haunting Adagio&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This String Quartet got my attention right at the beginning. The opening is a slow and haunting Adagio introduction, which features discordant harmonies that create a sense of tension and unease. The pulsating cello descends chromatically leaving a harmonic ambiguity that surprised me. I wasn&#8217;t expecting this kind of introduction by Mozart. The other strings keep playing colliding notes, while the dynamics keep going from p to f and back to p. These 22 bars of the Adagio create a stark contrast with the subsequent Allegro movement, which is characterized by its lively and playful nature.</p>



<p>This string quartet in C major was composed in 1785 and is part of the set of six quartets composed between 1782 and 1785 that he dedicated to Joseph Haydn. This introduction was so innovative and disruptive for its time that it received mixed reviews from critics, publishers and players.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Research Point 5.1: Bartók’s String Quartet No. 4 (1928)</title>
		<link>./../../../../../research-point-5-1-bartoks-string-quartet-no-4-1928/index.html</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pedro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 13:27:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Coursework]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Listening Log]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Part 5 The Classical Era]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stylistic Techniques]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../../../index.html?p=1345</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Béla Bartók (1881 &#8211; 1945) was a Hungarian composer, and one of the most influential figures in 20th-century&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Béla Bartók (1881 &#8211; 1945) was a Hungarian composer, and one of the most influential figures in 20th-century music. His pieces are known for their extensive chromaticism and novel rhythms. He is known for collecting and studying authentic Hungarian folk music and incorporating them into his music. He wrote six string quartets which were among his most impressive achievements, being the fourth, the most celebrated.</p>



<p>The String Quartet No.4 has five movements that are written symmetrically. It contains two sets of identical movements with a middle movement which is the central point of the quartet. Here is Bartók explaining it:</p>



<p>&#8220;The work is in five movements; their character corresponds to Classical sonata form. The slow movement is the kernel of the work; the other movements are, as it were, arranged in layers around it. Movement IV is a free variation of II, and I and V have the same thematic material; that is, around the kernel (Movement III), metaphorically speaking, I and V are the outer, II and IV the inner layers.&#8221; (Keller, 2011).</p>



<p>Although Bartók suggests that the nature of the first and final movements corresponds with that of the Classical sonata form, I believe that he merely employed the concept of the sonata form and utilized it liberally as a framework for his composition, without adhering rigorously to its conventions. Distinct motifs are present in the quartet, rather than explicitly articulated themes as found in the sonatas of Beethoven or Haydn. These motific ideas tend to appear for a very short time and disappear quickly. This reminds me of Debussy.</p>



<p>Upon listening to this piece for the first time, I found it much harder to distinguish the sonata sections, in contrast to Haydn&#8217;s quartet, wherein such segments were easily discernible. However, after reading the score and watching Andreyev&#8217;s analysis, I was able to understand the structure of the piece, the division of the sections, and the appearance of each motif.<br></p>



<p>When listening to the entire movement, I found it to be incredibly radical and challenging to follow. This left me confused, especially knowing that Bartók employs several counterpoint techniques that are commonly used in the works of many Western composers, including contrary motion, imitation, inversions, and call-and-response.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="193" height="300" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22-193x300.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1347" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22-193x300.png 193w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22-300x467.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.46.22.png 438w" sizes="(max-width: 193px) 100vw, 193px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Contrary Motion</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="297" height="300" src="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-297x300.png" alt="" class="wp-image-1346" srcset="./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-297x300.png 297w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-80x80.png 80w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-300x303.png 300w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35-640x647.png 640w, ./../../../../../wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Screenshot-2023-03-24-at-16.44.35.png 702w" sizes="(max-width: 297px) 100vw, 297px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Inversion</figcaption></figure>



<p>Bartók demonstrates an innovative use of the quartet by investigating the sonorities of the three instruments through techniques such as extreme note ranges, varied glissandos, and his unique interpretation of pizzicato, which involves a vigorous plucking motion that produces a sharp snap upon the string&#8217;s impact with the instrument.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 id="references" class="cnvs-block-section-heading cnvs-block-section-heading-1679676452719 is-style-cnvs-block-section-heading-6 halignleft" >
	<span class="cnvs-section-title">
		<span>References</span>
	</span>
</h2>



<p>Stevens, H. (2023) <em>Béla Bartók | Hungarian composer</em>. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/biography/Bela-Bartok (Accessed: March 28, 2023).</p>



<p>Keller, J.M. (2011) <em>Chamber Music: A Listener’s Guide</em>. Oxford University Press, USA.</p>



<p>Samuel Andreyev (2017) <em>Béla Bartók’s String Quartet N° 4: Analysis</em>. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pMV7KaxyBIE.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
